<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <session.header>
        <date>1904-05-19</date>
        <parliament.no>2</parliament.no>
        <session.no>1</session.no>
        <period.no>0</period.no>
        <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
        <page.no>1290</page.no>
        <proof>0</proof>
    </session.header>
    <chamber.xscript>
        <para class="block">Senate. </para>
        <business.start>
            <day.start>1904-05-19</day.start>
            <para>The President took the chair at 2.30 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
        </business.start>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>1290</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TRANS-CONTINENTAL RAILWAY</title>
                    <page.no>1290</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1290</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I desire to ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council, without notice, if the Government have communicated with the Governments of the States of South Australia and Western Australia in reference to the. trans-Australian railway, and, if So, has he any objection to informing the Senate as to the nature of the communications and the replies received ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1290</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Prime Minister has communicated by telegram with, the Premier of Western Australia asking for information in connexion with the responsibilities of that State, and he has received a reply by telegram that, if the direction and gauge of the proposed trans-continental line is left to the discretion of the Commonwealth, the Government &#39; of Western Australia will be prepared to bear a substantial proportion of any loss which may occur for the first ten years, but &#34;that at this stage they do not . think that they could state exactly the amount I shall lay the- communications on the table presently. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SUB-LETTING OF POST-OFFICES</title>
                    <page.no>1290</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Postage of Printed Matter</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1290</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                            <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator FINDLEY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I desire to ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council, without notice, the following questions : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="loweralpha-dotted">
                        <item label="x.">
                            <para>The number of post-offices in the State of Victoria which have been &#34;farmed out&#34; or let to -applicants at an annual rate of remuneration, fixed by the Department ? </para>
                            <list type="decimal-dotted">
                                <item label="2.">
                                    <para>The reasons which led to the adoption of such a system by the -Honorable the Postmaster-General ? </para>
                                </item>
                                <item label="3.">
                                    <para>If the system referred to has been adopted on the. score of economy, then is it the intention of the Honorable the Postmaster-General to extend its operation 50 as to include the more important offices controlled by his Department? </para>
                                </item>
                                <item label="4.">
                                    <para>In the event of no suitable applicant tendering his services to the Commonwealth at the remuneration originally fixed, has it been the practice of the Department to increase the amount and invite applications afresh on the system known in commerce as the &#34;Dutch auction&#34;? </para>
                                </item>
                                <item label="5.">
                                    <para>The amount or the average percentage ordinarily saved by the letting of post-offices in the &#34;way indicated as compared, with the amount payable by way of salary if the same services were performed by regular officers of the Department? </para>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KUL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Millen</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Are these questions being asked without notice? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JVC</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DOBSON, Henry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Dobson</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- By arrangement. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McGregor</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- There is no arrangement about it. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator FINDLEY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I also desire to ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council these questions: - </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="6.">
                            <para>Has the attention of the Honorable the Post master-General been directed to the fact that much printed matter is now being distributed through the Post-office at the reduced charge foi the transmission of newspapers, this purpose being effected by registering printed matter as a newspaper, although the so-called journal has no subscribers, does not publish news, and is entirely devoted to the advocacy of a single political purpose - that of Scripture instruction in State schools? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="7.">
                            <para>Has the attention of the Honorable the Post master-General been drawn to the fact that of the printed matter referred to no less than 300,000 copies, addressed to individual residents of the State, have been distributed through the medium of the Post-office at a rate which does not exceed one penny for. seventy-two copies, and what action, if any, does the Government purpose taking in connexion with the matter? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KUL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Millen</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I desire to know, sir, whether the sixth question can be put in that way, seeing that it contains statements which are in conflict with the Standing Orders? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The Standing Orders provide that in asking a question no facts shall be stated, except such as are necessary to explain the question, and that no argument or imputation shall be permitted. It is very difficult for me. from merely hearing them read, to say whether all these questions are in order or not. I think the bulk of them are in order. I understand that the honorable senator intends to alter one of them. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Findley</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I shall alter it in accordance with your suggestion, sir. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1291</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MCGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I do not think that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Findley</inline> expects me to answer his questions straight away. With respect to the interjection that there was an arrangement for him to ask these questions, I desire to say that there was no such&#39; arrangement, as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator- Findley</inline> will acknowledge. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Findley</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Hear, hear. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- In asking the honorable senator to give notice of the questions, I wish to point out what I think should have been pointed out here-long ago. When an honorable senator asks a question without notice, and he is asked to give notice of it, or even when he gives notice of a question, and the preparation of a reply involves a large amount of research, and perhaps communication with the Departments concerned in all the States of the Commonwealth, I think that, instead of giving notice of the question for tomorrow, the notice should be given for such a date as will allow a reasonable time in which to procure the answer. I ask my honorable friend to give notice of his questions. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator FINDLEY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I am anxious to get an answer as soon as possible to the last question. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The honorable senator can split up his questions if he likes. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator FINDLEY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I beg to give notice of the last two questions for to-morrow, and of the others for Wednesday next. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>FEDERAL CAPITAL</title>
                    <page.no>1291</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1291</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6D</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SMITH, Miles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator STANIFORTH SMITH</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I desire to ask the Vice-President of&#39; the Executive Council, without notice, if he will lay upon the table the report prepared by <inline font-weight="bold">Sir John</inline> Forrest with regard to Lyndhurst as a Federal Capital site? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1291</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I think that the honorable senator is aware that an attempt was made in another place to do the very same thing. The Government have no objection to hear the opinion of such an eminent authority as the Right Honorable <inline font-weight="bold">Sir John</inline> Forrest ; but as that report was made by him as a private member, I do not think that it would be wise for the Government to establish a precedent which would allow any member to make a report on a proposed Capital site, and then to ask that it should be laid upon the table. I know that the honorable senator, or any one else, can move that such a course should be adopted ; but whether the motion would be carried or not is a different question. I think that the very extensive summary which has been published in the press to-day ought to satisfy the honorable senator. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PAPER</title>
                <page.no>1291</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McGREGOR</inline>
                laid upon the table the following paper: -
            </para>
            <quote>
                <para>Western Australian Railway - Telegraphic Correspondence between the Prime Minister and the Premier of Western Australia.  </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>1292</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>ANGLO-CHINESE LABOUR CONVENTION</title>
                    <page.no>1292</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6D</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SMITH, Miles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator STANIFORTH SMITH</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Vice-President of the Executive Council, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Has the attention of the Ministry been directed to a cabled statement in the papers of the 16th instant that an Anglo-Chinese Labour Convention had been signed dealing on general lines with the question of Chinese emigration to all British Colonies and Possessions? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Can the Vice-President of the Executive Council inform the Senate if this conflicts in any way with Commonwealth legislation ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions are as follow : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="loweralpha-dotted">
                        <item label="r.">
                            <para>Yes. <inline font-style="italic">j..</inline> I am not aware; but as soon as copies of the </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para class="block">Convention are received a careful examination of its provisions will be made to see whether the Commonwealth is in any way affected. </para>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>POST AND TELEGRAPH DEPARTMENT</title>
                    <page.no>1292</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Vice-President of the Executive Council, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>Will the Minister take steps to lay upon the table of the Senate all papers relating to - </para>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Retirement of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. R&#39;.</inline> Sholl, from the position of Deputy Postmaster-General of Western Australia? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>The proposed transfer of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Woodrow,</inline> Postmaster at Bunbury, to the position of Postmaster at Fremantle, Western Australia. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answer to the honorable senator&#39;s questions is as follows : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>The Postmaster-General will cause extracts of the papers in both instances to he prepared for the purpose of being placed on the table of the Senate. </para>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>BLIND SEA PASSENGERS</title>
                    <page.no>1292</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In asking the Vice-President of tha Executive Council, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>In reference to a question asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce</inline> on Thursday, 14th April, 1904, relative to the treatment of persons afflicted with blindness by the steam-ship companies trading round the Australian coasts, in answer to which the Government of the day promised to make inquiries, will the Vice-President of the Executive Council ascertain if such inquiries have been made, and with what result? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If no such inquiries have been made, will the Minister cause inquiries to be made on the subject ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para class="block">I desire to explain that I am following up a question which I previously asked in reference to the action of steam-ship companies&#39; trading round Australia in preventing blind persons from taking out a ticket from one port to another port, unless they will give them a guarantee that they will not become a charge on the State to which they desire to go. This was rendered necessary under the States laws, because a person afflicted with blindness might become a charge on the State, but since the Commonwealth has legislated in reference to this matter, it is not necessary, and the steam-ship companies are now under no liability in that regard. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1292</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KNB</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">GUTHRIE, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Guthrie</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Oh, yes they are. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>1292</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I have very good legal advice to the effect that they are under no liability, but they are still compelling persons afflicted with blindness to provide a substantial guarantee that they will not become a charge on. the State. In the case of the Conference of Associations of the Blind, which met recently in - Melbourne, all the delegates who came from other States were compelled to furnish guarantees before the steam-ship companies would provide them with tickets, and in the case of a gentleman who is now touring South Australia as a lecturer on behalf of the Western Australian Government, the steam-ship company refused to take him as a passenger until the Government of Western Australia gave a guarantee that he would not become a charge on the State to which he was going. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGREGOR</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions are as follow : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Certain State Acts provide that if any passenger arriving by sea in the State is blind, Aic, the ship-owners shall give a bond in a certain sum for his support should such passenger become a charge on any charitable institution. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>It is a question of law whether any such provision is contrary to the Constitution. The Acts referred to are not enforced by the Commonwealth. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PATENTS OFFICE: STAFF</title>
                    <page.no>1292</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Vice-President of the Executive Council, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What are the names of the officers appointed to administer the Patents Act, and what States do they belong to? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Were any of these officers formerly in the employ of the States Governments; and if so.-, which ? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>Were &#39;any persons in the employ of the States Governments applicants for such positions, and refused ; if so, what were the reasons of such refusal ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1292</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTV</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DAWSON, Anderson</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DAWSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Marvellous as is the memory of my honorable colleague, the </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para class="block">1293 </para>
                    <para class="block">Vice-President of the Executive Council, perhaps it is better that I should be allowed to read the answers to these questions, which are as follow : - </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="019332190405194_3_0.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>All the officers mentioned in No. (1) be longed to the States Patents Service, with the three following exceptions : - G. S. Knowles and T. Hammond, Clerks, Central Office, belonged to the Federal Service, and were employed in Melbourne. B. Wallach, Examiner in Electricity, appointed from outside the Service. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>The following information has been supplied by the Public Service Commissioner : - Yes, there were a number for the different positions, and in every case the most eligible applicant was selected. In establishing the new Patents Office it was considered that, in connexion with such a progressive science as electricity, the applicant with the best experience and highest credentials should be secured. The gentleman appointed as Examiner in Electricity holds the degree of Bachelor of Engineering, and received his training in one of the largest electrical engineering establishments in the world ; his qualifications were considered superior to those of any of the other applicants. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SEAT OF GOVERNMENT BILL</title>
                <page.no>1293</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McGregor)</inline> agreed to- &#39; </para>
            <para>That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to determine the Seat of Government of the Commonwealth. </para>
            <para>Bill presented and read a first time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>FEDERAL IRON WORKS</title>
                <page.no>1293</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Debate resumed from 14th April <inline font-style="italic">{vide</inline> page 960), on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That this Senate affirms the principle of iron works being established and owned by the Federal Government, for the purpose of manufacturing pig-iron, and steel from native ore, believing this would be in the best interests of Australian industry, State rights, and Commonwealth prosperity. </para>
            </quote>
            <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator HENDERSON</inline>
                (Western Australia). Seeing that at a previous sitting this motion was very forcibly proposed by
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline>
                Largie, and that at that time almost the whole of the detailed evidence in connexion with the establishment of an iron industry for the Commonwealth was fairly well placed before the Senate, it is unnecessary for me to attempt to give details now. I want particularly to ask the Senate to bear in mind that in discussing a proposition of this character, we are face to face with one of those matters that a Royal Commission has emphasized as important, in a report that has been presented to Parliament. It appears that the Commission, having satisfied itself that the question to be dealt with was one involving great risk and great responsibility, took every care to produce such evidence as would make it clear to Parliament whether, first of all, there was the material required within the Commonwealth for the establishment of an iron industry ; and, secondly, whether, if the material was here, there was really sufficient importance attaching to the industry to permit of its establishment under a certain condition of things. The Commission was appointed, not with the intention that it should inquire whether the industry should be established under the regime of the Commonwealth Parliament, as is suggested by the motion, but for the purpose of ascertaining whether under a bonus system it would be likely to be successful, or to meet the requirements of this young and rising nation.
            </para>
            <interjection>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1293</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JTV</name.id>
                        <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                        <party>ALP</party>
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DAWSON, Anderson</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DAWSON</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- A young nation that has arisen. </para>
                </talk.start>
            </interjection>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1293</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KOS</name.id>
                        <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">HENDERSON, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator HENDERSON</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Yes; the young nation has arisen. It appears from the whole of the evidence collected by the Royal Commission that there were just and reasonable grounds for reporting to Parliament that this is one of the most important questions that can be dealt with by_ the Commonwealth. At the same time, it is indicated that there is evidence sufficient to show that material of every description necessary for the purpose is to be found within the Commonwealth. The appointment of the Commission showed conclusively that public men connected with the high offices of the Commonwealth had had their attention drawn towards the importance of the industry. They thought it so important that they first of all proposed to give an amount of ^250,000 as a bonus for its establishment. My own opinion with respect to the matter, is that if we can afford to give the slightest consideration to the idea of spending ^&#163;2 50,000 - or at least allowing some one else to spend it - for the purpose of establishing this industry, surely, in the face of the evidence taken, we can afford to spend the money in order that we may con- trol the business and utilize its product to the best advantage. The evidence goes to show practically that the industry can be established by the expenditure, once and for all, of the amount of money that was proposed to be paid as a bonus to some one else to establish it. That being so, it must appeal to every honorable senator who has read the Royal Commission&#39;s report, that to do something that would practically give away the principle of establishing this industry by the Commonwealth, would be conduct for which we should, each and all, receive the direct and certainly the well-earned disapprobation of the people. The gentleman who advocated &#39; the bonus system for the establishment of the iron industry - as <inline font-style="italic">per</inline> evidence - showed that he was prepared to undertake to provide iron ready for use at a rate per ton which some of the members of the Commission were in a position to say at once put away the idea of any necessity for granting a bonus. But even if that be so, it does not alter the situation. It remains a fact that we have a nation that has been using, and will continue to use, iron and steel, and which, we believe, will use it in greater quantities in future than it has hitherto done. We also have to look forward to a time - and I presume that all the public men of Australia to-day are looking forward to that time - when our own ship-building yards will be established, and will be of such proportions as to supply very largely the requirements of Australia in the matter of her merchant shipping fleet. Therefore the&#39; establishment of an industry that is so much needed has much to recommend it. In my opinion the industry would employ not merely the. moderate number of hands estimated bv the mover of the motion. It is&#39; fair to say that he simply estimated those who would be directly employed within foundries for the purpose of producing iron. But we have also to remember that the iron industry employs a considerable number of men who never touch the iron itself. There are those who have to produce the material that is required, apart from the mining of the iron-stone.. The production of those other materials is a very&#39; considerable factor. There are probably a larger number of miners to be employed in producing the other material necessary for the making of iron than in extracting the iron ore. There is the coal and there is the flux. A considerable quantity of both of those factors is required to produce good iron. That being so, we see at once that, independently of the number of men who would be directly employed in the iron industry, there would be a possibility of the employment of many hundreds of others in industries which are primary to the production of iron. &#39; Surely, this motion should appeal to honorable senators as suggesting a method by which we might possibly employ the whole, or almost the whole, of our present surplus labour. There are a large number of unemployed in some of our States to-day. Whilst that is so, we are importing two of the most important materials used in Australia, iron and steel. We are importing practically everything that we, as a Commonwealth, coul&#39;d produce of a quality fit for use by this nation. By making our own iron and steel we should not only be building up this nation&#39; in all the healthy requirements of national life, but also providing the bone and sinew of the population with work. Further than that, we should be extending the arts that are contingent to the operations carried on within the iron trade. Therefore, a motion the effect of which would certainly be to bring to this nation the importance that justly belongs- to it, and that would give it facilities for providing that which at present other people have to provide for us, and would do so without our trammelling ourselves with the giving of bonuses, is certainly worthy of adoption by this or any other Parliament. The question that was raised when the motion was tabled, with regard to whether the Constitution would permit the Commonwealth to adopt such a system as is involved in becoming an employer and the producer, apart from the sanction of the States, or from States rights, is one that I have no intention of entering into. But it appears to me that almost anything becomes a State right when the people of a State demand that it is essential to them, and to their civilization and humanity. We have the knowledge that during the last election the principle of the establishment of the iron industry under </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para class="block">Commonwealth control, and of providing for all our requirements in that direction, was very&#39; largely discussed throughout the whole Commonwealth. More than that, the number of members of Parliament returned on the advocacy of that principle showed unquestionably that the people of the Commonwealth are rising to the necessity of this policy. If there is any constitutional disability standing in their way, I am prepared to believe that they look on this matter as being of so much importance as affecting &#39; their welfare, that they will take the proper means to remodel or vary the Constitution so as to remove that disability to the advancement of the general welfare of the Commonwealth. Therefore I trust that the motion as submitted will not only meet with the hearty support of the Senate, and of another place, but that there will be that hearty co-operation in its principle . which will at once give an incentive to its immediate application to a question that demands the most candid consideration of every member of the Commonwealth Parliament. </para>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1295</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KAH</name.id>
                        <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">WALKER, James</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator WALKER</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- When this motion was under discussion before, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Playford</inline> gave us an opinion from the Attorney-General that the principle contained in it was <inline font-style="italic">ultra vires</inline> of the Constitution. I do not intend&#39; to enlarge on that subject, except to say that I am not a State Socialist, and that if the motion goes to a division I shall vote against it. </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1295</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JU7</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- I am in the position of having very little to reply to in this debate. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KAH</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">WALKER, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Walker</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There is the constitutional point. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JU7</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I replied to that very fully when I was introducing my motion. I simply desire to say that even if there is any necessity for the alteration of the Constitution - and I do not think that there is - seeing that the Prime Minister, in outlining his policy in another place yesterday, proposed in regard to another industry to do something similar to what I propose in connexion with the iron industry, I think the same principle might very well apply in this case. If there is any necessity to alter the Constitution- in order that the Commonwealth may take the matter in hand, that can be done. Having perused the opinion given bv <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Deakin,</inline> when he was Attorney-General, I am under the impression that no alteration of the Constitution is necessary. Be that as it may, the contention does not act against the merits . of the motion to any appreciable degree. I regard this as a question of very great significance to the Commonwealth, the iron trade being one of the most important in civilized countries ; and the wonder is that it has not been established in Australia before now. On a former occasion, I explained very fully the reasons why the iron industry was not established long ago in New South Wales. Those reasons were principally fiscal, and arose under the free-trade regime of that State. Had the policy of New South Wales been protectionist, I believe ah attempt would have been made years ago to establish the industry. Under all the circumstances, we cannot stand any longer in the way of the establishment of the. iron trade. Were the industry to be established in works owned by a State Government, or in works promoted by private enterprise, I feel quite sure that there would not result the same satisfaction and confidence as would follow the adoption of the proposal now before the Senate. We have to recognise that State rights may be affected. If a State-owned works was established, I should have the same objection, though, perhaps, to not quite so great a degree, as I should have to the manipulation of the trade by private individuals. Works owned by a State would place every other Government in Australia at the mercy of that State, which could charge what it liked for the iron required for the carrying on of various Government Departments, especially the Railway Departments. This is a monopoly which we should not lightly place in the hands of even a State Government. It would be much more satisfactory if the industry were under the control of the Australian Government. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0X</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PLAYFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Playford</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Australian Government, like a State Government, could charge what prices they chose. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JU7</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I do not think so. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K8T</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">TRENWITH, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Trenwith</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The difference is that each State would be part manager of the works. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1295</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JU7</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- And if more were- charged to a particular State, that State would get a share of the profits. However,. I do not anticipate any such contingency.. I am not aware of any Government Department overcharging for services rendered ina public sense ; indeed, it is often said that the charges for the various functions performed by Governments are placed&#39; too low, and &#34;that the Departments in consequence are not run on what are called commercial principles. For that reason I should not agree to any State Government having control of these important iron works. I have already pointed out that there is not room in Australia for more than one iron works; and, that being so, it is seen at- a glance that the industry must be a monopoly, whether it be in the hands of a State Government or in the hands of a private individual. Under the circumstances I think that, however strong may be the opinion of honorable senators as &#34; private enterprisers,&#34; it will be conceded that such a monopoly would not be in the best interests of Australia. I hope that honorable senators, having viewed the matter from that stand-point, and being convinced of the necessity of having the trade established, will vote in support of the motion, as an indication to the present or some future Government that the matter should be taken up and&#39; legislated upon at the earliest possible date. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
            </speech>
            <division>
                <division.header>
                    <time.stamp />
                    <para>Question put. The Senate divided.</para>
                </division.header>
                <division.data>
                    <ayes>
                        <num.votes>0</num.votes>
                        <title>AYES</title>
                    </ayes>
                    <noes>
                        <num.votes>0</num.votes>
                        <title>NOES</title>
                    </noes>
                </division.data>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_6_1.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_6_2.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_6_3.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para>AYES</para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_6_1_1_A.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para>NOES</para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_6_1_2_N.jpg" />
                </para>
                <division.result>
                    <para class="block">Question so </para>
                </division.result>
                <para class="block">resolved in. the affirmative. </para>
            </division>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>COMPULSORY DRILLING OF YOUTHS</title>
                <page.no>1296</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Dobson)</inline> proposed - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That Order of the Day No. 2 be an Order of the Day for Thursday, 16th June. </para>
            </quote>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1296</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JTV</name.id>
                        <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                        <party>ALP</party>
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DAWSON, Anderson</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DAWSON</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- This order of the day relates to the compulsory drilling of youths. I desire to know whether the honorable and learned senator intends to proceed with the motion on the date he has mentioned, because I should like to have the matter settled. </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1296</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JVC</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DOBSON, Henry</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DOBSON</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Quite so. I shall be prepared to proceed on the 16th June. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>NATIONAL MONOPOLY IN TOBACCO</title>
                <page.no>1296</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Old-age Pensions. Debate resumed from 17 th March <inline font-style="italic">(indi</inline> page 664), on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce</inline> - </para>
            <quote>
                <list type="decimal">
                    <item label="(1)">
                        <para>That, in the opinion of this Senate, in order to provide the necessary money for the payment of old-age pensions and for other purposes, the Commonwealth Government should undertake the manufacture and sale pf tobacco, cigars, and cigarettes. </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(2)">
                        <para>That the foregoing resolution be referred to the House of Representatives, with a message requesting their concurrence therein. </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(3)">
                        <para>That a Select Committee, consisting of six members of the Senate and the mover, be appointed with power to sit and confer with a similar number of members of the House of Representatives, to inquire into, and report on the best method of carrying the foregoing resolution into effect. </para>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </quote>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1296</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- I shall be very brief in my reply, because the Opposition has been conspicuous by its absence. The only conclusion that one can come to is that the opponents of the motion are waiting for a more convenient season, or exhibit a wonderful dearth of material. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0X</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PLAYFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Playford</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I asked for more information before action is taken. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There was plenty of information at the disposal of honorable senators. I occupied five or six pages of <inline font-style="italic">Hansard,</inline> and I do not suppose the honorable senator desired me to monopolize that publication. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0X</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PLAYFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Playford</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- What I said was that we had not sufficient information before us, seeing that nobody connected with the trade had been examined. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The only objection raised - and I notice that it has been repeated by a newspaper in this city - was that in France the price of tobacco, under a monopoly, is high, and the quality poor. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYX</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FINDLEY, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Findley</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is not true. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is an absolute misstatement of fact, seeing that the price in France is about one half the average price in Australia. In France the price is 3s. 9d. a pound, as compared&#39; with an average price in Australia of 6s. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0X</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PLAYFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Playford</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The higher price here is on account of the duty. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1296</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The people of Fiance must be satisfied with the quality of the tobacco supplied to them, or they would not smoke such large quantities as to give the Government a revenue of ^15,000,000 annually. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Millen</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I am weaning myself off tobacco in view of the stuff that will be turned out of the Government factories. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The weaning may be good for the honorable senator, but will certainly be bad for the revenue. I shall not take up time by putting forward arguments for the opponents of the motion; let them put forward their own arguments, and we shall bowl them over. It is a poor thing for my opponents to say to me, &#34; Having put your own case, put ours, and reply to it.&#34; It is for the Opposition to show that the arguments which I put forward are not capable of proof. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
            </speech>
            <division>
                <division.header>
                    <time.stamp />
                    <para>Question put. The Senate divided.&#39; Ayes ... .... ... 17</para>
                </division.header>
                <division.data>
                    <ayes>
                        <num.votes>0</num.votes>
                        <title>AYES</title>
                    </ayes>
                    <noes>
                        <num.votes>0</num.votes>
                        <title>NOES</title>
                    </noes>
                </division.data>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_7_4.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_7_5.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_7_6.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para>AYES</para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_7_2_1_A.jpg" />
                </para>
                <para>NOES</para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="019332190405194_7_2_2_N.jpg" />
                </para>
                <division.result>
                    <para>Question so resolved in the affirmative. </para>
                </division.result>
            </division>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>1297</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- The Senate will now proceed to ballot for a Select Committee, consisting of six honorable senators and the mover. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- According to our Standing Orders the mover for the appointment of a Select Committee is not necessarily included in&#39; the Committee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The resolution says that the mover shall be a member. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Does the resolution override our Standing Orders? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Standing Orders provide that, &#34; unless otherwise ordered,&#34; all Select Committees shall consist of seven members. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have no objection to the mover being a member of the Select Committee ; but I desire to know whether the motion can override our Standing Orders, which say that the mover shall not necessarily be appointed. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTV</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DAWSON, Anderson</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DAWSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- But the resolution states that the mover shall be- a member of the Committee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGregor</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- - Before we proceed to the ballot, sir, I desire to know whether it is necessary to mark the name of the mover on the ballot-paper, seeing that he is necessarily a member of the. Select Committee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I cannot see anything in the Standing Orders which would prevent that from being done. Standing order 277 says - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <quote>
                    <para>Unless otherwise ordered, all Select Committees shall consist of seven senators. </para>
                </quote>
                <para class="block">That does not say that the Senate shall not be authorized to order that the mover of the motion be a member. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Look at standing order 278. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0X</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PLAYFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Playford</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Iri South Australia the practice was to appoint the mover and six other members. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- We must be guided by our own Standing Orders. - I dp not think it is necessary for a senator to vote for the mover j he is required to vote for six other senators. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- - I do not rise, sir, to dispute your ruling, but to recall to your recollection the debate on that very point, in which, I think, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McGregor</inline> took part. We recognised that it was not desirable because a senator moved for a Select Committee that he should necessarily be on it. We decided that the Senate could if it chose, in making the selection by ballot,. leave out the name of- the mover. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There is really no question before the Chair. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CLEMONS, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Clemons</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I desire to know, sir, whether you rule that if by any chance the mover of this motion were excluded, trie ballot would be invalid on that ground. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I do not say anything of the sort. What I do say is that the Senate has already ordered, that the mover be a member df the Select Com- &#62;mittee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Millen</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can we vote for only six senators? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Yes. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Millen</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I decline to take part in the ballot. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1297</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTF</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCGREGOR, Gregor</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McGregor</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- As I have been referred to, I think that I might be allow&#39;ed to point out to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Clemons</inline> that I thoroughly understand the .position. If a motion were moved by an honorable senator for the appointment of a Select Committee, and it were, not distinctly stated in&#39; the. motion that the mover be a member of the Select &#39;Committee, his name could then be left out, but in this motion it is distinctly stated that the mover shall be on the Select Committee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KHE</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HIGGS, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Higgs</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I beg, sir, to draw your attention to standing order 278, which says that- - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <quote>
                    <para>The Senators to serve on a Select Committee shall bc nominated by the mover; but if one senator so demand, they shall be selected by ballot. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>I desire to ask you, sir, whether any honorable senator has demanded that a ballot shall take place? </para>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- No. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KHE</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HIGGS, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Higgs</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If an honorable senator has not so demanded, will you call on <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce</inline> to nominate the senators whom he desires to serve on the Select Committee. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- No. What I understand the standing order to mean is that if an honorable senator moving a motion for a Select Committee wishes to nominate the members he can do <inline font-style="italic">so,</inline> but it is for the Senate to appoint them. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KPE</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Keating</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Are we to strike out seven or six names on the ballot-paper? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable and learned senator can strike out seven names if he includes that of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce,</inline> otherwise he must strike out six names. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para class="italic">
                    <inline font-style="italic">A ballot having been taken,</inline>
                </para>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>1298</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have to announce that the Select Committee will consist of Senators Findley, Gray, Keating, Playford, Stewart, Styles, and the mover, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce.</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce)</inline> agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para class="block"> That the Select Committee have power to call for persons, papers, and records, and to report this day month. </para>
                </quote>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PRIVILEGE : FREEDOM&#34; OF SPEECH</title>
                <page.no>1298</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">The Order of the Day for the bringing up of the report of the Select Committee, on the case of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator J-t.-Col.</inline> Neild, having been read; Motion (bv <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Playford)</inline> agreed to - That the Committee have leave to extend the time for bringing up the report to this day fortnight. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>1298</page.no>
                <type>special adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McGregor)</inline> agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the Senate, at its rising, adjourn until Wednesday next. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <adjournment>
            <adjournmentinfo>
                <page.no>1298</page.no>
                <time.stamp>15:51:00</time.stamp>
            </adjournmentinfo>
            <para class="block">Senate adjourned at 3.51 p.m. </para>
        </adjournment>
    </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>