<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1938-09-21</date>
    <parliament.no>15</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>2</period.no>
    <chamber>REPS</chamber>
    <page.no>3</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para class="block">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA </para>
    <para class="block">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES. </para>
    <para class="block">FirstSessionoftheFifteenthParliament. (Second Period.) </para>
    <para class="block">House of Representatives. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1938-09-21</day.start>
      <para>The House of Representatives, on the 30th June, 1938, adjourned until a date and hour to be fixed by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker,</inline> and notified by him to each honorable member. The House met pursuant to such notification. </para>
      <para>
        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker (Hon. G. J. Bell)</inline>took the chair at 3 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ASSENT TO BILLS</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Assent to the following bills re ported :  - </para>
      <para>Ashmore and Cartier Islands Acceptance Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Canned Fruits Export Control Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Canned Fruits Export Charges Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Census and Statistics Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Citrus Fruit Bounty Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Dairy Produce Export Control Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Dried Fruits Export Control Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Empire Air Service (England to Australia) Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Excise Tariff 1938. </para>
      <para>Geneva Convention Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Income Tax Collection Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Meat Export Control Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>National Health and Pensions Insurance Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>National Health and Pensions Insurance (Employers&#39; Contributions) Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>National Health and Pensions Insurance (Employees&#39; Contributions) Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>New Guinea Loan Guarantee Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Passports Bill 1938. </para>
      <para>Scat of Government Acceptance Bill 1938. Supply Bill (No. 1) 1938. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>LATE HONORABLE JOHN BARNES</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>
        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. SPEAKER (Hon. G. J. Bell).I</inline>have to inform the House that I have received from <inline font-weight="bold">Mrs. Barnes,</inline> widow of the late Honorable John Barnes, a letter thanking the House for its resolution of sympathy. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>RETURN OF GOVERNORGENERAL</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>3</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>F4O</name.id>
            <electorate>Wilmot</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Prime Minister</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
            <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I desire to . announce to the House that  His Excellency  the GovernorGeneral, Lord Gowrie, will return to Australia on Saturday, the 24th September, and will assume the administration of the Government of the Commonwealth on that day. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</title>
          <page.no>3</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Czechoslovakia</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>3</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate>Wilmot</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Prime Minister</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - I had intended to-day to make a statement on the international situation generally, with special relation to the acute crisis which has arisen over Czechoslovakia. The negotiations following upon <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chamberlain&#39;s</inline> visit to Herr Hitler and the subsequent agreement between the British and French Cabinets upon a policy for the peaceful settlement of the Sudeten question are still proceeding, and have, at the moment, reached such a delicate stage that a premature statement, or even a loose word, might well imperil the peace of the world. In the circumstances, I feel that I cannot, and ought not, speak. I hope that I shall soon be in a position to make a full statement. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate>Fremantle</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>
              <inline font-style="italic">- hy leaveThe</inline>Opposition had intended that a full statement should be made and discussed to-day on the matter referred to by the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons).</inline> However, the Labour party&#39;s policy in regard to international affairs is well known, and there is not, nor will there be, any wavering in regard to it; it stands. We are advocates and supporters of peace. Therefore, we agree that nothing should be done or said to-day which might prejudice the efforts being made to secure a peaceful solution of the problem. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <para>Later:</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MC</name.id>
              <electorate>FAWKNER, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HOLT, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HOLT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the decision of the Government not to conduct a debate on international affairs at this stage can the Prime Minister give the House an assurance that full and prior consultation of all matters affecting Empire defence policy has proceeded between the British Government and the Government of the Commonwealth before proceedings are taken ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I suggest to honorable members that as it is not intended -to discuss international affairs at this stage, questions in regard to that subject should not be asked or answered. I ask honorable members to reserve such questions until a later stage. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>4</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HOME-CONSUMPTION PRICE FOR WHEAT</title>
          <page.no>4</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KK7</name.id>
              <electorate>WATSON, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JENNINGS, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr JENNINGS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Will the Prime Minister confirm the statement attributed to him in the press that in the event of excise powers being used to secure a homeconsumption price for wheat, flour and bread prices will not bc affected? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable member intimated to me that he intended to ask this question. My reply is - The statement, as issued, did not correctly convey that which was in the mind of the Government. The decision of the State governments to fix a home-consumption price for flour on the basis of a return of 4s. 8d. a bushel for wheat at country sidings, will require supplementary legislation by the Commonwealth to make the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">State acts effective. During its consideraation of the subject, the Commonwealth Government noted that flour prices would: be increased only to such a degree aswould make bread prices approximately those which ruled during last year, when no legislation on the lines contemplated, was in force. </para>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">Later:</inline>
          </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KOC</name.id>
              <electorate>WAKEFIELD, SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HAWKER, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HAWKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Minister give any information to the House as towhether the published statements of government policy with regard to the assistance of the  wheat  industry during, a period of low prices may be taken as accurate, and whether any steps haveactually been taken to carry out that policy up to the present? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7E</name.id>
              <electorate>COWPER, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>CP</party>
              <role>Minister for Commerce</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PAGE, Earle</name>
              <name role="display">Sir EARLE PAGE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- -I think that the Prime Minister, in reply to a question this afternoon, has already indicated, what steps the Government, in conjunction with the State governments, is prepared to take in connexion with thismatter. That is the official government policy, and the only one as far as I know that has been outlined by the Government. We have asked the States to proceed with their proposals, and they know exactly what we shall do. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KV7</name.id>
              <electorate>PARRAMATTA, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">STEWART, Frederick</name>
              <name role="display">Sir FREDERICK STEWART</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Prime Minister able to give an assurance that in considering methods of offering relief to the wheat-growers, the Government will do nothing to prejudice industries which depend on wheat offals as their essential foodstuffs? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Full consideration will be given to the matter raised by the honorable member. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KX7</name.id>
              <electorate>EAST SYDNEY, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WARD, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Prime Minister state whether the proposed plan agreed upon by the Commonwealth Government and certain State governments, with respect to the stabilization of the price of wheat, is in direct conflict with the expressed will of the people, as made known by the result of the marketing referendum ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>4</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The answer is &#34; No.&#34; </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>4</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZF</name.id>
              <electorate>BARTON, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LANE, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LANE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- -Will the Prime &#39;Minister give Parliament an opportunity to discuss the price that is to be fixed for home consumed wheat? Before deciding on 4s. 8d. a bushel as the home-consumption  price, will he have expert advice as to whether 3s. 6d. a bushel would not be fairer ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>5</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The fixation of the price of wheat is a matter with which the States will be concerned. The States will pass legislation dealing with the matter of fixing the price of wheat and supplementary legislation will be passed, I hope, by the Commonwealth Parliament. This Parliament will have a full opportunity to consider that legislation. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Prime Minister &#39; give this House an assurance that it will not -be asked to consider legislation dealing with the home-consumption price of wheat until the States have enacted their price fixation legislation? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>5</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- That is the intention of the Commonwealth Government. The States will do their part - they have undertaken unanimously to do it - and after . that has been done the necessary Commonwealth legislation will be introduced. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>Mr.WILSON.- I address this question to the Prime Minister, not with any discourtesy to the Minister for Commerce, but because I think the Prime Minister is more conversant with the matter. I should like to know if the right honorable gentleman has knowledge of any action taken by the Commonwealth Government, or by any State government, to give effect to the proposal for a home-consumption price of wheat for Australian farmers? </para>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>5</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have to-day tabled the report of the conference of State and Commonwealth Ministers in connexion with this matter. If the honorable mem-, ber would even read the newspapers he would not have to ask either the Minister for Commerce or myself the question which he has now submitted. He would know that the States came to an agreement,&#39; submitted it to the Commonwealth, and were promised that when the full Cabinet was present the Commonwealth Government would deal with the matter. The Government has intimated its approval of the plan, and its willingness to co-operate, and when the proposal comes before the House the honorable member will be in possession of all the information available in regard to it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AIR TRAVEL FOR MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT</title>
          <page.no>5</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZX</name.id>
              <electorate>BRISBANE, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party>FLP; ALP from 1936</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAWSON, George</name>
              <name role="display">Mr GEORGE LAWSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Prime Minister given further consideration to the request of honorable members residing in far-distant States to be permitted to use air travel during the time when the Parliament is in session, similar to that granted to honorable members from Tasmania? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The matter of the transport of honorable members comes primarily under the control of the Minister for the Interior. During a great part of the recent recess . that Minister was visiting the northern part of Australia, . but he has now taken this matter into consideration. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>OVERSEAS TRADE NEGOTIATIONS</title>
          <page.no>5</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Ang lo-American Agreement. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KQ8</name.id>
              <electorate>WANNON, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SCHOLFIELD, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr SCHOLFIELD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Commerce any comment to make on the report from the United States of America, that the rather negative results of the trade negotiations in London was due to the attitude of the delegation from Australia? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PAGE, Earle</name>
              <name role="display">Sir EARLE PAGE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- A statement cabled from New York appeared in the <inline font-style="italic">Canberra Times</inline> this morning, in which that suggestion was repudiated. The concluding paragraph of the statement is as follows :  - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>The Secretary of the Council <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lindsay Crawford),</inline> interviewed by the Australian Associated Press, said that he did not attribute delay in completing the Anglo-American agreement to Australia. He said that any delay could be attributable to complex problems under the Ottawa Agreement within the Umpire. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I think it will be found, when the agreement is concluded, that the response of Australia to assist world trade was most ready. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>5</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1L</name.id>
              <electorate>WIMMERA, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Alexander</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Referring to the recent overseas trade discussions at which the Commonwealth was represented by the Minister for Commerce and other members of the Cabinet, can the Minister inform the House whether the United States of America is to be given by Great Britain improved marketing facilities in the British market, by way of preferences.  or increased preferences or in any way, in connexion with dried fruits, wheat, or other primary products of American origin ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>SirEARLE PAGE. - It is my intention at the earliest possible moment to make a statement on the whole mission of the delegation overseas and to state the position clearly with regard to what has been done. The Anglo-American trade negotiations are at present incomplete and it is impossible to say what will be the final outcome until decisions have been reached. I venture to say, however, that the statements that will be made by me on these subjects will cover the point raised by the honorable member. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>NEWSPRINT INDUSTRY</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Mr.FORDE. - Has the Minister for Trade and Customs yet received the report and recommendations of the Tariff Board in regard to the establishment of the newsprint industry in Australia? </para>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>6</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KZR</name.id>
            <electorate>BALACLAVA, VICTORIA</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Yes, the report has been received, and a statement will be made by the Government, probably this week, in relation to it. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AIR-MAIL POSTAGE RATES</title>
          <page.no>6</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KNX</name.id>
              <electorate>WENTWORTH, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HARRISON, Eric</name>
              <name role="display">Mr E J HARRISON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In directing a question to the Minister representing the Postmaster-General, I point out by way of explanation that I have received from an authoritative body in New South Wales a statement that a parcel sent by air-liner to Tasmania at a cost of approximately 7s. would cost about 28s. if sent by air through the Post Office. I am told that Air Lines of Australia will carry parcels to Hobart by air at 9d. per lb., with a minimum charge of 2s., whilst the cost of sending a 1 lb. parcel through the Post Office to Hobart by air is 8s. 8d. If the parcel weighed more than 1 lb., the Post Office would charge letter rate for it, namely, 2d. per ounce, plus 3d. per half ounce for air mail, a total of 8d. per ounce. If a private individual can make arrangements with private air lines for the despatch of parcels at such reasonable rates, cannot the Postmaster-General&#39;s department supply similar facilities for the benefit of the people generally? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KXY</name.id>
              <electorate>EDEN-MONARO, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Minister without portfolio assisting the Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PERKINS, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr PERKINS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I cannot answer  the  question offhand, but I shall bring it under the notice of the PostmasterGeneral, and an answer will be furnished in due course. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>CANBERRA AMBULANCE</title>
          <page.no>6</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L07</name.id>
              <electorate>WERRIWA, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAZZARINI, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LAZZARINI</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Assistant Minister for Health say whether the report is correct that the Canberra ambulance recently broke down, and that a maternity case had to be transported to the local hospital by waggon? Has this matter been rectified, and has&#39; a proper and efficient service been provided in Canberra ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTY</name.id>
              <electorate>BARKER, SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>CP</party>
              <role>Minister without portfolio assisting the Minister for Commerce</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Archie</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ARCHIE CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have no knowledge as to the matter referred to in the first part of the honorable member&#39;s question, but I know that  approval  was given recently for the purchase of a new ambulance, notwithstanding the report that the present vehicle is in fairly good order.&#39; </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AIR SERVICES INQUIRY</title>
          <page.no>6</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KQ8</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SCHOLFIELD, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr SCHOLFIELD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Defence whether in view of the fears of the smaller air service companies that they may not be in a position to expand their services he is able to give the House any information in regard to the inquiry that is being made into air services, which may allay these fears ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KWC</name.id>
              <electorate>CALARE, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>CP</party>
              <role>Minister for Defence</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THORBY, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr THORBY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- A comprehensive survey is being made of the whole of the minor internal air services of Australia and it is expected that the report on the subject will be submitted to the Government in the near future. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PARLIAMENTARY SECRETARIES</title>
          <page.no>6</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>6</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In connexion with a report which has been published to the effect that the Government has appointed certain private members of the House as Parliamentary Under Secretaries, I ask the Prime Minister who these gentlemen are and what duties they will perform? Will they answer letters addressed to the department with which they are associated? Will they answer questions addressed to them in this House? What administrative or other duties will they&#39; perform? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I should have notified the House of the appointment of the honorable member for Corangamite <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Street)</inline> as Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Defence, and the  honorable member for Macquarie <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. John Lawson)</inline> as Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer. These honorable gentlemen will not answer questions in the House. Questions will be answered by Ministers. The Parliamentary Secretaries will co-operate with Ministers in administrative work. Letters should be addressed to the Ministers, who are the heads of the heads of the departments, and not to the Parliamentary Secretaries. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>7</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE</title>
          <page.no>7</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KV7</name.id>
              <electorate>PARRAMATTA, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">STEWART, Frederick</name>
              <name role="display">Sir FREDERICK: STEWART</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the increasing importance of the matters discussed at the International Labour Conference at Geneva, I ask the Prime Minister whether in the future, in selecting representatives of the employers and of the Government, the same practice will be followed as in selecting representatives of employees, who are selected from the whole field of appropriate candidates in Australia? Hitherto,  in  selecting the Government representative and the representative of the employers, the Government has depended upon the almost adventitious presence of certain persons on the other side of the world at the time the conference is held. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The practice that has been followed in selecting other than the representatives of the employees has been, as the honorable member has intimated; but I do not think that there is any need for criticism or reflections, for suitable persons have always been chosen, and they have, been good representative Australians. However, the honorable member&#39;s suggestion in connexion with future selections will be given consideration. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>7</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>RIFLE CLUBS</title>
          <page.no>7</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KQB</name.id>
              <electorate>GWYDIR, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SCULLY, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr SCULLY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Defence whether he will reconsider the rejected applications of a number of proposed new country rifle clubs for assistance? These particular bodies have been refused assistance by the Defence Department on the ground that the vote for rifle clubs for this financial year has been exhausted. As rifle clubs are of vital importance to the adequate defence - of the Commonwealth, will the Minister have funds made available immediately to enable new clubs to be formed? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KWC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THORBY, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr THORBY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The whole subject of rifle clubs, particularly the formation of new rifle clubs, is at present receiving the consideration of the Military Board, and upon receiving advice from the Board the Government will give further attention to the question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SUBSIDIES FOR AIR LINES</title>
        <page.no>7</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>7</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KMW</name.id>
            <electorate>PARKES, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MARR, Charles</name>
            <name role="display">Sir CHARLES MARR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I direct the attention of the Minister for Defence to a report which appeared in the press . recently that the Government intended to subsidize a company known as Airlines of Australia, which is operating in Queensland. As this company has been able to reduce passenger fares by &#163;2 or &#163;3 each just recently, and as it is owned and controlled by Australian National Airways, which is controlled by the Peninsula and Oriental Company- </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>7</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SPEAKER, Mr</name>
            <name role="display">Mr SPEAKER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Order 1 The honorable member is giving information, not asking a question. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KMW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MARR, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Sir CHARLES MARR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Does the Government consider that in view of the situation that I have outlined, this particular company should receive a subsidy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>7</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KWC</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party>CP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">THORBY, Harold</name>
            <name role="display">Mr THORBY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I have not read the newspaper paragraph to which the honorable member has referred. Subsidies have, been granted to certain air lines which are co-operating with the Postal Department in the carrying of mail matter. I have no information at hand concerning the specific case mentioned by the honorable member, but I shall have inquiries made and furnish him with the information received. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>7</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SANDY BAY RIFLE RANGE</title>
          <page.no>7</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>7</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLC</name.id>
              <electorate>DENISON, TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MAHONEY, Gerald</name>
              <name role="display">Mr MAHONEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister for Defence in a position to say whether the tension in Europe is the result of the  Commonwealth Government not being able to reach an agreement with the Hobart City Council concerning the removal of the Sandy Bay Rifle Range ?&#39;  &#34;Will tlie honorable gentleman take immediate steps to conclude this agreement and remove the rifle range from its present site? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Question not answered. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>8</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>IRON ORE DEPOSITS</title>
          <page.no>8</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>8</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JVR</name.id>
              <electorate>PERTH, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">NAIRN, Walter</name>
              <name role="display">Mr NAIRN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister for the Interior able to give honorable members any. idea when the examination of the iron ore deposits at Yampi Sound is likely to be completed? Will he also tell us whether he made a statement recently to the effect that it was estimated that the deposits at Yampi were approximately 57,000,000 tons ? On &#39;whose report was that estimate based, and may the report be made available to the public? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>8</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MB</name.id>
              <electorate>INDI, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>CP</party>
              <role>Minister for the Interior</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not able to give the honorable member any accurate estimate of the time likely to be occupied in making the survey of the Yampi Sound iron ore deposits. . The work is being done by the Mines Department of Western Australia acting in co-operation with the Commonwealth Geological Adviser. At present it is believed that the survey will not be concluded in less than six months, but it is quite impossible to gauge accurately the time likely to be occupied by it. <inline font-style="italic">As</inline> to the extent of the deposits, I said that among other estimates made of the quantity of iron ore at Yampi one was 63,000,000 tons. That estimate was&#39; made by officers of the North Australian Geological Survey. I shall inquire whether it is possible to make that report available to the public. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>8</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KFE</name.id>
              <electorate>SWAN, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GREGORY, Henry</name>
              <name role="display">Mr GREGORY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Will the Minister for the Interior inform me whether he desires honorable members to understand that the Mines Department of Western Australia is making its investigation for the purpose of trying to determine the quantity of iron ore at Yampi? Is the Minister aware of the enormous amount of tunnelling which it is considered will be necessary to enable an estimate to be made? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>8</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009MB</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The position with regard to the conduct of this survey is that the Commonwealth Government intimated to the Western Australian Government, as it did to other State governments, its intention that such a survey should be made, and offered that, should the State governments so desire, they would have an opportunity to con duct the survey through their own Mines Departments, the expense being borne by the Commonwealth. The Western Australian Government elected to conduct the survey itself. The Commonwealth Geological Adviser and the Geological Adviser of the Western Australian Government proceeded together to Yampi Sound, and there agreed upon the work necessary to be done in order to conduct the survey. The work now in progress is work of a nature mutually agreed upon by the Commonwealth and State Geological Advisers. Naturally, no new estimate of the ore resources can be made at this stage, because that is the purpose of the survey. As to the cost of the survey, preliminary estimates have, of course, been made, but it is not possible. I believe, to make further estimates of cost at this stage. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>8</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JNX</name.id>
              <electorate>BASS, TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- 13 the Minister for the Interior in a position to say whether, as the result of the visit to Tasmania of <inline font-weight="bold">Dr. Woolnough,</inline> that gentleman himself has made a survey of the iron ore deposits in that State; whether ho has made arrangements with the State Government for its Mines Department to conduct the survey, whether any report has been received by the Government on the subject, and, if so, whether it can be made available to honorable members and, if not, when it is likely to be made available? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>8</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009MB</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The Government of Tasmania has asked that the survey of the iron ore resources of that State be undertaken by the Commonwealth Government. <inline font-weight="bold">Dr. Woolnough</inline> has visited Tasmania and preliminary arrangements are now in hand for the conduct of the survey by Commonwealth officers. No report is yet available. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>8</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>GEOLOGICAL AND GEOPHYSICAL SURVEY</title>
          <page.no>8</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>8</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Treasurer if it is a fact that the amount spent on geophysical research in Australia exceeds the &#163;75,000 specified as the maximum Commonwealth liability in the act? If that is so, from what other votes has additional money been provided, and how has parliamentary authorization been secured for expenditure in -excess of that specified in the statute? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate>CORIO, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Treasurer</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have not exactly in mind the total expenditure by the Commonwealth on the North Australia geophysical and geological survey. Speaking from memory, an extension of the work was decided on by the Government, I think, about twelve months ago. I shall obtain the information and make it available to the honorable member at an early date. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>9</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COAL STRIKE</title>
          <page.no>9</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KJQ</name.id>
              <electorate>HUNTER, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JAMES, Rowland</name>
              <name role="display">Mr JAMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the fact that both the Leader of the Opposition and myself, prior to the close of the sittings of the House in June last, drew attention to the pending dispute on the coal-fields, why has the Prime Minister said in a press statement that he had never been approached to bring the parties together? How can he claim that he had not been asked until recently to bring about a conference of the parties to the dispute? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- First of all, when I said that I had not been approached in regard to this matter I very clearly meant, that I had not been approached by a person associated with the union. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KJQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">JAMES, Rowland</name>
                <name role="display">Mr James</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I am a member of the union, and I was requested by it to ask the right honorable gentleman to call such a conference. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- That was never intimated to me. &#39;Communications in regard to matters of this kind must come from officials of the union. I had not been approached to intervene in the dispute until recently when the Leader of the Opposition induced union representatives to come to Canberra and discuss the matter with me and asked me if I would be prepared to discuss it&#39; with them. I then made it perfectly clear that the attitude of the Government was that 11 tribunal had been appointed to settle matters of this kind, that if the dispute was confined to a State a State tribunal could deal with it, and that if it reached interstate proportions the Federal Arbitration Court could deal with it. Recently the Federal Arbitration Court, through one of its judges, has called a compulsory conference. I hope that that will have the effect of bringing tho parties together, and of inducing the men to go back to work. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>9</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NATIONAL HEALTH AND PENSIONS INSURANCE</title>
          <page.no>9</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLL</name.id>
              <electorate>HINDMARSH, SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MAKIN, Norman</name>
              <name role="display">Mr MAKIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Government, or the commission dealing with national health and pensions insurance, yet determined whether or not Commonwealth and State employees are to be covered by the scheme? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I take it that the honorable member refers only to certain classes and sections of Commonwealth and State employees. That matter is in hand. It is first necessary to examine the conditions under which various classes of public servants work. That examination is not yet complete. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>9</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is it a fact that the commission appointed under the provisions of the National Health and Pensions Insurance Act, has arranged that approved societies will be paid ls. for every insured person who joins their membership? If so, will this not involve an expenditure of approximately &#163;90,000 in order to ensure the enrolment of persons who, under the act, are obliged to join approved societies, and who, moreover, in the event of a society not being named by them, will be allotted by the commission to such society as it thinks fit? In the circumstances, what is the justification for the expenditure of so large a sum of money? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The honorable, gentleman is correct. The justification of the payment is the recoupment of the approved societies approximately the amount of clerical and other expenditure to which they will be put in starting the approved societies and in the initial enrolment of members. The commission does not believe that the amount , of 3 s. a head is at all excessive as the amount essential to recoup that initial expenditure. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Would the Treasurer take objection to an approved society paying ls. a head to a canvasser&#34; for each new mem&#39;ber that he brings into the society? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The honorable gentleman asks me if the Government has anything to say about approved societies paying canvassers for new members that they may introduce. That is not a matter which is within the concern of the Government. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  That is what the money is being used for. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- In that ease the approved society is denying itself the use of the amount for which it is intended. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>10</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L07</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAZZARINI, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LAZZARINI</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Treasurer seen the- statement of the honorable member for Riverina <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Nock)</inline> at a meeting of the Farmers and Settlers&#39; Association that it is the intention of the Government to introduce a supplementary national insurance scheme within the next twelve months with the object of covering small farmers? If so, is it in accordance with Government policy and does the Treasurer intend to introduce .legislation to establish such a scheme within the next twelve months? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have not seen the statement referred to. On behalf of the Government, I have nothing to add to the statements made by the right honorable the Prime Minister and myself during the debate on the national insurance proposals last session. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>10</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JOM</name.id>
              <electorate>WEST SYDNEY, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BEASLEY, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BEASLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- &#39;Can the Treasurer inform the House as to the number of appointments that have been made to the department of the National Health and Pensions Insurance Commission, and the number of appeals lodged ? is it intended to appoint persons outside the Public Service to any positions in the department? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- As to the first part <inline font-style="italic">oi</inline> the question, I shall be glad to got the information sought and make it available to the honorable member. I understand that the Public Service Commissioner, in terms of the Public Service Act, is obliged to confine his choice to persons within the Service, unless he is conscientiously able to say that the post cannot be filled from within the Service. I understand that very few appointments have been made up to the present time of persons outside the Service. Possibly only one such appointment has been made - a professional person. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JOM</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BEASLEY, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BEASLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Was that an actuary? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Yes, I think so. There may have been one other such appointment. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>L07</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LAZZARINI, Hubert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LAZZARINI</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Is the Treasurer aware that many large employers of labour are forming approved societies under the National Health and Pensions Insurance Act, and that in the formation of these societies the covert threat is held out to the employees that they will lose their employment if they do not join the bosses&#39; organization? Will the Minister see that the provision of the Act which lays down that all persons shall have a free choice as to which society they join is not abrogated by the implied threat of these employers? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The present time is one of great competition between those persons who wish to form approved societies. The National Insurance Commission has become aware of quite a large number of unwarranted statements that have been made in circulars issued by one or other of those persons forming approved societies. The statements to which the commission has taken exception are by no means confined to those which originate with employers&#39; organizations. In all cases where the commission has found that unjustified statements have been made it has taken steps at once, by correspondence or otherwise, to notify the persons concern-ed of such statements. It is hoped that approved societies will be formed under fair conditions. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>10</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NATIONAL INCOME</title>
          <page.no>10</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Commonwealth Bank&#39;s Credit Policy</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>10</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KOQ</name.id>
              <electorate>MARTIN, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCALL, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McCALL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the substantial reduction of national income due to the fall of the value of primary products and to the effects of drought throughout Australia, can the Treasurer indicate to the House any steps that the Commonwealth Bank has taken in regard to credit policy which would mitigate the effects of the reduced income on the community as a whole? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>10</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. I do not think that it would be in the public interest to state specifically the steps taken by the Commonwealth Bank, other than to say that it is in close touch with the situation and, within the limits of sound finance, is prepared to act should there be a recession of Australian activities. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>10</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING COMMISSION</title>
          <page.no>10</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>10</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4U</name.id>
              <electorate>CAPRICORNIA, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FORDE, Francis Michael</name>
              <name role="display">Mr FORDE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Prime Minister in a position to make a statement regarding the proposed re-organization of the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Australian Broadcasting Commission? In particular, can he say that the commission will not be permitted to exercise in an arbitrary manner the power to prevent prominent citizens, such as the Premier of Queensland, from broadcasting addresses on non-party political subjects, as was done on a previous occasion when the broadcasting of addresses by the Premier of Queensland, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forgan</inline> Smith, and the Treasurer of that State, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Cooper,</inline> at an Anglican church communion breakfast was refused? </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government has under consideration certain suggestions for an improvement of the methods of control of the  Australian  Broadcasting Commission, but I am afraid that I am not able to agree to make any provision for dictation to the commission as to how it shall carry out its duties. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>11</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4U</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">FORDE, Francis Michael</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Forde</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The right honorable gentleman is satisfied so long as the dictation comes from the Government. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>11</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4O</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
                <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Like the Premier of Queensland, I, too, have been subjected to limitations in the broadcasting of addresses. As has been pointed out on previous occasions, the Australian Broadcasting Commission has specified certain hours within which broadcasts may be made. It makes no discrimination against individuals or churches, but it does prescribe the hours during which .broadcasts may be made. So far as I am aware, the only broadcasts of the nature referred to which have been refused have been those asked for at hours earlier than the opening hour for the day. I should not attempt to dictate to the commission in this connexion, even though I myself have been affected by its decision. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>11</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MOTOR CAR MANUFACTURE IN AUSTRALIA</title>
          <page.no>11</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KFS</name.id>
              <electorate>HENTY, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GULLETT, Henry</name>
              <name role="display">Sir HENRY GULLETT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is it correct, as reported in the <inline font-style="italic">Canberra Times,</inline> that the Government intends to abandon the proposal to manufacture motorcar chassis in Australia? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The report in the <inline font-style="italic">Canberra Times</inline> is entirely unauthorized and misleading. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>11</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It may be unauthorized, but is it really misleading? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>11</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It is misleading. A statement on the subject of motor-car manufacture in Australia should be made to the House this week and the report of the Tariff Board on the subject will be tabled. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>11</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>OREGON</title>
          <page.no>11</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KNX</name.id>
              <electorate>WENTWORTH, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HARRISON, Eric</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HARRISON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Trade and Customs given consideration to the report by the Department of the Interior on Oregon, and, if so, when will the decision of the Government be conveyed to this House? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The report has been received, but in view of the necessity to deal with more important matters it has not yet been considered by the Government. I expect to make a statement on the&#39; subject next week. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>11</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SHIP-BUILDING INDUSTRY</title>
          <page.no>11</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JOM</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BEASLEY, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BEASLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is it correct, as reported, that the Department of Trade and Customs is conducting an inquiry into the ship-building industry? If so, can the Minister give the personnel of the body conducting the inquiry, and can he say how far the inquiry has proceeded, and whether a report will be submitted to Parliament? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There has been a departmental inquiry and a report on the subject was received yesterday. So far, it has not been considered by the Government. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>11</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>IMMIGRATION</title>
          <page.no>11</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KOC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HAWKER, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HAWKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Oan the Minister for the Interior say what steps, if any, are being taken with regard to the admission into Australia of either refugees generally from Germany and Austria, or alternatively, non-Jewish refugees? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>11</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MB</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- As to the latter part of the honorable member&#39;s .question, it is the policy of the Government that there shall be no discrimination . as between nations in regard to the immigration of white aliens. The Commonwealth Government arranged that the Minister for Trade and Customs should represent it at the international conference held at  Evain,  when the problem of refugee Jews from Central European countries was discussed. The Government has not yet had an opportunity to consider the report submitted by the Minister. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>OIL RESEARCH</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KFS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GULLETT, Henry</name>
              <name role="display">Sir HENRY GULLETT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Oan the Minister for the Interior inform the House whether the whole of the &#163;250,000 set aside as a subsidy for the search for oil has been expended, and can he say how much of the money expended has been paid to boring companies and how much has been absorbed by salaries and other expenses? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MB</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There is a statutory obligation to table in the Parliament an annual statement setting out the particulars sought by the honorable member. Within the next day or two, I hope to table a return containing the information asked for by him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>CANBERRA MILK SUPPLY</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLM</name.id>
              <electorate>MELBOURNE, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MALONEY, William</name>
              <name role="display">Dr MALONEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for the Interior - (1) Whether, in view of the awful disclosures in the late case an the courts regarding the terrible supply of milk to the Federal City, the Health Department has taken efficient measures to provide that the milk . supply shall he safe for drinking without the necessity of sterilizing or boiling it? (2) What is the present proportion of estimated tubercular cows in the Territory ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MB</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think that this is a question which should properly he directed to the Minister for Health; but I am. able to inform the honorable member that just recently the Canberra Dairy Society has opened a new depot, where all milk is received and treated, before distribution in Canberra. I am sure that the Minister- for Health will secure the statistics sought. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN TRADE</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLL</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MAKIN, Norman</name>
              <name role="display">Mr MAKIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- During his recent visit abroad, did the Attorney-General visit Europe with a view to surveying trade possibilities in the various countries on the Continent? If he did, will this Parliament have the advantage of receiving from him a report upon such possibilities ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>N76</name.id>
              <electorate>KOOYONG, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Attorney-General</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MENZIES, Robert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr MENZIES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN FOOD COUNCIL</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HOLT, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HOLT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Department of Commerce reached any decision as to the practicability of setting up in Australia a food council similar to that established in Great Britain to examine the distribution and consumption of essential foodstuffs ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTY</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Archie</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ARCHIE CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That question is still under consideration, and. in view of a certain report which will be tabled shortly dealing with some aspects of it, it will require still further consideration. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EXPLOITATION OF NATIVES IN NEW GUINEA</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KJQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JAMES, Rowland</name>
              <name role="display">Mr JAMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for External Affairs whether it is a fact that in the Mandated Territory of New Guinea recruiting officers go into the native villages, recruit natives and sell them to farms, plantations and mines for the sum of &#163;10 a head? Is it also a fact that these natives are contracted to work for 10s. a month and their keep, which consists of sweet potatoes-? If this is correct, will the labour that is proposed to be used for the construction of a new road, for which &#163;250,000 has been made available by the Commonwealth Government, be exploited in a similar manner by the contractors? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DQC</name.id>
              <electorate>NORTH SYDNEY, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HUGHES, William Morris</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HUGHES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Many of the things to which the honorable member for Hunter referred come as news to me. I know nothing at all about sweet potatoes or any of those matters. It is not a fact that the Commonwealth Government has expended or contemplates expending &#163;250,000 on a road. The only road that is to be built is to be built by those persons who have interests in New Guinea. They will find the money and will build the roam As the honorable member has a passion for information, however, I . shall make inquiries myself and, when I have information about the things of which he has spoken, I shall pass it on to him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>12</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>VALUE OF EXPORTS</title>
          <page.no>12</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KFE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GREGORY, Henry</name>
              <name role="display">Mr GREGORY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Will the  Treasurer,  in delivering his budget speech, be able to supply an estimate of the value of Australian exports in the current year? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>12</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. I am sure that that is .in the lap of the gods. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MINISTERIAL VISIT OVERSEAS</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JSC</name.id>
              <electorate>BATMAN, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BRENNAN, Frank</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BRENNAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the right honorable Minister for Commerce whether I am correctly informed that a great deal of the time of the London conference, at which he was present with the Attorney-General, was devoted to an effort to reconcile the conflicting views of the Attorney-General, representing one branch of the party, and of the Minister for Commerce, representing another branch, and whether at this critical period the Minister for Trade and -Customs was presenting a posy to the Mayor of Brighton, England, with an expression of goodwill from the Mayor and Mayoress of Brighton, Victoria. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PAGE, Earle</name>
              <name role="display">Sir EARLE PAGE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I assure the honorable member that during our discussions the Attorney-General and the Minister for Trade and Customs always concurred with the Minister for Commerce and presented a united and very satisfactory front. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PROTECTION OF ABORIGINES</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4U</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FORDE, Francis Michael</name>
              <name role="display">Mr FORDE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for the Interior - (a) When is the reported new policy for aborigines to be formulated and discussed in Parliament? <inline font-style="italic">(b)</inline> When and where is the conference of protectors of aborigines to be held? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009MB</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCEWEN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McEWEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- At a very early date I shall be submitting to the Government for its consideration certain proposals dealing with aborigines policy as it may be carried out or instituted by the Commonwealth within its own territory. No conference of protectors of aborigines is projected; one was held about twelve months ago. The Ministers responsible for the administration of native affairs in the States will be asked to meet in conference with the Commonwealth Minister concerned - myself, at the present time - to consider aboriginal affairs on a wider basis. That conference will probably be held early in the new year. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MANUFACTURE OF NEWSPRINT</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KV7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">STEWART, Frederick</name>
              <name role="display">Sir FREDERICK STEWART</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Trade and Customs yet received from the Tariff Board its report on its investigation of the proposal to commence the manufacture of newsprint in Australia? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Probably the honorable member came into the chamber late; I answered a similar question earlier in the day. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEFENCE FORCES</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Queensland Battalions</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZX</name.id>
              <electorate>BRISBANE, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party>FLP; ALP from 1936</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAWSON, George</name>
              <name role="display">Mr GEORGE LAWSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Defence, in view  of  the proposal of the Defence Department to merge certain Queensland Australian Imperial Force battalions and to alter the unit numbers of others as a consequence of the gazettal of the Queensland Cameron Highlanders as the 15th Battalion, and further, in view  of  the many protests made to his department by the Queensland Australian Imperial Force units and other returned soldier organizations, has he given further consideration to the subject as promised by him to a deputation of returned soldiers in Brisbane recently? If so, what decision has been arrived at in order to safeguard the traditions associated with wartime units? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KWC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THORBY, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr THORBY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- When I was in Brisbane recently, several deputations waited upon me and made representations in connexion with the proposal to unlink certain battalions and create a new battalion, the 15th. These representations have been submitted to the Military Board and I am awaiting a recommendation and advice from that body. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SIR GEORGE PEARCE</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KJQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JAMES, Rowland</name>
              <name role="display">Mr JAMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Treasurer yet in a position to reply to the question which I asked on the 21st June last, regarding the total amount received by <inline font-weight="bold">Sir George</inline> Pearce during the period when he was in Parliament, by way of salary as a private member, and salary and allowance as a Minister ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I regret if the question lias not yet been answered, but I shall take note of it now, and see that the honorable gentleman is given the information he desires if it is available. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN CUT-GLASS INDUSTRY</title>
          <page.no>13</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZF</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LANE, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LANE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Minister for Trade and Customs state when the Tariff Board&#39;s report on the cut-glass industry will be laid on the table of the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>House? I point out that it is two years since the board&#39;s last report was tabled. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is not correct. The first report was tabled over two years ago, but, owing to the closing down of certain sections of the industry, there has been a more recent inquiry. The report on this investigation has been received by the Government and is now under consideration. Negotiations are in progress between the Trade Treaty sections of the Department of Trade and Customs and one of the countries engaged in the export of cut glass. I expect to announce the result shortly. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">Later:</inline>
          </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L08</name.id>
              <electorate>DALLEY, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ROSEVEAR, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ROSEVEAR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister for Trade and Customs aware that the employers in the cut-glass industry have repeatedly said that they would be unable to find employment for some hundreds of men who have been out of work for the last nine months until they could get favorable consideration of their requests for more protection from the Tariff Board or the Government? I desire to know further whether the complications which have arisen, and have prevented the Tariff Board and the Government from doing justice to this industry, arise out of the Czechoslovak trade treaty? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not wish to give further details with regard to this industry than I gave in reply to a previous question. I said that the matter would be finalized shortly. The Government is most concerned over the fact that 400 men are out of work owing to the closing of that branch of the industry, but, if negotiations succeed, it hopes to announce within a few days that the men will have an opportunity to return to work. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>14</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NEW GUINEA CAPITAL</title>
          <page.no>14</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate>RICHMOND, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ANTHONY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for External Affairs whether a final determination has yet been made in connexion with the selection of a site for the new capital of New Guinea? A paragraph has appeared in the press stating that there would be a reconsideration of the claims of Salamaua and Lae. I should also like to know if the report of the Griffiths committee on this subject is to be made available to honorable members? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DQC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HUGHES, William Morris</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HUGHES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Answering the last part of the honorable member&#39;s question  first, I point out that the report of the Griffiths committee was laid on the table of the House some months ago. I am rather surprised that the honorable gentleman has not seen it. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>14</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have seen one copy. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>14</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DQC</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">HUGHES, William Morris</name>
                <name role="display">Mr HUGHES</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It is well worth reading. With regard to the rest of the honorable member&#39;s question, there has been no further decision by the Government. The honorable member has, no doubt, read with some interest paragraphs which have appeared in the press from time to time with regard to Salamaua and Lae and other places. We are still searching diligently for the right site. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KMW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MARR, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Sir CHARLES MARR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- . Can the Minister state if the report in the press that the Administrator of New Guinea has left on a trip to China has anything to do with this diligent search for a new capital for New Guinea? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>14</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DQC</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">HUGHES, William Morris</name>
                <name role="display">Mr HUGHES</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have not heard that it has. It is a fact, however, that the Administrator has applied for and been granted four months&#39; leave of absence. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>14</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY</title>
          <page.no>14</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KOQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCALL, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr McCALL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Defence been informed of the statement by Admiral <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Howard</inline> Kelly, one of the world&#39;s highest naval authorities, that Australia is in urgent need of a battleship? Has the Minister any statement  to make regarding the further suggestion of the admiral that it would be in the immediate interests of Australia to exchange two of our cruisers for a battleship? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KWC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THORBY, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Mr THORBY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My attention has been directed to the statement by a certain admiral, and all I have to say is that the policy of the Commonwealth Government in naval matters has been adopted on the best advice of the highest naval experts in the Empire. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>14</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>IMPORTATION OF MOTORCARS</title>
          <page.no>14</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>14</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KHL</name.id>
              <electorate>MELBOURNE, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HOLLOWAY, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HOLLOWAY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Will the Minister for Trade and Customs inform the House whether there are insurmountable obstacles &#39;which prevent Australian automotive distributors from transferring any portion of their quota of motor vehicles now coming from the United States of America to Canada? If there are no objections, will the Minister allow officers of the department to assist those persons who wish to make that transfer ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The matter has been already investigated by the department, but it is too soon to say what the result will be. Many firms are not importing up to the full limit of their quotas. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KOC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HAWKER, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HAWKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister for Trade and Customs aware that certain importers of motor vehicles from North America who are npt filling the .quotas allowed to them are selling quotas to other distributors? If he is not aware of this trafficking in quotas, will he have the matter investigated, and seek to see that quotas are made available as far &#39;as possible to other distributors who are handling cars which the public are desirous of buying, without their having to pay a special levy to certain importers or distributors who are thus increasing their profit at the expense of the purchasers of other cars ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>15</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The honorable member is scarcely correct in saying that there is a trafficking in quotas. Some makes of cars have gone off the market, and other makes are being obtained through the same firms; but, if the honorable member gives me a specific instance of what he has in mind, I shall have a full inquiry made and a reply will be furnished to him. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>15</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DOMINIONS OFFICE</title>
          <page.no>15</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JSC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BRENNAN, Frank</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BRENNAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- With regard to the reported conflict of opinion between the Prime Minister and the Minister for External Affairs as to the Dominions Office, has the Prime Minister taken any action in regard to the matter? Has he made any representations to the Dominions Office or to the Minister for External Affairs.? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>15</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ITALIAN CRUISER RAIMONDO MONTECUCCOLI</title>
          <page.no>15</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">Incident at Post Melbourne. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JSC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BRENNAN, Frank</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BRENNAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister for External Affairs yet in a position to make the statement promised some months ago in regard to the representations made, or said to have been made, on the question of payment of compensation to one.  Frigo  Orlando, who was assaulted and injured on an Italian cruiser in one of the ports of Melbourne? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DQC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HUGHES, William Morris</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HUGHES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Yes, I am in a position to make a further statement. Following upon my assurance to the honorable gentleman, when he called the attention of the House and the country to the injuries suffered by Frigo Orlando, I saw the new Italian Consul-General, and I discussed the matter with him at great length. He gave me the benefit of his views, and I corrected him on points of fact. I was able to present him with the depositions of Orlando, and with the first-hand evidence that was available to the department. The Consul-General professed himself greatly impressed by them, and asked for an opportunity to review the position in the light of these facts. There the matter rests. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>15</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ABOLITION OF SLUMS</title>
          <page.no>15</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L07</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAZZARINI, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LAZZARINI</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Prime Minister seen the statement of <inline font-weight="bold">Dr. H.</inline> G. Wallis, Director of Tuberculosis in New South Wales, in which he says that tuberculosis is the greatest producer of widows and orphans, and is caused by poverty-stricken conditions? In view of that statement, does the Prime Minister intend to give effect to his election promise to abolish slums?&#39; </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I need only answer the latter part of the question. I gave no assurance in regard to the abolition of slums, because it is not possible for the Commonwealth Government to do that. The slums fall within the jurisdiction of the State authorities, and they constitute a difficult problem for the States. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>15</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>JUDGE WELLS</title>
          <page.no>15</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>15</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KJQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JAMES, Rowland</name>
              <name role="display">Mr JAMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- During the visit by the Minister for the Interior to the Northern Territory, did he come in contact with Judge Wells ? If so, did he keep in mind the strictures passed by the honorable member for Batman, and what was his reaction ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Question not answered. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>BULK HANDLING OF WHEAT</title>
          <page.no>16</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L08</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ROSEVEAR, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ROSEVEAR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Assistant Minister for Health yet had an opportunity to peruse the report of the Commonwealth medical officers into the effect of wheat, dust on the general health of those who handle bulk wheat? If so, does the Government consider the findings of the board to be of sufficient importance to take action to compel the employers of these men at least to provide proper respirators for them while working on bulk wheat? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTY</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Archie</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ARCHIE CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have not yet had an opportunity to examine the report, but, as soon as I am able to do so, I shall make recommendations to Cabinet, and the decision of the Cabinet will be conveyed to the honorable member. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ESTIMATES 1938-39</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Messages reported transmitting Estimates of Revenue and Expenditure and Estimates of Expenditure for Additions, New Works, Buildings, &#38;c, for the year ending the 30th June, 1939, and recommending appropriations accordingly. </para>
      <para>Ordered to be printed, and referred to Committee of Supply. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>BUDGET 1938-39</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>In Committee of Supply:</title>
          <page.no>16</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate>Corio</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Treasurer</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - In spite of considerable difficulties created by overseas developments, the past year has been one of appreciable economic advance in Australia. The&#34; wide fluctuations and instability experienced in many important oversea countries have not been, to any appreciable extent, reflected in Australia as a whole. Indeed, we may congratulate ourselves on the degree of resistance that Australia has shown to adverse oversea influences. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>In regard to employment in Australia, the average trade union unemployment percentage in 1936-37 was 10.6 and in 1937-38 it was8.5. A slight increase occurred in the last quarter of the financial year, the latest available figure being 8.6 per cent. </para>
          <para>The value of Australian recorded material production, which had fallen to &#163;305,000,000 in 1931-32, reached &#163;456,000,000 in 1936-37, and the final results for 1937-38 will probably showabout the same figure. But for the unfortunate decline of export prices, which began in May, 1937, the value of production for 1937-38 would, of course, have reached a considerably higher level. </para>
          <para>Building activity continued to expand in 1937-38 from its previous high level. The value of building permits issued in Australia in 1937-38, apart from governmental buildings, is estimated to have been approximately &#163;56,000,000, as compared . with about &#163;48,000,000 in 1936-37, and only about &#163;9,000,000 in 1931-32. </para>
          <para>The value of our wool clip was approximately &#163;52,600,000 in 1937-38, as compared with &#163;63,600,000 in 1936-37 The prospects for the coming year arc difficult to gauge, but it is not unreasonable to expect that any change will be for the better, particularly if the European political difficulties are overcome. </para>
          <para>Wheat has been heavily hit by falling prices. It is difficult to be optimistic about the prospects for wheat prices in the coming year. </para>
          <para>Taking our exports as a whole, average prices realized in 1937-38 were 12&#189; per cent, below those for 1936-37. However, although prices were down in 1937-38, the volume of exported production was appreciably higher, and our 1937-38 export income was but little below that of 1936-37- &#163;125,400,000 sterling against &#163;129,000,000 sterling. </para>
          <para>The investment of overseas capital in Australia also continued at a satisfactory rate, and the call on London funds was less than might, have been expected. The net drain on London funds in 1937-38 was probably not over &#163;10,000,000 sterling. Taking the last two years together, it is probable that at least &#163;15,000,000 sterling has been added to Australia&#39;s reserves of London funds. </para>
          <para>Prophecy as to the future entails speculation as to political and economic trends which at present are very confused. In the political sphere, particularly in Europe, one can only hope for the best. In the economic sphere, I do not believe that the situation is as disquieting as we might be led to believe. The recent trend towards recovery in the United  &#39;States  of America may well grow in strength sufficiently to offset and eventually to  change the hesitant and downward trends in some other countries. The favorable developments will have to be accelerated appreciably, however, if they are to make themselves feltbefore the bulk of our own export commodities of this season begin to be sold on the world&#39;s markets. </para>
          <para>I have already referred to the remarkable resistance that the Australian economy has shown towards adverse overseas developments. This may be attributed to some extent to an increased production, which has offset a decline of prices, but I believe that just as potent a factor has been the determination of those in charge of our institutions not to let their minds be unduly affected by every economic breeze that blows from overseas. </para>
          <para>The Board of the Commonwealth Bank is carefully watching business activities for any signs of recession. With the helpful co-operation of manufacturers and others, the Board is in a position to keep itself promptly and fully informed of current trends and, within the limits of sound finance, can be relied upon to use appropriate central banking measures to assist in counteracting or lessening a decline of activity. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PUBLIC DEBT</title>
        <page.no>17</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Loan Operations in London. </para>
      <para>Two loan operations were carried out in London during last financial year. The first was a conversion loan of &#163;11,410,000, which was carried out in November, 1937 at a rate to yield &#163;3 15s.1d. per cent, per annum. </para>
      <para>The second operation was a loan of &#163;7,000,000 sterling, which was arranged in May last. This was to provide &#163;2,000,000 for defence equipment purchases in Great Britain, and &#163;5,000,000 for the redemption of Australian treasurybills held by the Commonwealth Bank in London. The loan was floated at a rate to yield &#163;3 16s. 6d. per cent, per annum. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Internal Loans</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>During 1937-38 two loans were issued in the Australian market. The first, in November, 1937, was for &#163;8,000,000, at a rate to yield &#163;3 15s. 6d. per cent, per annum. The second was issued in May, 1938, for &#163;10,250,000, at a rate to yield &#163;3 15s.10d. per cent, per annum. </para>
        <para>Of the &#163;10,250,000, an amount of &#163;4,000,000 was for defence purposes, the balance being for the ordinary loan programmes of the Commonwealth and States. </para>
        <para>The Loan Council has agreed to the raising of &#163;14,000,000 in 1938-39 for the ordinary loan purposes of the Commonwealth and States. The Commonwealth share of this will be &#163;2,000,000, all of which is to be used for grants to the States for farmers&#39; debt adjustment purposes. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Conversion Loan</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The Loan Council will shortly undertake the task of arranging the first large conversion loan in Australia since the internal conversion of 1931. The amount of loans to be converted is about &#163;68,000,000, which falls due for repayment on the 15th December next. Of this amount &#163;6,000,000 carries interest at 3 per cent, and &#163;62,000.000 carries interest at 4 per cent. Approximately half of the ma turing loans represents Commonwealth debt, and the balance is debt of the various State governments. </para>
        <para>Sinking fund operations in recent years reduced these securities from the peak of &#163;78,000,000, and a further &#163;4,000,000 of sinking fund moneys will be available towards redemption of the loans before the15th December. </para>
        <para>The Loan Council is meeting in Melbourne next week to consider terms for the conversion of the maturing securities, and I anticipate that an offer of conversion to existing holders will be made late in October. </para>
        <para>Although the operation is a large one. I am confident of success. The cooperation of the Commonwealth Bank, the trading banks and the principal financial institutions is assured, and investors generally may be relied upon to support the operation. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Debt Redemption</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Since 1923 over &#163;80,000,000 has been provided for the redemption of Commonwealth debt. In addition, since States&#39; sinking funds were established in 1928, over &#163;41,000,000 of State debt has been redeemed by the national debt sinking fund. </para>
        <para class="block"> In the present financial year the receipts of the sinking fund will amount to &#163;10,830,000, of which &#163;4,930,000 will be payable to the Commonwealth sinking fund and &#163;5,900,000 to State sinking funds. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AGGREGATE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC DEBT</title>
        <page.no>18</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The movement in the aggregate public debt of the Commonwealth and States since the Lyons Government assumed office in December, 1931, is as follows: - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_15_0.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para>During this period of six and a half years the public debt of the Commonwealth itself decreased by &#163;7,084,000. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>FINANCIAL YEAR 1937-38</title>
        <page.no>18</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Before coming to the budget for the current year, I will deal briefly with the past year. The actual revenue and expenditure for 1937-38 resulted in an excess of revenue of &#163;3,494,733. Details of the revenue and expenditure compared with the budget estimates are as  folow:  - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_15_1.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_15_2.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_15_1.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_15_2.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para>The principal factor which contributed to the excess revenue was customs and excise revenue. The budget estimate for these revenue items was &#163;44,500,000, and the actual revenue &#163;48,3S3,000, an increase of &#163;3,883,000. . The difficulty of estimating customs and excise revenue is well known. The improvement over the estimate in this case was due to circumstances which could not be foreseen. Internal conditions continued very buoyant during 1937-38, despite the decline of export prices. Imports for the year just closed amounted to &#163;112,000,000 sterling compared with &#163;91,000,000 sterling for the previous year. </para>
      <para>Revenue receipts under headings other than those of customs and excise were close to the revenue estimates, as were also almost all of the expenditure items. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Excess Revenue of 1937-38</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>In view of the urgent and heavy demands for defence, the Government proposes to set aside the whole of the excess receipts of 1937-38, &#163;3,494,733, in a trust account for defence purposes. Of this sum, &#163;2,494,733 will he expended on the defence programme of this year and so relieve the current budget, and the balance of &#163;1,000,000 will be available towards meeting the defence expenditure of 1939-40. </para>
        <para class="block">1938-39 FINANCES. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Estimates of Expenditure</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>In the expenditure for 1938-39 the Government, as is well known, faces very largely increased obligations mainly arising out of defence, national insurance and invalid and old-age pensions. These three items alone account for an increase of about &#163;7,000,000. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Defence,</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Last financial year the total provision for defence from all sources was &#163;11,531,000. Nearly half of that sum was provided from loan and trust funds, and the balance came from revenue. </para>
        <para>In April last the Prime Minister outlined to Parliament the main features of the Government&#39;s defence programme for the next three years, under which extensive measures will be taken to strengthen greatly the Navy, Army and Air Force, to expand the Government munitions factories, and to organize civil industry for an emergency. The subsequent trend of the international situation has unfortunately only emphasized the urgency and importance of pressing on with J;he strengthening of our defences. The progress of the programme has been constantly under review by the Government and &#39; satisfactory results are being achieved. </para>
        <para>In May last Parliament approved of a loan appropriation of &#163;10,000,000 for defence purposes. Of this amount &#163;4,000,000 has already been raised, and is being applied towards the defence programme of this financial year. </para>
        <para>I have already stated that it is the intention of the Government that the whole of the excess revenue of last year, amounting to &#163;3,494,733, will be taken to Defence Equipment Trust Account. Of this sum &#163;2,494,733 will be applied towards defence expenditure this year. </para>
        <para>The total estimated defence expenditure this year from all sources is &#163;16,796,000. This is a formidable figure, but a3 the Prime Minister said in his national broadcast of March last - &#34; The Government is sure that the Australian people have only to be made aware of the increase necessary in order readily to accept the obligations involved.&#34; </para>
        <para>The total expenditure for defence will be financed as follows: - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_16_3.jpg" />
        </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That means that only one half of the current expenditure is to be derived from revenue. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Yes, for this year. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Of this total, capital expenditure is estimated at &#163;9,922,000 and maintenance expenditure at &#163;6,874,000. &#34; Capital expenditure &#34; signifies expenditure on works, ships, aircraft, equipment, stores, armaments and the like. As the programme progresses, capital expenditure may be expected to diminish, but the expansion of the defence services will entail an increasing maintenance vote. </para>
          <para>The most urgent projects entail high capital expenditure in the initial stages of the programme. This is necessary to ensure synchronization of the various parts of the programme, both within and between the services. Thus, in the Navy, ships and trained crews must become available together. In the Army provision of accommodation and equipment must coincide with the enlistment and training of personnel, whilst deliveries of aircraft must synchronize with the formation of new squadrons in. the Air Force. From the joint service aspect, security of our main ports depends on the simultaneous completion of the local seaward defences by the Navy, the fixed coast and anti-aircraft defences by the Army, and the air co-operation squadrons by the Air Force. </para>
          <para>I may say that my colleague the Minister for Defence <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Thorby)</inline> will seek an early opportunity to give further information to honorable members concerning the objectives and progress of the defence programme. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Civil Aviation</title>
          <page.no>20</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The total figures for defence expenditure which I have just given include civil aviation. The estimated total expenditure on civil aviation from all sources in 193S-39 is &#163;1,283,000 covering - administration, &#163;101,000; development, &#163;797,000; and Empire air mail, &#163;3S5,000. </para>
        <para>Payments by the Postal Department for air mails and recoveries from the United Kingdom are estimated to amount to &#163;168,000, leaving a net total expenditure of &#163;1,115,000, of which &#163;405,000 will be financed from moneys already available in trust account and the balance of &#163;710,000 will be charged to the budget of this year. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>National Insurance</title>
          <page.no>20</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The proposals for national insurance passed by Parliament during the last sitting are now well advanced in preparation for its full operation in January next. The National Insurance Commission is established with offices in Canberra and in each State, and the organization of societies for insured persons is proceeding rapidly. During the next three months, the many problems which are at present occupying the attention of State governments, employers, friendly societies and other organizations and individuals, will have found their appropriate solutions, or at least to an extent sufficient for the inauguration of the scheme. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JOM</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BEASLEY, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Beasley</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Does that anticipate that the doctors will accept the scheme? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have confined myself to complete silence in &#39;respect of the doctors for six months; I must observe that limitation for a few months yet. It is not to be expected that every development will have been completed this year, but the preparations are being made on sound lines. It has not as yet been found possible to develop the proposed scheme for the voluntary insurance of self-employed persons by reason of the great amount of work and negotiation involved in preparation for the main national insurance scheme, but this is the only reason for delay. The Commonwealth itself, as a large employer of persons not  covered  by superannuation or other benefit  entitling  certain employments to exemption from the scheme, will be a large contributor as an employer, and the costs of those contributions will form part of departmental expenditures. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Liability for Treasury contributions under the act will not commence until all insurance contributions commence, and the present budget will not be called upon to face a full year&#39;s contribution. The budget must, however, include the cost of administration prior to January next and for other expenditures associated with national insurance which are not statutory obligations at present. </para>
          <para>The total estimated expenditure set down in the budget for national insurance is &#163;1,100,000, made up as follows: - </para>
          <para class="block">
            <graphic href="157331193809215_17_4.jpg" />
          </para>
          <para>The provision for grants for the medical treatment of the wives and children of insured persons is in accordance with the promise made in the House when the National Insurance Bill was under discussion. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>21</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Will the Treasurer introduce a bill to give authority for those payments? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>21</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Yes. It is anticipated that contributions by and in respect of insured persons under the national insurance scheme will commence on the 2nd January, 1939, and that for the halfyear ended 30th June, 1939, approximately &#163;5,500,000 will be received. Of the amount mentioned, approximately &#163;3,000,000 will be credited to the Pensions Fund and &#163;2,500,000 to the Health Fund. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">Invalid and Old-age Pensions.</inline>
          </para>
          <para>In September, 1937, the rate of pension was increased to its former maximum level of &#163;1 per week and the total expenditure for the year ended 30th June, 1938, amounted to just under &#163;15,800,000, an increase of approximately &#163;1,800,000 on the previous year. This increase was due to the normal net growth of the number of pensioners, the cost of the increase of the maximum rate of pension from 19s. to 20s. per week, and the fact that there were 27 pay-days during the year instead of the usual 26. </para>
          <para>At the 30th June, 1938, there were 310,250 invalid and old-age pensioners, <inline font-style="italic">an</inline> increase of a little over 11,000 during, the year. </para>
          <para>Approximately85 per cent, of the pensioners receive the maximum rate of pension, &#163;1 per week, and the average rate of pension is 19s. 3d. per week. </para>
          <para>It is estimated that the net increase of the number of pensioners during the current year will be approximately 11,500 and that the total cost of invalid and oldage pensions for the year will be &#163;16,150,000. This represents an increase of &#163;350,000 over the actual expenditure last year. But for the extra pay-day last year the increase would be &#163;865,000. </para>
          <para>During this session the Government will introduce legislation relating to reciprocity between the Commonwealth and New Zealand in the matter of invalid and oldage pensions. At the present time, residence in New Zealand is not accepted as residence in Australia for pension pur poses, and vice versa. The new legislation will enable residence in either country to be taken into account, with the result that the total period of residence in the two countries will , be accepted by both. </para>
          <para>In regard to invalid pensions, an essential qualification at present is that permanent incapacity for work shall have occurred in Australia. It is now proposed that permanent incapacity occurring in New Zealand shall be accepted as having occurred in Australia, and vice versa. </para>
          <para>The cost of these liberalizations will be borne by the Commonwealth and the Dominion of New Zealand in proportion to the respective period of qualifying residence in each country. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>War Pensions and Repatriation</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The additional concessions granted to war pensioners in recent years by way of provision made for the medical care and treatment of incapacitated men have involved considerable increased expenditure. The total cost of war pensions and repatriation for 1938-39 is estimated at &#163;9,400,000. This represents an increase of &#163;348,000 over last year and an increase of &#163;1,700,000 comparedwith the expenditure of five years ago. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Public Works</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The growing responsibilities of the Commonwealth in respect of public works necessitate substantial increased provision this year. Apart from defence, the estimate for additions and new works is &#163;5,423,000, an increase of &#163;885,000 over the actual expenditure of last year. The increase is mainly due to post office, Northern Territory and Australian Capital Territory. For the post office, the estimated expenditure is &#163;3,938,000, which will be referred to later. </para>
        <para>For the Northern Territory, &#163;300,000 is to be provided. The increase over last year is &#163;197,000 and is necessary to provide water supply, a new hospital and other services in keeping with the growing needs of the territory. </para>
        <para>For the Australian Capital Territory, the estimated expenditure is &#163;545,000, an increase of &#163;68,000 over last year. </para>
        <para>The following table shows the substantially increased obligations of the Com monwealth Government for public works(omitting defence), in 1938-39: - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_19_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">The figures in this table do not include defence works. The estimated total expenditure from all sources on these works in 1938-39 is &#163;9,922,000 of which about &#163;7,000,000 will be spent in Australia. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Departmental Expenditure</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The ordinary services of departments also necessitate increased expenditure this year. For ordinary departments - excluding business undertakings and territories - the increase over last year is &#163;407,000. About &#163;30,000 is due to the restoration by an award of portion of cost of living reduction; &#163;42,000 is due to exchange charges now being included in ordinary departmental votes instead of in a special Treasury vote. Apart from these special items, the increase is &#163;335,000 and is mainly due to expansion of the Department of the Interior caused by the heavy defence programme and general increase of works. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Postal Activities</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The activities of the Postal Depart ment continue to expand in all directions necessitating heavy expenditure for the provision of new services and for the replacement of buildings and plant which have reached, or are reaching, the limits of their capacity. </para>
        <para>The Postmaster-General&#39;s Department has been hard pressed to cope with the progressive public demand for increased services in all branches of its business, in spite of the expenditure of over &#163;3,000,000 on new works in 1937-38. These new works include the progressive installation of new automatic exchanges, new trunk line telephone channels, underground telephone cables, new trunk line exchanges, improved telegraph equipment, new broadcasting stations and general renovations and improvements of plant, buildings and equipment in all branches. </para>
        <para>In order to meet the expansion of business it has been necessary to allocate progressively increasing sums for new works in recent years - the figures being as follows :  - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_19_1.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block" pgwide="yes">The activities of the Postmaster-General&#39;s Department in recent years have been financed as under: - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_20_7.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">It will be seen that whereas during recent years this department has contributed to the general revenue of the Commonwealth, it is expected that during the current financial year, it will have to draw on general revenue for over &#163;1,000,000. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Council for Scientific and Industrial Research</title>
          <page.no>23</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Provision is made for governmental expenditure for the Council for Scientific) and Industrial Research of &#163;207,000 as compared with an actual expenditure of &#163;175,000 last year and &#163;138,000 in 1936-37. </para>
        <para>There is no need to reiterate the great importance of scientific research in our national life. Such results as the discovery that Australian hardwoods are suitable for paper manufacture, the development of a process for the transport of chilled beef from Australia to the London market, valuable work done on kiln seasoning of timbers, and achievements in respect of animal health and the control of pests, have been of inestimable benefit to the country. </para>
        <para>During last year, the Government decided to extend the scope of the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research to cover work on matters affecting secondary industries, to be planned and carried out over the next few years. The sum of &#163;250,000 was provided for this purpose. Following this decision, steps are being taken to establish a National Standards Reference Laboratory in Sydney and an Aeronautical and Engineering Research Laboratory in Melbourne. </para>
        <para>In addition to the amounts provided by the Government for scientific and industrial research, moneys have been provided from other sources. In view of the heavy demands upon the resources of the Government entailed by the enlarged defence programme and the establishment of national insurance, the Government looks forward to increased contributions from those industries which have benefited or are likely to benefit from research. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Aeronautics and Meteorology</title>
          <page.no>23</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>As part of the Government&#39;s policy to encourage the development of aviation in Australia on sound lines, it has been decided tQ provide &#163;32,000 for capital expenditure in connexion with a Chair of Aeronautics, and &#163;3,000 a year to cover maintenance. This chair will be established in the University of Sydney. </para>
        <para>This decision marks an important step forward in national development. The Chair of Aeronautics will provide a training ground for Australia&#39;s young aeronautical engineers of the future and should give a valuable stimulus to aviation generally. </para>
        <para>The Government also proposes to make financial provision for an associate Professorship in Meteorology. We are advised that Australian weather conditions are best studied in the&#39; southeastern corner of the continent and this work will in consequence be done in the Melbourne University. The need for such work, both in connexion with aviation and otherwise, is clear. </para>
        <para class="italic">
          <inline font-style="italic">Payments to the States.</inline>
        </para>
        <para>The fifth annual report of the Commonwealth Grants Commission has now been received and contains recommendations that the payments for 1938-39  should be as follow :  - South Australia, &#163;1,040,000; Western Australia, &#163;570,000; Tasmania, &#163;410,000; or a total of &#163;2,020,000. This is a decrease of &#163;330,000 on the total paid last year. </para>
        <para>In considering the . grant to Western Australia it is necessary to hear in mind that the normal grant paid in 1937-38 was &#163;439,000 plus a special advance of &#163;136,000 on account of drought, to he. adjusted in 1939-40, bringing the total sum to &#163;575,000. The normal grant recommended for this year is &#163;614,000, from which is deducted a special advance of &#163;44,000 made in 1936-37. The normal grant recommended this year is therefore, in fact, &#163;175,000 greater than the normal grant of last year. </para>
        <para>The Government proposes to ask Parliament to approve the recommendations of the commission, and when the necessary legislation is brought down further information will be given to honorable members. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Youth Employment</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Last year &#163;200,000 was provided in grants to the States to assist them in providing technical training and securing skilled employment for youths. This year the Government proposes to make provision for a further amount of &#163;200,000 for the same purpose. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>24</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Who will get the money ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>24</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It will be paid as grants to the States, the amount being determined after consultation between the Commonwealth and State governments. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>24</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JOM</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BEASLEY, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Beasley</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  Are reports on these activities received from the States? If so, they should be submitted to Parliament. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>24</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The appropriate Minister receives reports, but I do not know that they are submitted to the Parliament. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Primary Products: Fertilizers Subsidy</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Since 1932 the Government has paid a subsidy to primary producers, other than wheat-growers, to assist them to purchase artificial manures. </para>
        <para>The subsidy has been instrumental in demonstrating to primary producers the advantages of using fertilizers, which has been reflected in the volume of production and in -better farming methods. </para>
        <para>The subsidy is primarily designed tohelp the small primary producer - and to this end it was decided last year to limit the payment to the first 20 tons of fertilizers purchased by any individual. With this restriction the cost to the Government last year was  approximately  &#163;262,000. </para>
        <para>In order to keep the expenditure within reasonable limits, the Government now proposes to limit the payment of the subsidy to the first 10 tons of fertilizer purchased by any individual. The estimated cost of this assistance during this financial year is &#163;215,000. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Overseas Publicity</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Last year the Commonwealth increased  its grant to the Australian National Travel Association from &#163;15,000 to &#163;20,000, and this latter sum is being repeated in this year&#39;s estimates. In addition, it has been decided to grant &#163;21,000 to the association for the purpose of a comprehensive tourist and travel display at the San Francisco Exposition of 1939. </para>
        <para>The Government has also decided to participate in the New York World&#39;s Fair opening in New York on the 30th April, 1939. Provision has accordingly been made on the Estimates of a sum of &#163;40,000 to cover the cost of the Australian exhibit. </para>
        <para>The Government will again make available the sum of &#163;30,000 sterling to the Australian Overseas Trade Publicity Committee for the purpose of publicity and trade promotion in the United Kingdom, in addition to &#163;7,500 sterling for general exhibitions of Australian products in that country. </para>
        <para>An amount of &#163;2,500 will be made available to cover the cost of campaigns to advertise Australian products in the East and other special markets, and this sum will be supplemented by funds made available by the Australian Dairy Produce Board for the advertising of Australian butter in eastern countries. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Total Expenditure, 1938-39</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The total estimated budgetary expen  diture for the year is set out in the following table together with the actual expenditure of 1937-38. </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_22_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para>Expenditure out of excess receipts of past years, which has been excluded from this summary, is as follows: - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_22_1.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ESTIMATES OF REVENUE, 1938-39</title>
        <page.no>25</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Turning now to the estimates of revenue, it is necessary to set out what may be expected this year based on present rates of taxation. I Submit hereunder a table showing these estimates in comparison with the revenue actually received last year - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_22_2.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para>Last year the estimate for customs and excise revenue was &#163;44,500,000, and the actual revenue was &#163;48,383,000.For the current year the difficulty of estimating this revenue is accentuated by the high level of . imports last year, the decline of export prices during the last twelve months, and the impossibility of forecasting the future trend of prices. Inquiries indicate that traders generally anticipate no decline of business activities in the first six months of the financial year and are making their arrangements on that basis. Some fall of imports and customs revenue seems inevitable during the financial year. After careful consideration I have put down the customs and excise revenue for this year at &#163;46,750,000, namely - customs, &#163;31,250,000 ; excise, &#163;15,500,000. This estimate represents a reduction of customs revenue by &#163;1,723,000, and assumes that excise collections will be at about the same level as last year. </para>
      <para>For sales tax the estimate of &#163;7,800,000 allows for a slight fall as compared with last year. </para>
      <para>For income tax the estimate is &#163;10,700,000, which represents an increase of &#163;1,302,000 over last year. This is due to the improved incomes last year upon which assessments this year will be based, together with the fact that the system of averaging will cease to operate under existing legislation, except in respect of primar y producers. </para>
      <para>The estimate of &#163;3,265,000 for &#34;Miscellaneous &#34; includes an amount of &#163;500,000, being balances of sundry trust accounts which are no longerrequired for their original purposes. This is a non-recurring item of revenue. </para>
      <para>Other items of revenue call for no special comment. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>BUDGET GAP</title>
        <page.no>26</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>At this stage the budget position, based on the departmental estimates, can be summarized thus - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_23_0.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para>The Government has given full consideration to the various ways and means of bridging this gap of &#163;3,184,000. It is necessary to bear in mind not only this year&#39;s budget, but also the position next year when the Government will be faced with further liabilities for defence, national insurance, and invalid and oldage pensions, and will only have available &#163;1,000,000 of excess revenue of last year, in lieu of &#163;2,495,000 which is available towards this year&#39;s budget. </para>
      <para>The question of raising further loan moneys has been explored, as this source of finance to assist the budget might be justified on the grounds of the defence programme and the public works expenditure, particularly for the Postal Department. In view, however, of the large conversion loan which is to be faced in the immediate future and the requirements of the States for their public works programmes, it was found impracticable for further loan moneys to be provided beyond the &#163;4,000,000 which has already been raised for defence and the amount of &#163;2,000,000 which is being raised for grants to States for farmers&#39; debt adjustment. </para>
      <para>The Government was therefore forced to the conclusion that the whole of the shortage of &#163;3,184,000 must be covered by additional taxation. The proposals of the Government are as follows :  - </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>TAXATION PROPOSALS</title>
        <page.no>26</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Income Tax</title>
          <page.no>26</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>It is proposed to increase the rates of income tax payable by companies and individuals by 15 per cent. The additional revenue to be derived from this increase this year is estimated at &#163;1,400,000. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>26</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the increase to be uniform throughout all grades? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <para>Mr.CASEY.- Yes. </para>
        <para>Mr.Curtin. - The same increase on salaries on the lower ranges as on the higher ? </para>
        <para>Mr.CASEY. - Yes. The honorable member is aware that there is a steep graduation of the rates as incomes increase. </para>
        <para>In announcing this increase, it is well to remind honorable members that this is the first occasion since this Government assumed office that this form of taxation has been increased. </para>
        <para>It will be recollected that under the Financial Emergency legislation during the depression the rates of income tax were increased to very high levels. Since 1932-33 the Government has consistently reduced the burden of income tax, in addition to approximately equivalent reductions of indirect taxation, principally the sales tax. </para>
        <para>Last year the revenue from income, tax was &#163;9,400,000. For the present year all taxpayers, other than primary producers, will lose the benefit of the &#34; averaging &#34; system, and, even if the rates were unaltered, many taxpayers will be called upon to pay extra taxation, as their taxable incomes for 1937-38 will be higher than the average of the last five years and will therefore attract a higher rate of tax. </para>
        <para>For 1938-39 the total revenue estimated to be derived from income tax under the proposed new conditions is &#163;12,100,000, or an increase of &#163;2,700,000 compared with last year. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Sales Tax</title>
          <page.no>26</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>It is proposed to increase the rate of sales tax from 4 per cent, to 5 per cent, legislation will he introduced to provide that the 5 per cent, rate will come into operation as from the commencement of business to-morrow, the 22nd September, 1938. The estimated additional revenue for a full year is &#163;1,900,000 and for the remainder of thisyear &#163;1,300,000. </para>
        <para>After progressive reductions of this tax from 6 per cent, to 4 per cent, the Government is now obliged by budget necessities to make this increase, and it is &#34;roper that I should make some observations on the incidence of sales tax generally. </para>
        <para>Sales tax is imposed on goods consumed in Australia other than those that are specifically exempted. </para>
        <para>In selecting goods for exemption, this Government has been concerned, in the main, to lift the burden of the tax from the requirements of - </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>Basic wage earners. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>The sick and the destitute </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>Primary production. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>Fields which offer particular opportunities for the encouragement of employment. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>Education, science, religion and the like. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>The wage earner has been chiefly provided for by the progressive exemption of most of the prime necessaries of life. Examination of the regimens used by wage-fixing tribunals in determining the basic wage shows that only a small proportion, of the average basic wage earner&#39;s purchases is now subject to the sales tax. The Government therefore believes that progressive adherence to its sales tax exemptions policy has resulted in this indirect tax being, to as great an extent as possible, based on capacity to pay- </para>
        <para>Those industries andthose persons who have been largely benefited by exemptions will not, of course, be deprived of their benefit by the proposed increase of the rate of tax. </para>
        <para>The sales tax revenue for 1938-39 is now estimated to be &#163;9,100,000, as compared with &#163;8,024,000 in the last financial year. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Land Tax</title>
          <page.no>27</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>It is proposed to increase the present rates of land tax by approximately 11.1 per cent, on the rates that have been operating for the last five years. This particular rate of increase has been chosen, in lieu of a round percentage, in order to reacha readily calculable rate in conjunction with the technical formula that is in operation. The estimated additional revenue for a full year is &#163;140,000, and for the remainder of this year &#163;135,000. </para>
        <para>In submitting this proposal, the Government considers that the landowners of the Commonwealth should contribute their share to the burden of increased taxation which the present situation demands. About three-fourths of the land tax is derived from urban land and the balance from country land. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Excise Duties</title>
          <page.no>27</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Certain increases of excise duties are proposed which are expected to yield an additional &#163;500,000 overa full twelve months&#39; period. It is estimated that the additional revenue which will be collected during the currency of the present financial year will be &#163;375,000. Details will be given to the committee by my colleague, the Minister for Trade and Customs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. White)</inline> at a later stage. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Taxation Proposals Summarized</title>
          <page.no>27</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para> Summarized, the extra revenue esti mated to be obtained this year from the taxation proposals of the Government is as follows: - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_24_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para>With these proposals, the estimated receipts for taxation this year, compared with last year&#39;s actual receipts, are as follow :  - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_24_1.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para>It will be observed that from indirect taxation a net decrease of &#163;182,000 is expected, and from direct taxation, a net increase of &#163;2,696,000. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SUMMARY OF ESTIMATED BUDGET RESULTS, 1938-39</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The budget position may now be summarized thus - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_25_0.jpg" />
      </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>LOAN EXPENDITURE</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The estimated loan expenditure 1938-39 is &#163;6,400,000, compared with an actual expenditure of &#163;4,567,500 in 1937-38. </para>
      <para>Particulars are as follows :  - </para>
      <para class="block">
        <graphic href="157331193809215_25_1.jpg" />
      </para>
      <para>The estimated expenditure of  66,400,000 for 1938-39 is covered by appropriations already granted by Parliament. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>BUDGET LEGISLATION</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Legislation arising out of the budget will be proceeded with at the earliest possible date. It will also be necessary to introduce a Supply Bill immediately. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>BANKING LEGISLATION</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The Government proposes to bring down at an early date a measure to amend the Commonwealth Bank Act. Provision will be made in the bill to give effect to certain recommendations of the Royal Commission on the Monetary and Banking System, including . mortgage banking. Opportunity will also be taken to make other necessary amendments to the Commonwealth Bank Act. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>CONCLUSION</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>A budget speech has necessarily to cover a great deal of ground. I have attempted this year to condense the story as much as possible, in order that the broad picture of our Commonwealth finances should not be encumbered with too much detail. </para>
      <para>Despite some recession overseas, our own internal financial and economic position has remained good - I might even say remarkably good - compared with other countries. We are, as a country, preparing to meet very large increases of expenditure on defence and on social services, and, at the same time, maintain our progressive development in the manifold other directions in which the hand of government is essential for the welfare of the people. We are doing this in the face of world difficulties of a serious order. As a self-governing member of the British Commonwealth of Nations, we have no enemies and no enmities - and yet we find it essential, the world being as it is, to impose great burdens on ourselves in an endeavour to ensure some measure of security for ourselves and for our children. This endeavour means increased taxation which, as I have outlined, the Government proposes should be spread in as equitable a manner as possible. </para>
      <para>No government enjoys placing a higher burden of taxation on its people, but we believe that the responsible taxpayers of Australia are ready to meet the task of endeavouring to achieve social betterment and national security. The times are too serious to allow of dispersion of effort in internal political dissension, and the Government hopes that the Parliament will accept this defence budget as a courageous effort to add to our national security in the widest sense of the term. </para>
      <para>I move - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the first item in the Estimates under Division I. - The Senate - namely, &#34; Salaries and Allowances, &#163;8,210,&#34; be agreed to. </para>
      </quote>
      <para>Progress reported. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PAPER</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The following paper was presented :  - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>The Budget 1938-39. - Papers presented by the Honorable R. G. Casey, M.P., for the information of honorable members on the occasion of the Budget 1938-39. </para>
      </quote>
      <para>Ordered to be printed. - </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SUPPLY BILL (No. 2) 1938-39</title>
        <page.no>29</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="italic">
        <inline font-style="italic">In Committee of Supply:</inline>
      </para>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Casey)</inline> agreed to - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That there be granted to His Majesty for or towards defraying the services of the year 1938-39 a sum not exceeding &#163;5,349,050. </para>
      </quote>
      <para class="block">Resolution reported. </para>
      <para class="block">Standing Orders &#34;suspended, resolution adopted. </para>
      <para class="italic">
        <inline font-style="italic">In Committee of Ways and Means:</inline>
      </para>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>29</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JWE</name.id>
            <electorate>Corio</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Treasurer</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
            <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That, towards making good the Supply granted to His Majesty for the services of the year . 1938-39, there be granted out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund a sum not exceeding &#163;5,349,050. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">Under the Supply Act (No. 1) which was passed in June last, provision was made in the ordinary services of the Commonwealth for the first three months of the current financial year. The present measure makes provision for a further amount of &#163;5,349,050 for another two months to meet expenditure under the following headings :  - </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="157331193809215_26_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">The provision made in this bill is for essential services only. The amounts provided, together with the Supply already granted by Parliament, represent the provision necessary for the services up to the end of November. The amounts included in this Supply Bill are &#39;based on the rate of expenditure for the last financial year, or for the current year, whichever is the lower, and represent the proportionate amount of the total provision, with a few exceptions, in which cases the expenditure is heavier in the earlier months of the financial year, such as, for example, certain defence expenditure, in connexion with which it is necessary to place orders in the early part of the year, and also in respect of some items in the Postal Department, where mail contracts have to be made in the earlier months of the year. The provision of &#163;400,000 for refunds of revenue is necessary to enable refunds to be made of amount which, under statutory authority, are temporarily credited to revenue for payment at a later date. Honorable members will notice an . amount of &#163;500,000 for Treasurer&#39;s Advance. This sum, with the &#163;2,000,000 included in the earlier Supply Bill, brings the total up to &#163;2,500,000 for 1938-39, as against &#163;2,000,000 in recent years. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>29</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The ordinary provision is only &#163;2,000,000 for the whole of the financial year. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>29</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is so. I may be allowed to offer a word or two of explanation with reference to this item, in order to remove . a misunderstanding of its purpose. This is a vote, usually of appreciable size in one or two Supply bills introduced before the budget is passed. Supply bills make provision only for the ordinary expenditure of departments and not for such items as additions, new works, or for other proposals which are the subject of special appropriation by the Parliament. The most important of these are grants to the States. Accordingly, in addition to providing for the ordinary services, the Government, at the beginning of each financial year, has also to make provision for carrying out publicworks from the 30th June, from which period the- vote of the previous year ceased, until the budget is passed by Parliament. The normal public works programme has to be carried on and other financial commitments met, such as Commonwealth grants to the States. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>29</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Curtin</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The Treasurer pays these amounts monthly out of the Treasurer&#39;s Advance at the rate for theprevious year? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>29</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Yes, subject to adjustment later. These are the two heaviest items contained in Supply bills before the budget is presented. Although a large sum is set down in the annual Estimates for the Treasurer&#39;s Advance, it is not the practice to include any portion as a charge to the budget. Items contained in Supply bills in respect of&#34; which Treasurer&#39;s Advance has been expended are subsequently incorporated in. the budget, which gives authority, retrospectively, of course, for the expenditure. The Treasurer&#39;s Advance also covers other unexpected items of expenditure, but usually they are relatively small amounts which are later accounted for in Supplementary Estimates. The increased provision in respect of the Treasurer&#39;s Advance in this measure and the earlier supply bill is due to the largely expanded works programme, mainly on the defence side; but as I have already said, the expenditure under each relevant heading is proportionate to last year&#39;s expenditure or to this year&#39;s expenditure whichever is the less. The Government gives an undertaking that the bill contains no provision for new proposals. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
        <para>Resolution reported and adopted. </para>
        <para class="italic">
          <inline font-style="italic">Ordered -</inline>
        </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Casey</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Menzies</inline> do prepare and bring in a bill to carry out the foregoing resolution. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Bill brought up by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Casey,</inline> and read a first time. </para>
      </speech>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>30</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Casey)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the bill  be  read a second  time. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Curtin)</inline> adjourned. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>TARIFF PROPOSALS 1938</title>
        <page.no>30</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Customs Tariff Amendment (No. 3); Excise Tariff Amendment (No. 3)</title>
          <page.no>30</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>In Committee of Ways and Means:</title>
          <page.no>30</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate>Balaclava</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>.- I move- &#91;Customs Tariff Amendment No. 3.&#93; </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para pgwide="yes">That the Schedule to the <inline font-style="italic">Customs Tariff</inline> 1933-1938 as proposed to be amended by the Customs Tariff Proposals introduced into the House of Representatives on the fourth day of May, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight, be further amended as hereunder set out, and that on and after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight, at nine o&#39;clock in the forenoon, reckoned according to standard time in the Australian Capital Territory, Duties of Customs be collected in pursuance of the <inline font-style="italic">Customs Tariff</inline> 1933-1938 as so amended. </para>
          <para class="block">
            <graphic href="157331193809215_27_0.jpg" />
          </para>
          <para class="block">
            <graphic href="157331193809215_28_0.jpg" />
          </para>
          <para class="block">
            <graphic href="157331193809215_29_0.jpg" />
          </para>
          <para class="block">&#91;Excise Tariff Amendment No. 3.&#93; </para>
          <para pgwide="yes">That the  Schedule  to the <inline font-style="italic">Excise Tariff</inline> 1921-1938  as  proposed to be amended by the Excise Tariff Proposals introduced into the House of Representatives on the fourth day of May, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight,  be  further amended as hereunder set out, and that on  and  after the twentyaecond day  of  September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight,  at  nine o&#39;clock in the forenoon, reckoned according  to  standard time in the Australian Capital Territory, Duties  of  Excise  bo  collected in pursuance  of  the <inline font-style="italic">Excise Tariff</inline> 1921-1938  as so  amended. </para>
          <para class="block">
            <graphic href="157331193809215_29_1.jpg" />
          </para>
          <para>As honorable members are aware, the Government, in May, 1936, imposed increased rates of duty on imported tobacco leaf unless such leaf was used in  conjunction with 13 per cent, of Australiangrown leaf in manufactured tobacco and with 2&#189; per cent, of Australiangrown leaf in cigarettes. </para>
          <para>The action taken at that time has resulted in Australian manufacturers incorporating the required percentage of Australian leaf in practically all their blends, and has made practicable the purchase of all merchantable leaf grown locally at prices considerably higher than world parity. </para>
          <para>In order that Australian tobacco manufacturers might be compensated for the increased rates of import duty imposed on tobacco leaf, the duties on imported manufactured tobacco and cigarettes were also increased in May, 1936, but subsequently the old rate was reverted to on manufactured, tobacco and cigarettes imported from the United Kingdom, provided these manufactured products contained the required percentages of Australian leaf. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>33</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>F4U</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">FORDE, Francis Michael</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Forde</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Has the Minister proof that this has been of any assistance to Australian growers? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>33</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Not with regard to the United Kingdom, because there is not much export of Australian leaf. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>A review of the Australian tobacco industry has recently been undertaken, and, having regard to the increased production of Australian leaf, combined with the remarkable improvement of quality, the G overnment has decided to take the necessary steps to raise the minimum percentages of Australian-grown leaf used in the manufacture of cigarettes and tobacco. For cigarettes the required percentage is to be raised from 2&#189; per cent, to3 per cent., whilst in the case of tobacco the percentage is to be increased from 13 per cent, to 15 per cent. This action can be regarded as a second step in the implementation of the Government&#39;s policy to ensure the purchase and consumption of all usable tobacco leaf grown in Australia. Further steps in conformity with this policy will depend upon future crop production, improvement of the quality of Australian leaf, stocks of matured tobacco leaf held by manufacturers and the effect of the present measures on consumption. Future percentage increases will be investigated by the Tariff Board. The increased percentages take effect from the 1st October, 1938, as far as leaf used by Australian manufacturers is concerned, and from the 1st January, 1939, with respect to manufactured tobacco and cigarettes imported from the United Kingdom. These brief periods are allowed in order that manufacturers may have sufficient time in which to adjust the formulae used in connexion with the manufacture of the numerous brands of tobacco and cigarettes produced by them. My colleague, the Treasurer <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Casey)</inline> has already indicated that certain increased excise duties are proposed under the budget. I am able to enlarge on the information he has already given by stating that an increase is proposed in respect of the excise duties on manufactured tobacco by 8d. per lb. This increase is expected to yield &#163;500,000 additional revenue over a f ull twelve months&#39; period. During the currency of the present financial year this increase of excise duty is expected to add &#163;375,000 to the revenue. </para>
          <para class="block">Progress reported. </para>
          <para class="block">SALES TAX BILLS (Nos. 1 to 9) 1938. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>In Committee of Ways and Means:</title>
          <page.no>33</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>33</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JWE</name.id>
              <electorate>Corio</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Treasurer</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CASEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>.- I move- </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 1) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods manufactured in Australia by a taxpayer and on or after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight sold by him or treated by him as stock for sale by retail or applied to his own use. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 2) 1930-1936 there be &#34;imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods manufactured in Australia . and sold on or after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight by a taxpayer who purchased them from the manufacturer. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="3.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 3) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods manufactured in Australia and sold on or after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight by a taxpayer, not being&#39; either the manufacturer of those goods or a purchaser . ofthose&#39; goods from the manufacturer, </para>
            </item>
            <item label="4.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 4) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per Centura upon the sale value of goods manufactured in Australia and sold to a taxpayer who has, on or after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight, applied those goods to his own use. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="5.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 5) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods imported into Australia by a taxpayer on or- after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="6.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 6) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods imported into Australia by a taxpayer and, on or after the twenty-second . day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight, sold by him or applied by him to his own use. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="7.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 7) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods imported into Australia and sold on or after the twentysecond day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight by a taxpayer not being the &#39;importer of the goods. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="8.">
              <para>That in lieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 8) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of &#39; five per centum upon the sale value of goods imported into Australia and sold to a taxpayer who has, on or after the twenty-second day of September, One thousand nine hundred&#39; and thirtyeight, applied those goods to his own use. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="9.">
              <para>That inlieu of the rate of tax imposed by the Sales Tax Act (No. 9) 1930-1936 there be imposed sales tax at the rate of five per centum upon the sale value of goods in Australia, including goods which have gone into use or consumption in Australia, leased by a taxpayer to a lessee on or after the twentysecond day of September, One thousand nine hundred and thirty-eight. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para class="block">I do not wish to expand on what I said in the budget speech, in respect of the proposed increase of the rate of sales tax, except to remind the committee that the new proposed 5 per cent, rate will, it is estimated, produce &#163;1,300,000 for the balance of this financial year. It is estimated that the total value of the wholesale turnover in Australia is about &#163;550,000,000 per annum. By progressive steps, exemptions have amounted to about &#163;350,000,000, leaving taxable turnover to the value of only about &#163;200,000,000. As I have said in the budget speech, the Government has, as far as it is possible to do so, in respect of indirect taxation, by a judicious selection of exemptions, particularly of those items which enter into the regimen of the basic wage earner, endeavoured to make this tax one in regard to which those who can afford to pay do so, and those on the lower range of income are shielded from &#34;the tax. </para>
          <para>The value of the wholesale turnover of exempted foodstuffs is estimated at &#163;130,000,000; fuel, light, and other services of a similar character, &#163;70,000,000; clothing, &#163;10,000,000; medicines required by hospitals, benevolent institutions and the like, &#163;2,000,000, making a total wholesale turnover to the value of about &#163;220,000,000 that can be said to be related directly to the budget of the average basic wage worker and others on the lower ranges of income. The Government, in its sales tax exemption policy, has examined progressively each year the regimen of the various wage fixing tribunals and has selected for exemption items that in the main affect those on the lower ranges of income. </para>
          <para>Honorable members may wish to know why such an early date as to-morrow has been fixed for the operation of the new rate of tax, instead of the end of the month or the 1st of October. The object is to prevent a dislocation of trade that would certainly occur if any date other than the nearest possible date to to-day were chosen. If the end of the month were chosen there would be a definite dislocation of trade, in that there would be a large turnover in the remaining stages of this month to the detriment of the succeeding month&#39;s business, so it has always Been the policy of the Government in the past, when the rates of sales tax have been decreased, to make them applicable as from the next day after the date of the budget speech. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>34</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
              <electorate>Fremantle</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - I quite realize that the mere adoption of the motion before the committee will not give effect to the increase of sales tax, but the motion is a preliminary stage to the introduction of legislation which has for its purpose the imposition of an increased rate of tax as from to-morrow. Yet any steps the committee may subsequently take once it has accepted the principle of the 5 per cent, tax would appear to me to be steps which would lead naturally to the acceptance of the Treasurer&#39;s proposal. Therefore, as I am not able to support the increase of the sales tax from 4 per cent, to 5 per cent., I have to oppose the adoption of the motion at this stage. I submit to the Treasurer that the procedure he has explained as being part, apparently, of the practice of the House in previous years was one which worked fairly when sales tax rates were being reduced. The presumption is that no parliament would seek to tax a community to a greater extent than the financial position of the Government made necessary, and that therefore any reduction of tax would obviously be a proposal which the Parliament would support. The theoretical position, at any rate, is that the Parliament does not ask the citizens to pay more for the services of government than the Treasurer for the time deems necessary; but, once we agree to the adoption of this motion, we say that the principle of an increase of the sales tax from 4 to 5 per cent, is acceptable to us, and, logically, the committee authorizes the bringing down of the bills providing for the increase. Therefore, the substantive proposal is now before us. I speak under great disadvantages, for the Treasurer <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Casey)</inline> must realize that is was not until a few minutes ago that the Parliament had any cognizance of his intention to increase the sales tax. I object to the increase on the ground that the general budget could have made provision for the extra revenue desired in some alternative way which would have been fairer to the community than is the proposal before us. It would be much fairer for the committee to deal with the general principles of the budget prior to considering the specific legislation arising out of if. &#34;We are now asked to agree in part to a specific proposal in the budget, without at the same time dealing with the budget as a whole. With the very limited notice we have had, but for which I do not hold the Government culpable, as we are the victims of our procedure, I am unable to support the motion. I submit that the Government should have arranged the incidence of taxation more fairly in other ways than by raising the tax on the commodities which are at present subject to sales tax. I know the Treasurer says that the basic wage earners are, for the most part, relieved of the contribution to sales tax. That is a most extraordinary argument, since the commodities which the workers consume and which are not subject to sales tax are the very same commodities which, if the rich consume them, are also exempt from the tax. The rich man eats foodstuffs the same as the poor man. It is merely a trivial debating point to say that the basic wage earner does not pay sales tax because foodstuffs are not subject to the tax. The bread which the Treasurer eats is as much bread  a3  that which is consumed by any other citizen. I do not think the Australian public or business community can regard the proposed annual approximate increase of the sales tax by 25 per cent, as the only reasonable course which the Treasurer could have followed in bridging the gap in his budget. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>35</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Casey</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  This is not the only one. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>35</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I know that. A flat rate of increase is to be imposed on all articles at present subject to sales tax. It might have been preferable to lift the rate of tax on certain articles but maintain it at the present figure on the other articles. We have no opportunity to examine that point at this juncture. It might also have been preferable to increase the land tax rather than the sales tax, more particularly as the primary cause of this budget gap is the insurance of the property and lives of the community against aggression. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>We should have been given an opportunity to consider the general policy of the Government before being asked to affirm any specific proposal in that general policy. The sales tax was introduced at a time of great financial emergency. The Government of the day, being faced with a staggering deficit, adopted this unusual form of taxation for Australia. Since that time not only has the rate of sales tax been reduced but the scope of goods exempt from the tax has also been greatly widened. The Treasurer is not faced, at this moment, with a condition of economic stringency. His trouble is that he has to meet  a  specific obligation in respect of the defence of this country. He proposes to obtain an additional &#163;2,000,000 from  revenue for this purpose this year, compared with last year. We are to find approximately &#163;8,000,000 from revenue for defence this year, whereas last year we found &#163;6,000,000 from revenue towards the total defence expenditure. The Treasurer estimates that he will obtain an additional &#163;2,000,000 from sales tax alone. The other burdens on the budget arise out of the national insurance policy and the necessity for increased provision for invalid and old-age pensions, and for an expansion of the works programme of the Postal Department. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JWE</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CASEY, Richard</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Casey</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- There is additional expenditure in other directions. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Certainly it is intended to spend a little more money in the Northern Territory and in the Australian Capital Territory ; but that would surely be on capital works, and not on maintenance. While I appreciate that Commonwealth activities in general are expanding and that therefore the annual maintenance charges must necessarily increase to some extent, I point out that the revenue must also expand. It must be apparent that with an increase of population there must be an increase of the general sources from which revenue will be available to the Government. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>In these circumstances it appears to me to be undeniable that the proposal of the Government to increase the rate of sales tax indicates that it prefers to impose indirect rather than direct taxation. The increases of direct taxation proposed this year will, it is true, give a greater yield of revenue than the increases of indirect taxation; but this is duo to the lower revenue which the Treasurer expects to obtain from customs duties. I must say that the Treasurer is the most consistent person I have ever known in making errors in respect of customs revenue. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KHL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">HOLLOWAY, Edward</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Holloway</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I do not think that they are errors. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>009FQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CURTIN, John</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CURTIN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I should say that they are. I should hesitate to accuse the Treasurer of deliberately understating the revenue which he expects to get through customs; but it is an amazing thing that each year since he has held the portfolio of Treasurer the receipts through the customs have exceeded his estimates by millions of pounds. The honorable gentleman has .never been optimistic in respect of customs revenue. While 1 think that he acted sensibly in forecasting a falling off of customs revenue in the current financial year compared with last year, it must be remembered that his actual receipts from this source last year were &#163;4,000,000 in excess of the estimate. I think he has erred in assuming that the customs revenue will fall to such a great extent as he has indicated. To make up the leeway in this respect the honorable gentleman has turned not only to sales tax, but also to excise duties. It is from these two sources that he anticipates making up a good deal of the revenue that may be lost through the reduction of customs revenue. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>The honorable gentleman has shown himself to be very reluctant to increase direct taxation in such a way as, in my opinion, the national necessity demands. If the Treasurer feels that he cannot prune his expenditure to a greater extent he should have made provision for a greater yield from income tax. </para>
          <para>We have been unable to examine the estimates of expenditure in order to determine for ourselves whether this great volume of additional taxation should be approved. That is another dilemma in which we find ourselves. We have to say in effect, &#34; You intend to spend so much. We do not know whether it is justified or not because we have not had an opportunity to examine the expenditure. Yet you ask us to approve of the imposition of sales tax at a rate 25 per cent, higher than was in operation last financial year, and you want us to agree to this new tax coming into effect from to-morrow &#34;. In such circumstances &#34;I find myself in the position of having to vote against th&#39; = proposal, not because, in the ultimate, I might not find such a  course inevitable  - I do not say that - but because the circumstances make it impossible to say whether the proposal is justified or not. We should be given an opportunity to examine the general principles of the budget before we are called upon to approve of one specific proposal which will be the subject of legislation to be introduced subsequently. </para>
          <para>Progress reported. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>37</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HOUR OF MEETING</title>
          <page.no>37</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>37</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4O</name.id>
              <electorate>Wilmot</electorate>
              <party>UAP</party>
              <role>Prime Minis ter</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Joseph Aloysius</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - I move - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the House at its rising adjourn until 11 a.m. to-morrow. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">It is intended to resume the discussion of the Supply Bill to-morrow provided that it is not possible to make a statement on. international affairs. If that is possible that business will, of course, take precedence over Supply. </para>
          <para>Question resolved in- the affirmative. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PAPERS</title>
        <page.no>37</page.no>
        <type>papers</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The following papers were pre sented :  - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>Commonwealth Bank Act- Balance-sheets of Commonwealth Bank and Commonwealth Savings Bank and Statement of the Liabilities and Assets of the Note Issue Department, as at the 30th June, 1938: together with Auditor-General&#39;s Reports thereon. </para>
        <para>Commonwealth and State Ministers - Conference on Wheat, Canberra, 28th August, 1938- Proceedings. </para>
        <para>Advances to Settlers Ace - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 84. </para>
        <para>Air Force Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 77. </para>
        <para>Australian Soldiers&#39; Repatriation Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, Nos. 71, 73. </para>
        <para>War Pensions Entitlement&#39; Appeal Tribunals - Report for year 1937-38. </para>
        <para>Canned Fruits Export Control Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 67. </para>
        <para>Citrus Fruits Bounty Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 87. </para>
        <para>Commonwealth Grants Commission Act - Report of the Commonwealth Grants Commission on applications made by the States of South Australia, Western Australia and Tasmania, for Financial Assistance in 1938-39 from the Commonwealth under section 96 of the Constitution. </para>
        <para>Commonwealth Public Service Act- </para>
        <para>Appointments - Department - </para>
        <para>Attorney-General - H. G. Bond, T. K. Hogan, K. B.Petersson. </para>
        <para>Commerce- <inline font-style="italic">-L.</inline> T. Maplestone. </para>
        <para>Health- A. C. McKay. </para>
        <para>Parliamentary Reporting Staff - </para>
        <list type="upperalpha-dotted">
          <item label="R.">
            <para>L. Hume. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, Nos. 69 (Parliamentary Officers), 79. </para>
        <para>Customs Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, Nos. 72, 85. </para>
        <para>Defence Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, Nos. 75, 76, 80, 82, 89, 90, 93. </para>
        <para>Defence Act and Naval Defence Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938. No. 92. </para>
        <para class="block">Defence Act, Naval Defence Act and Air Force Act - Regulations amended- Statutory Rules 1938, No. 81. </para>
        <para class="block">Iron and Steel Products Bounty Act - Return for year 1937-38. </para>
        <para class="block">Lands Acquisition Act - Land acquired at - Birkenhead, South Australia  -  For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Goulburn, New South Wales - For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Maylands,Western Australia - For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Merredin, Western Australia- For Postal purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Oaks Estate, Australian Capital Territory -In connexion with the Establishment of the Seat of Government. </para>
        <para class="block">Paraficld, South Australia - For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para>Pendle Hill, New South Wales  -  For Postal purposes. </para>
        <para>Port Wakefield, South Australia  -  Fox Defence purposes. </para>
        <para>South Arm, Tasmania - For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Western Junction, Tasmania - For Defence purposes. </para>
        <para class="block">Meat Export Charges Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 83. </para>
        <para class="block">Naval Defence Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, Nos. 66, 70, 91. </para>
        <para class="block">Navigation Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 78. </para>
        <para class="block">Norfolk Island Act. </para>
        <para>Ordinance of 1938 - No. 3 - Advisory Council. </para>
        <para class="block">Regulations amended, &#38;c, under - Education Ordinance. </para>
        <para class="block">Exportation of Fruit Ordinance. </para>
        <para class="block">Northern Territory Acceptance Act and </para>
        <para>Northern Territory (Administration) Act- </para>
        <para class="block">Ordinances of 1938- </para>
        <para class="block">No. 10 - Defamation. </para>
        <para class="block">No. 11 - Compensation (Fatal Injuries). </para>
        <para>No. 12 - Police and . Police Offences. </para>
        <para>No. 13 - Control of Waters. - Regulations under - </para>
        <para>Alice Springs Administration Ordinance  (I). </para>
        <para>Pharmacy Ordinance. </para>
        <para>Papua Act - </para>
        <para>Infirm and Destitute Natives&#39; Account -Statement of Transactions of Trustees for year 1937-38. </para>
        <para>Ordinance of 1938 - </para>
        <para class="block">No. 2- Supplementary Appropriation (No. 1) 1937-1938. </para>
        <para class="block">Papua and New Guinea Bounties ActReturns for year 1937-38. </para>
        <para class="block">Post and Telegraph Act - Regulations amunded - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 63. </para>
        <para class="block">Post and Telegraph Act and Wireless  Telegraphy Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 62. </para>
        <para class="block">Raw Cotton Bounty Act - Return for year 1937-38. </para>
      </quote>
      <para>Seat of Government Acceptance Act and Seat of Government (Administration) Act- </para>
      <para>Ordinances of 1938 - </para>
      <para>No. 24- Walter Oswald Watt Memorial Fund. </para>
      <para>No. 25 - Seat of Government (Designation ) . </para>
      <para>Regulations amended under - </para>
      <para>Building and Services Ordinance (2). </para>
      <para>Canberra University College Ordinance. </para>
      <para>Hospital Tax Ordinance. </para>
      <para>Sulphur Bounty Act - Return for year 1937-38. </para>
      <para>Transport Workers Act - Regulations amended - Statutory Rules 1938, No. 74. </para>
      <para>War Service Homes Act - RegulationsStatutory Rules 1938, No. 64. </para>
      <para>Wine Export Bounty Act - Return for year 1937-38. </para>
      <para>Wine Overseas Marketing Act - Regulations -Statutory Rules 1938, No.68. </para>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>38</page.no>
        <time.stamp>17:55:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para>House adjourned at 5.55 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>
