<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" []>
<HANSARD DATE="24/02/1994" PROOF="No" PAGE="1023" CHAMBER = "Senate" PARLIAMENT.NO = "37" SESSION.NO = "1" PERIOD.NO = "3" > 
<CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><BUSINESS.START>
<DAY.START DATE="24/02/1994">Thursday, 24 February 1994</DAY.START>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Michael Beahan)</EMPHASIS> took the chair at 9.30 a.m., and read prayers.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</BUSINESS.START><QWN PAGE="1023">
<TITLE>QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</TITLE>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1023">
<TITLE>Senate: Constitutional Power</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1023" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Leader of the Government. I refer to the minister's appearance on <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Meet the Press</EMPHASIS> last Sunday and his passionate defence of Mr Willis's claim that the Senate should not question the minister's right to withhold documents from a Senate committee if the government decides that to do so is in the public interest. I ask: why, then, did Senator Gareth Evans tell the Senate in 1982 that any claim of executive privilege would clearly, under established law and practice, be a matter for the Senate itself to determine and, furthermore, that there is no foundation whatsoever in constitutional law or convention for any claim that the Senate has no constitutional power to require the production of documents? Is this not just another case of monumental hypocrisy? I ask the minister whether he still agrees with his own words at that time:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">This latest obstructive stance by the Government is now ample demonstration of the fact that the Government has something to hide which the documents in question would clearly reveal.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1023" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The short response to that is: what were you lot saying in government at the time? You are asking why I said what I said in 1982. The short answer is because I was in opposition. Why are you saying what you are saying now? The short answer: because you are in opposition. Why were you saying then what we are saying now? Because we are in government and you are in opposition&mdash;this is the whole point. We go through this ritual, this minuet, on all these occasions.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The basic issues are that there is such a thing as public interest grounds for refusing disclosure. There will always be a legal argument at the end of the day as to what fits in that category, and there will always be a political argument about what is appropriate to put in that category. There will always be differences in the legal analysis, depending on how the case is put, because we are all paid advocates for our respective positions and, ultimately, some of those things as a legal character can be resolved only at the end of the day in the courts. But there is also, equally, a political dimension which we all are in the business of putting and claiming for our respective sides. So do not let us have any crocodile hypocrisy coming from opposition senators on this issue. The opposition knows what the ground rules of this thing are. We know what the ground rules are&mdash;we were playing that particular game in 1982 and the opposition is playing it now.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1023" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. With his well-known self-proclaimed reputation as a great upholder of civil liberties, as someone who admires the conventions, who aspires to the High Court if he gets the knock-back as secretary-general, is this minister seriously standing up and saying that the standards of this government have sunk so low that the government is officially prepared to concede that it lied its head off in opposition because it really did not matter, that the Australian Labor Party would say or do anything to get into government? If that is true, what has changed? Why would the Labor Party not lie and cheat in government simply to stay there? So why does the government not come clean and tell us what its real standards are? Does the Labor Party have any sense of propriety in government, or is it prepared to do anything to stay in office?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1023" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I repeat that there are always going to be legal arguments and political arguments about the proper scope of parliamentary or executive claims to immunity from scrutiny and disclosure on public interest grounds. The inherent nature of the concept of public interest is flexible and has a flexible legal content. It remains to be determined by the High Court of Australia as to what the criteria are, because the issue has never been squarely addressed by the High Court. It remains to be dealt with on a case-by-case basis. But the arguments that are involved in this case are compelling and very easily put so far as the government is concerned. It is always a matter of case-by-case determination in all the circumstances of the particular case.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1024">
<TITLE>Trade: Relationship between Australia and the European Union</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1024" SPEAKER="Devereux Sen J.R." NAMEID="1G4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1G4">Senator DEVEREUX</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Trade. I refer to discussions which the minister had yesterday with his counterpart from the European Commission, Sir Leon Brittan. Given that this was the first ministerial-level meeting between Australia and the European Union since the conclusion of the Uruguay Round negotiations last December, can the minister inform the Senate of the outcome of these talks and their significance for the relationship between Australia and the European Union in the future?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1024" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" MINISTERIAL="TRADE; ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I thank Senator Devereux for actually getting around to some issues that are of practical significance to Australians, as opposed to indulgences of their interests to the Senate's. It does get to an issue that I think particularly people in the National Party would be interested in, even if the Liberals have given up on rural Australia. The Uruguay Round set a basis, due to the contribution of a number of people&mdash;not least my colleague Senator Cook&mdash;for significant potential benefits for many levels of the Australian economy, particularly the Australian rural community.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Kemp" NAMEID="WW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="WW4">Senator Kemp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Hey, Bob, your questioner is showing no interest.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;If he heard it, he understood it. That is the difference between him and Senator Kemp. On that basis we now have some additional assurances from the representatives of the European Union that will be of significant benefit to the Australian agricultural community. I would have thought it would be welcomed by all honourable senators. But I am pleased that at least the National Party avoids the hilarity that besets the B-graders on the other side.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">There are two very important points. One is Sir Leon's confirmation that the European Union does not intend to dispose of its large agricultural stocks in a way which would disrupt world markets. Senator Boswell and others would know that there has been concern in the Australian agricultural community about the existence of those stocks and their potential to cause disruption and concern in this period leading up to the implementation of the Uruguay Round. We have been pleased that up until now the community has not been disposing of them in a disruptive way, and the assurance that it will not is welcome news for our agricultural sector.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The second point, and probably even bigger news, is the reaffirmation of what was previously known as the Andriessen-Delors assurance not to export subsidised beef to specific markets in Asia. As those markets open up they will be of extreme importance to Australia. That assurance, which was reaffirmed yesterday, means a lot to Australian beef producers and our economy. My colleague Senator Collins and I raised several other issues about agricultural products and coal. They are matters on which we will need to exert continuing pressure, not because we are seeking to reopen the Uruguay Round commitments but because we have a strong interest in the way those commitments are interpreted and implemented.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The agricultural issues that have been of such profound concern and have dominated the relationship between Australia and the European Union over the years are not over, but there is now a framework for their improvement and we have had some assurances which we welcome. The benefit is that it has enabled us to focus on some of the ongoing strengths in the relationship that have been underemphasised in the past because we have and should have focused on the profound problems in the agricultural area. We have now been able to build on that industrial and investment relationship which is extremely strong. It is possible to say that the European Union is Australia's largest economic partner. It is not our biggest trading partner&mdash;it is on the short list&mdash;but when investment is taken into account also, merchandise trade, services trade and investment, it is our largest economic partner.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We want to concentrate on those positive aspects. We signed a science and technology agreement yesterday and Senator Collins signed a bilateral wine agreement this year. So we have got significant pluses from the Uruguay Round for farmers and miners, and the assurances yesterday will build on that as a very good basis for Australia.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1025">
<TITLE>Breast Cancer</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1025" SPEAKER="Newman Sen J.M." NAMEID="BE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister for Health. This week the minister justified spending only 20c per woman per year on breast cancer research by pointing to his government's abysmal record on research into testicular and prostate cancer, namely an expenditure of approximately just 2c per man per year. Given that these two cancers kill approximately 5,000 Australians a year, and that his government has been in charge of medical research funding for over a decade, what does he have to say to the families of those whose quality of life may have been maximised or whose deaths may have been prevented if research funding had been at the required level over the last 11 years?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1025" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There has been considerable argument as to what a required level is. In the last election the government promised to increase our medical research funding to two per cent, and we will be making that promise a reality or very close to it in the current budget.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Harradine" NAMEID="6H4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6H4">Senator Harradine</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;What priority can be set?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Just a moment; if Senator Harradine hangs on, I will get to that. Senator Newman referred to the fact that 4,900 Australians are killed each year by two forms of cancer and said that it is woefully inadequate to spend what is about $1.65 million, I think, on the two in total this year. The funding for testicular&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Newman" NAMEID="BE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator Newman</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is less than that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is not less than that. Funding for testicular and prostate cancer is actually $500,000 over two years. Senator Newman added up the number of deaths and said that that makes it inadequate. What has to be understood is that $14 million is being spent this year on cancer research, and we do not isolate entirely each form of research into cancer as if it had no relevance to another, because it obviously does.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What really angers me about the argument, I suppose, is that we cannot simply take a relativity of deaths, look at that mortality rate and say that therefore it should get X percentage of the total budget. If I look at a disease such as MS, which does not kill people at the same rate but which causes a gradual decline in their functions and makes their life very much less a pleasure than for many of the rest of us, what do I say to those people? Do they not get any money because not enough of them die?  What do I say to the asthmatics&mdash;there are only a handful? Do I say, `Look, not enough of you die, you get nothing. You can't have any money because so many die from something else.'? It is a ridiculous priority to try to put on medical research. We cannot do it.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I referred yesterday in a radio interview to a disease I had never heard of until a few days ago called Goucher's Syndrome, which affects children. It is costing almost $1 million a year to treat each one of those 40 kids in Australia who have got this very unfortunate problem. We have to work out a way of assessing them and getting enough money to them just to keep those children alive. No research has been done into that disease&mdash;nothing.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What do I say to those 40 kids? Do I say, `There aren't enough of you dying, I am sorry; we are not going to research you.'? Why do we not get around to a proper assessment of the way that we divide our research funds? I have been through the whole list of the recommendations in the Bienenstock review, which was completed some months ago. One of them is for a strategies and priorities committee to sit with the NHMRC to set some priorities which may result in breast cancer being a priority or may not; that would depend on the views of those who sit on that committee.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I have accepted that recommendation because I think it is important that we make sure that the NHMRC is in some way reflecting the priorities that Australia wants to set it. But I do not think we will ever set the priorities by measuring the deaths and then having a pro rata division of the spoils. To do that would ignore the misery of hundreds of thousands of Australians, and I will not be a part of it.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1025" SPEAKER="Newman Sen J.M." NAMEID="BE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. The minister has just given us a disgraceful answer that only demonstrates the abysmal failure of his government over 11 years to produce a proper amount of funding for medical research in this country. I ask the minister why he is now talking about getting around to a proper assessment when his government has had 11 years to get around to a proper assessment and has had priorities for research directed to the National Health and Medical Research Council which include research into the health of the aged, women and Aborigines. If prostate and testicular cancer are not diseases of the aged, what are they? If breast cancer is not a disease of women, what is it? These have been the priority areas the minister's government nominated for several years. Why has more funding not been put into those areas? Two cents per man and 20c per woman is a national disgrace.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1025" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I think that points out the appalling ignorance upon which this question is based. If we look at diseases of the aged, has Senator Newman heard of cardiovascular disease? It kills an awful lot more people than the diseases the honourable senator mentioned. I have not actually added up whether the pro rata basis for the numbers who die from it is good enough for Senator Newman and therefore whether the amount is good enough. I have not added that up, and I will not, for all the reasons I gave earlier.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">There are many diseases of the aged that are a problem. I was discussing Alzheimer's and dementia with Minister Howe this morning with regard to the response we will have on them in the budget. We are looking at a whole range of those priorities every single day and we will continue to deliver on them. Over the course of the years of the Hawke and Keating governments, as a percentage of the budget medical research expenditure has gone from 0.37 per cent of one per cent, where it was when the opposition was in charge, to the 0.45 that it is now.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1026">
<TITLE>Tourism: Economic Recovery</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1026" SPEAKER="West Sen S.M." NAMEID="1X4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1X4">Senator WEST</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Tourism. There have been  reports of increasing visitor arrivals into this country and of the hotel industry feeling the effects of economic recovery. Are these reports accurate? What are the ramifications for the tourism industry of economic recovery, especially in the area of job creation?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1026" SPEAKER="Ray Sen The Hon R.F." NAMEID="UI4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UI4">Senator ROBERT RAY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Statistics from the 1993 September quarter international visitors survey show that we are attracting an increasing number of international visitors, who are staying longer and spending more. This means increased foreign exchange earnings and, most importantly, increased job opportunities for young Australians. Year-to-date figures show that international arrivals are 15 per cent higher than the same period last year, with international arrivals into Perth up 18 per cent.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">While arrival increases are an important indicator of the strength of the industry, the number of nights spent in Australia by tourists and the amount of money they spend directly influences the profitability of industry and the benefits that accrue to Australia. In the September quarter 1993, the number of nights spent by international visitors in commercial accommodation increased by 23 per cent over the same period in 1992. The increase in visitor nights has been matched by a seven per cent increase in average visitor expenditure.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">These improved results are reflected in new surveys of hotel business confidence by Horwath &amp; Horwath in its Perth and Queensland hotel markets, which indicate growing confidence about hotel business prospects. Over 80 per cent of hoteliers surveyed in Perth and over 60 per cent in Queensland are now more optimistic than they were six months ago. An Ernst &amp; Young survey of 16 four- and five-star hotels in Sydney, commissioned by the Tourism task force, shows that hoteliers expect an increase in staffing levels of between five and 20 per cent over the next 12 months. This equates to between 600 and 2,300 new jobs, which is great news for new job seekers.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1027">
<TITLE>Educational Exports</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1027" SPEAKER="Bell Sen R.J." NAMEID="7U4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7U4">Senator BELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Employment, Education and Training. Yesterday the minister referred to the growth in educational exports and, quite rightly, was pleased to tell us about the industry's value of about $2 billion. He singled out the university sector as a significant beneficiary of the growth that has occurred. I ask the minister today to provide us with an indication of how much secondary colleges and business colleges contribute to the $1.2 billion earned by the education sector in 1993. Could the minister also give us a comparison with earnings for the education industry in 1988-89 in terms of university and secondary and business college sectors? Finally, what kind and level of support is now being provided by the government to the private education sector in terms of its participation in the overseas education export market?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1027" SPEAKER="Schacht Sen The Hon C.C." NAMEID="4J4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="SCIENCE AND SMALL BUSINESS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4J4">Senator SCHACHT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I appreciate the fact that Senator Bell informed me that he was going to ask a question relating to an answer that I gave in the Senate yesterday. Because question time is being held early this morning, I have not yet been able to get enough information from the Department of Employment, Education and Training. I will get that information as soon as I can. Apparently, it requires some effort to ascertain the information. At the moment the department is not able to give a precise figure of the value of private verses public institutional income based on the export earnings of education.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Apparently, a Roy Morgan survey of international students was commissioned by the Department of Employment, Education and Training. We are hopeful that will provide the information. I hope to be able to come back to Senator Bell next week with the information that he requests.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1027">
<TITLE>Hollywood Repatriation General Hospital: Sale</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1027" SPEAKER="Evans Sen C.V." NAMEID="AX5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="AX5">Senator CHRIS EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Veterans' Affairs. The minister recently announced the government's sale of the Hollywood hospital in Perth to the Ramsay Health Care group. Can the minister advise the Senate whether the final handover of the hospital has taken place yet.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1027" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The official handover date of Repatriation General Hospital Hollywood to Ramsay Health Care Pty Ltd was midnight last night. On 5 December last year, I announced that the Ramsay Health Care co. was successful in tendering for the purchase of Hollywood following the state government's decision not to integrate that hospital into the state public health system. Although the changeover means the beginning of a new era for Hollywood, veterans and war widows will continue to have access to high quality treatment services.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">RGH Hollywood has had a magnificent record in caring for Western Australia's veterans and war widows over the last 47 years. I cannot speak too highly of the care that the hospital staff have provided to the veteran community over that period. I am pleased that many of them have decided to stay with the hospital under its new private ownership. The manner in which veterans have been cared for has created a unique relationship between the hospital and the ex-service community. I am very confident that this relationship will now continue.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Ramsay Health Care will develop Hollywood as a 300-bed private teaching hospital and will upgrade it with a $20 million building and refurbishment program and a significant expansion of services. The successful sale of Hollywood to Ramsay Health Care means that we have achieved our two principal objectives. The first objective was to secure Hollywood's future as a top level teaching hospital while guaranteeing continuing access for veterans and war widows. The second objective was to give Western Australian veterans and war widows greater access to the local treatment they want and need as they grow older.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">At the same time as the hospital is transferred, the repatriation private patient scheme will be operating in Western Australia and this will ensure that our entitled beneficiaries are able to be treated locally if they prefer. Through this scheme the government will spend $500 million over the next 10 years to purchase treatment for entitled veterans and war widows in Western Australia.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The government's contract with Ramsay Health Care clearly stipulates that the new operator, Hollywood Private Hospital, must deliver high quality treatment services for veterans and war widows in Hollywood. It must proceed with a hospital upgrading and refurbishment program. The new operator must also maintain services of special interest to the ex-service community, such as the aged and extended care department, the palliative care unit and the special psychiatric unit.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This week the Department of Veterans' Affairs posted an information package to all entitled veterans and war widows in Western Australia to help them understand the benefits that will be available to them through the repatriation private patients scheme. The Western Australian treatment monitoring committee, on which key ex-service groups are represented, will play a very crucial role in monitoring the new health care arrangements. I thank the ex-service community for the positive and supportive role they have played in bringing about the new arrangements. I also acknowledge the thorough and professional way that officers of the Department of Veterans' Affairs have handled a most complex tendering process with a very good outcome for war widows and veterans in Western Australia.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1028">
<TITLE>Aboriginal Health</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1028" SPEAKER="Tambling Sen G.E.J." NAMEID="6E4" PARTY="NP" ELECTORATE="NT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6E4">Senator TAMBLING</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Health. I commend the minister on his newfound concern for Aboriginal health in the Northern Territory, 11 years after Labor took office and four years after the infamous `no child will live in poverty' deadline.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Collins" NAMEID="OF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OF4">Senator Collins</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;All you have done is bag Aboriginals for your whole parliamentary career.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6E4">Senator TAMBLING</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Jump in the lake and read the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS>.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order!</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I take a point of order. I take it the interjection was referring to Senator Tambling. It was clearly a reflection on him, and should be withdrawn.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do think it is a reflection on Senator Tambling and I would ask you to withdraw, Senator Collins.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Collins" NAMEID="OF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OF4">Senator Collins</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It absolutely was a reflection on Senator Tambling, and I withdraw it.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6E4">Senator TAMBLING</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is: now that the minister has won national attention on this issue of Aboriginal health, how will he tackle the appalling state of Aboriginal health throughout Australia, or will he walk away from this promise, just as he walked away from his 1991 commitment to territorians to look at ways of stopping habitual drunks spending their social security money on alcohol?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1028" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I really worry about the kind of person who can ask that sort of question; I really do. There is, I hope, going to be a lot more national attention given to the question of Aboriginal health. I certainly would be endeavouring to get as much of it as I could, because I do not think there is a bigger disgrace in Australia today than the state of Aboriginal health. It is an incredibly serious problem. All of us have to take some blame for that.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Ian Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Ian Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Why didn't you?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I make the point to Senator Macdonald, who interjects, that when I went to Katherine five years ago, I saw the Katherine Gorge. I did not take a trip a quarter of a mile off the highway to see people living in conditions that I described a few weeks ago as similar to those of war ravaged African nations.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Ian Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Ian Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You haven't told anybody for 11 years.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You have not been telling anybody about it; what are you talking about? What is your record? Look at the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS> yourself, you clown. You have said nothing. I notice now it is `we', not `I'. That figures.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order!</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Herron" NAMEID="VW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VW4">Senator Herron</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I take a point of order. I would like your ruling on whether `clown' is acceptable parliamentary language, in light of your previous ruling.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do not think it is unparliamentary, but I do think it is unnecessary.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Like a lot of other Australians, I took that opportunity to see Katherine Gorge. I did not go to see a lot of the other things because I suppose I was never fully enough aware of them as I never saw enough of them. I intend to try to make sure that Australians are made aware of them.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">If we are going to spend the amount of money necessary and take the decisions necessary to make an impact on Aboriginal health status, we will have to try to take Australia with us. We will have to try to make sure that, in the lounge rooms and around the dinner tables of Australia, there is discussion of the problem. So I do intend to press this issue. I am certain that we will have a really significant announcement in the budget that will enable Australia finally to make an impact on a problem it should have been tackling not simply in the last 11 years but in the last 200 years.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1028" SPEAKER="Tambling Sen G.E.J." NAMEID="6E4" PARTY="NP" ELECTORATE="NT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6E4">Senator TAMBLING</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Senator Richardson seems to be full of emotional compassion, hope, endeavour and discussion but is absolutely short on details. Rather than just letting us rely on some significant expenditure in the budget, I would like to know about the areas, programs and priorities that the minister will pursue in this particular area. We have had significant expenditure in budgets for the last decade, and that has not achieved any result. What are the changes to the programs and the priorities that will concentrate on Aboriginal health?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1028" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do not think it is possible to detail prior to the budget what will happen in the budget. That detailing should happen on budget night. To give honourable senators some indication, what I would like to do is greatly expand the role of Aboriginal medical services. There ought to be a much greater number of Aboriginal health workers trained because the numbers of those are poor, and the training they have received so far has been inadequate.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We need to move some specialist services out to Aboriginal communities to give them access to a service they have never had. I have spoken to the colleges about that. There will be something in the budget for that. We will be doing things like looking to the armed services for their mobile hospitals. In many cases, we think they can be taken around to some communities that could desperately do with them. As well as all of that, there needs to be better federal coordination of the effort of all the departments because environmental health is of course the key. I hope I can supply the medicines to make people better when they are feeling sick, but if the causes of the sickness remain, of course they will keep getting sick. We have to attack both of those things at the same time.</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Herron" NAMEID="VW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VW4">Senator Herron</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I raise a point of order. You ruled previously that calling somebody a clown was not unparliamentary. I draw your attention to the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS> of 9 May 1984 when the Deputy President at the time ruled that the interjection was unparliamentary. Senator Macklin was called a clown. The word was ruled unparliamentary, and had to be withdrawn.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am not aware of all the precedents that have been set in this house. I do not think it is a matter of such great import. I will check the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS> record and, if that is so, I will rule it unparliamentary.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1029">
<TITLE>International Year of the Family</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1029" SPEAKER="Denman Sen K.J." NAMEID="FY5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FY5">Senator DENMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister for Family Services. Can the minister inform the Senate of the federal government's plans to promote the International Year of the Family at the local level?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1029" SPEAKER="Crowley Sen The Hon R.A." NAMEID="ZF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="FAMILY SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZF4">Senator CROWLEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;As honourable senators would know, it is not too long since I launched the federal government's campaign theme for the International Year of the Family called `Let's look after families'. That theme particularly called on the community for participation and partnership this year for the betterment of Australian families. That partnership and participation calls on all levels of government, the business sector, trade unions, community and all sorts of organisations, particularly those at the local level.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I particularly want to highlight today the involvement of local government in the International Year of the Family. I am pleased to be able to inform the Senate that a very significant partnership has been formed for the International Year of the Family between the federal government and local government through the Australian Local Government Association.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Tomorrow at the Sutherland Shire Council in Sydney I will formally announce a joint federal-local government project. This cooperative approach will be directed at tangible outcomes at the local level for Australian families. We hear a lot of criticism that nothing much will come out of IYF. Through this project, particularly at the local government level, some very real and immediate improvements for families will be able to be set up and may happen sooner rather than later.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Most honourable senators, when visiting local governments, would notice, as I have, a very big difference in the delivery of services between one council or shire and another. We are concerned about taking a cooperative approach with local government to set up models of best practice for local government in the delivery of family services and for local governments to be able to use those best practice models, or models of excellence, to assist other local councils with providing increased services and benefits to families in their local electorates. Four Australian shires will be selected to develop these models of excellence. They will include large and small shire councils in rural and metropolitan areas. Having piloted those models of excellence, the Local Government Association will distribute information relating to them to all councils and shires throughout Australia.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This is a very useful project. I notice that a number of honourable senators are interested in this answer; they know what services are provided for families at the local community level. It is interesting to note the contribution made at the local community level during the recent Sydney bushfires. It was very much a local community grassroots response, matched by local, state and federal governments. Very important also was the response that came from the Australian community generally. Some of those people had special skills, such as fire fighting and so on; but there was a tremendous response from the local community in supporting each other&mdash;family for family, person for person. It was an excellent example of what Australians can be like, particularly with support from local government.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This joint project is about assisting that process to happen, even in the absence of disasters. I am looking forward to the outcome of this very useful cooperation between local government and the federal government in the IYF.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1030">
<TITLE>Australian Secret Intelligence Service</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1030" SPEAKER="Gibson Sen B.F." NAMEID="BX5" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BX5">Senator GIBSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. Yesterday the minister denied that ASIS officers had been refused access to personal files. Is it not a fact that one agent's spouse was refused permission to view files held by the Inspector-General containing information and allegations made against the spouse concerned? Why did the minister mislead the Senate on this matter yesterday?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1030" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, as I recall, the question yesterday was whether, by any direction of mine, someone had been refused access to files. That was the question; my answer was no. I had certainly seen reports about the conduct of certain of these inquiries. In at least one such inquiry&mdash;including, I think, the case the honourable senator is referring to, and this is what I said yesterday&mdash;a file had been refused disclosure initially but at a subsequent stage in the process of dealing with that particular grievance that file was handed over. The file dealt with a highly sensitive matter, and there were questions of source protection, privacy and so on involved. It was an understandable judgment made by the person in question at that stage, but it had nothing to do with me.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Really, it is a bizarre question. The honourable senator should read his <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS> before coming up with that sort of stuff again.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1030" SPEAKER="Gibson Sen B.F." NAMEID="BX5" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BX5">Senator GIBSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I did read the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS>. Yesterday the minister denied that access was prevented to the files by these people who have been complaining about ASIS. Will the minister give the Senate an assurance today that these people will get access to their files?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1030" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I did not deny yesterday that access was not granted. I said that access had not been denied as a result of any decision by me. I also referred specifically yesterday to a case where it had been denied. I could hardly be denying&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Senator Gibson interjecting</EMPHASIS>&mdash;</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That was the whole point of my answer yesterday: I could recall one case where it had happened but it had been corrected later on. I am not going to make any undertakings about anything. These matters of dealing with grievances are presently the subject of jurisdiction by the Inspector-General for Intelligence and Security, in whom I have the utmost confidence.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">One of the things that will be looked at in the course of this judicial inquiry, which I announced in principle yesterday, will be the whole system of complaint resolution and grievance procedures. If there is anything that can sensibly be done to change or improve those procedures, no doubt it will be done as a result of this inquiry. In the meantime, I am not going to plunge around in that sort of territory. It is wholly inappropriate for a minister to do so.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1031">
<TITLE>Water Pollution</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1031" SPEAKER="Coulter Sen J.R." NAMEID="TF4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator COULTER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories. Has the minister seen the reports by the Sydney Water Board detailing the massive extent of pollution of rivers, estuaries, harbours and oceans by sewage and stormwater run-off in the Sydney area? Is the minister aware that every city in Australia suffers severe environmental degradation from the increase in sewage and stormwater run-off, with Glenelg, in my own state, being labelled by the Surfrider Association as the most polluted beach in Australia? In the light of Senator Evans's reply to my question on Monday in which he said that as countries become richer they can spend more on the environment to ensure a clean environment, and in the light of the fact that Australia is a rich country, is the federal government going to adequately fund the clean-up of Australia's sewage and stormwater problems? If not, why not?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1031" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have seen a number of the reports to which Senator Coulter has referred, although I probably have not seen all of them. Certainly in Sydney the question of the damage done by sewage and stormwater run-off has been a pretty big issue for the last four or five years. My understanding was that the Fahey government, and the Greiner government before it, had a strategy over time to ameliorate the problem. However, there would appear to be a fair bit of evidence in recent times that that strategy has failed and that it needs to be looked at again. I do not think it would be a matter of debate between us that, in terms of constitutional responsibility on these matters, that responsibility does lie with the states. When I was environment minister, and I believe since then, it has been a matter of encouraging the states to live up fully to that responsibility. There is a varying response from the states; some do, some do not and some never will.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In terms of whether there needs to be a national plan, we first have to decide whether the states would agree to one in the first place. As honourable senators know, many states resist any sense of national involvement in these matters because they believe it cuts across their constitutional role. I will ask Mrs Kelly what stage the matter has reached at the moment, what discussions have been held, and what plans she has. It is a hell of a problem and I do hope that, nationally, we can do something to assist the states to remedy it.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1031">
<TITLE>Leather Industry: Administrative Appeals Decision</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1031" SPEAKER="Brownhill Sen D.G.C." NAMEID="RD4" PARTY="NP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RD4">Senator BROWNHILL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister for Science and Small Business. I remind the minister of the AAT decision in September 1993 which effectively reclassified imports of chrome split leather&mdash;the sort used in gardening gloves and industrial aprons&mdash;to duty free status. Is the minister aware of the concern this decision has caused to members of the Australian Tanners Association? Further, is he aware that before the decision was made there was no consultation with manufacturers which were gearing up to manufacture in Australia on the basis that the duty free status of chrome split leather would be maintained? Can the minister give the industry an assurance that no decision to amend the customs tariff will be made until there have been full discussions with all sectors of the leather industry?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1031" SPEAKER="Schacht Sen The Hon C.C." NAMEID="4J4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="SCIENCE AND SMALL BUSINESS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4J4">Senator SCHACHT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have to confess that until Senator Brownhill gave me notice a few minutes ago of this question I was not aware of that particular reclassification decision. As Senator Brownhill would be aware, there are literally hundreds, if not thousands, of those decisions made every year. I do understand the importance of the tanning industry in Australia. It is an industry that is rapidly becoming world competitive. The quality of its output and its product certainly is improving and that is why we are getting exports and also import replacement in Australia.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I understand that many Australian furniture manufacturers are now using Australian sourced leather because it is of world standard and is world competitive both in price and quality. As a minister in the industry portfolio, I assure Senator Brownhill that I understand the importance of the tanning industry. As I said before, I do not know the details of that decision but I will give an assurance that the customs department within the industry portfolio will have broad consultations with the tanning industry association about this decision. When those consultations are completed and any further decision is made, I will give further information to the Senate.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1032">
<TITLE>National Competition Policy</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1032" SPEAKER="Burns Sen B.R" NAMEID="2F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2F4">Senator BURNS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask the Minister for Administrative Services what implications the Hilmer committee's report on a national competition policy has for the Department of Administrative Services commercialised businesses?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1032" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" MINISTERIAL="TRADE; ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is a very timely question because I am hoping that the Council of Australian Governments will actually make some positive responses to Hilmer tomorrow. It is very important nationally that it does, from both the trade point of view and that of my administrative services responsibility, to which I will refer in a moment. It is a very important micro-economic reform in which I hope the states will cooperate.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That part of the Hilmer report recommendations most directly relevant to the Department of Administrative Services is that which refers to what is now called `competitive neutrality', an issue on which Senator Campbell and I have had some jousts in recent months. It is expressed in the recommendations of Hilmer in this way:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Government businesses should not enjoy any net competitive advantage by virtue of their ownership when competing with other businesses.</PARA>
<PARA>I support that principle and its corollary. That principle has been the central characteristic of the commercialisation of DAS businesses. We have had some debate here about how well we have achieved it, and that is a legitimate debate, but that it should be the objective I think is agreed.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"> As an aside about the DAS businesses, I should say that the Hilmer report acknowledges the productivity improvements and cost savings achieved by the DAS businesses in meeting the challenges of commercialisation, and I welcome the fact that that has occurred and has been recognised. It has been the result of a lot of diligent and difficult work by a lot of public servants, and it has gone substantially unnoticed.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The concern I want to refer to on the eve of the COAG meeting is the fact that the principle of competitive neutrality is not being applied by the states in some instances&mdash;in some instances only&mdash;in respect of either their instrumentalities competing with the Commonwealth or the Commonwealth instrumentalities having adequate opportunity to compete for state and territory work. For example, I quote the case of Australian Government Analytical Laboratories which operates on a fully commercial basis in relation to the costing and charging of its services. It competes with state-owned laboratories which are able to offer lower prices because they are subsidised by the state government. We have actually had Commonwealth tenders won by state governments because their bids were lower because they were subsidised by the states.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The states advocate that we should adopt micro-economic reform, and we should, and that we should apply competitive neutrality to our businesses, and we do&mdash;but they do not. It is very important that they start to recognise this and to address the consequences for the efficient use of public sector resources and the efficiency of the economy.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We also have the example of a territory government which has a procurement policy which specifically excludes Commonwealth government instrumentalities from tendering for work. That means that even when the Commonwealth business is the most efficient it is excluded from work simply by this policy which cuts directly across the principle of competitive neutrality.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">People will get up here and make speeches about the importance of this neutrality, but they will not do it when they go back to their own states. I do not ask, within the Commonwealth or within the wider economy, for any special advantage for Commonwealth businesses, but they are entitled to compete on an equal basis. If people think the competitive neutrality principle is not being properly implemented, let us have that debate, as we have. I think it is. But it is very important that the state governments be prepared to give to those Commonwealth instrumentalities that same opportunity for competitive neutrality. I hope that will flow from the Hilmer report adoption by COAG tomorrow, which is so important.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1033">
<TITLE>Veterans' Entitlements: Merchant Mariners</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1033" SPEAKER="MacGibbon Sen D.J." NAMEID="YH4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YH4">Senator MacGIBBON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question without notice is directed to the Minister for Veterans' Affairs. On 18 November 1993, Mr Peter Morris, a Labor member in the House of Representatives, successfully moved that those merchant mariners who served in the Second World War be entitled to the benefits of the Veterans' Entitlements Act. He also moved that the Seamen's War Pensions and Allowances Act 1940 be repealed, pointing out that only five per cent of merchant mariners who served in the Second World War have received a disability pension. As that motion was carried in the House of Representatives, when is the government going to act on it?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1033" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The government certainly recognises the significant contribution Australian merchant mariners have made to the defence of Australia. World War II Australian merchant mariners are covered for war injuries under the Seamen's War Pensions and Allowances Act. War injuries are defined to restrict the scope of compensable conditions essentially to those conditions which can be shown to be directly related or due to enemy action. Claims under the Seamen's War Pensions and Allowances Act are determined on the civil standard of proof, that is, on the balance of probabilities.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In January 1989, my predecessor as Minister for Veterans' Affairs, Ben Humphreys, asked the then Deputy President of the Repatriation Commission, Ms Jocelyn McGirr, to report on the needs of Australian mariners, Commonwealth and Allied veterans and Allied mariners. Ms McGirr's report was released in October 1989. Australian merchant mariners are already eligible for service pensions under the Veterans' Entitlements Act and disability pensions under the Seamen's War Pensions and Allowances Act.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In the 1991-92 and 1992-93 budgets, the government acted on a number of the major recommendations in the McGirr report. Treatment benefits available to Australian merchant mariners were considerably extended and Australian merchant mariners were given access to compensation arrangements which provided a sum of $10,000 to any Australian merchant mariner who was illegally detained in Nazi concentration camps during World War II.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I am surprised that Senator MacGibbon is not aware that the question of benefits available to Australian merchant mariners is one of the terms of reference for the Baume review committee, which is currently looking at a range of issues involved in the compensation program of the Department of Veterans' Affairs. That committee, chaired by the Hon. Peter Baume, who is well known to many coalition senators in this place, will be reporting to me by 18 March 1994. At that time, the recommendations of that report will be examined by the government in the context of the next budget. One of the issues that will be reported upon is the issue raised by Senator MacGibbon in his question today.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">There is very little more I can say, or am willing to say, to Senator MacGibbon, apart from the fact that it will be addressed in a budget context. Of course I have made myself aware of the resolution of the House of Representatives and the arguments in support of that resolution that were so effectively mounted by the honourable member for Shortland, Mr Peter Morris, and other members of the House of Representatives.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1033" SPEAKER="MacGibbon Sen D.J." NAMEID="YH4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YH4">Senator MacGIBBON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Will the minister outline the changes the government has made since 18 November 1993? He seemed to imply that changes had been made. My impression was that the changes consequent on the McGirr inquiry preceded this motion by Mr Morris. Is Mr Morris correct in asserting that only five per cent of merchant mariners qualify for a disability pension?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1033" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have nothing further to add to the substantive answer I gave to Senator MacGibbon's question. The issue of entitlements for Australian merchant mariners will be addressed after the report of the review committee into the compensation subprogram of the Department of Veterans' Affairs is brought down and handed to me on 18 March.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I stress again that the matters that are canvassed in that report&mdash;and they are far more wide ranging, as I am sure all senators would know, than just a question of entitlements for Australian merchant mariners&mdash;will be then addressed by the government in the context of the next budget.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1034">
<TITLE>National Health and Medical Research Council: Funding</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1034" SPEAKER="Harradine Sen B." NAMEID="6H4" PARTY="IND" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6H4">Senator HARRADINE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Health, and it follows an answer that the minister gave earlier today. Is it a fact that the minister is saying that priorities for National Health and Medical Research Council funding should be considered by another body which is responsive to the views of the public? How will the parliament be involved in that? Can the minister tell the Senate whether he agrees that the National Health and Medical Research Council should spend public moneys on supporting experiments which require the aborted foetal subjects to be as fresh as possible, with adequately developed organs? The fact is that such experiments; that is, grafts into patients with diabetes, have been singularly unsuccessful. Would the minister examine that as well, and identify to the Senate how these issues are going to be dealt with in response to public fears?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1034" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I gave an indication earlier that, as part of the response to the Bienenstock review of the National Health and Medical Research Council, Bienenstock recommended a committee, which he called SHARP, which is about health and research priorities. I have accepted that recommendation. That committee therefore will be set up later in the year. But I have to respond formally, and before I do that I intend to discuss with the National Health and Medical Research Council the exact details of that&mdash;and who should be on it.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">If it is to reflect priorities&mdash;which is a broad term, and therefore needs some input from a source other than the strict research community&mdash;then it is going to be a matter of determining the kinds of people who ought to be on it. I have not done that yet, but I will discuss that with the National Health and Medical Research Council first, and I will present a formal response to that review. I intend to do that here in the parliament so that the honourable senator and others with an interest in the area can form an opinion before we take any action.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In terms of any particular research which the NHMRC has funded, I would have to check on the matter and get a response. As the honourable senator would be aware, not every bit of research is going to be successful. There are failures in the research community. That is a matter of fact. That is why so much money is always spent in developing any cure or improvement, because researchers will follow up on as many leads as they can. Some will lead nowhere but, just occasionally, one leads to the right place.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">So there are failures, and I cannot ever administer a program under the NHMRC where we do not have them. That is an inevitability. All we can do is hope that the standard of those who are allocating the grants is so high that they do not make mistakes. In the end they recommend those grants to me. I am yet to refuse one. I am not aware of predecessors refusing them either, because the group in NHMRC is impressive, and when they come up with recommendations&mdash;experts examining research programs to determine how good they are&mdash;then I think it is difficult for politicians to start refusing them.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1034" SPEAKER="Harradine Sen B." NAMEID="6H4" PARTY="IND" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6H4">Senator HARRADINE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I accept the point that was made by Senator Richardson about whether experiments are successful. But precisely what right has the NHMRC got, being a science-driven organisation, to examine major issues which are involved in this question that I have raised? Those major issues involve the reliance of experiments on the deliberate abortion of foetal subjects, the inability of the subjects to grant consent to the utilisation of their organs for donor purposes, questions of brain death determinants and sentience, the nature and timing of interventions likely to occur on the aborted foetal subjects in the course of harvesting transplantable organs, and the social consequences of those procedures, including the implications for other incompetent human subjects manifesting features which differ from the norm. How does the minister say that the National Health and Medical Research Council, which is a research group, is capable of determining those issues?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1034" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="HEALTH" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will have to get an answer for Senator Harradine on the specifics of his question, because I do not have one. I will go and do that. But I guess if one is going to say that the National Health and Medical Research Council should not have any role in determining whether or not that kind of research would be proceeded with, then one has to wonder what we do with the medical profession at large, because the National Health and Medical Research Council is largely made up of pretty eminent people from the profession.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Newman" NAMEID="BE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator Newman</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You should spend more on research.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have already said we are going to announce the largest increase in research spending since federation on budget day, and I will proceed to do that. There is a dilemma in trying to determine those questions. It is very hard to understand how to cut the profession out. I will get a fuller answer tomorrow.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1035">
<TITLE>Broome Crocodile Farm</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1035" SPEAKER="Ellison Sen C.M." NAMEID="9X5" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9X5">Senator ELLISON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs. Further to the minister's recent intervention in the development of the Broome Crocodile Farm, and an article on this matter in the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">West Australian</EMPHASIS> on 21 February 1994 by Frank Devine, is the minister aware of any surviving Djugan people who have traditional ties to the area in question surviving in Broome, and if there are such people, how can the minister justify his intervention in this matter on behalf of the Kimberley Land Council which represents the Yawuru people?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1035" SPEAKER="Collins Sen The Hon R.L." NAMEID="OF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NT" MINISTERIAL="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OF4">Senator COLLINS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am sure that if there is a problem in this area Fred Chaney will find out about it.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1035" SPEAKER="Ellison Sen C.M." NAMEID="9X5" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9X5">Senator ELLISON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Can the minister advise whether he will continue his declaration which comes up for consideration on 5 March this year?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1035" SPEAKER="Collins Sen The Hon R.L." NAMEID="OF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NT" MINISTERIAL="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OF4">Senator COLLINS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have just said that the minister, as I am sure Senator Ellison knows full well, has just appointed Mr Fred Chaney&mdash;a person I am sure well known to members of the coalition&mdash;to investigate this issue and I am sure he will do it effectively. Senator Ellison did not like him, I know, but he is doing it.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Gareth Evans" NAMEID="VD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator Gareth Evans</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask that further questions be placed on the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Notice Paper</EMPHASIS>.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
</QWN><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1036"><TITLE>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS ON NOTICE</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1036">
<TITLE>Export Market Development Grant Applications</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1036" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" MINISTERIAL="TRADE; ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (Minister for Administrative Services and Minister for Trade)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have a further answer to a question on notice asked by Senator Ian Macdonald on 21 December 1993. There are nine questions and the answer is in nine parts. I seek leave to have it incorporated in <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS>.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Leave granted. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">The answer read as follows</EMPHASIS>&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator McMullan&mdash;The answers to the honourable senator's questions are as follows:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(1) (a) 2473</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b) 3251</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(2) 771</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(3) 603</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(4) Compared to 1991-92 claims, fewer 1992-93 claims had been processed by 1 December 1993. The main factors for this situation were increased levels of relatively late lodgments for the 1992-93 grant year (November 1993 lodgments as a proportion of total lodgments were higher than in prior years), implementation of new techniques to improve risk management procedures and a high proportion of difficult and high risk claims requiring in-depth investigation.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(5) While I acknowledge that there may be anecdotal evidence to support such an assertion, there are many factors which influence exporters' overseas marketing activities. However, Austrade advises me that it responds quickly to requests from grant applicants for urgent assessment.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(6) No.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(7) No.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(8) Not applicable.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(9) Not applicable.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1036"><TITLE>COMMITTEES: CONDUCT OF SENATORS</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1036" SPEAKER="Beahan Sen M.E." NAMEID="NE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;After question time yesterday Senator Alston asked me a question, the pertinent part of which was whether the writing of an article by Senator Loosley involved him in a conflict of interest in respect of his membership of the select committee on the print media within the terms of standing order 27(5). While the interpretation and application of the standing order is not a matter for the Senate in appointing senators to committees, I do not believe that the writing of an article by a senator on the subject matter of an inquiry by a committee, of which the senator is a member, involves any conflict of interest.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">A conflict of interest within the meaning of the standing order arises when a senator has an interest in the subject matter of an inquiry which conflicts with the senator's duty to participate conscientiously in the conduct of the inquiry; for example, if a senator is a shareholder in a company the activities of which are under investigation by the inquiry. The other matters raised in the question do not refer to any questions of order and are therefore not matters for the chair. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1036" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Deputy Leader of the Opposition)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP> (10.35 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate take note of the statement.</PARA>
<PARA>As I recall, I also asked you whether you considered it improper or unethical for Senator Loosley not to have disclosed the fact that he was a member of the committee. I therefore ask you to reflect on why it is not proper for you to at least put the Senate's position on such a matter. After all, any reasonable reader of that article would regard Senator Loosley as somehow a quasi-independent observer rather than a very active partisan player. In those circumstances, I would have thought that the Senate would have an interest in full disclosure. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Murphy" NAMEID="FX5">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FX5">Senator Murphy</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;We can certainly have a debate.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;We can have those discussions at some other time. If those opposite want a meeting after this, we will arrange it. I was just asking you, Mr President, to reflect on whether it might be desirable for the Senate to have a view on whether there should be full disclosure in such circumstances. I accept your ruling that there is not a direct conflict of interest, but I think the Senate is interested in upholding standards of propriety.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We would all expect senators to not want to mislead the public and, in these circumstances where otherwise people might be inclined to believe that somehow Senator Loosley was not a member of the committee and was simply expressing an independent view, the facts are quite to the contrary. I would have thought in those circumstances it would be helpful for you to give some indication of what standard you think ought to apply. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have nothing to add to the statement I have made, but I would just say that the article in question which I have a copy of now has a by-line which says, `Senator Loosley, ALP senator'. I would have thought that that identifies him quite clearly. I would have thought that it is a question of editorial consideration as to whether they put anything in addition to that, not a question for the Senate.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Again, if you are suggesting that somehow Senator Loosley volunteered the proposition but&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, on a point of order: is Senator Alston seeking leave?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Are you seeking leave, Senator Alston. You have no right to speak otherwise.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Yes, I am. I seek leave.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Leave not granted. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1037"><TITLE>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1037">
<TITLE>Breast Cancer</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1037" SPEAKER="Bishop Sen B.K." NAMEID="SE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator BISHOP</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (10.38 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Health (Senator Richardson) to a question without notice asked by Senator Newman this day, relating to the funding of cancer research.</PARA>
<PARA>In doing so, I wish to point out the cynicism of that answer as it was given trying to justify the fact that only between $1 million and $2 million a year is provided by way of research money into breast cancer, a disease which, as I said on Tuesday, kills between six and seven women a day. Senator Richardson's defence was couched in the terms of the interjection he made to me across the chamber. He said to me that the speech and the points that I made on Tuesday about breast cancer did not get a line's reporting from the press gallery because he checked. What an appalling way to measure the value of women's lives in Australia. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The fact of the matter is we had a dorothy dix question to Senator Crowley on the year of the family and we were made to hear feel-good statements about collectives, not about individuals. I said on Tuesday that I knew women who had died of the disease and that I now have another friend who was just diagnosed and is about to become very active in making other people aware of the fact that for 11 years this government has done nothing. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">As I said, we had an answer to a question on the year of the family&mdash;a dorothy dixer&mdash;which said absolutely nothing. Many of those women who are dying of breast cancer are mothers with quite small children. If the government needs something to justify finding additional money to spend, surely the year of the family can provide such a reason. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">On Tuesday I said that the way in which the government prioritised its spending has caused great anger. I pointed out that in the so-called health benefits for women statement published in the budget papers the government has provided $51 million in the name of AIDS education for women, trying to place upon them a guilt in respect of being able to prevent the disease. According to the government's own documentation, only 127 women have had the disease. The point is that there is valid reason to give research for AIDS funding but there are also enormous calls for proper funding to be made available for women who are dying of breast cancer. No improvement has been made in more than 20 years. The daughters of women who died 20 years ago now realise that there is no prospect of an improvement in the treatment, and they themselves are looking at being in a risk category. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Richardson rose and said what a good job the government is doing and that there is no case to answer because the speech I made did not get a line in the press&mdash;that is, we are to measure the success or failure of human lives by his collectivist tag. The government stitches up deals with groups, and to hell with individuals. The concern on this side of the Senate is with every individual Australian woman who contracts the disease. The treatment has not been improved because the research has not been done. Mammography has been introduced, but it does not treat the disease. There are plenty of examples of women who have to get in line to get the treatment. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Herron's speech on Tuesday outlined, with great precision, the neglect and the cynicism that this government, in office for 11 years, has shown in this area. Using the number of lines that appear in newspapers to measure whether there has been adequate funding for a problem which is grave and needs attention is not the way that Australian women deserve to be treated. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1038" SPEAKER="Reynolds Sen The Hon M." NAMEID="XI4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XI4">Senator REYNOLDS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (10.42 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Bishop has talked about feel-good statements. We have heard a lot from Senator Tambling about emotional compassion. Senator Newman talked about Senator Richardson's statement being disgraceful. There has been a lot of criticism from the opposition about the government's policies. It is very easy for the opposition simply to sit back and say that the government is not doing enough. The government has done a great deal in its national breast cancer prevention program.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">On the issue of medical research, I would suggest that it is important to look at the coalition's record and its intention in Fightback. I am sure that the coalition's policy, when we get to hear it, will need to vastly improve on the policy of John Hewson, as announced in Fightback. Let me read from the opposition's Fightback document. We realise that it may not be Senator Bishop's document, but it certainly was the opposition's document when it went to the people at the last election. Let us hear the opposition's commitment to the prevention of breast cancer and testicular cancer. The document states:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">Medical Research</EMPHASIS></PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Medical research will continue to be strongly supported&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA>easy to say&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">to maintain Australia's record of excellence in this area.</PARA>
<PARA>It goes on to state:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The role of the general practitioner in practising preventative medicine has been downgraded in recent years. We believe it is vital that general practitioners again be encouraged to practice preventative medicine . . . </PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The Coalition believes that a strong national capacity in the public health area should be maintained, over and above efforts at a community or area health level.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">AIDS is a major problem. The Coalition will maintain a strong research effort into AIDS and will ensure that as new, effective drugs emerge they are rapidly made available to treat patients with AIDS. We will also continue public education programs aimed both at the prevention of AIDS and public understanding of the needs of people with AIDS.</PARA>
<PARA>There was no mention of any other area of medical research funding. If we look at women's health, we find that in almost two pages of documentation about what the opposition may have done in regard to women's health, apart, of course, from cutting the health budget by $8 billion&mdash;</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Bishop" NAMEID="SE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator Bishop</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You are the government, and have been so for 11 years and have done nothing.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XI4">Senator REYNOLDS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Of course, we are the government, and we are responsible for the national breast cancer prevention program. But what I object to is the hypocrisy and cant from those on the other side about what we may or may not have done. Senator Bishop singled out AIDS education and suggested that it was a waste of money, when in actual fact that is the only area of medical research funding that she mentioned.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In relation to public health measures, perhaps this is the section of the document which will contain some indication of the concern that Senator Bishop put to Dr Hewson when he was drawing up his Fightback package. It reads:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Public health measures to be introduced will include:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">development of goals and targets . . .</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">priority for AIDS programs . . .</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">close attention to women's health, including $8 million for mobile mammography . . .</PARA>
<PARA>That is something that the government has already been involved in and for which it has vastly increased expenditure. There is still no mention of the issue on which Senator Newman, Senator Bishop and, no doubt, Senator Patterson and Senator Herron will continue to grandstand in this place, as if they are the only people who have ever considered funding for medical research in the area of women's health. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"> This government has a proud record in women's health promotion. It should be remembered we developed a federal-state women's health program. There was no such program from the coalition during all its years in office. It was a Labor government that had to introduce it. Opposition senators then have the temerity to come in here and pretend that somehow medical research in terms of women's health was their priority. It is not in their Fightback documents; it is not in any of Senator Bishop's public speeches&mdash;</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Bishop" NAMEID="SE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator Bishop</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Oh yes, it is!</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XI4">Senator REYNOLDS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have certainly not heard her speak of it in this place.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Bishop" NAMEID="SE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator Bishop</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Oh, what a shame you have not been to every one.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XI4">Senator REYNOLDS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am certainly missing out then, Senator Bishop. <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">(Time expired)</EMPHASIS></PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1039" SPEAKER="Newman Sen J.M." NAMEID="BE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (10.47 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;We have just heard a diatribe from Senator Reynolds, who put her finger on the real problem just as she was completing her speech when she mentioned women's health promotion. Sadly, for the last 11 years that is the gist of what we have had in women's health&mdash;promotion, but not too much action. Sadly, after 11 years of this government we have seen a lot of talk and not much action. There have been 11 years in which we could have seen that medical research funding increased, and people's lives saved.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Crowley" NAMEID="ZF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZF4">Senator Crowley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Over $100 million.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The pity of it is that in this chamber now, with the harridans who were screeching opposite, there is little or no likelihood that we are going to get bipartisan support for something that is desperately needed&mdash;an increase in medical funding, a focus on prevention of breast cancer, a focus on the quality of treatment and best practice in breast cancer work.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Government senators interjecting</EMPHASIS>&mdash;</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Government senators can yell as much as they like, but the truth is that they have not done well. Their actions over the last 10 or 11 years are what our criticisms are based on. In the last budget there was no increase for research funding when this government had promised it in its election policy. It was a broken promise straight off; there was no increase in funding. We wait to see what we get in this budget.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Crowley" NAMEID="ZF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZF4">Senator Crowley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I raise a point of order. The honourable senator knows that that is a complete untruth. I ask her to take account of putting facts on the record in here. There was an allocation&mdash;I can cite a specific one, and there were others&mdash;for women's research. Her claim is absolutely out of order and completely untrue.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator McKiernan)</EMPHASIS>&mdash;There is no point of order. </PARA>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That point of order was just an attempt to try to avoid the issue. I did not focus my question today only on breast cancer. I also focused on the fact that this country is spending only something like 2c per man per year for research into testicular and prostate cancer, yet 2,300 men die each year from those cancers. This is a very serious matter, particularly for older men in this country, and we understand that the health of older people is one of the government's research priorities and has been, apparently, for some years. Some research priority, if we are not going to save the lives of 2,300 men as well as 2,600 women.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Carr" NAMEID="AW5">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="AW5">Senator Carr</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr Acting Deputy President, I rise on a point of order. I understand that Senator Newman referred to honourable senators on my left and right as harridans. According to the dictionary, a harridan is a vicious old hag. I believe that word to be offensive and ask that it be withdrawn.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask that that word be withdrawn, Senator Newman.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I withdraw it and substitute `witches', if that will do any better.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Newman, I ask for an unconditional withdrawal of the word you used.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I did withdraw it. I substituted `witches'.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is hardly unconditional. I ask for an unconditional withdrawal of the word.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I withdraw unconditionally. Unfortunately, the witches on the other side are not prepared to recognise that the real problem in this issue is that there is only half a loaf to divide between the medical researchers in this country when there needs to be a whole loaf. Senator Richardson can talk as hard as he likes about the need for an assessment of priorities, but the problem lies in there not being enough funds to distribute in the first place. The government recognised this when it went to the election. It promised that it would double health research funding. It has had its first budget since that election, and it did not honour its promise. We will be waiting anxiously to see what it does in this budget about its promise.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The people of Australia recognise that this government has had 11 years to do something about setting priorities and putting more money into the bucket for medical research. That is where the failure lies. Something like 5,000 men and women in this country are dying each year from two of the most common cancers, yet we are spending 20c per woman per year and 2c per man per year on research. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What is also interesting is that the same national health goals and targets implementation working group on cancers that says we need more money says that the incidence of breast cancer will increase from 63 cases per year per 100,000 women to 81 cases per year per 100,000 women by the year 2000. That is a rate of increase of 2.1 per cent per annum, yet there has been absolutely no drop in the mortality rates for breast cancer in the last 40 years. It is no good the government pointing to previous governments in this country. For 11 years it has had the opportunity to do something about the mortality rates. When the government is facing an increase of 2.1 per cent per annum in years to come, this situation has become a crisis. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We recognise full well the need for resources for clinical breast cancer trials. The government's own report has told us that that is an important means of evaluating new therapeutic methods and a scientific basis for developing effective methods of breast cancer treatment. The government has refused to accept the hand being held out by the Leader of the Opposition (Dr Hewson) for bipartisan support on this matter through assistance to private individuals by making donations to breast cancer research tax deductible and by having a national day for funding of breast cancer. The Prime Minister (Mr Keating) ignored the Leader of the Opposition altogether on the issue. <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">(Time expired)</EMPHASIS></PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1040" SPEAKER="West Sen S.M." NAMEID="1X4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1X4">Senator WEST</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (10.54 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I begin my remarks by looking at what the spending was on medical research back in March 1983. It was 0.37 of one per cent. Let us look at what the expenditure is on medical research in 1994. It is 0.45 of one per cent.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">People say that we are not spending enough and should spend more. I agree. Of course we would like to spend more. But perhaps those opposite might tell us why they did not do very much when they had the chance and why they feel they can be so critical of what we have done?</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I find it very interesting that they should talk about the mortality rates for this disease not changing in 40 years. Perhaps they should look at the mortality rates overseas. If mortality rates for this disease are dropping overseas, we should be asking what the hell doctors in this country are doing. Why are they not looking at overseas research and treatment if it is actually reducing the mortality rate? That is the question that the medical profession has to answer. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We have also heard from those opposite that we are spending only one or two cents per person on this disease. Are they suggesting that we go through all the diseases and allocate funding on the basis of their rate of mortality? If that is what those opposite are suggesting, what should we be doing for people suffering from non-fatal but nevertheless very debilitating diseases? Do they suggest that we spend less money because those sorts of diseases do not cost lives&mdash;or cost fewer lives? That is the sort of logic they are putting up. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">To quote Senator Newman, `People's lives are saved by this research'. Is she saying that the amount of money spent on research depends on the number of lives lost? Senator Newman should try saying that to people suffering from osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis, people who represent a large proportion of the community. I think she would find that they disagree with her. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Medical research also depends to some degree on the level of specialisation and the body of knowledge that we have in this country. When it comes to performing clinical trials, we have to look at the number of people we have to make those trials statistically valid and of true research importance. We should be very conscious of that fact. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Newman is saying that the number of lives saved is an important factor in determining the amount of money spent on research. I would like Senator Newman to say that to those suffering from the rarer malabsorption syndromes&mdash;the small children who do not make it past three or four years of age. With some of these disorders, each year there may be only five or six sufferers across the country who die. Is Senator Newman suggesting that because it is such a small number we should not be spending any money on research? If she is, that is a stupid argument. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Zakharov" NAMEID="FE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FE4">Senator Zakharov</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Heartless!</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1X4">Senator WEST</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is a heartless argument. What should we be saying to the one million people who suffer from diabetes and die not from it but from related illnesses? Do we tell them that we are using the criteria suggested by those opposite for the allocation of research money? That is heartless and ridiculous.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The opposition should be reminded that it was going to cut $8 billion from health outlays. It was not going to spend any more money on aged care so, presumably, there would be no further research in that area. It was going to cut veterans affairs spending by $8 billion. It was going to make total savings to its budget of $40 billion. I would be very sensitive about this matter if I were a member of the opposition because its cold, heartless and cruel attitude to the allocation of research funding is appalling. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1041" SPEAKER="Herron Sen J." NAMEID="VW4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VW4">Senator HERRON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (10.59 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The word `harridan' would not even enter my mind when considering the diatribe just delivered on the other side. I would not have the temerity of accusing anybody on the other side of being a harridan, even after the sort of behaviour we have just witnessed.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Reynolds said that we were grandstanding. The greatest grandstander in this parliament is the Minister for Health (Senator Richardson)&mdash;every week, a disease a week. He started on the AIDS bandwagon. Now he is off the AIDS bandwagon. Then we saw him on the front page of the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Australian</EMPHASIS> walking around with an Aboriginal lady and saying that he was going to cure Aboriginal health problems; he got one tap turned on for one Aboriginal tribe and was on the front page of the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Australian</EMPHASIS>. I have already told him that I have got the statistics on Aboriginal health for when this government came to power 11 years ago. What has happened since then? In the 11 years since this government came to power Aboriginal infant mortality has increased and Aboriginal health has deteriorated. The real answer to the Aboriginal health problem is to educate the Aboriginals in relation to their own care. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I will be reminding the minister of his promises, year by year, if we are all still here&mdash;and hopefully we will be in government. The latest thing is breast cancer and he is on the breast cancer bandwagon. The coalition has put forward proposals on breast cancer research in a bipartisan fashion, but suddenly it has become a political football. It should not be a political football. We should not be hearing this screaming diatribe from the other side about what we might or might not have done&mdash;</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Zakharov" NAMEID="FE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FE4">Senator Zakharov</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;How about the screaming diatribe from your side?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VW4">Senator HERRON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I would tell Senator Zakharov that it is a bipartisan approach that we are pursuing. I take Senator Richardson's example. He said today that the reason he does these things in relation to Aboriginal health is to highlight Aboriginal health so that the community as a whole appreciates the problem and so that it will discuss the problem, and out of that we will get community support. I agree with him totally. That is what we are trying to do in relation to breast cancer research. The reality is that the government allocates $1.2 million for breast cancer research and $750,000 of that goes to one institute in New South Wales. That $1.2 million would not even run Senator Richardson's personal staff, his department, his salary or his travel. Yet that is the amount of money that is spent on breast cancer research in Australia. It is a national disgrace. We are trying to bring attention to it so that that amount of money will be increased.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The reality of breast cancer is absolutely tragic. Forty per cent of women who get breast cancer die of it; that is half the population of this country. The incidence at the moment is one in 12. Lady senators here&mdash;</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator West" NAMEID="1X4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1X4">Senator West</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;What is the rate overseas?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VW4">Senator HERRON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The overseas rate is much the same, depending on which country one is in. Senator West knows that we heard about Korea where the incidence of the disease affects women between the ages of 35 and 45&mdash;a distinct difference to our own population. As Senator Newman said, there are young women in this country who get breast cancer, and young children and families who are affected by that. It is not a political football, and it is a disgrace that it has become one. It should not be; it affects all of us. There is an increasing incidence of breast cancer in this country; it has increased by 20 per cent in New South Wales in the last 10 years. In America breast cancer affects one in 10 and the figure is going down to one in nine with the ageing population; there is nothing magic about this.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I was appalled at Senator West casting aspersions on the treatment of breast cancer in this country. We are world standard. In many respects we are leading the world in relation to the lesser surgery that is done. I instanced the other day the shortage of radiotherapy departments and equipment in this country to handle this disease. I say to those opposite: do not make this matter a political football; it is not a political football. It is far more important than that. Those opposite should not denigrate themselves by trying to attack us about something that we were talking about 10 or 11 years ago, before they came to government. It is a national disgrace. I applaud Senator Richardson in his aim to increase the amount of money being spent on medical research. Only 25 per cent of applications for research to the NHMRC succeed, and the paltry sum is a disgrace. It is a disgrace that those opposite have not increased the amount in the 11 years they have been in government. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1042" SPEAKER="Zakharov Sen A.O." NAMEID="FE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FE4">Senator ZAKHAROV</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (11.04 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I would like to make a very brief comment to correct a couple of things said by honourable senators opposite. I do not think it was intentional, but Senator Herron said that 40 per cent of breast cancer sufferers die from it, and in the next sentence said that we were talking about half the population. I do not think he was intending to link those two figures; obviously, not half the population get breast cancer.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator MacGibbon" NAMEID="YH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YH4">Senator MacGibbon</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Half the population are women.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FE4">Senator ZAKHAROV</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Half the population are women. I wanted to make sure that the record did not imply that half the population were at risk. Also, reference was made to figures showing that the rate was not dropping. I point out that this is the pattern all over the world, not just in Australia. That again is a function of the ageing of the population. With most diseases that strike people later in life, the incidence is not dropping because the population is ageing; we are living longer. When women's life expectancy was in the forties, obviously a much lesser proportion died of breast cancer. With women's life expectancy now nearing the eighties, obviously the incidence will rise.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1043">
<TITLE>Broome Crocodile Farm</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1043" SPEAKER="Ellison Sen C.M." NAMEID="9X5" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9X5">Senator ELLISON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Western Australia)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (11.06 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy (Senator Collins) to a question without notice asked by Senator Ellison this day, relating to the Broome Crocodile Farm.</PARA>
<PARA>There was a very sound reason for my question and the supplementary question. It has come to my attention over the last few days that there are some surviving people from the Djugan tribe who have had traditional ties with the land in and around the Broome Crocodile Farm. The ramification of that fact is that the Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs has gone ahead and, under the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Heritage Protection Act, intervened in the development of that crocodile farm and issued a declaration halting any development for 30 days. He has now set about a mediation process, presided over by Mr Fred Chaney, whereby there will be mediation between the Yawuru people, who initiated the application by the Kimberley Land Council to the minister to have this intervention come about, and Mr Malcolm Douglas, the proprietor of the Broome Crocodile Farm. But that excludes any surviving Djugan people, and they say that they are the traditional custodians of this land. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What the minister said in a very high-handed manner was, `I will just assume that the Yawuru people are the claimants in this instance, I will set up a mediation process which recognises them only, and we will take it from there'. I am querying whether the minister made sufficient inquiry before he issued this declaration. I challenge the minister to show that he did carry out such inquiry. I put it to the Senate that he did not. We will have a fiasco, with continuing uncertainty over the development of the Broome Crocodile Farm and with any chance the Djugan people might have had being ruled out. It will be a matter of game, set and match. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The government has taken the view that automatically the Yawuru people are the claimants here because they are the ones who have the ear of the Kimberley Land Council, which one could say has the ear of the government. I do not think it is Mr Chaney's position to investigate, as Senator Collins said; the minister should have investigated this matter more thoroughly before he intervened in such a high-handed manner. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator McKiernan)</EMPHASIS>&mdash;Order! The time for debate on motions to take note of answers has expired. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1043"><TITLE>COMMITTEES: CONDUCT OF SENATORS</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1043" SPEAKER="Loosley Sen S." NAMEID="BS4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator LOOSLEY</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (11.09 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I seek leave to make some remarks on the President's statement earlier this morning.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator McKiernan)</EMPHASIS>&mdash;Is leave granted?</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Alston" NAMEID="LD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;After discussion with members on all sides of the chamber, I indicate that there is still a motion before the Chair to take note of the President's statement. I had spoken to it, the President had replied, and I had said a few words. Rather than denying Senator Loosley leave, which I am not minded to do, and in order to enable others to contribute&mdash;I understand Senator Carr and Senator Kernot are interested&mdash;I suggest that we simply resume debate on that motion. I do not think anyone wants to prolong the matter, but I think that would be the most effective way of enabling proper debate to take place on the matter.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator McKiernan)</EMPHASIS>&mdash;Order!  The motion that you were talking about, Senator Alston, has actually been disposed of. </PARA>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Alston" NAMEID="LD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Could I therefore suggest that Senator Loosley seek leave to move a further motion to take note of the President's statement, and we will grant leave.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is that your wish, Senator Loosley?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator LOOSLEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I seek such leave in those terms.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Leave granted. </PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator LOOSLEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate take note of the statement made by the President this day.</PARA>
<PARA>I do not wish to delay the Senate unduly as I know estimates committees are looming and they are of particular importance. But I do want to make some remarks about the President's statement earlier today and some of the issues that Senator Alston raised. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Alston seems peculiarly sensitive about the article that I wrote in the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Sunday Telegraph</EMPHASIS> last weekend. I could perhaps understand why he might be sensitive on the issues that I canvassed and why others might be sensitive because what that article sought to do from my personal perspective as an ALP senator&mdash;and the article was clearly marked, Stephen Loosley ALP senator&mdash;was to expose the grotesque way in which the committee on the print media has been operating and to draw certain parallels with other committees that operated in other jurisdictions, particularly in the United States. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I used terms such as `witch-hunt' very deliberately because that was the direction in which the committee, to my mind, appeared to be going and still appears to be going. It also exposed the manner, to an extent, in which the committee has been operating. We have seen over the past several weeks a gross lack of consultation within the committee framework. The government has been deliberately excluded from decision making on the committee itself, even though there are four government senators sitting on the body, and even though at times very useful contributions have been made by the government on issues such as how best to look at cross-media ownership. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">When people wanted to wave subpoenas around and begin threatening gaol terms, the government senators suggested we simply communicate, for example, with Minister Michael Lee, and ask for a briefing. The briefing was forthcoming. We suggested on another occasion, for example, a private meeting with Treasurer Willis to try to sort out some of the contentious matters. That option, for example, was never taken up. Again, it was falling back on the notion of legal advice, subpoenas and threatening gaol. All of those issues were canvassed in the article. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The suggestion has been made that perhaps it should have been stated very clearly at the bottom of the article or across the top of the article that I was a member of the committee. But no-one need be in any doubt about my position. For heaven's sake, over the past several weeks, in concert with my colleagues Senator Sherry, Senator Murphy and Senator Carr, every Labor member of the committee has been continually identified in the mass media, whether it be ABC television, commercial television, SBS, the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Sydney Morning Herald</EMPHASIS>, the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Australian</EMPHASIS>, the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Canberra Times</EMPHASIS> or any other number of mass media outlets. No-one need be in any doubt about my position. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">No-one also need be in any doubt that I used any material that was either sensitive or confidential to the committee in preparing that article. Everything that I used was a matter of public record, whether in Australia or in the United States. I did not seek to be a casual observer. I did not seek to be objective. I sought to argue a position. It was a elementary matter of free speech. And on this committee, continually, issues arise of free speech, basic civil liberties and fundamental human rights. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I am very pleased to be numbered amongst those people, with Senator Murphy, Senator Sherry and Senator Carr, who continually defend the fundamental rights of Australians against the encroachments of those who would seek arbitrarily to wave subpoenas at people, to threaten people with gaol or to intimidate witnesses before the committee. This is a very important issue, not only in the immediate framework of the year 1994 but for the long-term future. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I do not apologise for one word in that article. I do not resile from anything which I wrote. I am proud to have made that contribution. I am very pleased that it stung a number of people opposite. One can always tell when something has hit home when one's opponents complain loudly about it. Every word in that article, from my position and, I believe, from the position of the government, is an accurate reflection of what has been happening or what has happened on other occasions in other jurisdictions. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The point that I made fundamentally was that, as of 1857, the American congress had legislated away its power to prosecutors, when there were rulings of the court that the congress could only gaol people until the congress rose, until the session ended. By 1857 congress reasoned that this power should be given away to the judiciary. It voluntarily legislated it away. I could have added, of course, something which emerged in the hearings in Sydney&mdash;and Senator Carr and Senator Sherry will remember this, when we had Mr Mulholland before us, for example&mdash;that as of 1971 the United States house of representatives decided it would not even contest anymore people's right to plead the first amendment in refusing to hand over documents. That is not even contested by the United States house of representatives. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Yet here we are in 1994 threatening people with gaol, incarceration, imprisonment&mdash;dusting off the cells downstairs! My view is that the power ought to be legislated away by this parliament, by the House and the Senate and given to prosecutors. Contempt findings may certainly be made but the power to prosecute, the power to incarcerate, the power to imprison ought to go off to where it should be, with the judiciary, under separation of powers under the Australian Constitution. That, basically, is what we will arrive at at the end of the day when this committee is operating.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Alston has said to me both privately and publicly, has said to my colleagues, `Assume goodwill'. This morning he began to approach matters from the point of view of consultation. We will see how that works. If he has changed his view, if he has changed his perspective, if he has changed his approach, we will see if that works. It has not worked to date because it has not been tried. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We have seen things come into the chamber that have never been before the committee. Senator Carr tells me that, as of 8.20 last night, AAP had the details of a meeting that was still in progress. We have been faced with constant leaking of things to the media from informed sources on the committee&mdash;not the government, because we have not been part of the play. We have not been part of the loop of information. We have been excluded from the processes of deliberation and decision making. Things have been organised behind closed doors. There has been no openness; there has been no transparency&mdash;none whatsoever. I hope that will change. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I am saying to Senator Alston as chairman of the committee now: we are prepared to take him on his merits; we are prepared to test that view. Senator Alston is accusing me of, alternatively, contempt for process, of unethical behaviour, of impropriety. I will not level those charges against Senator Alston, although a number of my colleagues might be minded to. Let me just say that, as the chairman to date, Senator Alston has not distinguished himself. I hope that changes. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">When we write the minority report on this committee, it will be about ethics and propriety. It will be about courtesies that ought to be observed on Senate committees. It ought to be about the manner in which Senate committees ought to operate. As chair of the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances or the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade, I never walked into this chamber without having consulted the committee and had a committee decision below the basis on which I was operating and moving proposals in the chamber. I have not done that and I am unaware of anyone on the government side who has ever done that. Perhaps we might debate that later on. But if we are ever to achieve any results, there has to be a capacity on the part of the committee to involve everyone and to take contributions from everybody on the committee. It cannot be selective and it cannot be a deliberate policy of isolating a minority on the committee in order to achieve straight five-four votes all the time, as we have seen to date on this committee. A characteristic of this committee is that inevitably there have been majority decisions on the contentious issues. That really ought to change. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I will say more about these matters in future articles that I intend to write on the workings of the committee. I hope those articles have exactly the same impact that the original piece has had today. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1046" SPEAKER="Kernot Sen C." NAMEID="XW4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator KERNOT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Australian Democrats)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP> (11.19 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The President ruled that there was no conflict of interest under the quoted standing order and, strictly, according to his explanation that is true. But we are not here today debating whether Senator Alston is a good chairman of this committee. We are debating whether by selectively misleading, by omission of a vital fact, Senator Loosley misled people who read his column. I believe that he did.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I believe that it is absolutely pertinent to the interpretation of that article that Senator Loosley identified his membership of that committee. I am referring, of course, to the power that has been cited far too often during the sittings of the Senate print media committee. He says, `This seems to have escaped much of the coalition which dominates the committee in strong alliance with the Democrats'. All he needed to say was,`And, as a government member of this committee, I object to that' or, `As a government member of this committee, I have a different view' or, `As a government member of this committee. . . whatever'. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I think all members of the committee enjoy benefits from being a member of that committee&mdash;benefits of access to information; of access to legal opinions. Senator Loosley is entitled to his opinion. All I am saying&mdash;and I say this about any newspaper column&mdash;is that readers are entitled to transparency. They are entitled to read the article and make a connection if they wish. It is not enough simply to say, `Senator Loosley is an ALP senator'. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The critical fact is that he is an ALP senator representing the government on that committee. He is expressing views, expressions of interest&mdash;whatever. He is seeking to be objective in making his comments on the matters on which he is speaking, but he cannot be, as a member of that committee. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">It is not a matter simply of editorial policy. Senator Loosley is the one who introduced the notion of ethics into this debate. It is not a matter of people being stung. It is a matter of the ethical behaviour of a person who is a member of this place and who has the opportunity to use a newspaper column. He should adhere to basic standards. A basic standard should be that he identifies that he is a member of that committee, because that one fact is probably the most pertinent fact that ought to be included in that article. He is guaranteed newspaper space. I believe he has some obligations as a result of that. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Nobody can oblige him to present the facts honestly. Mention was made yesterday about the inaccuracy of Senator Loosley's view of what congress has or has not done. Additionally, as he wants to get into the facts that have not been mentioned in here, it is his government which passed the Parliamentary Privileges Act 1987, which put in place the sanctions. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;He wasn't here then.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator KERNOT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Loosley was an influential member of the Labor Party in New South Wales in 1987. If he wanted to have a say, he could have. This is another fact which has been selectively omitted. All he had to say was, `This was put in place by a Labor government in 1987. I do not like it, and I think the parliament should rescind it'.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Loosley" NAMEID="BS4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator Loosley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I just said that then.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator KERNOT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;But Senator Loosley has not said it in the article. He has implied the very opposite; that it is everybody else's fault that these powers exist and may be tested, and it has nothing to do with the Labor Party nor, indirectly, with him.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Can we see your next newspaper article as subeditors?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator KERNOT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Certainly. Senator Loosley also said that nobody need be in any doubt about his position; he is so unbelievably well-known throughout Australia that everybody would see `Stephen Loosley, ALP Senator' and know everything he stands for. The starting point should be that a person comes fresh to an article, and is entitled to read that article, make the connection between the author's position and the article, and come to whatever conclusion he or she sees fit, based on the facts that are in this article. That is the whole point. The whole point about Senator Alston's question to the President is whether he behaved appropriately in not disclosing his committee membership.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">It is quite clear that Senator Loosley did not. It would have been very simple to say, `I am making these expressions of opinion from the perspective of a government member of this committee'. That is the most pertinent fact. Irrespective of what the honourable senator thinks about sanctions and the actions of the United States Congress, the most pertinent fact that readers are entitled to know is that Senator Loosley is not simply an ALP senator, but a government member of that committee. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1047" SPEAKER="Carr Sen K.J." NAMEID="AW5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="AW5">Senator CARR</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (11.24 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The President has indicated that there is no conflict of interest in terms of Senator Loosley writing an article for the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Sunday Telegraph</EMPHASIS> on 20 February. In that article he argued cogently and forcefully that the behaviour of some members of the Senate in establishing committees such as this inevitably leads to a miscarriage of justice, in that individuals are persecuted and, potentially&mdash;as has been seen in historical cases&mdash;their careers and lives are destroyed. He also indicated that the right of this Senate to gaol people was one that he did not support, and that he would like to see some changes in the legislation and the way in which these matters are dealt with by the Senate.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">It was perfectly proper for Senator Loosley to put a point of view about his position regarding what are fundamental questions in this country about the rights of citizens and their relationship to their parliament. It is perfectly proper for him to be able to say, as a member of this parliament, that this is not an appropriate use of this place. That, in essence, is what has happened here. It is not proper for the Senate to be used to dragoon and abuse the citizens of this country by threatening them with gaol and, as Senator Loosley has indicated, attempting to intimidate and coerce people, in order to force a political agenda through this place&mdash;which clearly has happened with the establishment of this committee. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What is apparent is that this is an inevitable consequence of the establishment of committees such as this. It is not designed primarily to deal with substantial issues of public policy, but as a political stunt&mdash;a political agenda&mdash;by certain members of this place to attempt to prosecute their political claims and political views about actions that have taken place. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">It was abundantly clear from the examination of the terms of reference that were forced through this place that this committee has been established with the premeditated view that a political agenda should be prosecuted using the powers of this Senate. As Senator Loosley has indicated quite clearly, that is a view that members of the government do not share. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Kernot indicates that we should have transparency of action, and I agree. There should be transparency of action of all senators in this place. The threat to intimidate people, gaol them, and drag public servants before the Bar of this place should be exposed. The public should understand exactly what is involved. We should be clear about what people are intending to do with the citizens of this country. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We talk about public accountability. What about the public accountability of senators to treat the citizens of this country with a measure of respect; to be able to explain to people what senators are trying to achieve? The transparency works both ways. Honourable senators opposite have to be clear and make sure that they are publicly accountable for their actions. There should be no apology for this. If they are so right in what they are doing, they should explain themselves. We are quite clear that we intend to explain to the public exactly what is involved with the abuse of the powers that have been proposed in this matter. Public interest immunity does not mean that anybody can refuse to cooperate with the Senate, but we are saying that the right to gaol people has to be challenged very seriously. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Kernot" NAMEID="XW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator Kernot</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You don't tell people that it is your government's bill; that is the relevant point.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="AW5">Senator CARR</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Of course Senator Kernot talks about my government. It is quite apparent that the legislation, in terms of the privileges matter, was brought through this place and is a product of discussion from within this place. Is the honourable senator saying that she did not vote for it? Is she saying that she did not support it? That is a lot of nonsense. Is the honourable senator saying that it was not a product of the discussion within this chamber? Of course she is not. There is a political agenda.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What we see here are the standing orders, which in essence come down to standing order 5(4); that is, five votes against four votes. This is what this committee is all about. Five votes of those opposite against our four votes; and those votes are going to be used to abuse the power that they perceive we, as a Senate, have. The basic standards that they talk about in effect mean that the rights of citizens in this country will be trampled upon in the pursuit of their political agendas. Those opposite want to abuse and intimidate&mdash;and attempt to score a political point about the operations of this parliament. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We are talking about the substantive issue&mdash;and that is what I am interested in&mdash;of foreign ownership in this country. There are plenty of opportunities in this place for senators to discuss the substantive question of who owns what and why. But that is not the question. We have not heard anyone from the conservative benches in this chamber talk about the substantive issue because the policy of the conservatives on this matter is that foreigners can own whatever they like. Those opposite do not believe in putting restrictions on foreign ownership. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This government has a position on foreign ownership and it is rightly subject to public debate. The question has to be: what is the position of the conservatives? The terms of reference as indicated by this chamber suggest to me that that should be the matter that is under review. That is clearly not what is under review. What has been under review is the rights of public servants and the freedoms of public servants in terms of their civil liberties and their capacity to resist the overbearing abuse of power by members in this chamber. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We have indicated that there is some concern about the right of Senator Loosley to have his say. That is a concern that we have. We have our say publicly because this committee is not functioning to allow the members of the Labor Party to have their say. It is quite apparent that the operations of this committee are fundamentally flawed. What we are seeing is the committee's abuse of not only the citizens of this country, but also the procedures of this place. The terms of reference were established to allow that to happen. The chairman is able to make statements on behalf of the committee. The problem is that statements are being made on behalf of the chairman, which is fair enough, but it should be clear that that is what they are&mdash;the chairman's statements, not necessarily the committee's statements. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">At 20 past eight last night I picked up the AAP wire service and I read that the request for confidentiality before the committee would not always be met. Senator Alston told the AAP that requests for confidentiality would not necessarily be accepted in relation to all documents. That is not a decision of the committee. I cannot recall any resolution to that effect of the committee. But Senator Alston indicated publicly at 20 past eight last night, according to the AAP wire service, that that is what the position would be. That is fair enough, it may well turn out to be the case, but it is not appropriate for the chairman to announce unilaterally the position of the committee without a resolution of the committee. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Standing order 5(4) is not the appropriate way to run this place, and that is essentially what is going on. That is what our complaint is. Senator Loosley is correct when he says that he has nothing to apologise for. He has a right to put a view about his attitudes before the people of this country. Day in, day out, our positions have been explained with regard to all the mass media of this country. Senator Murphy, Senator Loosley, Senator Sherry and I have been quoted directly on our views. It is preposterous to suggest that there is any conflict of interest. The position of the President in that matter is entirely appropriate and completely justified. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1049" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Deputy Leader of the Opposition)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP> (11.33 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I go to the heart of Senator Loosley's defence to what we are debating today and that is whether he should have disclosed the fact that he was a member of that committee when he wrote that article, for which I presume he was handsomely paid. His defence was essentially this: `I am such a well known public figure that anyone reading that article would immediately say, "That's Stephen Loosley who is a member of the print media committee".'</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Rubbish.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That was his defence. That is the way he put it. He said, `Anyone who reads the newspapers, anyone who watches television, knows that I am on that committee and so is Senator Murphy, Senator Sherry and Senator Carr'. This is a matter of public notoriety, if you like&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Sherry is confirming my point. What follows from that is that he does not need to tell the punters that he is a member of that committee because the minute they pick up and read an article by Senator Stephen Loosley they immediately say to themselves, `That's the bloke on the print media committee'.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It doesn't matter.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Precisely. Senator Sherry is making the point. That is a preposterous suggestion. That article is there to influence public opinion and to have casual and not so casual observers read it, ingest its contents and be persuaded by it. To the extent that they read it and it purports to express views on the way in which committee systems operate or how disgraceful it is that people can still be put in goal in the 20th century, I would have thought it is a very relevant matter to know that the writer of the article is heavily and intimately involved in the whole political debate that goes on in that committee. Senator Sherry might like to think that that committee is not having much of an impact, but that is somewhat contradicted by&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Sherry" NAMEID="ZW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator Sherry</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is having an impact.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is? Okay. That is interesting. It is very important to remember how we come to this point of considering whether or not sanctions ought to be applied. Senators will remember what Senator Gareth Evans had to say this morning in question time. I do not think he is notorious, but perhaps a future article of Senator Loosley's might like to reflect on this. In the final report of the Joint Select Committee on Parliamentary Privilege&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Murphy" NAMEID="FX5">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FX5">Senator Murphy</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Are we here to debate the sanction or not?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Just a moment. In the Joint Select Committee on Parliamentary Privilege, of which Senator Evans was the deputy chairman, a number of these matters were canvassed, in particular, whether or not the right of ultimate sanction should remain a matter for the parliament as opposed to being transferred to the courts&mdash;which I think is what Senator Loosley is now arguing. What that committee said in chapter six was:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">A House is not confined to breaches of undoubted privilege such as those conferred by Article 9 of the Bill of Rights. It is the ultimate arbiter of what constitutes contempt and is bound neither by the courts nor by precedent . . . It is easy enough, by concentrating on serious matters, to pick out actions which may be held to be contempts of Parliament.</PARA>
<PARA>One of those was disobedience of the lawful directions of parliament or its committees. </PARA>
<PARA>It continues:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">If, as we think should be the case, imprisonment is to be maintained as an ultimate sanction against those who commit serious breaches of privilege or other serious contempts of parliament, we have decided that the jurisdiction should remain with parliament.</PARA>
<PARA>Here we have a committee that over a period of years seriously considered all of these issues and rejected what Senator Loosley is putting. In other words, this government, with Senator Evans intimately involved in that whole process&mdash;because he actually moved amendments which tightened it in many respects&mdash;made a decision that it was proper for the committee to retain the powers it had to compel the disclosure of documents and the ultimate sanction of fine or imprisonment. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In those circumstances, I would have thought Senator Loosley, as Senator Kernot rightly pointed out, should at least have the political courage to say, `This is the government's position. It has never been queried to date but in the context of this committee I am now suddenly objecting to it. I have not until now objected to this but a committee has been set up on which we happen not to have the numbers'. I am sure those opposite are acutely aware of the power of numbers; that is how they come to be in government in the lower house. There happens to be a second chamber and, whether they like it or not, that chamber also operates by the power of numbers. A committee is able to be set up and, for once, those opposite do not have the numbers on the committee.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That is not a licence for us to ride roughshod over those opposite and it is not our intention to do so. But let me  take the opportunity to explain why it was that notice of a motion was given in the parliament yesterday&mdash;and I thought those opposite would have understood the reasons advanced elsewhere for that fact. It was in no way an attempt to predetermine what the committee would do. It was simply to safeguard the position of the Senate because, unless that had happened, it would have been too late to have given the notice today for the matter to have then come on on Monday, by which time the committee's original motion would have bound us to adhere to an earlier date and we would not have been able to take evidence from a whole range of witnesses, whom Senator Loosley concedes are a necessary part of the inquiry. So let us not be precious about all that. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">As I understand the position of those opposite, they do not really object to that extension of time; they object to the manner in which it came about. I have said to them and I will say it publicly that it is my intention to consult at every opportunity, to the extent that a note was circulated to them that they thought did not allow the full opportunity to consult, so I will do my very best to make sure that we improve on that situation in the future. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">What Senator Carr was talking about was not a briefing&mdash;I am looking at an AAP print-out&mdash;and was in no way canvassing what the committee might have decided or would decide in the future. It was simply stating facts which I would have thought are very much on the record. Indeed, it has been pointed out to me that I have been quoted as saying that this would be an option for the committee. That is in no way canvassing what was discussed. As I am sure all senators would appreciate, we have only to look at the standing orders of the parliament to see that the Senate is given clear powers, that public servants are required to cooperate, that documents must be produced when requested, and that it is a matter for the Senate to make these decisions. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Loosley can argue as much as he likes&mdash;it is a matter of political contest&mdash;that somehow he has this right to claim executive privilege and that no-one should go behind it. It just happens that he is flying in the face of all the conventions, all the judicial decisions over the last 20 years and all that Senator Gareth Evans said in the Senate in 1982. Senator Loosley ought to at least acknowledge all that and acknowledge that he is flying in the face of what is on the public record. Therefore, it is proper for me in the circumstances to make that fact known. If the media wants to know what are the rules of the game, I am entitled to point out to them what the standing orders say, what the terms of reference of the committee say, and what is contained in the Parliamentary Privileges Act. They are all matters of record. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">If Senator Loosley wants to disagree with the merits of them, if he wants to foreshadow amendments, fine, he can do it. But there can be no argument, surely, with me stating propositions about what is disclosable, what witnesses are compellable and what procedures ought to be followed. He can argue the toss if he likes. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Finally, to get back to the substance of the argument, I would hope that in future when Senator Loosley writes these paid contributions he will at least acknowledge that he is not such a figure of public notoriety and not so worldwide famous that we can reasonably expect every person who reads the article immediately to say, `That's him. That's that Senator Loosley on the print media committee. I can put all this in context. I know where he is coming from'. There might just be someone with a little less intelligence, or someone who did not happen to be paying attention when he was out there on the box one night, who might think that he was making a statement just as an ALP senator&mdash;someone who did not have an interest in the proceedings, someone who, between 1987 and the present time, has not absolutely accepted the provisions of that act. I would be very interested if he would like to tell us in a future article where he has ever quarrelled with all those propositions until now. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Loosley" NAMEID="BS4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator Loosley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I quarrel with the abuse of power by people like you.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There is no issue of abuse of power. The government's act gives the power.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Loosley" NAMEID="BS4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator Loosley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is the central issue.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Let us be clear on this because it is very important. Let us talk about abuse of power. I do not quarrel for a moment with the proposition that a Senate committee has to exercise its powers very carefully, and that if it acts arbitrarily or capriciously&mdash;</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Loosley" NAMEID="BS4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator Loosley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You have threatened all and sundry with subpoenas and gaol.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Just a moment.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Loosley" NAMEID="BS4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BS4">Senator Loosley</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There is a list of people. You can read it in the papers every day.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is not the fact. As Senator Loosley well knows, all that Senator Kernot did was point to the contents of the government's own Parliamentary Privileges Act which says in its final section that those who do not cooperate and produce documents are exposed to a range of penalties which, as I have pointed out, Senator Evans carefully thought about between 1982 and 1987 and finally he put in place an act which recognised the necessity to retain those powers.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Loosley can argue, and I will be in heated agreement with him, that that does not give us the right to kick a head whenever we see it. We have to act responsibly and we have to act sensibly. To the extent that we do not, it will be a matter of public debate and public backlash. That is a completely separate argument to saying that somehow it is outrageous and improper to even contemplate in the 20th century that parliamentary committees should have these powers. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Loosley should have the guts to admit that his government thought about it, put those powers in place, and has never, until this committee arose, quarrelled with the proposition. Let us read next time that he is actually intimately involved in this committee. He has his political barrow to push. He may keep pushing it, but he should let us know where he is coming from. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><PETITION.GRP PAGE="1051">
<TITLE>PETITIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The Clerk" NAMEID="10001">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10001">The Clerk</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
</PROCTEXT><PETITION PAGE="1051" PRESENTERS="BELL" NAMEIDS="7U4">
<TITLE>Jarosite Dumping</TITLE>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">We the undersigned respectfully call upon the Federal Government to (a) reverse the decision to extend the time allowed Pasminco EZ to dump jarosite at sea, and (b) endorse and comply with the December 1995 deadline established by the London Dumping Convention.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="7U4">Senator Bell</NAME><FROM> (from nine citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PETITION PAGE="1052" PRESENTERS="NEWMAN" NAMEIDS="BE4">
<TITLE>Homeless Rate Benefits</TITLE>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The petition of the undersigned shows that:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">1.We are concerned that teenagers are able to leave home by obtaining young homeless rate benefits without adequate investigation.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">2.We believe that the flawed nature of the guidelines governing eligibility for young homeless rate benefits is in some circumstances encouraging family breakdown.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">3.With the number of young people receiving youth homeless rate benefits increasing by a factor of ten over the past six years, we consider that there are insufficient programs to help keep families together.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Your Petitioners ask that the Senate should:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Call on the Government to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a) review the guidelines for young homeless rate benefits; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b) show a greater commitment to programs which prevent family breakdown.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator Newman</NAME><FROM> (from 92 citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PETITION PAGE="1052" PRESENTERS="SPINDLER" NAMEIDS="0X4">
<TITLE>Family Law Act</TITLE>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia draws to the attention of the Senate the need for changes to the Family Law Act of Australia and to the child support scheme.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Your petitioners therefore request that the Senate support the following changes.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(1)That the existing Family Law Act be scrapped and replaced by a more simplified version together with the minimum of rules and regulations necessary.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(2)That the Family Court be replaced by a Tribunal and that all matters resulting from divorce and family breakdown be heard before, and determined by a panel; the panel to be made up of persons qualified in matters arising from family breakdown.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(3)That legal professionals be barred from appearing before the Tribunal resulting in vast savings to the disputing parties.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(4)That a modified fault clause be re-introduced to Family Law primarily designed to discourage adultery and to stop rewarding adulterers at the expense of deserted and innocent parties. </PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(5)That the Child Support Agency be scrapped and replaced by an appropriate administrative procedure within the Tribunal.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(6)That apart from cases of exceptional circumstances parental-child access become the inalienable right of all parents.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(7)That alternative counselling, (Government funded) be made available through the Churches and that much more emphasis be placed on mediation in resolving disputes prior to the commencement of legal proceedings.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="0X4">Senator Spindler</NAME><FROM> (from 4,000 citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PARA>Petitions received.</PARA></PETITION.GRP><DEBATE TYPE="Notice of Motion" PAGE="1052"><TITLE>NOTICES OF MOTION</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1052">
<TITLE>Aquatic Centre in Hobart</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1052" SPEAKER="Calvert Sen P.H." NAMEID="5F4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator CALVERT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)congratulates the Tasmanian State Liberal Government and the Hobart City Council for their announcement of a joint funding proposal for a Hobart aquatic centre;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)recognises that Hobart is the only State capital city without such a facility, a fact which is hampering the development of aquatic sports in Tasmania;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)calls on the Federal Government to match the contributions of the State Government and the Hobart City Council as a matter of priority; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(d)acknowledges that the failure of the Federal Government to contribute to this proposal will not only place the entire project in jeopardy, but will once again highlight the fact that the Government has forgotten that Tasmania exists.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1052">
<TITLE>Breast Cancer</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1052" SPEAKER="Newman Sen J.M." NAMEID="BE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BE4">Senator NEWMAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)notes:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(i)that the draft report of the National Health Goals and Targets Implementation Working Group on Cancers states that the incidence of breast cancer will increase from 63 cases per year per 100 000 women to 81 cases per year per 100 000 women by the year 2000, a rate of 2.1 per cent per annum, and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(ii)the report's statement that only a small proportion of women with breast cancer will be entered into clinical trials during 1994, despite the failure of mortality rates from breast cancer to fall in the last 40 years; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)calls on the Government to urgently increase resources for clinical breast cancer trials which according to the report provide both an important means of evaluating new therapeutic methods and the scientific basis for developing effective methods of breast cancer treatment.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1053">
<TITLE>East Coast Armaments Complex</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1053" SPEAKER="Margetts Sen D." NAMEID="DX5" PARTY="GWA" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DX5">Senator MARGETTS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Western Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)commends:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(i)the protest actions organised by the Australian Conservation Foundation and the people of Jervis Bay for 24 February 1994 to protest against the proposal to site an armaments depot at Jervis Bay on the New South Wales coast, and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(ii)the protest actions organised by Greenpeace Australia and the local community at Jervis Bay for the weekend of 26 and 27 February 1994 to protest against the same development proposal;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)notes that the Federal Cabinet is set to make a decision regarding the armaments depot on 24 March 1994;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)expresses outrage at the fact that the Australian Government is considering sacrificing such an important ecological asset as Jervis Bay without proper public consultation just because of military involvement, therefore avoiding normal scrutiny; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(d)calls on the Australian Government to remove Jervis Bay from its list of possible sites and to undertake a full cost benefit analysis of the remaining site options for this armaments depot, incorporating all environmental and social impacts.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1053">
<TITLE>Unemployment</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1053" SPEAKER="Tierney Sen J.W." NAMEID="O15" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="O15">Senator TIERNEY</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)notes:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(i)that Newcastle and the lower Hunter regions have one of Australia's highest rates of long-term unemployment, with virtually half of its more than 30 000 jobless out of work for a year or more, and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(ii)that this rate of long-term unemployed is 6.7 per cent, compared to a national rate of 3.9 per cent and a State rate of 3.8 per cent;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)condemns the Member for Shortland (Mr Peter Morris) for suggesting that the figures are `unsurprising and a result of structural change and the recession';</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)calls on the Member and the other Australian Labor Party representatives of Newcastle and the Hunter to actually begin to work on their Government to introduce policies which will assist the long-term unemployed in the region; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(d)urges the Government to stop neglecting the Hunter region and support developments in the Hunter such as an adequate airport and service industries, particularly tourism, which are the answer to long-term unemployment in the region.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1053">
<TITLE>Community Affairs Committee</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1053" SPEAKER="Burns Sen B.R" NAMEID="2F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2F4">Senator BURNS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of Senator West, I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, she will move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the time for the presentation of the report of the Standing Committee on Community Affairs on breast cancer screening and treatment in Australia be extended to 5 May 1994.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1053">
<TITLE>Mental Illness</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1053" SPEAKER="Reid Sen M.E." NAMEID="VI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VI4">Senator REID</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)notes that the Federal Government has recently released a discussion paper on the report of the National Inquiry into the Human Rights of People with Mental Illness and that this discussion paper has been widely criticised by community groups as a superficial insult to the mentally ill and their families;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)condemns the Government for issuing a discussion paper which ignores many of the specific recommendations from the Burdekin Inquiry which makes scant reference to the many groups affected by mental illness and which contains no new proposals for programs;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)deplores the fact that the discussion paper scarcely mentions the needs of elderly people despite the fact that the Burdekin Inquiry devoted several chapters to their mental health problems and despite the fact that in an ageing population almost every family in Australia will be affected directly or indirectly by dementia; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(d)calls on the Government to respond appropriately, and as a matter of urgency, to the mental health crisis which was uncovered by the Burdekin report.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Unemployment</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1054" SPEAKER="Spindler Sen S.E." NAMEID="0X4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="0X4">Senator SPINDLER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)notes the endorsement in the Australian newspaper by Bishop Michael Challen, Executive Director of the Brotherhood of St Laurence, of the Australian Democrats' proposal that any windfalls in revenue from higher than expected economic growth be directed towards assisting the long-term unemployed rather than being used to reduce the budget deficit more rapidly; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)calls on the Government to use any windfalls in revenue and any funds derived from a jobs levy to fund the Jobs Compact, increased social security provisions for the unemployed and national infrastructure projects.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Universities</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1054" SPEAKER="Tierney Sen J.W." NAMEID="O15" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="O15">Senator TIERNEY</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)notes that:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(i)at the eleventh hour the Government has changed the guidelines for its dubious Quality Assurance Program which will distribute $76 million to Australian universities, and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(ii)the Quality Assurance Committee will now allocate the funds across all universities rather than to just the top half of the institutions as planned, proving that trying to define educational quality is simply too difficult;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)expresses its concern at the reports that the committee will divide Australia's universities into four so-called bands which will in fact result in the creation of 1st, 2nd, 3rd and 4th class universities, essentially another version of the old binary system; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)condemns the Australian Labor Party Government for yet another ill-conceived and half-baked scheme in education.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1054"><TITLE>ORDER OF BUSINESS</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Turkish Kurds</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Postponement</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Margetts</EMPHASIS>) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That general business notice of motion No. 601, standing in the name of Senator Margetts, relating to the Kurdish people of Turkey, be postponed till the next day of sitting.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1054"><TITLE>COMMITTEES</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Print Media Committee</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Extension of Time</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Alston</EMPHASIS>)&mdash;as amended by leave&mdash;agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the resolution of the Senate of 9 December 1993 establishing the Select Committee on Certain Aspects of Foreign Ownership Decisions in relation to the Print Media be amended to provide that its term of appointment be extended till 4 May 1994 to allow the committee to complete its schedule of hearings and prepare its report.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Environment, Recreation and the Arts Committee</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1054">
<TITLE>Reference</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Burns</EMPHASIS>, on behalf of <EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">Senator Devereux</EMPHASIS>) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the following matter be referred to the Standing Committee on Environment, Recreation and the Arts for inquiry and report by the last sitting day of 1994&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Arts and cultural education in Australian educational institutions, and in particular:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(a)the present level and status of education in the arts and the involvement of students in Australian educational institutions;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(b)current training practices, skills levels and involvement by teachers and the general community in providing arts education in educational institutions;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(c)the allocation and use of resources to arts education in educational institutions; and</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(d)the consistency of arts education policies and programs within and between educational institutions and States and Territories. </PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Bill" PAGE="1055"><TITLE>MIGRATION LEGISLATION AMENDMENT BILL 1994</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1055">
<TITLE>First Reading</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by <EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">Senator Sherry</EMPHASIS>) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the following bill be introduced: a bill for an act to amend the Migration Act 1958, and for related purposes.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by <EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">Senator Sherry</EMPHASIS>) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That this bill may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Bill read a first time.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1055">
<TITLE>Second Reading</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1055" SPEAKER="Sherry Sen The Hon N.J." NAMEID="ZW4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ZW4">Senator SHERRY</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP> (11.56 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I table the explanatory memorandum and move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That this bill be now read a second time.</PARA>
<PARA>I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in<EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL"> Hansard</EMPHASIS>.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Leave granted. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">The speech read as follows</EMPHASIS>&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The purpose of this bill is to amend the Migration Act 1958 as amended by the Migration Reform Act 1992. The reforms effected by both the Migration Reform Act and this bill are to commence on 1 September 1994. The bill also provides for consequential technical amendments to other Commonwealth legislation.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The Migration Reform Act 1992 makes important changes to the Migration Act 1958. It seeks to simplify the legal basis for administration of entry to and stay in Australia. It expands merits review by the Migration Internal Review Office and the Immigration Review Tribunal, and modifies appeal rights to the courts. It also establishes a detailed code of procedures for the processing of visa applications and reviews and clarifies the procedures in relation to cancellation of visas.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The commencement of those parts of the Migration Reform Act 1992 that were originally to commence on 1 November 1992 was deferred to 1 September 1994 by the Migration Laws Amendment Bill 1993. A major reason for seeking deferment, as I advised honourable senators at the time, was to allow for the making of a number of amendments, mainly of a technical nature, to ensure that the legislation operates smoothly. The bill now before the Senate contains the amendments which I foreshadowed last year.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">All the changes provided for in the bill are consistent with the principles and scheme of the Migration Reform Act, as enunciated by the former Minister. Most are of a technical nature, correcting drafting errors, ensuring consistency of language or, in some instances, rewriting provisions to achieve the same outcome with greater clarity.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The remainder of the amendments will ensure that particular migration matters are administered in a way consistent with the scheme of the Migration Reform Act previously passed by Parliament.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">For example, one of the key objectives of the reforms is to clarify the status of all non-citizens in Australia. In simple terms, a non-citizen in Australia will be required to have a visa to be lawful. A non-citizen who does not hold a valid visa must be detained and is then subject to removal from Australia.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Grant of a bridging visa will provide a non-citizen, who would otherwise be subject to detention and removal, with lawful status for a limited period. The bill provides for more than one class of bridging visa. This reflects the fact that bridging visas will serve a number of different purposes and will be granted on the basis of a number of different sets of criteria. The detail of the bridging visa scheme will be contained in regulations.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The creation of a class of visas to be called special purpose visas clarifies the status of persons currently exempt from the requirement to hold an entry permit to enter and remain in Australia. Currently the Migration Act exempts from this requirement a variety of non-citizens, including representatives of foreign governments and their families, heads of State, military personnel from other countries engaged in military exercises, ship and airline crew in Australia for a brief period, and New Zealand citizens who present a valid New Zealand passport on entry. This exemption will not apply under the reforms as it is inconsistent with the principle that lawful status flows only from holding a visa.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Special purpose visas will provide lawful status for non-citizens who are presently exempt non-citizens other than New Zealand citizens,  and will be held when, and for as long as, a non-citizen continues to be present in Australia for a specified purpose. These visas will not be subject to the usual provisions relating to visas such as the need for an application, the need for an administrative grant of the visa, and the need for the grant to be evidenced. This reflects the fact that many of the non-citizens who will be holders of these visas enter Australia in a manner that makes it impractical for the usual administrative procedures to apply; for example, foreign military personnel engaged in joint military exercises.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">New Zealand citizens will be granted special category visas at the border on presentation of a valid New Zealand passport. Given that they arrive in Australia in the normal way it is appropriate that normal administrative processes requiring an application, grant and the issuing of evidence of grant, apply.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Another amendment which is intended to clarify the status of non-citizens in Australia is the creation of a new class of visa to be known as an ex-citizen visa. This amendment will provide that, while in Australia, a person who loses their Australian citizenship, for example by acquiring the citizenship of another country, will be taken to be the holder of visa entitling them to remain in Australia indefinitely. This visa will be subject to the same cancellation provisions as any other permanent visa. Creation of this new class will avoid the situation where such persons could automatically become unlawful non-citizens, subject to mandatory detention and removal.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Other areas where the bill provides for minor amendments are in regard to the procedures for considering visa applications and cancellations, clearance of arrivals at the border  and in regard to review.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Visa application procedures are to be amended to ensure that applicants can effectively nominate a representative to receive communications from the Department and to ensure that applicants are given a greater opportunity to comment on adverse information about them which they may not previously have seen. The procedure for cancelling visas, where incorrect information has been provided, is refined in the bill to ensure that a visa holder has the opportunity to both show that incorrect information has not been given and, if the decision-maker concludes that incorrect information has been given by the applicant, show that there are mitigating reasons why the visa should not be cancelled.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The bill refines provisions relating to the clearance of arrivals at the border to ensure the smooth processing of both citizens and non-citizens. For example, provision is made for the clearance of a person that a clearance officer knows or reasonably believes is an Australian citizen, even though the person may not have documentary evidence of their citizenship. There are also amendments to ensure that a consistent approach can be taken to all persons who arrive in Australia without a visa.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The bill ensures that particular decisions that are currently reviewable on their merits remain amenable to review after 1 September 1994. These include decisions refusing close family visitor visas and  resident return visas where the applicant is overseas, as well as review of points assessments where an application is put into a pool. Proposed amendments also enable expedited review of bridging visa decisions where the applicant is in detention. </PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">In order to provide for smoother implementation of the legislation it is proposed that the Migration Act 1958, as amended by the Reform Act, be renumbered. The insertion of a large number of new provisions into the Migration Act means that, without renumbering, awkward references to provisions such as section 26ZEA will result. The renumbering of the Migration Act will take effect on 1 September 1994.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The bill also provides for consequential amendments to other Commonwealth Acts, largely reflecting changes in terminology, such as the substitution of the term "entry permit" with "visa", and the creation of the special category visa for New Zealand citizens in Australia.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">Since the decision was made to defer the commencement of the Reform Act there has been considerable activity within my Department in preparation for implementation of the proposed changes. As well as the identification of necessary amendments to the Reform Act and other related legislation, significant progress has been made towards the drafting of subordinate legislation, the preparation of procedural instructions, and the revision of computer systems and data bases. In addition, a strategy has been developed for the provision of information and training to target groups, both inside and outside the Department.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">It is essential for the successful implementation of the changes contained in the Reform Act that many of  these activities are completed well in advance of the 1 September 1994 commencement date. In particular, I would note that the Act itself, the regulations and procedures, and appropriate forms need to be finalised, printed and distributed to all officers well before the commencement date so that they can become familiar with the reforms and be able to provide an effective and high quality service from the first day. Members of the public, including clients and registered migration agents, also need time to become familiar with the reforms.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">While much of the preparatory work is being done concurrently with the consideration by Parliament of  this bill, none of these matters essential for effective implementation can be finalised until the amending legislation is settled by Parliament. It is therefore vital that the bill passes through both Houses of Parliament by early May.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">I commend the bill to the Senate and I present the Explanatory Memorandum to this bill.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Debate (on motion by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Reid</EMPHASIS>) adjourned.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1057"><TITLE>COMMITTEES</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>Employment, Education and Training Committee</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>Reference</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Zakharov</EMPHASIS>) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the following matters be referred to the Standing Committee on Employment, Education and Training for inquiry and report by the last sitting day of December 1994:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(1)The accountability of Commonwealth, state and territory authorities for the expenditure of Commonwealth funds under the Schools Program, including general recurrent grants, capital grants, targeted assistance and national priority programs, with specific reference to the appropriateness and effectiveness of current accountability mechanisms.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(2)The implications of Commonwealth funding arrangements for schools for the quality of, and equity of access to, primary and secondary education.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(3)The extent to which the Commonwealth's role in post-compulsory education and training could be strengthened to enhance national economic and social objectives such as:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">  (i)the achievement of full employment;</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">  (ii)the development of a more flexible, highly skilled and productive workforce; and </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">(iii)the development of a more literate, articulate and democratic society.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>Membership</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>Variations</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME><NAME NAMEID="VW4"> (Senator Herron)</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The President has received letters from the Leader of the Government in the Senate and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate seeking variations in the membership of various committees.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Sherry</EMPHASIS>)&mdash;by leave&mdash;agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That Senators be appointed to and discharged from committees as follows&mdash;</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(1)Estimates Committees A (standing order 26)</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Discharged:Senator Jones</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Appointed:Senator Chris Evans</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">for the hearings on 25 February 1994 only.</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(2)Regulations and Ordinances Committee (standing order 23)</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Discharged:Senator Gibson</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Appointed:Senator Abetz</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">(3)Standing Committee on Industry, Science, Technology, Transport, Communications and Infrastructure (standing order 25)</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Appointed:Senator Panizza</PARA>
</INTERJECT>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Documents" PAGE="1057"><TITLE>DOCUMENTS</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>Auditor-General's Report</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1057">
<TITLE>No. 28 of 1993-94</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In accordance with the provisions of the Audit Act 1901, I present the following report of the Auditor-General: <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Report No. 28 of 1993-94&mdash;Efficiency Audit&mdash;Department of Veterans' Affairs&mdash;Use of Private Hospitals.</EMPHASIS></PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</PROCTEXT>
<SPEECH PAGE="1057" SPEAKER="MacGibbon Sen D.J." NAMEID="YH4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YH4">Senator MacGIBBON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (11.58 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate take note of the document.</PARA>
<PARA>The Senate has before it an efficiency audit report into the use of private hospitals by the Department of Veterans' Affairs. In 1915 the first of the repatriation acts was passed in Australia to look after those who enlisted in the First World War. From that time onwards there has been an expanding range of benefits available for those who have served this country in the armed services in time of war. One of the benefits has been the provision of hospital care for veterans. That has been administered through what has been known as the repatriation general hospitals, which have been sited in all the capital cities&mdash;Greenslopes in Brisbane, Concord in Sydney, Heidelberg in Melbourne, Daw Park in Adelaide, Hollywood in Perth and a similar hospital in Hobart. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Some years ago the government decided to sell the repatriation general hospitals and incorporate those into the health services of the various states and, where that could not be done, to sell them to private authorities. At the same time, they introduced the RPPHS, the repatriation private patient health scheme. That scheme allowed veterans to have access, under certain conditions, to intermediate level health care in private hospitals. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Health care is very important to veterans. This report points out that 70 per cent of the treatment population, that is, the veteran population, will be 75 years or older by the year 2002. Hospital admissions for this group are expected to double by that time. That is because the great bulk of veterans presently are veterans of the Second World War. There is a tidal wave going through, and the demand by veterans for health care is increasing. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This audit report assesses the treatment veterans are getting from private hospitals under the RPPHS. It makes 29 recommendations. Dealing with those recommendations briefly and in sequence, the first is for a standard approach be made between the states, which is a commonsense approach. There is a recommendation that there be a review of the indemnity provisions so that the Department of Veterans' Affairs is better protected against claims arising from treatment; that multi-year contracts be entered into where possible with private health care providers; that there be a national approach where possible; and that there be reasonably equal input from both the administrative and medical staff in negotiating these agreements. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In all public services in Australia there has been a tendency to believe that there is such a perfect animal as a manager who knows everything about everything, and that it really does not matter what he is managing; if he has management skills, he can manage, and manage brilliantly.<TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">There are many shortcomings with that proposition, and as the Auditor-General reports, it is important that the medical staff have an equal say in the arrangements being made to guarantee there is decent and adequate treatment for the patients. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The basic approach of the audit office is to set up the best commercial practice for all the arrangements that are entered into. We are looking at something that will run to well over $100 million a year in the provision of treatment. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Further, there are recommendations about standard assessments and methods of treatment. There is quite a bit about how payment should be audited&mdash;that there should be standard charging procedures, and a way of assessing charges in a fair and accurate way. There is also a recommendation that the DVA should pay rapidly for the treatment so that accounts can be checked at or close to the time of treatment being delivered in order that any anomalies can be picked up. The ANAO overlooks the fact that rapidity of payment is also very important for the providers of treatment. Those running private hospitals need their bills to be paid rapidly because they have to pay their accounts within 30 days, or whatever the terms are, and often the government forgets people are in a bind for ready money. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">At the end of the day, the report can be summarised in terms of saying that it stresses the need for the Department of Veterans' Affairs to make sure care is available when required for veterans; that high quality care is available and that it is delivered. Those are the two undertakings the government entered into with the veterans community when it moved down the path of getting rid of the repatriation general hospitals. Many veterans were very concerned about that because they thought their special access to high quality health care through the repatriation general hospitals could be diluted or become of a lesser standard if the hospitals went into the state health services. The government went out of its way to give undertakings that high quality health care and access to that care would be readily available, which is re-enforced by the Auditor-General. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Procedures are also recommended by the Auditor-General to improve the accounting system, making it more accurate and accountable, because there are quite large sums involved here. Of course, ultimately, the obligation is on this parliament. We are the inheritors of those promises made many years ago in the early days of the First World War to look after the veterans who served this country. It is quite proper that the Auditor-General, being an officer of the parliament, not of the government, should bring this matter before the parliament. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1058" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Minister for Veterans' Affairs and Minister for Defence Science and Personnel)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP> (12.05 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will respond to a couple of comments made by Senator MacGibbon and also, briefly, to the report of the Australian National Audit Office on private hospital usage. The report outlines that the Department of Veterans' Affairs has made considerable progress in establishing private hospital arrangements as an important backup to the public hospital system under the repatriation private patient scheme. Over 200 contracts around Australia have been put in place since 1991.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The report notes that my department has approached the audit from a positive stance and provided detailed and comprehensive responses to the audit office throughout the 12-month process. My department stressed to the audit office that private hospital negotiations are at a transitional stage. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The effect of integration or privatisation of the repatriation general hospitals has a significant impact on the use of public, as well as private, hospitals as each repatriation general hospital is either integrated or sold. Even after integration, there is a heavy emphasis on public hospital usage, which is the first level of care made available under the repatriation private patient scheme. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The availability of private hospitals and their role in providing services for veterans vary widely across the states. The vast majority of the Australian National Audit Office recommendations have been acted upon or considered for future development. For example, the standard contract is currently being refined, and where appropriate contracts are being extended beyond the single year term. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The Australian National Audit Office has highlighted potential savings of $4 million from the negotiation process and $3 million from contract administration. These so-called savings have been discussed at length with the audit office. The estimate of $4 million was based on an estimate of savings against one health insurance fund in one state. My department has had some problems with that methodology. The insurance fund concerned is not a major fund in that state, and a comparison against other health funds shows that my department has already made significant savings.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The department does agree further savings can be made through the establishment of preferred provider arrangements and expansion of volume discount arrangements. Opportunities for savings of this nature have been limited to date due to the uncertainty surrounding service levels required in various regions following integration. They will only be expanded to full potential after the expiry of the transition periods following the introduction in each state, when public and private sectors will be competing for departmental business on a case mix basis. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The Department of Veterans' Affairs acknowledges the difficulties with processing of private hospital payments to ensure their accuracy, particularly that the correct discounted rate is paid.<TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Systems are now in place to overcome the majority of these concerns, and other improvements are in the pipeline.<TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The savings of $3 million in contractor administration are based on errors noted in 1992-93, before the use of my department's private hospital validation system. This order of errors will not recur under the new system. The department is preparing a comprehensive private hospital strategy which will provide major directions for both the short and longer terms. This strategy does take into account the recommendations that have been made by the Australian National Audit Office. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Finally, private hospital negotiations are proceeding well. Following the audit, my department is taking steps to ensure that more cost-effective use is made of computer modelling to assess private hospital usage and private hospital demand. My department will continue to ensure that veterans have suitable access to high quality services in private hospitals, where they are needed and required. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1060"><TITLE>AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICALS BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICALS CODE BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICALS (CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS) BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICAL PRODUCTS (COLLECTION OF LEVY) BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICAL PRODUCTS LEVY IMPOSITION (EXCISE) BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICAL PRODUCTS LEVY IMPOSITION (CUSTOMS) BILL 1993<BREAK TYPE="LINE">AGRICULTURAL AND VETERINARY CHEMICAL PRODUCTS LEVY IMPOSITION (GENERAL) BILL 1993</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1060">
<TITLE>Report of Rural and Regional Affairs Committee</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1060" SPEAKER="Foreman Sen D.J." NAMEID="GG4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GG4">Senator FOREMAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of Senator Burns, I present the report of the Standing Committee on Rural and Regional Affairs on the Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals Bill 1993 and six related bills, together with submissions and the transcript of evidence.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Ordered that the report be printed. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1060"><TITLE>COMMITTEES</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1060">
<TITLE>Estimates Committee F</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1060">
<TITLE>Program Performance Statements</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1060" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Minister for Veterans' Affairs and Minister for Defence Science and Personnel)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I table corrigenda to the program performance statement of the Attorney-General's Department. Copies of this document have been distributed to members of Senate Estimates Committee F and other interested senators. Additional copies are available from the Senate Table Office.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Adjournment" PAGE="1060"><TITLE>ADJOURNMENT</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Motion (by<EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD"> Senator Faulkner</EMPHASIS>) proposed:</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate do now adjourn.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1060">
<TITLE>Commonwealth-State Relations</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1060" SPEAKER="Short Sen J.R." NAMEID="DJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator SHORT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (12.13 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Earlier this week, on 22 February, the Prime Minister (Mr Keating) made a speech at the Australian National University, entitled `Reshaping Australian institutions', in which he dealt with a range of issues. He claimed that, over the last 10 years, the government had gone a long way in reshaping some of the basic institutions in Australia. One to which he referred was the relationship between the Commonwealth and the states. He outlined four principles on which he believed institutional change would occur that would lead to `a much more cooperative relationship developing between the Commonwealth and the states'.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The speech has attracted a considerable degree of media attention, most of it favourable. It is the four principles the Prime Minister mentioned as underpinning his approach to Commonwealth-state relations that I wish to address briefly. I believe the press reporting of the speech has been quite distorted and that, far from ushering in a new era in Commonwealth-state relations which could be described as important institutional change, quite the opposite is the case. The government and the Prime Minister have failed totally to address the main aspect of change required in Commonwealth-state relations, which has always been acknowledged to be the Commonwealth-state financial relationship. That issue has not been addressed at all. Indeed, it has been specifically set aside by the Prime Minister. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The Prime Minister mentioned four principles for Commonwealth-state relations. Let us look at each of them. The first so-called principle he outlined states:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . we recognise that the States have a vital role as units of Government in Australia, because there is this debate, which you often see from time to time, about abolishing the States.</PARA>
<PARA>In other words, the first great new principle is that we are going to recognise the existence and the role of the states. What an extraordinary statement to list as a basic principle that is going to usher in a new era of institutional change. The whole basis of our nation is contained in the constitution. The essence of the constitution is the federal relationship between the Commonwealth and the states and the existence of the states themselves. It is pretty big of the Prime Minister to accept Australia's constitutional arrangements. It is great that our Prime Minister has now come to recognise that we have a constitution in which are enshrined the role and existence of the states. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I suppose it is a bit of a move forward because he and his party, the Labor Party, have always been antagonistic towards the states. They have sought progressively, and successfully, to reduce the role of the states in Australian government. It goes back many years. In terms of this Labor government, it started with the Franklin Dam dispute in 1983, when there was a total usurping of the role of the states in relation to the environmental issues associated with the Franklin Dam. At that time, and ever since then, this government has sought increasingly to encroach on, if not outright override, state jurisdiction. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I well recall&mdash;I am sure other senators would as well&mdash;Mr Keating's famous speech in October 1991, which he used as one of the springboards for his successful coup that saw him usurp the prime ministership from Mr Hawke a couple of months later. In that speech on Commonwealth-state relations and federal issues, the then aspirant to the prime ministerial throne, Mr Keating, pronounced:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">I admired Gough Whitlam for his unhesitating drive, in enhancing the powers of the Commonwealth.</PARA>
<PARA>That always has been, still is and, I am sure, will continue to be the agenda of the Prime Minister. So it is not only incredible that he has raised that as a first principle; it is also hypocritical in the extreme that he is now pretending that he and his government will ever do more than pay lip service to that principle. The second principle the Prime Minister outlined states:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . both the Commonwealth and the States should independently assess the value of reforms and use them for their own sake, not as part of a deal in which the Commonwealth is supposed to buy the cooperation of the States.</PARA>
<PARA>In other words, he is saying that there should be an independent assessment of reforms for the benefit of the states rather than relying on Commonwealth financial inducement. That is pretty rich, coming from a Prime Minister who sought to override the most fundamental reforms to industrial relations in my own state of Victoria and in Western Australia. Those reforms would have been of undoubted benefit to those states, particularly Victoria, in attracting investment, but they were thwarted in one of the greatest grabs for central power by Labor and the trade union movement that we have seen in this country. So much for the second principle that the Prime Minister enunciated. One could say much more about it. The third principle he enunciated states:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . that we are willing to enter into a genuine discussion between heads of Government and portfolio Ministers to look at the present roles and responsibilities of the States and the Commonwealth, to see where we can develop and deliver better policy outcomes, but where the Commonwealth Government will always have a role in setting priorities and national objectives to social programs such as health and education, as well as the environment and economic programs.</PARA>
<PARA>I remind the Prime Minister of the genuine reform discussions on many of these issues that were under way in 1991&mdash;initiated by the states because they had had a come-on nod from the then Prime Minister, Mr Hawke. It was precisely those putative developments in Commonwealth-state relations that Mr Keating crushed in his drive to become Prime Minister. As I said earlier, he used those very issues in his political assassination of the former Prime Minister.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">One would hope that the different levels of government would talk to each other, but that is hardly a new or major development. I hope the Prime Minister means what he says in that third principle. It would mark a return to a semblance of common sense on his part in relation to the issue. Perhaps it is just that reality has only now hit him. To say that it would be a fundamental change in institutional arrangements is quite nonsensical because it is an aspect that should always have been there anyway. As I say, it is one that the Labor government and this Prime Minister in particular have observed more in the breach than in the doing. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The fourth principle is the most important one that I wish to address. As enunciated by the Prime Minister, it is:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . that while the Commonwealth believes the States should be adequately resourced, it should be taken as understood that the Commonwealth will not be party to any substantial transfer of Commonwealth taxing powers to the States.</PARA>
<PARA>So the Prime Minister wants to transfer responsibility for resources to the states with no transfer at all of the financial wherewithal to go with it. It should be remembered that it was Mr Keating as Treasurer in the late 1980s who slashed Commonwealth payments to the states year after year as his main avenue for cutting the budget deficit. He did not have the gumption or the ability to cut own-purpose spending by the Commonwealth; he slashed Commonwealth payments to the states. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">During the first five or six years of the Hawke Labor government&mdash;between 1983-84 and 1989-90&mdash;when Mr Keating was the Treasurer, payments to the states as a percentage of gross domestic product fell by over one-third. It fell from 9.8 per cent of GDP to 6.8 per cent, and today the figure is only slightly above that low point. In other words, there has been no effort on the part of the Commonwealth&mdash;indeed, efforts have been made to the contrary&mdash;to redress the financial problem in a stable, consistent and on-going way. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">In his statement this week, the Prime Minister said that he is ruling out of court any prospect for the most fundamental reform required in the area of Commonwealth-state relations, that of the Commonwealth-state financial relationship, giving the states greater ability to and responsibility for raising the revenues they need to meet their own expenditure priorities. That is the most crucial area of Commonwealth-state reform&mdash;addressing the so-called vertical fiscal imbalance and providing the states, the main spenders of taxpayer's money, with a reliable and stable revenue source. The states account for around 50 per cent of total government expenditure in Australia yet they raise less than 25 per cent of the revenue. That is a totally unsatisfactory and unstable situation, yet in his speech the other night, the Prime Minister absolutely ruled out any reform to redress it. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The second most crucial area of Commonwealth-state reform is the need for a clear definition of responsibilities&mdash;a genuine attempt to eliminate duplication between the states and Commonwealth levels of government. Both problem areas can be directly traced to the on-going centralisation of the federal government. In just about every area of state expenditure and revenue raising one could look at&mdash;health, education, housing, child care, land management, industrial relations, training, consumer affairs, and so on&mdash;there is an increasing centralisation of powers and responsibilities in the hands of the Commonwealth government and a consequential diminution of the constitutional responsibilities of the states. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The Prime Minister's speech the other night concerns and disappoints me. He concluded by saying:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . within those four principles . . . a new commitment, if you like, a new consensus, a new understanding between the Commonwealth and the States . . . </PARA>
<PARA>There is nothing new about these principles. They may appear new to the Prime Minister because he has never understood or cared for our constitutional arrangements for government. He has never understood and cared for the role of anybody other than those under his control. Indeed, never in Australia's history has there been a political leader who has so attempted to trample on the basic institutions of our nation as the current Prime Minister. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Mr Keating's comments of the other night reek of nothing other than insincerity and hypocrisy. Instead of cooperative federalism, one could describe the Prime Minister's endeavours in the whole area of Commonwealth-state relations as authoritarian centralism. Commitment and consensus, particularly in the area of Commonwealth-state relations, are concepts totally alien to anything that the Prime Minister has ever stood for. I conclude by referring to his speech in October 1991&mdash;a major plank in his attempt to get rid of Prime Minister Hawke&mdash;when he said:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">. . . in the end, the Commonwealth has the power of the purse.</PARA>
<PARA>His speech this week simply reinforced his commitment to that totally centralist ideology. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1063">
<TITLE>Small Business</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1063" SPEAKER="Campbell Sen I.G." NAMEID="H15" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="H15">Senator CAMPBELL</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Western Australia)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP> (12.28 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I wish to address two subjects, but my remarks on both will be brief. Firstly, I would like to support the comments made by my colleague Senator Short in relation to what can only be described as the gross hypocrisy of the Prime Minister (Mr Keating) in his statement on the new-new-neo-federalism and his approach to the COAG meeting tomorrow. I will also be addressing the hypocrisy of this government by comparing its treatment of small business and its approach to audits and audit trails under the Corporations Law with the level of accountability that the Prime Minister and, in particular, the Attorney-General (Mr Lavarch) require of people such as Minister Kelly. They are diverse subjects but both could be put under the heading of `Hypocrisy' in the <EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Hansard</EMPHASIS>.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Senator Short made some very good points about the gross hypocrisy of Prime Minister Keating. The speech to which Senator Short referred was delivered by the same man who, in 1991, oversaw the destruction of what was probably the most genuine attempt at reconciling the federal balance in Australia in the 93 years since Federation&mdash;certainly since Malcolm Fraser's attempt at new federalism in the 1970s and 1980s, which was, in many respects, a failure. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Mr Keating's Placido Domingo, off-the-record speech at the National Press Club, in which he made the statements which Senator Short has already put on the record relating to his support of the Whitlamesque centralism of concentrating more power in Canberra and taking away the powers of the state governments, was a crude political attempt inside the Labor caucus to attract the support of centralists such as the Carrs and the Faulkners to vote for him. There is an innate centralist tendency within the Australian Labor Party that distrusts the states and sees that the best way to run Australia is to have power concentrated in Canberra. Many of us are extremely wary of any moves to move power away from the people, away from local communities, to this remote and unusual place of power in Canberra. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">There have been a number of changes since Mr Keating became Prime Minister. I suspect that the most rapid centralisation of power has occurred in the past couple of years. I am reminded of a number of specific examples which have occurred in the last 12 months. The Commonwealth's native title legislation that passed through this place in December in one fell swoop became the greatest centralisation of power that has occurred in this nation's history. When the case gets to the High Court we will see whether the Commonwealth has the constitutional power to take over land management in a way that was specifically excluded by the founding fathers when they wrote the constitution. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">More recently, on 4 February, the Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs, Mr Tickner, got an order from the Federal Court to halt the development of a crocodile farm at Broome. That is a very important example of what can, and will, happen under the native title legislation which became law late last year. Minister Tickner took that action under the heritage legislation. As I said in the Senate on 10 February, the action of that minister is very clearly an example of what can occur under the native title legislation. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I will reiterate the following point as many times as I can in the hope that someone may hear me at some stage: even if the Western Australian government under Premier Court decided to acquiesce in the Prime Minister's legislative structures and procedures and set up the sorts of tribunals wanted by the Prime Minister, and subjected people who wanted to make developments in Western Australia, such as a crocodile farm, a tourist development, an iron ore mine or a gold mine a process which takes a minimum of 12 months if there are no problems or objections along the way&mdash;bearing in mind that it takes about 70 days to go through it at the moment, so it means shifting a development approval procedure from 70 days out to 12 to 14 months without hiccups or disputes between Aboriginal communities which are trying to decide who should hold the native title&mdash;at the end of that period, under native title law, the federal minister still has a period of two months in which he has total discretion to veto the decision of the tribunal. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">A tribunal set up under the native title legislation for  negotiation, conciliation and agreement between all the parties can say, `Yes, you can go ahead with the development of a crocodile farm at Broome', but at the end of that process the federal minister still has the total right of veto over the tribunal's decision.<TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Those opposite talk about federal and state cooperation, saying, `We will recognise and give good and full faith to the decisions made by your state tribunals on land management', but at the end of the matter the federal minister has the right to intervene. A local traditional Aboriginal owner, recognised for centuries as the traditional owner of a place in Broome, may be successful before the tribunal. But if the Kimberley Land Council comes along&mdash;a highly politically motivated organisation, with the ear of the federal minister&mdash;and says, `We want you to veto this development because we did not get our way at the tribunal', then the federal minister can intervene. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">This is an effective veto over development within the states. It is a massive transfer of power away from the states&mdash;and, more importantly, from local citizens and communities&mdash;to the federal minister. The Prime Minister has no credentials, he will be travelling to the COAG meeting in Hobart tomorrow and he will not be taken seriously by the premiers who will be meeting him. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">One other example is voluntary student unionism. It is a very important issue for people who believe in liberty for Australian citizens. In Western Australia, the entire Court government, including the premier and the education minister, Norman Moore, went to the polls in February last year on a platform which has been our policy for the last 10 years, to ensure that individual students on campus had the right to decide whether or not to join unions. Students are going back to their campuses now&mdash;I was at the Curtin University campus last Friday&mdash;and are being forced to become members of student unions. Legislation to give effect to its policy is before the Western Australian parliament and will be passed in the next couple of months, depending on how good our manager of government business in the Western Australian parliament is. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Faulkner" NAMEID="5K4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator Faulkner</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Not a good as me.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="H15">Senator CAMPBELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Maybe not. That legislation will go through. We have passed through this chamber a bill that ensures that when a state government passes legislation which gives students the freedom to choose whether to join a union, the federal government will take funds away from that state through the higher education grants and penalise it. In the case of Western Australia, it will be a penalty of up to $5 million because that state government is putting into place its election promises and is delivering to Western Australian students, for the first time in history, the freedom to choose whether or not to join a union. This is yet another example of how the federal government can say one thing about giving full faith and credit to state government policies and decisions, but uses its power of the purse to ensure that the state government's policies are hindered and the taxpayers and citizens of that state are penalised because the federal government does not like the state government's policies.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">So it is a very hypocritical Prime Minister going to this COAG meeting tomorrow. He has now recognised that state governments exist. It has taken 93 years for that recognition to be given, so that is a step forward. But if one reads the Prime Minister's statements, as Senator Short has done, one sees that he has said that the state governments are just a post office for the Commonwealth government. He says they are good because they can provide a few services; they can be handed some money and they can be a post office, a regional office or an outpost for the federal government. That is not our idea of federalism. Our idea of federalism is to ensure that people have control over decisions that affect their lives. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">When it comes to environmental matters we want to ensure that people who have dirty rivers and dirty air can have that cleaned up by local and state authorities and not have boffins and politicians in Canberra telling them how to run their lives. It is not about states rights. That is a hackneyed, cliched phrase which has distorted federal-state relations for years. The debate is about democratic rights of individuals. Individuals who do not like their state government or the activities of the politicians who have control of these issues can march up St George's Terrace to Parliament House and demand action from their local politicians. It is very hard for a Western Australian or a Tasmanian to come to Canberra to lobby the environment minister, the  Minister for Defence or the Minister for Veterans' Affairs because it costs an absolute fortune. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Faulkner" NAMEID="5K4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator Faulkner</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;They will know how well you are going from reading your speech.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="H15">Senator CAMPBELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Faulkner was over in Perth yesterday, so he knows how far it is. It is a hell of a long way to come to Canberra when one is a bit upset because the Environment Protection Authority over here makes a bad decision. When Barry Carbon was back in Western Australia at least people could travel in a bus to see him or to protest outside his office if they did not like the decisions he made in relation to the environment. Now Barry Carbon is here with the Environment Protection Authority in Canberra it costs people thousands of dollars to come to see him if they do not like his decisions.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That is one example of the problems associated with centralising power in Canberra. It is something we oppose. We would like to see a sensible system of government where decisions that can be made affecting day-to-day lives are made as close to the people as possible. That is the sort of system we would like to get to. As Senator Short said, quite properly, that cannot be achieved unless there is a sensible solution to that horrible phrase&mdash;vertical fiscal imbalance. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I move to the next subject which will not take long. Again it is to do with hypocrisy. In the last couple of days I have had sent to me by a constituent, who will indeed receive a copy of this speech&mdash;it will only cost the Commonwealth one stamp&mdash;</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Faulkner" NAMEID="5K4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator Faulkner</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;But won't it go to all your pre-selectors too?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="H15">Senator CAMPBELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I never send speeches to pre-selectors.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Faulkner" NAMEID="5K4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator Faulkner</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am sure they will be relieved to hear that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="H15">Senator CAMPBELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have never done that&mdash;except for my maiden speech which I sent them and I am sure no-one read it. I am sure Senator Abetz will send out his maiden speech; it will probably be better than mine. It is good to have an ongoing commentary in this speech, but I will get through this quickly without Senator Faulkner's interjections, even though I am enjoying them.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The last point I raise relates to a bulletin sent out by the Australian Securities Commission in relation to a new program it is running called record keeping audits. It struck me as being quite hypocritical on the part of the federal government, particularly Michael Lavarch, the Attorney-General, as he has had quite an involvement in handing out some of these cultural and sporting grants. The bulletin about the record keeping audit required by the Australian Taxation Office said:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">The ATO has recently launched the Record Keeping Audit (RKA) program, which highlights the ATO's determination to ensure that small businesses keep adequate records.</PARA>
<PARA>Of course that is a very laudable thing, but on behalf of small business people around Australia I say to this federal government that if it is going to spend millions of dollars through the Taxation Office and the Australian Securities Commission sending out thousands of bulletins to small businesses around Australia to `record and explain all transactions and acts engaged', it should ensure that ministers of the federal government over here in Canberra maintain the same level of accountability and record keeping. Of course, I refer to Minister Kelly, if she is still a minister. I have not seen the latest news bulletins; I do not know whether she has gone yet. If a small businessman received that notification from the ASC and the Australian Taxation Office about keeping records&mdash;things like journals, sales invoices, loan agreements, minutes and all the records required to explain his business activities&mdash;and someone involved in overseeing this record keeping audit were to knock on that small businessman's door, saying, `Where are your records? Where do you keep your records? Where are the records that record and explain all your transactions and acts engaged in?', the taxpayer could say, `I have been watching the television; I have read the Auditor-General's report about the sports grants, the sports rorts affair.' If it is fair enough for a federal minister to keep her records and explanations on a 1 1/2 by 2 1/2 metre whiteboard&mdash;which is becoming infamous&mdash;and then to rub them out, it would be fair enough for the small businessman to say, `All my records were done on a whiteboard too, and I have not got a photocopier attached to my whiteboard'. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Of course, that will not happen because, as is stated in this bulletin:</PARA>
<PARA FONT-SIZE="-=2">It is an offence for a person to lodge documents with the ASC which they know contain false, misleading or inaccurate information and statements. The omission of any information or matter which causes the document to be misleading is also an offence.</PARA>
<PARA>The small businessman would be prosecuted by the Australian Securities Commission or the Australian Taxation Office and would suffer damage because there were no records. Of course, that will not happen to this minister because she is a mate of Paul and Annita Keating. She will probably survive this. I think the longer she is there the better, as far as the opposition is concerned. But for the Australian public, the Australian taxpayer and indeed for the credibility of the whole of our nation, the quicker she goes the better. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">But these small businessmen will suffer penalties ranging from as low as $100 up to thousands of dollars for not keeping adequate records. But if a small businessman said to the tax office auditor or to the Australian Securities Commission investigator, `All my records were on a whiteboard. I am very sorry, I had to use the whiteboard for something else. I had a whiteboard special on today at my lunch shop and I had to use my whiteboard to put the specials up, so the records have gone', he would be punished and severely fined. Of course, if you are a minister handing out grants of $30 million you do not suffer any penalty whatsoever, and Mrs Kelly has suffered no penalty whatsoever for her disgraceful behaviour in this sports rorts affair. </PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">I certainly think that this is a case of hypocrisy when we have organisations such as the Taxation Office and the Australian Securities Commission inflicting masses and masses of regulations requiring small businesses to keep records but a minister of the Crown is not required to keep records to explain her decisions, she just needs a 1 1/2 by a 2 1/2 metre whiteboard. In the last few days we have witnessed two acts of gross hypocrisy, and this government stands condemned on both counts. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Before I put the question for the adjournment, I advise honourable senators that estimates committee arrangements for today are as follows: Estimates Committee D is to meet in the main committee room and will be televised on channel 21 and broadcast on FM band 92.7; Estimates Committee E is to meet in committee room 2S1 and will be televised on channel 22 and broadcast on FM band 90.3; and Estimates Committee F is to meet in committee room 2S3 and will be televised on channel 23 and broadcast on FM band 91.1. I now put the question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">That the Senate do now adjourn.</PARA>
<PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
<PARA JUSTIFICATION="CENTERJUST"><EMPHASIS FONT-WEIGHT="BOLD">Senate adjourned at 12.47 p.m.</EMPHASIS></PARA>
</INTERJECT>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1066"><TITLE>PROCLAMATIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">A Proclamation by His Excellency the Governor-General was tabled, notifying that His Excellency had proclaimed the following provisions of an Act to come into operation on the date specified:</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Occupational Health and Safety (Maritime Industry) Act 1993&mdash;Division 4 of Part 1&mdash;21 February 1994 (<EMPHASIS FONT-SLANT="ITAL">Gazette</EMPHASIS> No. S 48, 16 February 1994).</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Documents" PAGE="1066"><TITLE>DOCUMENTS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA FIRST-INDENT="16"><TAB LEADING="NONE" TYPE="NORMAL">The following documents were tabled by the Clerk:</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Australian Bureau of Statistics Act&mdash;Proposals for the collection of information&mdash;1994 Nos 1 and 2.</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Defence Act&mdash;Determination under section 58B&mdash;1994 No. 3.</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Public Service Act&mdash;Determinations&mdash;1994 Nos 104-106, 108-110 and LES 2-LES 4.</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">States Grants (TAFE Assistance) Act&mdash;Determination&mdash;1993 No. TAFE 46.</PARA>
<PARA LEFT-INDENT="16" FONT-SIZE="-=2">Superannuation Benefits (Supervisory Mechanisms) Act&mdash;Determination&mdash;1994 No. 1.</PARA>
</DEBATE></CHAMBER.XSCRIPT></HANSARD>

