
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1941-05-28</date>
    <parliament.no>16</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>3</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>3</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para class="block">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA. </para>
    <para class="block">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES. </para>
    <para class="block">FirstSessionoftheSixteenth Parliament. (Third Period.) </para>
    <para>On  the 3rd April, 1941, the Parliament adjourned until  a  date and hour to be fixed by the  President  and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker,</inline> such date and hour to be not later than the 28th  May, 1941,  at  3  p.m. </para>
    <para>The  President  and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker</inline> summoned the Senate and the House of Representatives respectively to meet on the 28th May, 1941 at 3 p.m. </para>
    <para class="block">Senate. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1941-05-28</day.start>
      <para>The  President <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator the Hon.</inline> J. B. Hayes)  took the chair at 3 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ASSENT TO BILLS</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Assent to the following bills  reported  - </para>
      <para>War Service Homes Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Pay-roll Tax Assessment Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Pay-roll Tax Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Defence Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Commonwealth Public Service Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Crimes Bill 194,1. </para>
      <para>Acts Interpretation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Child Endowment Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Raw Cotton Bounty Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Trade Agreement (Southern Rhodesia) Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Empire Air Service (England to Australia) Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Air Force Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff (Southern (Rhodesian Preference) 1941. </para>
      <para>War Pensions Appropriation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Invalid and Old-age Pensions Appropriation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Wine GrapesCharges Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff Validation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff (Exchange Adjustment) Validation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff (Special War Duty) Validation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff (Canadian Preference) Validation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Customs Tariff (New Zealand Preference) Validation Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Loan Bill 1941. </para>
      <para>Berry Fruit-growers' Relief Bill 1941. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF ME, JOHN LLOYD PRICE</title>
        <page.no>3</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>3</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Vice-President of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Honorable  senators  will have read with deep regret  of the  death in Adelaide, on the 23rd April  last,  of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. John</inline> Lloyd Price, who  was a  member of the House of Representatives and represented the South Australian division of Boothby. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price</inline> had had a long parliamentary career,  having  been elected to the House  of  Assembly in South Australia in 1915. He  was  elected to the House of Representatives  in  1928 as the member for Boothby,  and  represented that division till the time of his death. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price</inline> was a member of the Bankruptcy Legislation Committee from 1932 to 1935, and was Temporary  Chairman  of Committees from December, 1937, to August, 1940. He was a member  of  the Joint Parliamentary Committee  on  Public Works from December, 1937,  to 1940,  and Government Whip in the House of Representatives from November,  1940,  to the date of his death. He was also  a  member of the House Committee. The late honorable member was well known to members of the present Parliament, and I feel sure that he will be missed by  all  of us.  I  extend to his widow and family our most sincere sympathy. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. John</inline> Lloyd Price, member of the House of Representatives for the division of Boothby, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public service, and tenders its sincere sympathy to his widow and family in their bereavement. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>4</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- It is always  an  occasion for regret and sadness when we have  to  refer to the passing of  one  with whom we have been accustomed to work over the years in this Parliament. I knew the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price,</inline> as we all  did,  very well. I was also acquainted with his father, who passed away many years ago.  It  is  fit  and proper that this motion of condolence should be passed, and I associate myself and the other members  of  the Opposition with it. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>4</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JNT</name.id>
            <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Macartney</name>
            <name role="display">Senator ABBOTT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- On .behalf of the members of the  Country  party in this chamber, I support the sentiments expressed by the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator MeLeay)</inline> and the Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator</inline> Collings). In all sincerity,  we  can say that we hold in affectionate memory John Price, whom most of us familiarly knew as " Jackie " Price. We recall how he seemed to be in the fullness of life only  a  week or two before we heard  the  sad news of his death. I was associatedwith him and had opportunities to know him well on the Bankruptcy Legislation Committee. I am glad that during my term in this Parliament I was privileged  to  claim him as a friend, and I join sincerely  in  this expression of sympathy to his widow and family. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>4</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KTX</name.id>
            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, James</name>
            <name role="display">Senator JAMES McLACHLAN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I have known the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price</inline> from boyhood. I was particularly friendly with his family, especially his father, the late Honorable Thomas Price, a former Premier of South Australia.  As  a colleague of the deceased gentleman when he was a member of the South Australian House of Assembly, I knew him intimately, and his death is generally regretted in South Australia. He  was a  loyal citizen and a valuable representative of his electorate. His nature  was  such that he endeared himself  to all of us.  There was no doubt as to his honesty  and  sincerity in politics. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>4</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Like my colleague, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator James</inline> McLachlan, I have known the  late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price</inline> as boy, man, legislator,  Agent-General  for South Australia, and afterwards as representative of the division of Boothby in the House of Representatives. I associate myself with this motion of condolence to the widow  and f amily, and I also wish  to pay one  other tribute to the memory of the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Price.</inline> He possessed the courage that his father possessed before him. It was a traditional courage, and, in his last days, it must have been most gratifying to the deceased, who had an illness which he bore with great cheerfulness, to know that that courage had been handed down to his distinguished son, who has been decorated for his services in the air arm of the Royal Australian Navy. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question resolved  in  the  affirmative,  honorable  senators  standing  in their  places. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF THE HONORABLE JAMES ARTHUR BOYD</title>
        <page.no>4</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>4</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Postmaster-General</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - It  is  with regret  that I inform honorable senators  of the  death, in Melbourne, on  the 12th April  last, of the Honorable James  Arthur  Boyd, who was  a  former member  of the  House of Representatives. The  late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline> Boyd was elected to the  Legislative Assembly  of Victoria in  1901 and was a  member of that chamber  till 1908. He  was an honorary Minister from February,  1907,  to December,  1908. He waselected  to the House of  Representatives  for the division of Henty in  1913,  and again in  1914  and  1917.  Although  many  years have passed since the  late member  sat in this Parliament, it is  in keeping  with the tradition of the  Senate that we to-day  honour his memory.  I  extend  to  his family our sincere sympathy. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death of the Honorable James Arthur Boyd, former member of the House of Representatives for the division of Henty and former State Minister, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public service, and tenders its sincere sympathy to the members of hie family in their bereavement. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I had  not  the privilege of acquaintanceship with the  late  Honorable J. A. Boyd,  nor,  J  think,  had  any  other member of the present Opposition in this chamber, but as the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator McLeay)</inline> has told us the deceased gentleman  Tendered  valuable service to  the  Parliament of this country, he is entitled to  the  respect which we now pay his memory. The Opposition associates itself with the motion, particularly with  the  expression of sympathy with the members of  the  family of  the  deceased. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KAY</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIBSON, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIBSON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- The Country party wishes to be associated with the motion before the Senate. I knew  the  late James Boyd when he and I were members of the House of Representatives. He  was  a man of sterling worth  and  forceful character who exhibited courage  and  forthrightness in all that he did. He will be greatly missed in business circles. Our sympathy goes  out  to his family in their bereavement. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KR9</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Assistant Minister</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">LECKIE, John</name>
            <name role="display">Senator LECKIE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - Although, as the Leader of  the  Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Collings)</inline> has said,  not  any members of  the  present Opposition were associated with the late James Arthur Boyd when he was a member of the House of Representatives, I knew him for many years when I too was a member of that chamber. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Boyd</inline> was indeed, as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Gibson</inline> has Raid, a man of sterling character, forthright  and  courageous in all that he undertook. To the last he  led  a  full  life  and  enjoyed the company of  his  friends. A rugged Scot, he was loyal,  not  only to Scotland,  the  land of his birth,  but  also to Australia, the land of  his  adoption. I regard his passing as  a  great personal loss. He will be sadly missed in Victoria where he  was  an outstanding personality. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATHOF MR. ALEXANDER HAY</title>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- It is with regret that I inform honorable senators of the death on the 8th May of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Alexander</inline> Hay, who was a former member of the House of Representatives, he having been elected for the division of New England at the general election in 1919. He represented that division till 1922. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hay</inline> served in the Australian Imperial Force in the last war. He was appointed a captain in the Force in 1915, and later in that year was promoted to major. He was second in command of the New South Wales and Queensland Remount Units. I extend to the members of his family our sincere sympathy.  I  move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>That the Senate expresses itssincere regret at the death of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Alexander</inline> Hay, former member of the House of Representatives for the division of New England, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public service, and tenders its sincere sympathy to the members of his  family in their bereavement. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Although, so far as I am aware, no member now sitting on this side of the chamber had the privilege of personal acquaintance with the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hay,</inline> it is fitting that the Senate should pay respect to his memory, and place on record its appreciation of the work which he, as a former member of the National Parliament, was able to do for this country. The Opposition joins in the expression of sympathy with the members of the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hay's</inline> family who to-day mourn his loss. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>5</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JQP</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COOPER, Walter</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COOPER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Although I had not the privilege of personal acquaintanceship with the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hay,</inline> the remarks of the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator McLeay)</inline> indicate clearly that he had a distinguished military career and rendered valuable service to this country. The Country party desires to associate itself with the motion before the Chair, particularly that portion of it which expresses sympathy with the members of the family of the 'deceased gentleman. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question  resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>6</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party>UAP</party>
            <role>Postmaster-General</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - As a mark of respect to the memory of the gentlemen whose passing we mourn, I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate  do now adjourn. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>6</page.no>
        <time.stamp>15:19:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para>Senate  adjourned at  3.19 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>