
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1976-10-12</date>
    <parliament.no>30</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>2</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>1107</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1976-10-12</day.start>
      <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Condor Laucke)</inline> took the chair at 2.30 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS</title>
        <page.no>1107</page.no>
        <type>ministerial arrangements</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1107</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>DV4</name.id>
            <electorate>Western AustraliaLeader of the Government in the Senate</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role>Minister for Administrative Services</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I inform the Senate that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Andrew</inline> Peacock, left Australia yesterday to lead the Australian delegation to the South Pacific Law of the Sea Conference which is being held in Suva. He is expected to return on 16 October. During his absence the Minister for Primary Industry, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Ian</inline> Sinclair, will act as Minister for Foreign Affairs. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PETITIONS</title>
        <page.no>1107</page.no>
        <type>petition</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Aboriginal Land Rights</title>
          <page.no>1107</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1107</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>0V4</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BONNER, Neville</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BONNER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I present the following petition from 17 citizens of Australia: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para class="block">To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled- The petition of the undersigned respectfully showeth: That the Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Bill 1976, does not satisfy the Aboriginal needs for land in the Northern Territory. Your petitioners most humbly pray that the Senate, m Parliament assembled, should: </para>
            <list type="decimal-dotted">
              <item label="1.">
                <para>Extend the freeze on European claims to the unalienated Crown Lands of the Northern Territory until 12 months after the passage of the Bill; and to provide for speedy lodging and hearing of Aboriginal claims. The hearing of the Aboriginal claims have been postponed as a result of Government decisions, Aboriginals should not be penalised. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="2.">
                <para>Amend the Bill to ensure: </para>
                <list type="loweralpha">
                  <item label="(a)">
                    <para>The removal of all powers to pass land rights legislation from the Northern Territory Legislative Assembly, particularly its control over sacred sights, entry permits, control over the seas adjoining Aboriginal land, the fishing rights of non-Aborigines, the right of Aborigines to enter pastoral stations and control of wildlife on Aboriginal land. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(b)">
                    <para>The control of Aborigines of all roads passing through Aboriginal lands. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(c)">
                    <para>The restoration of the Aboriginal Land Commissioner&#39;s powers to hear claims based on need as well as traditional claims lodged by Aborigines. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(d)">
                    <para>The restoration of all powers vested in land councils and the Land Commissioner in the 1975 Land Rights Bill. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(e)">
                    <para>A provision that any Government decision to override Aboriginal objections to mining on the basis of national interest itself be reviewed by both Houses of Parliament. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(f)">
                    <para>A provision that land-owning groups of Aborigines may apply to form separate trusts if they wish. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(g)">
                    <para>The removal of artificial barriers to traditional owners imposed by the Territory borders on all tribes so affected. </para>
                  </item>
                </list>
              </item>
            </list>
            <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>As the petition exceeds 250 words, under the sessional order it is not able to be read to the Senate, but the full text of the petition will be incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
          <para>Petition received. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Education</title>
          <page.no>1107</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1107</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3A</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I present the following petition from 5 1 citizens of Australia: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that the recent budgetary allocations endanger the quality of Australian education, especially for disadvantaged groups, and, in particular, for migrants, Aboriginals and tertiary students from poor backgrounds. </para>
            <para>Your petitioners believe that all persons admitted to institutions of tertiary education in Australia have a right to adequate living conditions and that it is the responsibility of Government to ensure that sufficient funds are allocated to protect that right. </para>
            <para>Your petitioners therefore humbly pray: </para>
            <list type="decimal-dotted">
              <item label="1.">
                <para>That the quality of education in schools and tertiary institutions be not eroded but extended through the provision of adequate funds. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="2.">
                <para>That in view of the sub-standard living conditions forced upon many tertiary students as a consequence of a totally inadequate student assistance scheme, there is an urgent need for a substantial increase and indexation of grants provided under the Tertiary Education Assistance Scheme to the level of a living wage, and, further, that the needs-based grants scheme be in no way jeopardised by any other program of student assistance. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="3.">
                <para>That in order to preserve the quality of higher education in Australia and so as to prevent discrimination against disadvantaged groups there should be no introduction of fees for overseas students, second degree students, higher degree students or any students. </para>
              </item>
            </list>
            <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>Petition received and read. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1107</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CLERK, The</name>
              <name role="display">The Clerk</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Building Activity</title>
          <page.no>1107</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">To the Honourable  President  and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>Concerned at the record number of building workers registered for unemployment benefits in Australia: </para>
        <para>Aware that the Federal Government&#39;s Budget for 1976-77 does not include measures to restore full employment in the building and construction industry; </para>
        <para>Alarmed at the fact that unemployment is at the highest level in New South Wales and Queensland since the depression years, with clear indications that the position will further deteriorate. </para>
        <para>Aware that at the same time more and more people are being denied proper housing and other building needs of great social importance are not being carried out. </para>
        <para>Aware that the apprenticeship system is being seriously threatened and many apprentices are unable to complete their apprenticeship. This along with the fact that thousands of tradesmen have been driven out of the industry, will, in years to come create a chronic shortage of skilled workers to the detriment of the community and with enormous adverse economic repercussions. </para>
        <para>We, the undersigned citizens of the Commonwealth of Australia, by this our humble petition respectfully request that members of the Senate insist that the 1976-77 Budget provides specific measures to lift building activity particularly: </para>
        <para>Government construction of homes, schools, hospitals and public works development projects, employment and training of unemployed young people, restoration of finance cuts in sewerage and urban development work, provide finance to land commission to provide cheaper land for home building, provide low interest home loans finance. </para>
        <para>We request that the Budget be returned to the House of Representatives with instructions from the Senate to include such measures. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Building Activity</title>
          <page.no>1108</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">To the Honourable  President  and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>Concerned at the record number of building workers registered for unemployment benefits in New South Wales; </para>
        <para>Aware of the Australian Bureau of Statistics report for New South Wales revealing a drastic fall off in both commencements and approvals for future commencements, of building projects this year as compared to previous years; </para>
        <para>Alarmed at the fact that 1568 building apprentices were registered for unemployment benefit payments during the month of July in New South Wales; </para>
        <para>Conscious of the fact that most of the unemployed apprentices will never be able to complete their training (thus creating a continuing problem for the industry, and indeed the community as a whole) unless immediate urgent measures are provided for the Federal Government Budget; </para>
        <para>We the undersigned citizens of New South Wales in the Commonwealth of Australia by this our humble petition respectfully request that members of the Senate insist that the 1976-77 Budget provides specific measures to lift building activity particularly welfare housing, schools, hospitals and other public buildings above the present dangerously low level; </para>
        <para>We request that the Budget be returned to the House of Representatives with instructions from the Senate to include such measures. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Employment of Articled Clerks</title>
          <page.no>1108</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble Petition of the undersigned staff and students of the Law School, University of Western Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>That 30 of the 80 final year law students seeking Articles for 1 977 are unable to obtain them, and there is no workshop course available. The Law Society of Western Australia has indicated that it is powerless to assist in placing these 30 students, and increased numbers of law students completing their courses in following years. </para>
        <para>Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that urgent consideration be given to this problem and call upon the Federal Government to alleviate this situation and re-commence the employment of Articled Clerks in the Attorney-General&#39;s Department. </para>
        <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Medibank</title>
          <page.no>1108</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. We the undersigned, citizens of the Commonwealth by this our humble petition respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>That Medibank has proved to be the cheapest and most efficient means of bringing health care to Australian citizens and that the citizens of Australia have received Medibank as a great and valued social reform. </para>
        <para>That Medibank has proved itself to be a far superior system of health care than was offered by the private funds prior to July 1975. </para>
        <para>Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that the Government will observe the promise made by the Prime Minister in his policy speech that &#39;We will maintain Medibank and ensure the standard of health care does not decline &#39;. </para>
        <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Button.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Metric System</title>
          <page.no>1108</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled: </para>
        <para>The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth objection to the Metric system and request the Government to restore the Imperial system. </para>
        <para>And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Rae.</inline></para>
        <para>Petitions received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Social Security Matters</title>
          <page.no>1108</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate, in Parliament assembled, the Petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>That distress is being caused to social security recipients by the delay in adjusting pensions to the Consumer Prices Index months after prices of goods and services have risen, and that medications which were formerly pharmaceutical benefits must now be paid for. Additionally, that State housing authorities&#39; waiting lists for low rental dwellings for pensioners grow ever longer, and the cost of funerals increase ever greater. </para>
        <para>Your petitioners call on the Australian Government as a matter of urgency to- </para>
        <para>Adjust social security payments instantly and automatically when the quarterly Consumer Prices Index is announced. </para>
        <para>Restore pharmaceutical benefits deleted from the free list. </para>
        <para>Update the State Grants (Dwellings for Pensioners) Act of 1974, eroded by inflation, to increase grants to overcome the backlog. </para>
        <para>Update Funeral Benefits to 60 per cent of reasonable cost of funeral. (This benefit was 200 shillings, 20 dollars, when  introduced in 1943. It was seven times the 1943 pension of 27 shillings a week). </para>
        <para>And your petitioners in duty bound will ever pray. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Scott.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Pharmaceutical Benefits: Cow&#39;s Milk Substitutes</title>
          <page.no>1109</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">To the Honourable  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>That the Goats&#39; Milk Production industry in Victoria is being threatened with extinction because of: </para>
        <list type="loweralpha">
          <item label="(a)">
            <para>reduction in the age limit from six years to eighteen months for persons eligible to receive cows&#39; milk substitute as a pharmaceutical benefit under the schedules of the National Health Act, and </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(b)">
            <para>the importation of powdered goats milk products from the United States of America and New Zealand. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Your petitioners further humbly pray that cows&#39; milk substitutes be restored to the schedule of Pharmaceutical Benefits for people up to the age of six years as soon as possible, and that protection be given to the Goats&#39; Milk producing industry from competition from imports of powdered goats&#39; milk from other countries. </para>
        <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Tehan.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</title>
        <page.no>1109</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INDONESIA</title>
          <page.no>1109</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1109</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ISW</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIEDT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I ask the Minister representing the Prime Minister: Is it the Government&#39;s understanding that the Indonesian Government now believes that the Australian Government recognises Indonesia&#39;s sovereignty over East Timor? If so, is its understanding correct? If not, will the Government issue a clear statement repudiating the Indonesian position as enunciated by Lieutenant-General Sudharmono? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1109</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-It is not possible for the Government to understand what the Indonesian Government understands to be the position. What is quite clear is this Government&#39;s stand - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1109</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Walsh</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-What is that? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1109</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-Wait for it. The honourable senator should contain himself. The Prime Minister said last night on his return from Indonesia that the position of the Australian Government was set out quite clearly in paragraph 13 on page 4 of the communique of  President  Suharto and himself. I will repeat it: </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <quote>
            <para>The Prime Minister recalled that Australian policy on the East Timor question had been clearly set out by the Minister for Foreign Affairs in the Parliament. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>We have no need to add to that statement or to qualify it. We have no need to parse it, if that is the right term. There is no need to do anything with it unless any honourable senator disagrees with the statement of the Government&#39;s policy, as set out in the House of Representatives by the Minister for Foreign Affairs. If any honourable senator disagrees with what my colleague, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Peacock,</inline> said on that day, let him stand in this place and say so. </para>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1109</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>ISW</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WRIEDT</name>
              </talker>
              <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">- Mr President,</inline>I wish to ask a supplementary question. In view of the answer given by the honourable senator, are we now to believe that the interpretation by the Indonesian Government of the policy statement of the Australian Government is different from that of the Australian Government? If that is the case, does the Government intend to communicate with the Indonesian Government that Government&#39;s misunderstanding of Australia&#39;s policy? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1109</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-The Prime Minister has been in Indonesia for 4 days. I understand from him that President Suharto is under no misunderstanding as to the policy of the Australian Government. I fail to see why the Government should answer every statement made after the cessation of that visit. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>READY RECKONER FOR PENSION ENTITLEMENTS</title>
          <page.no>1109</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1109</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ME4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAUME, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BAUME</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Social Security seen a simple new ready reckoner setting out the pension entitlements of pensioners in receipt of age, widow, invalid or supporting mothers&#39; pensions? Since pension entitlements will rise significantly in November and since the means test is to be replaced by a less restrictive income test, will the Minister agree that a need exists for clarity of the new entitlements and conditions? Accordingly, if the new ready reckoner, which seems to be clear and simple, is accurate, will the Government ensure that it is made available for wide and early distribution to ensure that pensioners know and understand the extent to which they will benefit from the Government&#39;s new arrangements? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1109</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government has in hand the matter of information to pensioners with regard to the application of the new income test and the matters that will take effect with the rises in pensions and the other consequential differences arising from these policy matters. I will be making a statement shortly with regard to the availability of this information. I assure the Senate that it will give clearly and explicitly the means testing arrangements and the new policies which have been put into effect. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HEAVY METALS IN COASTAL WATERS</title>
          <page.no>1110</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEEFFE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Science. Has Australia ratified the international agreement to monitor the incidence of heavy metals occurring in natural waters? Is it a fact that until recent years no chemical methods were available to study the presence of such metals at the very low concentrations that occur in Australian waters? Can the Minister indicate to the Senate the method which is currently available to Australian scientists to enable this country to fulfil its obligations to international pollution control in respect of heavy metals in our coastal waters? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role>Minister for Science</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The answer to the first 2 parts of the honourable senator&#39;s question is no. In relation to the third part of his question, the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation is involved in the testing of water in a variety of ways. The honourable senator mentioned heavy metals in coastal waters. I am unable to answer whether that is one branch of its research. Generally pollution of inland waters and water off the coast is the subject of investigation and research by CSIRO. The international connection, I believe, would come from the work that CSIRO is doing through its committees. I cannot give the name of the committees, but committees of CSIRO and scientists are involved internationally through either the Academy of Science or other bodies that may be associated with international agreements. I will seek for the honourable senator more information about heavy metals in off-shore waters. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DAIRY INDUSTRY</title>
          <page.no>1110</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>IE4</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ARCHER, Brian</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ARCHER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I preface my question, which is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs, by reminding him that the Industries Assistance Commission report on the dairy industry recommends that dairy farmers reduce production as a means of increasing the domestic market price and therefore the return to the farmers. If farmers make such a reduction in production to achieve the results outlined in the report, what action will the Government take to protect the dairy industry from the import of low cost production from other countries whose dairy industries could take advantage of a higher Australian domestic price? Can the Minister give an undertaking that the dumping of other countries&#39; dairy products in Australia wil not occur? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Veterans' Affairs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The Government has before it 2 reports from the Industries Assistance Commission dealing with the dairy industry. The first report deals with the general question of assistance to the industry; the second deals with the specific question of desirable marketing arrangements for dairy products. However, I understand that neither of these reports actually recommends any reduction in production either by individual farms or by the total industry. The marketing scheme proposed by the LAC is designed to ensure a greater stability in the marketing of Australian dairy products than currently exists and aims at achieving a more firmly based and reliable industry. As far as that part of the question relating to dumping is concerned, I remind the Senate that the Government has standing arrangements under which anti-dumping action can be initiated immediately goods are dumped on the Australian market. However, the recommendations of the reports to which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Archer</inline> referred, concerning both the tariffs and the anti-dumping action, have yet to be considered by the Government. They will be studied as soon as possible along with all the recommendations contained in the 2 reports currently before the Government. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>UNITED STATES BEEF QUOTAS</title>
          <page.no>1110</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>RG4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIETZELT, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIETZELT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry. I refer him to the blatantly partisan decision by  President  Ford to impose statutory quotas on beef exports to the United States by all countries. To what extent has the action of the  President  infringed the rules established under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade? Was there any consultation or negotiations between the United States authorities and Australian authorities at any relevant level before this seemingly unilateral action was taken by  President  Ford? In view of the imbalance of trade between Australia and the United States, which favours the United States approximately two to one, is the Government contemplating retaliatory action on Australian imports from the United States in order to establish beyond any doubt Australia&#39;s resolve to protect established Australian beef export markets? If such action is not considered, what action is the Government determined to take? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1110</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Industry and Commerce</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-One notices that people who are involved with the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade tend to worship at the shrine of GATT until they are affected by it themselves, when they tend to forget that the shrine exists. The general matter raised is a serious matter for the Australian beef producers. The imposition of quotas is a matter for substantial regret. As far as I am informed, there has been no consultation and we will not be exceeding the voluntary restraint arrangements we have agreed to. A Press statement was issued by the Acting Prime Minister yesterday, and the Prime Minister has been in touch with  President  Ford about this matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NATIONAL EMPLOYMENT AND TRAINING SCHEME</title>
          <page.no>1111</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>EF4</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHANEY, Fred</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CHANEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Social Security seen the report in the <inline font-style="italic">Age</inline> newspaper of today &#39;s date alleging that there has been 7 weeks delay in the distribution of allowances under the National Employment and Training scheme to migrant students taking English courses at La Trobe University? The article also claims a history of delays in 7 previous courses at the same university. Can the Minister inform the Senate whether the report is true? What system is followed in making such payments? If there are difficulties, can the system be examined with a view to removing them in the future? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have seen the report which refers to delays. I am able to inform the Senate that normally claims are determined and payment arranged within 2 days of the receipt of the claim. There are no delays in payment at present. There are no claims undetermined or awaiting payment processing in our Melbourne office. We have had an inquiry about certain claims from 9 trainees. We have been informed that in 6 cases no claims have yet been received by the Department of Social Security for processing, and of the other three, one was paid on 5 October and the other two have been processed and the claimants are due for their first payment on pay day, 14 October. I should mention as a general statement that claims under the NEAT scheme are not sent to my Department for processing from the Department of Employment and Industrial Relations until training is about to commence. Payments may begin only when training commences. If claimants are receiving unemployment benefit when selected for training they should be advised to continue to lodge their income statements until training under NEAT actually commences to allow continued payment of unemployment benefit in the void period mentioned. I undertake to discuss this matter with the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations and to bring to his attention the need to advise trainees of this aspect of the scheme. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MEDIBANK</title>
          <page.no>1111</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3T</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Donald Newton</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DONALD CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Has the Minister representing the Minister for Health seen a statement by the  President  of the Voluntary Health Insurance Association, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Moon,</inline> which appeared in today&#39;s <inline font-style="italic">Australian</inline> claiming that only 25 per cent of the population was relying on the Medibank levy as its only form of health cover? Can the Minister say whether there are reliable figures available to substantiate this claim? If not, will the Minister agree that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Moon</inline> is irresponsibly misleading the public with premature and inaccurate statements? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I did notice the Press statement to the effect that 25 per cent of people were relying on Medibank. I have no information from the Minister for Health to indicate whether this is accurate. I believe the same newspaper article stated that the Health Insurance Commission had no information at the de the article was reported to substantiate what it contained. I will refer the matter to the Minister for Health to see whether there are any accurate statistics that are relevant. If there are, I will see whether they can be released. I agree with the honourable senator that statements based on supposition are not necessarily accurate. Perhaps in this case it is too early to say whether the figures mentioned are accurate. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INCOME EQUALISATION DEPOSITS</title>
          <page.no>1111</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8H</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Andrew</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Minister representing the Treasurer and the Minister for Primary Industry. Can he give the Senate some indication of when the details of the income equalisation deposit scheme will be available? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Not yet, but I shall look for it this afternoon. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INDONESIA</title>
          <page.no>1111</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>7V4</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GEORGES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I would like to bring the Leader of the Government in the Senate back to the question of East Timor. The Opposition&#39;s concern is not with what the Government is saying but with what the Government is doing. I ask: Is it not a fact that the Prime Minister&#39;s visit to Indonesia at this time has been taken as an acceptance of the Indonesian policy in regard to East Timor? Will he state clearly what is the Government&#39;s policy? Is it for the withdrawal of Indonesian troops from East Timor and is it in support of a free act of self determination by the East Timorese people? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1111</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The honourable senator says that there is a difference between what the Government is saying and what it is doing. I thought that the Government was not only saying what its policy is but was also attempting to do something about helping the Timorese refugees in Australia and those who are in need in Timor. If the honourable senator has any suggestion as to how either the Timorese in Australia could be better helped or how we could better help those in distress in Timor I would be pleased if he would come forward with that suggestion. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>4F4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Button</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Answer the question. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">-If Senator Button</inline>is going to answer for me he can answer the lot and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Georges</inline> can go without. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>7V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
                <name role="display">Senator GEORGES</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I ask a supplementary question. It now seems that because <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Button</inline> has interjected the main point of my question is not being answered. What is the Government&#39;s policy in regard to the withdrawal of Indonesian troops from East Timor and what is the Government&#39;s policy now in regard to a free act of self determination by the East Timorese people? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I have said repeatedly in this place that the policy set out by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Peacock</inline> on 4 March was and is the Government&#39;s policy. We have nothing to add to it and we have nothing to subtract from it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K3A</name.id>
                <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
                <party>ALP</party>
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
                <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It is one of the unmentionables in the Senate now. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1112</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-If the honourable senator wants me to waste the rest of question time by reading <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Peacock&#39;s</inline> statement I will do so. I would have thought that a categorical assurance that what <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Peacock</inline> said on that date was and still is right at this moment- at 7 minutes to 3 p.m.- the Government&#39;s policy ought to satisfy everybody. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>WOOL HANDLING DISPUTE</title>
          <page.no>1112</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1112</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5H</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SCOTT, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SCOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations. Has the Minister&#39;s attention been drawn to the growing concern that an important decision of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission recommending removal of the bans on the handling of wool bales of 204 kilograms is being flouted by the Federated Storemen and Packers Union? Is the Minister aware that the rank and file of the Storemen and Packers Union have not been consulted by their leaders since the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission&#39;s decision was announced? Is the Minister also aware of the proposals for strong action by growers if the Commission&#39;s determinations are not implemented? Is it not true that there has been complaint only from the Storemen and Packers Union out of the 10 unions involved since the 1966 agreement on 204 kilograms as the maximum bale weight, an agreement to which the Australian Council of Trade Unions was a major party? Did the ACTU not advise against strike action in this dispute in February this year? Will the Minister seek to ensure that Australians in general and wool growers in particular are adequately protected against this sort of flagrant abuse of the law? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1112</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have been advised of the current developments relating to bans which have been imposed by the Federated Storemen and Packers Union in support of its demand that the maximum weight of wool bales handled by union members should be reduced from 204 kilograms to 180 kilograms. On 14 September Commissioner Heagney handed down a decision in which he stated that his interim recommendation made in June this year should stand and that storemen should handle bales up to 204 kilograms but, wherever possible, mechanical means should be used for the handling of bales in excess of 180 kilograms. Representatives of the union and of the Wool Selling Brokers Employers Federation have conferred on a number of occasions in relation to a number of recommendations made by Commissioner Heagney concerning the weight of wool bales and other issues, especially those relating to the provision of adequate safety facilities in the industry. Negotiations are proceeding and are apparently near finalisation. The Minister whom I represent is confident that agreements will shortly be reached between the parties on this question and it would be premature for the Government to intrude into this matter at this time when negotiations are at a delicate stage. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EAST TIMOR</title>
          <page.no>1112</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1112</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>CJO</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHEELDON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WHEELDON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I, too, wish to direct a question to the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the matter of East Timor. I am not for the moment disputing what the Minister has said, and that is that the policy of the Government has not changed, but in view of the fact that since the original statements were made earlier this year the Prime Minister has visited Indonesia and as it does appear that the Indonesian Government has construed, possibly quite incorrectly, things that were said as being a statement of support by the Australian Government for the Indonesian occupation of East Timor and its incorporation into Indonesia, will the Government consider making a further statement reaffirming Australian pokey on the question of East Timor so that there will not be any confusion on this subject? If, in fact, as has been said, the Indonesian Government has been assured that the Australian policy has not been altered this will not occasion any distress to the Indonesian Government but will make it completely clear to everybody else that there has not been any change. I ask this question without suggesting&#39; that there has been a change but just so that any possible shred of doubt can be removed. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1113</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I do not know whether or not to be flattered by the implication that I am not capable of making a statement on behalf of the Government. If the honourable senator thinks that the assurances I have given are not sufficient then I will pass his request on to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. I would just like to assure the honourable senator that this Government happens to run on collective responsibility and what I say binds my colleagues. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FM RADIO</title>
          <page.no>1113</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1113</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KQD</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAJOVIC, Milivoj</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LAJOVIC</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Has the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications read a report in the daily Press which states that &#39;commercial stations have been excluded from FM radio since a decision was made by the former Government to keep them from expanding their services into this band&#39;? Does the Minister know whether the report is correct? If it is will he ask his colleague to reconsider this decision in order to improve the quality of radio reception in metropolitan areas? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1113</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Federal Affairs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I have not seen the media report to which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Lajovic</inline> refers. I am able to recall, however, that it was the policy of the previous Government- it was certainly a stated policy at the time- that existing commercial radio stations should not be given the opportunity to change from AM to FM broadcasting. I remind the Senate that, nevertheless, the then Senate Standing Committee on Education, Science and the Arts which was inquiring into broadcasting and television reached a recommendation which was tabled in the Senate and which was unanimous from representatives of both sides of the Senate to the effect that FM facilities should be equally available to commercial stations as to new licensees. Quite clearly, upon reflection, that must be an equitable situation in that FM broadcasting is simply a new or an improved technique. If a licensee is given a licence to broadcast, the licensee should not be denied the use of a better technique which is then given to a new competitor to the first licensee&#39;s grave disadvantage. Having said that, and having drawn the attention of the Senate to that report, I shall direct the question asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Lajovic</inline> to my colleague, the Minister in another place. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>YOUTH EMPLOYMENT TRAINING SCHEME</title>
          <page.no>1113</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1113</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>6H4</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HARRADINE, Brian</name>
              <name role="display">Senator HARRADINE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations. Last Thursday in a question to the Minister about the youth employment training scheme I asked what procedures had been adopted to ensure that the trainees would not replace existing workers; whether there would be some continuity of employment for the trainees and whether the overall result of this scheme would be an increase in employment in the participating undertakings. In reply the Minister said he would try to obtain some information. I ask the Minister whether he has any information on this most vital matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1113</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>
              <inline font-weight="bold">- Senator Harradine</inline>asked this question of me last Thursday. It related to the Government&#39;s implementation of its policy regarding the special youth employment training scheme. I am pleased to advise the Senate that over the weekend I was able to obtain information from the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations whom I represent in this place. I have to advise that the special youth employment training scheme is intended to give the opportunity for on-the-job training to 1975 school leavers who have not yet established themselves in stable employment. The program is an extension of a well-tried form of training under the National Employment and Training scheme whereby unemployed persons may be placed in subsidised on-the-job training. There are currently some 4400 trainees of this type under NEAT and there is no evidence of the circumstances that the honourable senator fears, namely, that employers may put off those at present in employment in order to obtain subsidised trainees. The arrangement of training placements is handled under both NEAT and the special youth program on the basis that the training obtained should lead to stable employment or to the trainee obtaining skills which are acceptable and transferable to other employers. The experience under NEAT is that in the great majority of cases stable employment is achieved after training of this type. In making arrangements for placement under the special youth program, officers of the Commonwealth Employment Service are required to ensure that employers have not put off current employees in order to take on trainees. The response from employers to the special youth employment training scheme has been impressive. It is evident that the employers are willing to take on trainees under the program whereas they otherwise would not have done so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TRADE: ARAB BOYCOTT</title>
          <page.no>1114</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUU</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MISSEN, Alan</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MISSEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is addressed to the Minister for Industry and Commerce who may answer it either in his substantive role or as Minister representing the Minister for Overseas Trade. I refer to the recent controversy in the United States of America where, it is reported, some 1 1 000 American companies have been threatened by the Arab boycott arising out of trade with Israel and where it is further reported that some 10 000 of those companies have given in to the threat. I ask the Minister whether there is information available as to the number of Australian companies that have been likewise threatened by boycott because of trade or possible trade with Israel, including the names of companies that have in fact given way to such threats. I ask the Minister to make available to the public the names of all companies that have given way to such threats made by extremists and terrorists groups so that the public can judge whether it should give support to such companies or rather to other companies which have withstood the threat of boycott </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-In this chamber I represent the Minister for Overseas Trade, and naturally I represent myself from time to time. I have covered the Overseas Trade portfolio when the Minister has been away, I think on about 5 occasions. To my certain knowledge nobody has in that time taken up with me a case such as the one mentioned by the honourable senator, that is, Australian companies being prejudiced or in any way put at commercial hazard, but it is an interesting question. I shall certainly after question time try to ascertain any details for the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEPARTMENT OF SOCIAL SECURITY: SOCIAL WORKERS</title>
          <page.no>1114</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9V4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GRIMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is addressed to the Minister for Social Security. What information can the Minister give the Senate regarding an investigation to consider the possible incorporation of all social workers on the Commonwealth Government&#39;s payroll into the Department of Social Security? Has the Minister authorised this investigation? Can she give the Senate its terms of reference? Will the investigation team make the report public and allow social workers and perhaps their clients to comment on the findings of this committee? Can the Minister assure the Senate that there will be no arbitrary placing of social workers into a system of social controllers, thereby lessening their effectiveness in acting for people and, if necessary, acting against the advice of the Department of Social Security? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Administrative arrangements are the prerogative of the Prime Minister. Any matter that would refer to several departments in the way in which it has been mentioned in the honourable senator&#39;s question is not for my determination. I have not requested that an investigation be made into the practicability of all social workers coming within the Department of Social Security. I am unable to answer the honourable senator&#39;s question completely because it is outside my own area of responsibility. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EAST TIMOR</title>
          <page.no>1114</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>0V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BONNER, Neville</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BONNER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs: Can he tell the Senate the difference between the present Government&#39;s policy under <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Fraser</inline> and the policy of the previous Government under <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Whitlam</inline> in relation to East Timor? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1114</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I think the present policy of the Government and what it is trying to do regarding East Timor is well known. If the honourable senator wants to know the policy of the previous Government, I refer him to a speech made in this place- the date of which I have forgotten but I will obtain it for him- by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Gietzelt</inline> who now sits on the front bench of the Opposition. In that speech he said some quite devastating things about the conduct of the previous Government when this matter first arose. I think all those who have been interested at all in the situation in East Timor would be firmly of the opinion that the present circumstances would not have arisen but for the action or non-action of the previous Prime Minister at that time. If anybody sold the East Timorese down the drain - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1114</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JYA</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">O&#39;BYRNE, Justin</name>
                <name role="display">Senator O&#39;Byrne</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- You admit that they have been sold down the drain? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1114</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-Yes. There has never been any doubt about that. They were sold down the drain by the person who is the present parliamentary Leader of the Opposition. I suggest that honourable senators opposite go into their Caucus meeting tomorrow and do something about it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INSTALLATION AT CAPE GRIM</title>
          <page.no>1115</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JUH</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DEVITT, Donald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DEVITT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I direct a question to the Minister for Science. I should like to preface it by saying that I am intrigued- other people are also- by some construction activity which is going on in the vicinity of Cape Grim, which is a remote and unpopulated area in the far northwest of Tasmania. I think the Minister will know of that area. Can the Minister advise the Senate of the nature and purpose of this installation? Can he assure the Senate that this activity is not related to investigations into suitable sites for an Omega tracking station? If this matter is not within his ministerial responsibility, can he do anything to clear up what appears to be something of a mystery? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not aware of any particular major construction being carried out at Cape Grim. The Cape Grim premises are controlled basically by the Van Die men &#39;s Land Corporation and on Cape Grim, which is the most north-westerly point in Tasmania, the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation for some time has had a large caravan installed. This caravan was used originally by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration which handed it over to CSIRO so that it could carry out work on upper atmosphere physics. It is being used in a world program of testing the pollution of the atmosphere. The air stream coming across from the Great Australian Bight produces in actual fact one of the cleanest flows of air that has been found around the world. I can assure the honourable senator that when the wind changes to the north-west to some extent and the air blows down from the Victorian area it is not quite so clean. However, the only construction by CSIRO that has gone on in the area has been the building of a small ablution block about 12 feet by 12 feet. So far as I know, my Department is not connected with any other construction work. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ABORIGINES: ALCOHOL PROBLEMS</title>
          <page.no>1115</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPO</name.id>
              <electorate>NORTHERN TERRITORY</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KILGARIFF, Bernard</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KILGARIFF</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs. I refer to the interim report of the House of Representatives Standing Committee on Aboriginal Affairs titled <inline font-style="italic">Alcohol Problems of Aboriginals: Northern Territory Aspects</inline> and in particular to clauses 77 and 78 under the heading Adams Report&#39;. Clause 77 reads: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>In paragraph SI, the Committee emphasised its concern about the lack of action on the Adams Report. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">Clause 78 states: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>The Committee believes that closer liaison between the Legislative Assembly and the Department of the Northern </para>
            <para class="block">Territory is desirable in the preparation of drafting instructions. It is therefore recommended that there be greater cooperation and consultation between the Department of the Northern Territory and the Executive of the Northern Territory Legislative Assembly to improve the legislative process in respect of the Licensing Ordinance. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">What action is to be taken, bearing in mind that no government action has been taken since the Adams report was tabled in the Northern Territory Legislative Assembly in 1973? This lack of action has caused further deterioration in the Northern Territory, particularly as no amendments to the Licensing Ordinance to set up a liquor commission have been drafted despite the numerous requests by the Northern Territory Legislative Assembly. </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have taken note of the question asked by the honourable senator. I will refer it to the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs to see what action has been taken on the report that the honourable senator mentions and to see whether I can obtain any other information for him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING AND TELEVISION</title>
          <page.no>1115</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>4F4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BUTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question to the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications refers to 6 advertisements which appeared in the <inline font-style="italic">Government Gazette</inline> of 16 September relating to positions in the research and policy area of Australian broadcasting and television. As these 6 positions duplicate positions in the Australian Broadcasting Control Board, what is the Government&#39;s policy in relation to the duplication of positions already existing? Do the advertisements not pre-empt the finding of the broadcasting and television inquiry in which the Postal and Telecommunications Department as the conducting body has a vested interest? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Since I have not seen the advertisements I am not in a position either to evaluate them or to answer the remaining parts of the question. I will bring the question to the attention of the Minister in another place. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INTER-COUNTRY ADOPTIONS</title>
          <page.no>1115</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1115</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKD</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JESSOP, Donald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator JESSOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The Minister for Social Security may be aware of the confusion that exists with respect to the adoption of children from overseas. I refer particularly to an article that appeared in the <inline font-style="italic">Australian</inline> last week headed: &#39;Adoption battle: Children may be left homeless&#39;. The first paragraph reads: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Fears are growing that about 200 Asian children waiting to be adopted in Adelaide will stay officially homeless. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">Can the Minister explain the Government&#39;s responsibilities with respect to the adoption of these children. What steps can be taken to improve the existing procedures that seem to be causing concern? </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1116</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have been concerned about the articles that have been appearing with regard to Asian orphans- in some cases referring to the red tape barrier- and with other statements about the matter. It will be recalled that on 22 August I issued a statement on the procedures relating to inter-country adoptions. However, I will briefly outline the procedures. The Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs has the sole responsibility for determining the eligibility for admission of people for residence to Australia, including children who are admitted for the purpose of adoption. I am the Minister responsible for the administration of the Immigration (Guardianship of Children) Act. I am responsible for the welfare in Australia of those children who come within the provisions of the Act. Only after they arrive in. Australia and after they have been granted residence status do I become their guardian, and I remain their legal guardian until they reach the age of eighteen or are exempted from the provisions of the Act for other reasons including adoption, marriage or departure from the country. In practice I have delegated the function of guardianship to the competent State and Territory authorities, that is, the principal officer of the relevant welfare department of each of the States and Territories. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>It was stated earlier by me, and I think it is understood, that adoption is an extremely complex legal and social process which constitutionally is a matter which falls totally within the framework of State legislation and Territory ordinances, and applications for adoption are consequently matters for the State or Territory legal authorities to resolve. Naturally, I am concerned for the welfare of these children while I am their guardian but I would emphasise that adoptions of children from Vietnam have been granted in every State with the exception of Queensland where, I am informed, no cases have been presented. In an endeavour to facilitate and hasten adoption procedures, it will be recalled, I delegated further powers to my delegates on 26 June which enables them to take the adoption applications they receive as my delegates to finality without further reference to me except in cases of an unusual nature or in cases where malpractice is suspected. The question referred to matters in South Australia. It should be stated that there are matters currently before the courts in that State and I feel it would not be appropriate for me to comment further at this stage. I do want to assure the Senate that the adoption of Asian orphans who are in this country is a sensitive and complex matter but one which the Government in all cases wishes to facilitate in the interests of the children and their adoptive parents. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SHIPBUILDING INDUSTRY</title>
          <page.no>1116</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1116</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>EJ4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SIBRAA, Kerry</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SIBRAA</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Does the Minister representing the Minister for Defence agree with the statement made by the Deputy Premier of New South Wales on 10 October 1976 to the effect that a viable shipbuilding industry is vital to Australia&#39;s defence capabilities? If so, will the Government ensure the continued operation of this most necessary industry in the cities of Newcastle and Whyalla? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1116</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I think my colleague, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Cotton,</inline> has stated on numerous occasions what the Government is doing about its shipbuilding policy. As the  Deputy  Premier of New South Wales has all of a sudden discovered some defence need- I do not know how long after the original Industries Assistance Commission report came down- as a matter of courtesy I shall ask my colleague, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Killen,</inline> what he thinks of the honourable senator&#39;s question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PERFORMING ARTS</title>
          <page.no>1116</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1116</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTT</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DAVIDSON, Gordon</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DAVIDSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address my question to the Minister representing the Minister for the Capital Territory who is the Minister assisting the Prime Minister in relation to the arts. Naturally, I am speaking in my capacity as  Chairman  of the Senate Standing Committee on Education and the Arts and, as might be expected, I am referring to the Industries Assistance Commission report on the performing arts. I ask the Minister whether he has read the report? If so, when does he propose to be in a position to make a statement relating to the report? Does the Minister acknowledge that the report makes a savage attack on the quality and style of Australian life? If the report recommends the involvement of private patronage in the development of the performing arts, will the Government take early steps to encourage this patronage by generous incentives? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1116</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I represent in this place <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Staley,</inline> who is the Minister currently assisting the Prime Minister in relation to the arts. I think it best that I refer to <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Staley</inline> the several questions asked by the honourable senator. I shall bring a considered reply to the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COMMONWEALTH ROLLS ROYCE</title>
          <page.no>1117</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1117</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3A</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Administrative Services. Last Wednesday, 6 October, I asked a question about a Rolls Royce being freighted from Sydney to Melbourne for the Governor-General to use in attending the Victorian grand final football match. The Minister replied on the same day in these terms: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>When a booking was received recently for a Rolls Royce limousine the Department considered that one of the two held in Sydney ought to be sent down. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I asked a further question on the same matter on Thursday, 7 October, and the Minister replied in a similar vein as follows: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>A booking was made for a car for that date. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I ask the Minister whether he is aware that the Official Secretary of the Governor-General, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr David</inline> Smith, is reported in the Sydney <inline font-style="italic">Sun</inline> newspaper on the evening of Thursday, 7 October, in bold type, as follows: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>The Governor-General &#39;s official secretary, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr David</inline> Smith, said that there had been no official request for the Rolls to be transported from Sydney. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I now ask the Minister How does he reconcile his answers to me of 6 and 7 October with the quotation that I have just given, that is, the comment of the Official Secretary of the Governor-General which indicated that there had been no official request for a Rolls Royce to be transported from Sydney? </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1117</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I suppose one of my errors is that I do not read my own answers in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline> But I never intended to say that the Governor-General had asked for a Rolls Royce to be sent from Sydney to Melbourne. He asked for a vehicle for use in Melbourne. The one in Melbourne was not available as it had been damaged. Therefore, the Department decided to bring a vehicle down from Sydney. That was a departmental decision. It had nothing to do with <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Smith</inline> or the Governor-General. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>7V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Georges</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Why are you insisting that he should use a Rolls Royce? That is what you are saying. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-That is a decision, which the Department made, which I support totally and utterly. I imagine that the Governor-General would have been quite happy with a Volkswagen. As far as I am concerned, as long as there are Rolls Royce cars available in this country to the Government, they will be used to transport the Governor-General. The fact that Rent-a-crowd&#39; damages a vehicle in one city will not stop another vehicle from being brought from another city. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">Opposition senators interjecting-</inline>
          </para>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-Honourable senators opposite do not like my talking about &#39;Rentacrowd &#39;. The simple fact is that people who ought to have been able to behave themselves better had previously damaged the car that we had in Melbourne. I hope Opposition senators do not support that action. Their silence indicates that they do not. Therefore, when a request was received from Government House for a car to be made available in Melbourne as a Rolls Royce was not available, that request was met. Government House did not request any specific sort of vehicle. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>7V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Georges</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Well, why give him one? It is because you are a snob. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-Because I support totally and utterly the proposition that as we have a number of Rolls Royces in this country which are there for the conveyance of Governor-general and distinguished overseas visitors, they will continue to be used for that purpose. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K3A</name.id>
                <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
                <party>ALP</party>
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
                <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I wish to ask a supplementary question. If there is no official request for the use of a Rolls Royce, to ensure that such extravagance and waste of taxpayers&#39; money is not repeated in the future, will the Minister issue instructions to his departmental officers to the effect that, when a Rolls Royce is not available in a given area, a car from the VIP fleet must be used? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1117</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I have already told the honourable senator that the Rolls Royce was transported from Sydney to Melbourne free of charge. The only additional charge may have been a little bit of extra petrol used because the van had a loading and was not travelling to Melbourne empty. The vehicle will be returned in the same way. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator, before</inline> I get lectures from you about waste of taxpayers&#39; money, you tell  Rent-a-crowd &#39; to stop damaging our property. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PAYROLL TAX IN THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY</title>
          <page.no>1117</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1117</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPV</name.id>
              <electorate>ACT</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KNIGHT, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KNIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I refer to the increase in the recent Federal Budget in the exemption from payroll tax in the Australian Capital Territory from $20,800 to $41,600 designed specifically to bring the Australian Capital Territory into line with the States. Is the Minister representing the Treasurer aware that, in more recent State budgets, the basic level of exemption in New South Wales and Victoria has been raised to $48,000? Recognising the importance of this question, especially to smaller businesses in the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Territory, will the Minister give consideration to an increase in the level of exemption in the A.C.T. so that businesses in the Territory are not disadvantaged by a delay in the introduction of a similar exemption in the A.C.T.? </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1118</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I think this is a good point. Business in the Australian Capital Territory, I think, has been suffering quite a bit recently. The general level has not been as active as it has been in the past. There would be also some comparative disadvantage with cities like Goulburn and Queanbeyan which are operating under New South Wales laws and which these new concessions have affected. As soon as I possibly can I shall raise the matter with the Treasurer to see whether we can get some equality between the A.C.T. and the adjoining areas of New South Wales. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>CRASH HELMETS</title>
          <page.no>1118</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1118</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MULVIHILL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask a question of the Minister representing the Minister for Consumer Affairs. I remind the Minister that in an earlier question I asked about the apparently reprehensible conduct of some importers in foisting inferior crash helmets on the Australian community. I wonder whether the Minister can update his earlier reply? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1118</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-On 21 September <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Mulvihill</inline> asked me a question about this matter. I stated that further inquiries would be made into the circumstances of the import of this helmet. Those inquiries have now been completed. I advise the Senate that on the facts available it is not possible to determine the date of importation or, presumably, the importer. However, there is reason to believe that the helmet was imported before November 1975 when the customs import control was introduced. Apparently this brand of helmet has not been on the Australian market for some time. The safety standard of the brand of helmet in question is regarded highly by people in the motorcycle trade. The model worn by the victim bore a mark signifying that it met American safety standards comparable to the present Australian standards. Opinion was expressed that the victim&#39;s death may have been caused by the nature of the accident, and possibly would have occurred irrespective of the type of helmet that he was wearing. These views are supported by <inline font-weight="bold">Dr Henderson</inline> of the Traffic Accident Research Unit of the New South Wales Department of Motor Transport and by the New South Wales Minister for Consumer Affairs. In the circumstances it is reasonable to conclude that the helmet worn by the victim was not substandard. It seems that whatever helmet the victim might have been wearing it would not have afforded the protection needed in the type of accident that occurred. I assure the Senate, however, that the Bureau of Customs takes great pains to ensure that no sub-standard motorcyclist helmets are imported into Australia. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>POLITICAL PARTIES: CAMPAIGN FUNDS</title>
          <page.no>1118</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1118</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>EF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHANEY, Fred</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CHANEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Has the Minister for Administrative Services studied the legislation on the disclosure of campaign contributions to political parties which was introduced into the Parliament by the previous Government? Can he say whether the $ 100 a plate dinner being held at the Parmelia Hotel in Perth by the Australian Labor Party to raise campaign funds would have been within the terms of the Labor legislation? Would that legislation have required a disclosure of the names of guests at the dinner and, more importantly, whether any of the $100 payments came from trade union funds paid by hard working trade unionists to keep their leaders in the style to which they are becoming accustomed? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1118</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Most of the legislation of the previous Government on electoral matters has passed from me like a bad dream. I make this passing observation: I am delighted that the Australian Labor Party in Western Australia is confirming that in that State, under both the Fraser Government and the Court Government, things are sufficiently prosperous for Labor supporters to be prepared to pay $100 a head for dinner at perhaps Australia&#39;s most distinguished hotel. I am delighted to have proof of that matter. I am interested to discover that the Australian Labor Party had to invite the Premier of New South Wales to drum up enough interest in the presentation. Evidently the State parliamentary leader would not get $1 a head at Harry&#39;s Cafe de Wheels. That I can well understand. I note also that the ALP did not bother to invite the Federal parliamentary leader. I do not know whether he would rate $1 or 50c at Bernie &#39;s &#171;n Mounts Bay Road. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1118</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>EF4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CHANEY, Fred</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Chaney</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It depends whether you were eating him or eating with him. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1118</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I do not know about that. I am delighted that the Labor Party and its supporters are so prosperous that they can pay $ 100 a head to have dinner among themselves. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PRIME MINISTER&#39;S VISIT TO INDONESIA</title>
          <page.no>1119</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question, which is directed to the Minister representing the Prime Minister, relates to the Prime Minister&#39;s recent visit to Indonesia. Can the Minister explain why a joint communique was not issued following discussions between the Australian Prime Minister and the  President  of Indonesia, in accordance with normal procedures after discussions between heads of government? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I am interested in the honourable senator&#39;s question because I have in my hands- I thought it was a public document- a 6!&#163;-page 21-paragraph communique issued jointly by the Prime Minister and the  President  of Indonesia. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1119</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTA</name.id>
                <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                <party>ALP</party>
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have not seen a copy of it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1119</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I am sorry. I understand that it was issued in Jakarta prior to the Prime Minister leaving. I will send the honourable senator a copy. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SMALL BUSINESS UNIT</title>
          <page.no>1119</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9I4</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MESSNER, Tony</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MESSNER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question is addressed to the Minister for Industry and Commerce. I refer to the recent announcement by the Dunstan Government that a small business unit will soon be formed in South Australia. Will the operation of this unit cut across or will it complement the activities of the office of the National Small Business Bureau in Adelaide? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-They will work in association with each other. One of the first acts in which I became involved when I took over my Department was a discussion between State Ministers and myself in Hobart in January. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Dunstan</inline> was there representing his State as Minister for Industry and Development. The whole small business program was talked about. We agreed we would work together, that we would in fact do counterpart things. I imagine that the 2 organisations will work in close conjunction. The officials are doing it almost daily. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN POSTAL COMMISSION</title>
          <page.no>1119</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1Y</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BISHOP, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BISHOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question to the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications concerns reports which have reached the postal unions that one of Australia&#39;s largest transport operators is endeavouring to obtain a share of the Australian Postal Commission&#39;s mail and parcels business. Of course he will recall that earlier this year there was a report that the courier service might be going over to private interests, a report which was dispelled by the Minister. Is he able to give any information about the latest report? Is any offer such as that I have mentioned presently being considered by the Commission or the Government? If there is not, will he ask the Minister for Post and Telecommunications to give a quick denial so that the staff of the Postal Commission can be reassured that the province they have is to be preserved? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am informed that rumours to the effect that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bishop</inline> outlined have been circulating. I am advised that there is no basis of truth at all in those rumours. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>UNEMPLOYMENT AND THE WORK ETHIC</title>
          <page.no>1119</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COLSTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Did the Minister for Science, when opening the new Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation Standards Laboratory on 8 October, claim that unemployment benefits were helping to erode the work ethic, as he was quoted as saying in the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Age</inline> of 9 October 1976? Can the Minister&#39;s statement be taken to mean that he is opposed to the payment of unemployment benefit in Australia in all cases? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I was correctly reported in the news media as having said there was some challenge to dole payments and that I believed that in some instances the payment of the dole was creating some harm in the community. My comment was related mainly to the fact that payment for no work was coming to be regarded basically as a right. In a different situation altogether is a person who may be out of work through circumstances beyond his own control. I would agree completely that in all such instances the unemployment benefit should be available to those people. I was making the point that the payment of the dole is becoming something which is accepted by people who do not want to work. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>UNITED STATES BEEF QUOTAS</title>
          <page.no>1119</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1119</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYA</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">O&#39;BYRNE, Justin</name>
              <name role="display">Senator O&#39;BYRNE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Overseas Trade and the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry. It refers to a subject similar to that raised by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Gietzelt</inline> earlier in question time. In view of the serious decision of the  President  of the United States of America to impose further quotas on Australian beef to the extent of 8 million lb on our previously determined quota, will the Minister obtain the names of those exporters who shipped excessive and unauthorised quantities of Australian beef to the United States through Puerto Rico and Canada and so jeopardised the quotas available to orthodox exporters? Is there not some way that these people, who showed shortsightedness and acted regardless of its effect on the reputation of Australians as fair traders, can be made to forgo their future quotas for engaging in such damaging practices? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My information is that the situation in the area of voluntary restraint on quantity was being held by the Australian exporters in total. Various stories have been floating around that somebody has done the wrong thing through Puerto Rico or something like that. I have no proof that this has happened or that this is the case. It may well be like some other newspaper rumours- founded on no fact at all. But the honourable senator is entitled to have me ask the responsible Minister and, I am sure <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Georges</inline> will understand, I may even need to do that. I shall do so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PRIME MINISTER&#39;S VISIT TO INDONESIAN FARM</title>
          <page.no>1120</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Health. The Minister is no doubt aware of the great publicity given in the media and in particular in the film shots on television news services to the Prime Minister&#39;s visit in recent days to a cattle property in Indonesia. In view of the fact that a large number of Australian journalists and others accompanied the Prime Minister to this property, can the Minister assure the Senate that every possible precaution was taken to prevent the introduction into Australia of any exotic disease that could bring disaster to Australian primary industries? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that precautions were taken at the time of the visit, that shoes were encased in plastic and that fumigation was undertaken. I will refer the question to the Minister for Health to see whether there is further detail which I can provide for the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>UNEMPLOYMENT IN DROUGHT AREAS</title>
          <page.no>1120</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WALSH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Unemployment and Industrial Relations. Is he able to provide any information on the Government&#39;s response to a proposal put forward by the Koorda Shire Council which was originally directed to the Minister for Social Security- she has since informed me that she has referred it to the responsible Minister- for a Regional Employment Development type scheme for drought affected areas of Western Australia? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The question was directed to a Minister who does not exist and I do not propose to answer it. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DISTINGUISHED VISITORS</title>
        <page.no>1120</page.no>
        <type>distinguished visitors</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1120</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-I draw to the attention of honourable senators the presence in the gallery of a delegation from the Federal Assembly of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, led by Vice-President Rudi Kolac. On behalf of honourable senators I welcome them to our Parliament and trust that their visit to our country will prove both interesting and rewarding. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Honourable senators- Hear, hear! </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PERSONAL EXPLANATION</title>
        <page.no>1120</page.no>
        <type>personal explanation</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1120</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3A</name.id>
            <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
            <party>ALP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I seek leave to make a statement on a matter of misrepresentation by the Sydney based newspaper the <inline font-style="italic">Sun</inline> last Thursday evening. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1120</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1120</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3A</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have given serious consideration to the use of standing order 427 but on reflection I have decided to rely on the statement of correction which I propose to make and which will be recorded in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline> The article to which I refer appears on page 2 of the <inline font-style="italic">Sun</inline> dated 7 October 1976. It is entitled- under a large heading- &#39;Bloody Outrageous. Kerr&#39;s Car Bill Attacked&#39;. It reads: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <quote>
          <para>Quite frankly, I believe it was a bloody outrageous extravagance&#39;. </para>
          <para>That is how <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bill</inline> Brown (ALP, Victoria) today described the road freighting of a Rolls-Royce from Sydney to Melbourne for the Governor-General, <inline font-weight="bold">Sir John</inline> Kerr. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">That common, coarse word &#39;bloody&#39;, that crude descriptive word, is not part of my vocabulary. For me to be reported as using such a crudity offends my Christian upbringing and linguistic sensitivity. I categorically repudiate the use of that word by the reporter as being attributable to me and I trust that my rightful indignation will be respected in the future. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DAIRY ADJUSTMENT</title>
        <page.no>1120</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1120</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JQR</name.id>
            <electorate>New South Wales Minister for Industry and Commerce</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Pursuant to section 5 of the Dairy Adjustment Act 1974 I present agreements between the Commonwealth of Australia and the States of Victoria and Wester Australia in relation to dairy adjustment programs provided for in that Act. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>COMMONWEALTH BUREAU OF ROADS REPORT</title>
        <page.no>1121</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1121</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>2U4</name.id>
            <electorate>New South Wales Minister for Education</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
            <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators I present a report by the Commonwealth Bureau of Roads entitled <inline font-style="italic">Standards for Construction and Maintenance of National Highways.</inline></para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1121</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KPG</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEEFFE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-by leave- I move: </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate take note of the paper. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">I seek leave to continue my remarks at a later date. </para>
        <para>Leave granted; debate adjourned. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>FAWNMAC GROUP</title>
        <page.no>1121</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1121</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>C7D</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators I present the annual report and financial accounts of the Fawnmac Group for the year ended 30 June 1976. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1121</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>9V4</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GRIMES</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-by leave- I move: </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate take note of the paper. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">I seek leave to continue my remarks at a later date. </para>
        <para>Leave granted; debate adjourned. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>COMMONWEALTH SCIENTIFIC AND INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH ORGANISATION</title>
        <page.no>1121</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>1121</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KAS</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NCP/NP</party>
            <role>Minister for Science</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Pursuant to section 30 of the Science and Industry Research Act 1949 I present the annual report of the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation for the year ended 30 June 1976. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>LEAVE OF ABSENCE</title>
        <page.no>1121</page.no>
        <type>leave of absence</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers)-</inline> by leave agreed to: </para>
      <quote>
        <para class="block">That <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Greenwood</inline> be granted leave of absence for 2 months on account of ill health. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADVISORY COUNCIL FOR INTER-GOVERNMENT RELATIONS BILL 1976</title>
        <page.no>1121</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Carrick)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>1121</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1121</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate>New South Wales Minister for Education</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>This Bill provides for the establishment of an Advisory Council for Inter-government Relations. The formation of the Advisory Council is a further step in the implementation of our program of reform to improve the functioning of Australia&#39;s political institutions. Honourable senators will by now be familiar with the main thrust of that program. It is designed to strengthen the Federal system by giving the States and local government an assured source of revenue; by matching revenue to responsibilities and by a more appropriate allocation of functions among governments. </para>
          <para>The Advisory Council gives life to the Government &#39;s commitment as outlined in our federalism policy statement of September 1975. The Council should be looked at in the context of our overall federalism reforms. These reforms attempt to restore a proper balance between responsibilities and finances in Australia. The work of the Council will supplement other reforms, such as our tax sharing proposals which will be the subject of separate legislation soon to be introduced into Parliament. The Advisory Council is intended to bring together representatives of the Commonwealth, State and local governments and private citizens to review and consider matters relating to the improvement of co-operation between different spheres of government. The Council will operate under the Premiers Conference. By reference from the Premiers Conference, the Advisory Council will examine problems which emerge between the various spheres of government. Under the Premiers Conference the Council will give continuing attention to the range of intergovernmental problems in the Federal, State and local government spheres. It will be a most important source of advice on the most desirable allocation of governmental functions, responsibilities and revenues. </para>
          <para>The Bill provides for a Council of 22 members: Five representatives of the Commonwealth; 3 Government members and 2 Opposition members; 6 State representatives- one from each State Parliament; 6 local government representatives; and 5 citizens representatives. Three Commonwealth Government representatives will be nominated by the Prime Minister; two will be nominated by the Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives. So far as the local government membership is concerned, the States agreed to 3 local government representatives. We regret having to increase that number without the prior agreement of the States but we have come to the conclusion that 6 representatives of local government are necessary for the effective operation of the Council and for the reasonable representation of local government. </para>
          <para>So far as is practicable, the 6 local government members should be persons associated with local government in different States. Citizen representatives to the Council will be selected by the Commonwealth Government in consultation with the States. The  Chairman  of the Council will be one of the S citizen members. Members will normally have a 3-year term. Provision is also made in the Bill for the appointment of  deputy  members, and attendance by one observer from each of the Northern Territory and the Australian Capital Territory assemblies. </para>
          <para>The body will be distinctly bipartisan and the Government wishes to ensure that its independence is preserved. The Council is clearly not dominated by numbers of Commonwealth representatives. The Council will fulfil its function best if its members approach their tasks with a broad perspective, considering Australian Government as a whole system. The body which this Bill proposes to establish has been modelled on the United States Advisory Commission on Inter-governmental Relations. The United States Advisory Commission is a 17-year-old bipartisan body in which representatives of national, State and local governments and private citizens study the operations of the federal system in the United States. The American Commission conducts studies and investigations of specific intergovernmental conflict points and drafts proposed legislation and administrative orders to carry out its recommendations. The Commission is a successful and highly respected body which has done much to improve the American Federation. It is our intention that the Australian counterpart also establish itself as an independent and highly respected body. </para>
          <para>The Bill to establish the Council provides that the Premiers Conference, or a majority of governments participating, may request the Council to institute inquiries. Local governments, through their State Premiers, will be able to have matters brought to the Premiers Conference for reference to the Council for examination and report. This Bill makes provision for the Advisory Council to furnish reports of its inquiries and investigations to the Prime Minister, to the Premier of each participating State and to the Australian Council of Local Government Associations. The Advisory Council is also required to make an annual report on its activities. This report will be made public by being laid before both Houses of this Parliament within 15 sitting days after the Prime Minister has received a copy. </para>
          <para>This Bill is the result of a great deal of consultation and thought. All State Premiers, as well as the Australian Council of Local Government Associations, have had an opportunity to comment on the proposed Council which has been modified in the light of their comments. The charter of the Advisory Council was approved at the April Premiers Conference. And before that details of the Council were discussed at a meeting with State Ministers. The costs of the Council will be shared by agreement among the 3 spheres of government. At present it is intended that the Commonwealth and the States each meet 45 per cent of the Council&#39;s cost, the remaining 10 per cent being contributed by local government. Since this arrangement may be subject to change or re-negotiation as the Council develops, it has not been written into the Bill. </para>
          <para>Honourable senators will also note that the Bill contains no reference to staffing. This is to ensure maximum flexibility and the opportunity for participation by officers drawn from all spheres of government. A secretariat to service the Council will be based in Hobart. The staff will be small in number but of a calibre which will assist the Council to achieve the status and prestige which we envisage for it. Where necessary, it is hoped that other people and institutions can be used to research proposals. While the initial meetings will be in Hobart, when the Council is well established it is expected that it will feel free to meet in other centres around Australia at its own wish. </para>
          <para>An important role of the Council will be to promote discussion and disseminate ideas to reach a wide audience and to present to that audience an independent view on possible solutions to problems of inter-government relations. Such a role should do much to dispel the notion, so prevalent in recent years, that all wisdom resides at the centre. </para>
          <para>The Council possesses only advisory powers. The Council does not exist to pre-empt the decisions of governments. It exists to provide an effective vehicle to encourage public debate on the practical resolution of problems facing governments in Australia. It exists to make governments fully aware of the options which  Face  them. The governments concerned will be solely responsible for the decisions they make. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Douglas</inline> McClelland) adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>1123</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Senate Estimates Committees</title>
          <page.no>1123</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1123</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate>Western AustraliaLeader of the Government in the Senate</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the sitting of the Senate be suspended until 10.15 p.m. or such time as the  President  may take the chair to enable Estimates Committees De and r to meet </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">Estimates Committee D will meet in the Senate chamber. Estimates Committee E will meet in Senate committee room No. 1 and Estimates Committee F will meet in Senate committee room No. 5. </para>
          <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
          <para class="block">Sitting suspended from  3.52  to  10.15  p.m. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AIR FORCE AMENDMENT BILL 1976</title>
        <page.no>1123</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>1123</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1123</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate>Western AustraliaMinister for Administrative Services</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I ask for leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1123</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows-</inline>
          </para>
          <para>On 27 May the Senate was informed of the Government&#39;s decision to re-introduce schemes for the training of Army, Navy and Air cadets. Details were given of a new scheme for each Service, but with a greater degree of commonality among the 3 schemes. In accordance with the Government&#39;s decision, the new schemes were brought into operation with effect from the beginning of October. It was recognised when the Government made its decision that certain legislative action would be required. With regard to Army cadets, section 35 of the Defence Force Reorganization Act 1975, which amended the governing provisions of the Defence Act 1903, was brought into force on 24 September 1976. Interim regulations have been made to enable the Army Cadets to operate. There is a separate question whether the Air Force Act 1923 provides adequate authority to make appropriate regulations for the new Air Training Corps. </para>
          <para>Part V of the Defence Act 1 903 confers special powers to make regulations regarding Army cadets, and Part V of the Naval Defence Act 1910 contains corresponding provisions regarding Navy cadets. There is no corresponding provision in the Air Force Act. In order to put the matter beyond doubt, this Bill inserts similar provisions in the Air Force Act. The Bill adds a new section 8 to the Air Force Act, providing for the establishment of the Air Training Corps and dealing in general terms with its organisation. Provision is made for matters of detail, such as conditions of service of members of the Air Training Corps, to be prescribed in regulations. The Bill also makes provision to cover the transition from the body of cadets established under the Air Force Regulations to the new body established by the Act. The former scheme has continued to have a limited operation, and it is necessary to preserve the position of cadets in that scheme. </para>
          <para>Following passage of the Bill, comprehensive regulations will be made covering the 3 cadet schemes. In the interim period, existing legislation provides an adequate basis for the new schemes. I remind the Senate that the Government has adopted a common aim for the 3 cadet organisations as follows: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>The common aim of the Australian Services &#39; cadet scheme is, by predominantly voluntary effort, better to equip young people for community life by fostering initiative, leadership, discipline and loyalty through training programs also designed to stimulate an interest in a particular arm of the Defence Force. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">The Air Force Amendment Bill is part of the arrangements for the continuing operation and development of the cadet schemes towards this common aim. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wriedt)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIA COUNCIL AMENDMENT BILL 1976</title>
        <page.no>1123</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>1123</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1123</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role>Minister for Science</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I ask for leave to incorporate the second reading speech in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1124</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows-</inline>
          </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline>the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Malcolm Fraser)</inline> foreshadowed amendments to the Australia Council Act in his Ministerial statement on the arts in the House of Representatives on 3 June 1976. The amendments take into account the Government&#39;s stated policies on the arts. They are designed to improve the organisation of the Council, and to correct problems and deficiencies identified by the Council itself as a result of an internal review commissioned from the management consultants firm of Mckinney and Co. They also take account of the recommendations of the Administrative Review Committee. </para>
          <para>It is proposed to amend the Act by adding as a function of the Council the provision that it should be the Government&#39;s advisory agency on all matters falling within the areas of its responsibilities. Previously it was not charged with this specific responsibility. The Council will assume responsibility for and administer the public lending right scheme, previously under the control of the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet, as part of the Government&#39;s aim of rationalising governmental functions. </para>
          <para>Council control of the activities of the boards is to be increased. In the past the problem has been that the Council and its executive have carried responsibility for the organisation but have had insufficient authority to control its operations. While the Council will still continue to carry its assistance to different art forms through specialist boards, delegation of powers and functions by the Council to boards will no longer be mandatory. The Council may also lay down rules and guidelines for the boards to follow in the exercise of delegated functions and powers. </para>
          <para>To make the organisation more streamlined and manageable, the Council is to be reduced in size from a range of eighteen to twenty-four to a range of fifteen to nineteen. Public Service members are to be reduced from three to two. Membership of the boards is to be reduced from the present range of seven to ten to a range of five to seven, plus chairman, excepting the Aboriginal Arts Board which is to be reduced from the present range of nine to fourteen to a range of seven to nine plus chairman. In future, additional co-option of members will not be possible. </para>
          <para>With a view to stabilising the organisation and taking advantage of experience, the terms of appointment for Council and board members will be extended from 3 to 4 years, with provision for renewal for a further term of 2 years. These extensions should compensate for the reduction in size of the Council and boards and allow for the advantages of continuity of service. However, in order to prevent viewpoints from becoming entrenched it is proposed that, if terms of appointment are renewed for 2 years, further reappointment will not be considered until 2 more years have expired. </para>
          <para>Two new positions will be created. One will provide for a  deputy chairman  of the Council- a part-time office- to assist the  chairman  and generally facilitate the Council&#39;s operation. The second will provide for a general manager-a ultimo office- who will be the chief executive officer of the Council. The position of general manager will be a statutory office with a 7 year term and the office holder will be an ex-officio member of the Council. It is our hope that these amendments will further facilitate the promotion of the arts in Australia. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wriedt)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIAN FILM COMMISSION AMENDMENT BILL 1976</title>
        <page.no>1124</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>1124</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1124</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role>Minister for Science</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <motion>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </motion>
          <para class="block">I ask for leave to incorporate the second reading speech in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1124</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows-</inline>
          </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline>the purpose of the Bill is to give effect to decisions of the Government which the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Malcolm Fraser)</inline> outlined in his ministerial statement in the House of Representatives on 3 June last. In that statement, it was explained that the Australian Film Commission was to assume responsibility for the functions and powers of the Film, Radio and </para>
          <para class="block">Television Board of the Australia Council, and for the activities and assets of the Audio- Visual Branch of the Postal and Telecommunications Department. The Commission was also to be empowered to provide assistance for independent radio and audio-visual production, as it has in the past for film and television. </para>
          <para>The establishment of these new powers and functions for the Commission requires adjustment to the Australian Film Commission Act 1975 to expand the area of reference covered by the legislation. It has been found desirable to adopt a form of words which will include not only film, television, radio and audio-visual activities, but also other forms of presentation of images and sounds that may from time to time emerge from developing technology in the media. Allowance is to be made for the fact that some programs in television and radio are not recorded, but are broadcast live and for the possibility that cinema audiences of the future may be watching pictures of electronic or other origin, rather than films as we know them today. </para>
          <para>The opportunity has also been taken in this Bill to revise the legislation in accordance with recent drafting practice, and take account of certain administrative problems arising from the wording of the current Act. I should add that the Australia Council Act 1975 will retain a reference to film so the Council may continue to engage in film activity provided this is ancillary and does not impinge upon the Commission&#39;s responsibilities in this field. </para>
          <para>The Government accepts the need for assistance to experimental and developmental film, radio and television. The various forms of support for the study and appreciation of such productions as art forms are also accepted and specifically allowed for in these amendments. I want to make it plain that the Government does not intend that these areas of assistance should be neglected. Overall funding levels comparable with previous appropriations will be maintained, subject only to the restraints that have been applied in all areas of Government expenditure. </para>
          <para>What is different here is that the development of creative innovation in the various media will work side by side with the development of viable production industries, with one body- the Australian Film Commission- responsible for both. It is evident from recent developments, for example, <inline font-style="italic">Picnic at Hanging Rock,</inline> that artistic and commercial success are not incompatible. Rather, they complement each other and form part of a continuum. </para>
          <para>Today&#39;s art film can be tomorrow&#39;s box office attraction, and the very fact that so many of today&#39;s successful films have been generated out of experimental and developmental programs, if anything, demonstrates the need to ensure continuous contact is kept between artistic developments and the developments of the marketplace. We are dealing with an art form that has proved to be of interest to millions of people throughout the world. It is shortsighted, to say the least, to suggest that, when assistance is provided, it must come from one of 2 boxes- one labelled &#39;art* the other &#39;commerce&#39;. </para>
          <para>The task of the Film Commission with its new responsibilities will be a challenging one, but it is not really a task of reconciling the irreconcilable. It is a task of ensuring that the benefits derived from work at one end of the scale can flow through to the other, and vice versa. In the field of communication, the tyro has much to learn from the innovator. On the other hand, the artist involved in communication can derive only benefit from the exposure of his work to as wide an audience as is possible. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wriedt)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIAN FILM AND TELEVISION SCHOOL AMENDMENT BILL 1976</title>
        <page.no>1125</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>1125</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1125</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role>Minister for Science</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </quote>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1125</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KAS</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1125</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows-</inline>
          </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline>on 3 June last, the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Malcolm Fraser)</inline> informed the House of Representatives by way of a <inline font-style="italic">ministerial</inline> statement, of the Government&#39;s policy on the future of its arts organisations and outlined some proposed changes in those organisations. Among them was the decision that the Film and Television School will assume responsibility for training in radio, and audio-visual communications both of these areas, as the Prime Minister mentioned at the time, having been previously neglected. The purpose of this Bill is to implement those changes as far as the Film and Television School is concerned. These new functions should complement existing operations in both the full-time and open programs conducted by the school and it is expected that they will begin with the 1978 academic year. </para>
          <para>It is also anticipated that these new arrangements for radio and audio-visual training will be introduced with the maximum of economy consistent with professional standards. I might add that the Prime Minister asked the school to investigate jointly with the Australian Film Commission the feasibility of establishing permanent school facilities at the commission&#39;s Lindfield studio complex and to report on this study by the end of 1976. </para>
          <para>It is becoming ever more difficult and artificial to put film, television and radio into separate and isolated compartments, for a number of reasons. Technology, for instance, is bringing all three media closer together with each using the techniques and technologies of the other. The social impact of the media, likewise, cannot readily be compartmentalised. The people who work in film, television and radio have related responsibilities and share many skills. As the body responsible for training these people, the Film and Television School should logically concern itself with radio and audio-visual techniques. The likelihood is that all four disciplines will benefit from simultaneous on-the-spot training. </para>
          <para>The economic factor is also important. The Government has a responsibility to young people learning the film and broadcasting crafts to ensure for them at the end of their training the best possible chance and the widest possible choice of productive, worthwhile and fulfilling employment. For people trained in radio as well as in film and television, that choice would clearly be greater. Here too the Prime Minister asked the school to provide a full-scale assessment of actual employment opportunities which may be open to graduates in the foreseeable future. This is especially true now when radio is undergoing dramatic technological, creative and social expansion. Recent years have seen the introduction of an FM radio service with opportunities for stereo broadcasting not only of music but of drama and documentaries. There has been simultaneously a new awareness of the potential role of radio in education and community affairs. </para>
          <para class="block">The experiments that have so far taken place in these areas represent only a beginning. </para>
          <para>The Film and Television School was established with dual responsibilities, both to the film and broadcasting industry and to education. It is proper therefore that its charter should include audio-visual communications in the light of increasing awareness of the importance of sounds and images, either alone or in combination in the process of education. During the passage of the Bill through the House of Representatives, the name of the school was amended by the addition of &#39;Australian&#39;, to give sense to its international connections and to reflect what has become common practice. With this change I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wriedt)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>1126</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Immigration -Aboriginal Affairs</title>
          <page.no>1126</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Guilfoyle)</inline> proposed: That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1126</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MULVIHILL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I rise on behalf of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Frank</inline> Salerno, a reputable businessman in the central western suburbs of Sydney. He expressed to me as late as last night certain serious disquiet about the methods followed by the Australian Embassy or its immigration officers in Rome in the case of an Italian tourist, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Andrea</inline> Piroso, in the town of Bad ola to, in the province of Catanzaro. I believe that a cable to Rome tomorrow will accelerate a decision in this matter. I previously raised a similar matter concerning Belgrade. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Salerno</inline> is concerned about a tourist applicant from a town in Italy who happens to be an alderman. All of us in public life have our enemies. This man believes he has substantial enemies in his town. In asking for this tourist application to be reexamined I would also like to know whether to rely on Italian security for an assessment of a person as a tourist and what sort of other tittle tattle from his home town we evaluate. I do not think there is much more to say on the matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Some of the criticism I voiced in respect of hold-ups in Belgrade was vindicated. According to the Yugoslav Press, we seem to be getting a reasonable processing now. At least one honourable senator is nodding his head. The criticism now emanates from Italy. I simply convey it to the Minister for Social Security <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Guilfoyle),</inline> who represents the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr MacKellar).</inline> I will give her a letter which will not be too helpful because, while it has a name in English, I think it emanates from our consulate in Messina and is written in Italian. But with the file number it contains we should be able to get somewhere. The defence rests accordingly. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1127</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>5V4</name.id>
              <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I rise in the adjournment debate once again to bring to the attention of the Senate the situation which has existed over a period of some years now in Western Australia in Aboriginal housing. Honourable senators will remember that I spoke on this subject in the Budget debate some weeks ago. I used the entire half an hour available to me on a broadcast day to express my concern about the then slashing of Aboriginal programs. Whilst there has been a further injection of some $25m for Aboriginal housing and welfare programs by this Government, my concern has not changed. My apprehensions will be allayed only when I see the results of the money actually being spent. Honourable senators would agree that it is sometimes a very simple matter for federal governments to say they will allocate $25m, or any other amount of money for that matter. The test, of course, is when the money is spent and how it is spent. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>In the Budget debate I produced figures to show that $4.5m that had been appropriated by the Federal Government had been given to Western Australia for Aboriginal housing but had not been spent by the State. I said at the time that it had not been spent by the State Housing Commission. I expressed some amazement that at the time when the building and construction industry was suffering severe depression and when the building industry had more supply than demand, a State that makes up a third of the entire nation in land mass did not use this money and it was ultimately returned to the Treasury when the present Government took office. The point I am making is that $4. 5 m would have gone a long way towards providing housing for some Aborigines who are deserving of State Housing Commission assistance in Western Australia. But one cannot blame entirely the State Housing Commission because we are all aware that State housing commissions operate under the direction of State Premiers and State Ministers for Housing. </para>
          <para>I find it extremely interesting that the number of housing units to be built by the State Housing Commission for Aborigines following the August Budget is only 100. 1 am surprised also that last week after this further injection of $25m, the number of houses to be built for Aborigines in Western Australia is still only 100. There are 900 Aboriginal applications with the State Housing Commission in Western Australia. One has to wonder how genuine governments are when figures like that do not change with the injection of a further $2 5 m specifically for Aboriginal housing and welfare programs. </para>
          <para>My concern is for the people- the urban fringe dwellers, as some of them choose to call themselves who are forced by circumstance to live under bridges, under trees and behind shelter of any sort they can get. I wish to quote the <inline font-style="italic">West Australian</inline> newspaper. It could not be considered to be the most progressive newspaper in Australia but it and its evening partner are the only two daily newspapers in Western Australia. One has to be guided to a certain extent by what they allow the public to know. On Thursday, 7 October, under the heading &#39;Welcome boost&#39; it referred to the $25m boost which the Federal Government had given to Aboriginal advancement programs and stated: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>The Aboriginal Affairs Department&#39;s allocation is still $8m less than the $ 1 86m it received last year. When inflation is taken into account it is probably $30m (or almost 20 per cent) short of the 1 975-76 level of spending. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">It went on: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>But, even allowing for the likelihood of getting greater value for every dollar, the department will be hard put to make much impact on the four main problems of Aborigines- housing, health, education and employment. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">So perhaps I could say that my concern is well founded. We have to be concerned that in Western Australia the Premier and his Minister for Housing are responsible for making sure that the money given by the Federal Government actually gets through to the people who need it most. In Western Australia, as honourable senators would be aware, the Premier is <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Charles</inline> Court- the redoubtable <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Charles</inline> Court- who has never shirked what he sees as his responsibility to keep the disadvantaged further disadvantaged when the opportunity presents itself. As honourable senators will remember, he did not shirk this responsibility some months ago. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1127</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Order! <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Coleman,</inline> you must not reflect on another member of Parliament. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1127</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- In deference to you, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline> I withdraw that remark; but I will make members of this chamber aware that the Premier of Western Australia had a confrontation with parents of the profoundly mentally retarded children of the Tres ill ian Hostel earlier this year. They could only be considered as disadvantaged people, as the Aborigines must be considered disadvantaged people. In the Tres ill ian Hostel affair he used threats and was prepared even to use force if necessary to get his own way. He threatened the parents of the profoundly mentally retarded children that the children would be returned to their own homes unless the parents agreed to their being transferred to another hostel- a hostel which I might tell members of this chamber was entirely unsuitable for the children, who had already spent some time in a congenial atmosphere at Tres ill ian. The Forrestfield Hostel is almost totally inaccessible by public transport, and for those parents who were not fortunate enough to have their own transport it meant that their visits could be limited to perhaps one in each 3 months. There were no paths for wheelchairs. This was an advantage at Tres ill ian which the children had found to their liking. They were able to be wheeled out on to front lawns and taken for outings by children from various colleges in the neighbourhood. The only rejection from the general community that I know of was a confrontation with a near neighbour in the Nedlands electorate who considered them in some way unclean. Perhaps the only reason why <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Charles</inline> Court wanted them to move from Tres ill ian was that the hostel is in his own electorate. I think that when he decides to call the next State election the electors of Nedlands will remember his confrontation. They will remind him that they were not prepared to accept the move of their children from Tres ill ian, the parents and friends of Tres ill ian were not prepared to accept it, and doctors and specialists in the field who were actually treating these children were not prepared to accept it. I think that the people will also recall that the threat of force was used by the Premier against already disadvantaged people. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1128</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- You will recall it to them. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1128</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have no doubt that they will not need me to recall it to their minds. It is quite clear in their minds what the Premier of Western Australia was prepared to do at that time. I think it is quite clear in their own minds what the Premier of Western Australia is not prepared to do as far as Aboriginals are concerned. I doubt very much whether he would have any qualms about a confrontation with another disadvantaged group in our community. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>In the Budget debate I spoke about the problems of homeless people and I want to remind honourable senators on both sides of what I said then. A rather ridiculous &#39;Catch 22 &#39; situation was reported in the <inline font-style="italic">Daily News</inline> on Wednesday, 1 1 August. In that article reference was made to the Campaign Against Racial Exploitation. A member of that organisation explained that bulldozing was being carried out in various camping spots around the metropolitan area of Perth and the police were gradually moving Aborigines on. The police would say to the Aborigines as they are still doing now: &#39;Yes, you can move down further into East Perth and we will not move you until next week&#39;. This situation is, I think, abhorrent to the Australian way of life. The article refers to a mother of 6 children.  Her  children are in institutions because she has no home for them. The State Housing Commission will not let her have a home unless she can show that she has the children with her, and the Department for Community Welfare will not let her children go until she can show that she has a home. I think that all honourable senators would agree that that is a most ridiculous situation. How can a woman possibly care for her own children in a home atmosphere if the State Housing Commission refuses to give her a home unless she has the children with her and the Department for Community Welfare will not let her children go from State institutions until she can prove that she has a home? </para>
          <para>The urban fringe dwellers- the Swanee Noon gars Association, as they originally called themselves asked the State Government to provide them with a caravan park facility on a block of land at Lockridge. I intend to devote the rest of my speech tonight to this subject. On 12 August the <inline font-style="italic">West Australian</inline> reported as follows: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>The State Government is to be asked to provide caravan park facilities for up to 20 unhorsed Aboriginal families at a camp in the bush at Lockridge. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I have received a letter from the Shire of Swan. In this chamber as in the other place we tend to devote a great deal of our time to expressing concern about the importance of the 3 tiers of government. Local government is the third tier and to me it is a most important one. This shire council has written to members and Ministers of the Federal Parliament in this tone: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>Abori gin al Camp Lots 64, 65, 66 and 67 Saunders Street, Henley Park, West Swan. The abovementioned land, where a number of At iginal people have established a camp, is within the boundaries of the Shire of Swan. The Aboriginal Land Trust is the registered proprietor of the land. </para>
            <para>A great deal of concern has arisen within the Council of this Shire and amongst ratepayers as to the unsatisfactory conditions in which the Aboriginal people are living on the land. There is an extensive disregard of the Council &#39;s Health and Building By-laws and it is recognised that something must be done quickly in the interests of the health and general welfare of the campers. </para>
            <para>Council at its meeting on 13 September 1976 realised that it had a responsibility under the provisions of the statutes administered by it and did resolve as follows: </para>
            <para>That in pursuance of the provisions of (a) Local Government Act 1960 (as amended) (b) Town Planning and Development Act 1928 (as amended) and (c) the </para>
          </quote>
          <para>Health Act 1911 (as amended) and Regulations and Bylaws made under these Acts, the Aboriginal Land Trust being the registered proprietor of land known as lots 64, 65, 66 and 67 Saunders Street, Henley Park, West Swan, be ordered separately under the abovementioned Statutes and Regulations and By-laws made thereunder to have the camps and buildings removed from the aforementioned land within a period of seven (7) days as such camps and buildings are contravening the abovementioned Statutes and Regulations and By-laws made thereunder and the Shire of Swan Town Planning Scheme No. 1&#39;. </para>
          <para>Council appreciates that its action is not the complete answer to the problem of the Aboriginal people but is forced to take such action because the camp in general is lacking in proper hygiene facilities, with poor sanitation facilities, and these general substandard conditions constitute a health hazard which cannot be tolerated in a modern society. </para>
          <para>As you are aware, this local authority is not responsible for the welfare of the Aboriginal people and therefore has no funds made available to it, nor has it any statutory power to provide accommodation of a reasonable standard for these people. It is understood by Council that the Federal and State Governments either together or separately are responsible for the welfare of the Aboriginal community. </para>
          <para>Council has made other attempts to overcome the present problem by convening meetings at which representatives of Federal and State Government departments have attended together with representatives of the Aboriginal Community and the Council of this Shire. But nothing definite has resulted therefrom. </para>
          <para>Council is reluctant to take legal action but if responsible Government is not prepared to accept its responsibilities in respect of the welfare of the Aboriginal community then it must be realised by those administering the affairs of the Federal and State Governments that Council has no alternative but to enforce its standards - </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Is this a speech on the adjournment? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I am reading a letter. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Why do you not just table it? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-No. I intend to read a couple of others as well. I suggest that you doze off as you usually do. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I never doze but I am getting bored with this. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-You are entitled to feel exactly as you like, but if you want to go to sleep do not let me stop you. As I was saying, the letter read:  . . Council has no alternative but to enforce its standards under the provisions of the abovementioned statutes. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para class="block">As I have just mentioned to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir Magnus</inline> Cormack, who displays in this chamber or elsewhere very little interest in the problems of the Aboriginal people, I have a few more letters which I intend to read. My time is as limited as that of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir Magnus</inline> Cormack but I intend utilising it to advantage. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I can easily move that you be not further heard. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>1129</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>5V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator COLEMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- If you wish to do that, it is your privilege to do so. The Women&#39;s Electoral Lobby in Western Australia was so concerned about the situation that it formed a subgroup for Aboriginals to look into the problem of the urban fringe dwellers&#39; association, which is the Saunders Street reserve at Henley Park. I drove out past the reserve on Sunday of this week. I did not call in to make my presence known. I felt that these people were just as entitled to their privacy as are other Australian citizens. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Walters,</inline> who is interjecting, amazes me. She does not have problems with Aboriginals in her State of Tasmania because they were all shot. She should sit back and listen and she might even yet learn something to her advantage. Having been out to have a look at the site I was appalled to see that there were not only young children but also elderly people- about 70 or 80 men, women and children- living on 4 housing blocks in Henley Park. The conditions are not good. The ground is overgrown with weeds and there are no facilities, as stated in the letter from the Shire of Swan. It does not appear that a great many things are happening. So on 30 September the Women&#39;s Electoral Lobby wrote to the  Hon.  R. I. Viner, Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, in these terms: </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <quote>
            <para>We draw your attention to the plight of the aboriginal people at Saunders Street, Henley Park, Western Australia (approximately seventy women, children and men) particularly that they are in danger of eviction by the Swan Shire Council because they cannot conform to the Building and Health by-laws. </para>
            <para>As a short-term priority, we urge you to make funds available for the provision of ablution and septic facilities which could fit in with future plans for the 16 hectare site. We understand that the Department has committed an amount of money for the erection of a prototype house for Robert and Edna Bropho on the Saunders Street site. We urge you to take positive action to ensure the earliest materialisation of this project. </para>
            <para>We further urge that funds be made available for the erection of a further seven houses to properly accommodate the people living on this block, members of whom form the Urban Fringe Dwellers Association. </para>
            <para>As many years of uncertainty have culminated in clear realisation of what this group must do for themselves, it is imperative that they be encouraged in this very constructive venture. </para>
            <para>We look forward to learning what you are able to do with reference to the above. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I do not know whether the Women&#39;s Electoral Lobby has as yet received a reply from the Honourable R. I. Viner but we hope that eventually it will and that he will have something concrete to put before it. I understand that one of the large cement organisations in Western Australia has already agreed to donate a certain amount of mixed cement for the erection of ablution and toilet facilities on the block.&#39; But we should not be concerning ourselves to any great extent about what the private enterprise sector will do; we should be concerning ourselves more about what governments will do. In this particular instance governments are not really prepared to do a great deal. </para>
          <para>Reference was made in the Women&#39;s Electoral Lobby letter to the Bropho house. That house was designed by an Aboriginal couple to fit in with the Aboriginal way of life. Although we white people tend to say that Aborigines should be able to live in white people&#39;s housing, we have never got to the stage of asking them what type of housing they wish to live in. They live in a society which is much different from that of which we are a part. For instance, they tend to keep their elderly people with them; we tend to </para>
          <para class="block">But our elderly people into homes because they become a nuisance. The Aboriginal people live in an extended family situation, and their right to do that should not be taken away from them. </para>
          <para>Some years ago a Liberal government in Western Australia discontinued the day labour program carried out through the Department of Public Works, so it is no longer possible for State government departments to tender for such enterprises as the Bropho house. I understand that tenders have already been called and that only one has been received. That was a tender of $70,000 for the erection of one house. I believe that is exorbitant and I do not believe it is necessary that we should spend $70,000 on one house. However, I do believe that the Federal Government and the State Government now have to accept their full responsibilities in the field of housing. There are 900 Aboriginal people on the State Housing Commission waiting list, and still only 100 houses are to be built this financial year after the injection of a further $25m by the Federal Government into Aboriginal housing and welfare projects. I think it is disgraceful that we have the situation of people being forced to live under trees and in tents in areas such as Saunders Street in Henley Park. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1130</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have taken note of the matters raised by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Mulvihill</inline> in regard to immigration. I shall refer those matters to the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr MacKellar).</inline> I await with interest the letter to which the honourable senator referred. I shall also draw the Minister&#39;s attention to that to see whether any information can be provided. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Coleman</inline>raised matters concerning Aboriginal housing and other matters affecting Aborigines. I shall ensure that those matters are drawn to the attention of the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Viner).</inline></para>
          <para class="block">Question resolved in the affirmative. Senate adjourned at 10.44 p.m. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
  </chamber.xscript>
  <answers.to.questions>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</title>
        <page.no>1131</page.no>
        <type>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="block">The following answers to questions were circulated: </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Rabies (Question No. 849)</title>
          <page.no>1131</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Is the Minister aware that a severe outbreak of rabies has recently swept western Europe. If so, what precautions have been taken to ensure that there is no outbreak of rabies in Australia. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Yes, I am aware of the increased incidence of rabies in Europe. Strict quarantine controls are exercised over the importation of dogs and cats into Australia to prevent the introduction of the disease. Essentially these controls ensure that before release in Australia, any dog or cat which has originated in a rabies infected country has been in a rabies free environment for a period exceeding the possible incubation period. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Radio Australia (Question No. 868)</title>
          <page.no>1131</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>4F4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Button</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>Was it the practice until about April 1976 of Radio Australia to transmit English language programs from separate studios, each program being specifically designed for the area to which it was being transmitted. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Has Radio Australia since about April 1976 been broadcasting only one English language program, irrespective of where it is being transmitted to and is such program prepared in one studio. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(">
              <para>3 ) If this change has taken place, what is the reason for it. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(4)">
              <para>Was such a change proposed several years ago and abandoned because of strong listener reaction. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(5)">
              <para>If such changes have been made, what has the listener reaction been since about April 1976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Carrick</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Post and Telecommunications has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s : </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>Radio Australia&#39;s general English language service, directed to Asia and the Pacific, engages one studio for 2314 hours daily; it will soon be extended to 24 hours daily. Until April 1976, separate English language services, of It to 2 hours duration, were transmitted from other studios to Africa, Britain/Europe and North America. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Yes. The African British and North American services have been incorporated into this new format with the transmission to North America extended by 30 minutes. Listeners in these countries are welcomed to the program at the same transmission times as previously. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(">
              <para>3 ) The new format greatly increases Australian content in news, features and Australian artists and music and was introduced after extensive research, which began in 1974. Well established and popular programs in the previous schedule have been retained. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(4)">
              <para>No. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(5)">
              <para>Mail on the whole has been favourable to enthusiastic, particularly about the increase in Australian content. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Aborigines: Deaths from Tetanus (Question No. 876) </para>
        </answer>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ME4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAUME, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Baume</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) How many deaths from tetanus are known to have occurred in Aborigines in each of the past five years. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many total cases of tetanus are known to have occurred in Aborigines in each of the past five years. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>What is the available information as to the extent of immunisation of Aborigines against tetanus, either partial immunisation or full conventional immunisation </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) There are no separate figures available which indicate the number of deaths from tetanus which may have occurred among Aboriginals in past years. However, the number of deaths recorded as caused by tetanus for the total population, as indicated by the &#39;cause of death&#39; statistics compiled by the Australian Bureau of Statistics from death certificates during the years 1970-74, are 1970-8; 1971-9; 1972-7; 1973-9; 1974-4; Total-37. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para>Source: Australian Bureau of Statistics. </para>
        <para>Of the reported deaths during the above period 21 were males and 16 females, and 28 (76 per cent) were persons aged 60 years or more. None of these deaths were of persons aged 0-14 years. </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>There are no separate figures available giving details of the number of reported cases of tetanus which may have occurred in Aborigines in past years. However, figures giving details of the numbers of reported cases of tetanus notified in the States and Territories for the total population in each of the past five years are as follows: 1971-24; 1972-18; 1973-17; 1974-12; 1975-1 1; Total-82. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Source. Annual Reports of the Director-General of Health. </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>The State and Territory health authorities encourage tetanus immunisation, particularly in the early age groups including, of course, Aboriginals. The aim of the various programs is to immunise as many Aboriginals as possible against tetanus. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Advice from the various States indicates that immunisation coverage among Aboriginal infants, school age children and adults is generally better than in other sections of the population. </para>
        <para>In the Northern Territory, immunisation is offered to all young Aboriginals and the health authorities are confident that near full coverage is achieved. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Cocos (Keeling) Islanders: Australian Citizenship (Question No. 887)</title>
          <page.no>1131</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1131</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Mulvihill</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>What will be the status of the 700 Cocos (Keeling) Islanders who are to take up residence in Australia. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>I understand that there are about 400 Cocos Malays living in the Cocos (Keeling) Islands. Approximately 260 others are at present resident in Christmas Island. I am not aware of the specific number of Cocos Malays who may wish to take up residence in Australia. </para>
            <para>Of the Cocos (Keeling) Islanders who might take up residence in Australia those who are not already Australian citizens will be given resident status and will be entitled to engage in employment and enjoy the same amenities as any other settler. </para>
            <para>Under the provisions of the Australian Citizenship Act 1948 anyone born on the Cocos (Keeling) Islands since the islands became Australian territory on 23 November 1955 is an Australian citizen by birth. Additionally section 14 of the Cocos (Keeling) Islands Act 1955 provided for British subjects ordinarily resident on the islands immediately before 23 November 1955 to become Australian citizens by a simple process of making a declaration and having it registered. </para>
            <para>Any long term residents of the islands who have not become Australian citizens by either of the means mentioned would almost certainly have the status of British subjects as the islands were pan of the United Kingdom and colonies before they became Australian territory. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Rabies (Question No. 934)</title>
          <page.no>1132</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Mulvihill</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Has the increased incidence of rabies amongst dogs in Europe caused the Department of Health to institute quarantine precautions to avoid the spread of this disease to Australia. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Australia has long been aware of the incidence of rabies in Europe and has for many years exercised stringent quarantine controls to guard against the introduction of this disease into Australia. These controls ensure that before release in Australia, any dog or cat which has originated in a rabies infected country has been in a rabies free environment for a period exceeding the possible incubation period. &#39; </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Australian Film Institute: Financial Assistance (Question No. 1022)</title>
          <page.no>1132</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Prime Minister, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What financial assistance is made available to the Australian Film Institute from (a) the Australia Council and (b) any other source within the responsibility of the Australian Government. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What amount of any grants from sources referred to in ( 1 ) is spent on (a) the Play box Cinema, (b) the Vincent Library, and (c) fees and/or travel expenses for the Institute&#39;s directors. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Prime Minister has provided the following information for answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>I am informed that in 1975-76 the Australian Film Institute received: </para>
              <list type="loweralpha">
                <item label="(a)">
                  <para>$122,856 from the Australia Council for administrative expenses; </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(b)">
                  <para>Nil. </para>
                </item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item label="(2">
              <para>) The following sums were included in the allocation by the Australia Council: </para>
              <list type="loweralpha">
                <item label="(a)">
                  <para>Playbox Cinema (now the Longford Cinema )-$80,000; </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(b)">
                  <para>Vincent Library-$35,767; </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(c)">
                  <para>Fees- Nil. Travel and accommodation expenses for the Board of Directors-$6,423. </para>
                </item>
              </list>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Department of the Treasury: Journalists  (Question No.  1029) </para>
        </answer>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Treasurer&#39;s Department, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Treasurer&#39;s control, when the administrative arrangements of 22 December 1975 were made. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Department of the Treasury, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Treasurer&#39;s control, at 1 September 1976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Cotton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Treasurer has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) and (2) Subject to the following minor qualification, I am advised that no persons were employed in positions designated journalist, at either of the times referred to, by any of the organisations covered by the question. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>The Australian Statistician has advised that a journalist, seconded from the Australian Information Service, has been attached to the Australian Bureau of Statistics continuously since December 1973. No journalists have been employed directly by the Australian Bureau of Statistics. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Department of Administrative Services: Journalists (Question No. 1031)</title>
          <page.no>1132</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>20000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata" />
              <name role="display">Senator McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) How many journalists were employed in the Minister&#39;s Department, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, when the administrative arrangements of 22 December 1975 were made. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Department of Administrative Services, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, at 1 September 1976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1132</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) One hundred and twenty-eight. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>One hundred and nineteen. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Department of Transport: Journalists (Question No. 1034)</title>
          <page.no>1133</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Transport, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) How many journalists were employed in the Minister&#39;s Department, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, when the administrative arrangements of 22 December 1 973 were made. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Department of Transport, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, at 1 September 1976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Carrick</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Transport has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197610122_26_0.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Department of Social Security: Journalists (Question No. 1038)</title>
          <page.no>1133</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Minister&#39;s Department, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, when the administrative arrangements of 22 December 1 975 were made. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Department of Social Security and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, at 1 September 1 976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>and (2) As at 22 December 1975 a total often (10) persons were employed as journalists, or in positions requiring journalistic qualifications. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>As at 1 September 1976, following the creation of the Office of Child Care within the Department of Social Security, the number of such persons employed was eleven (11). </para>
          <para>The only commission or statutory body under my control on the abovementioned dates was the Social Welfare Commission which was not employing any journalists on those dates. </para>
          <para>Containers: Movement from Alice Springs to Katherine (Question No. 1054) </para>
        </answer>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2U</name.id>
              <electorate>NORTHERN TERRITORY</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ROBERTSON, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Robertson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Transport, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Will the Minister undertake to have discussions with Co-ord, a transport company in the Northern Territory, to see what can be done to remedy the late arrival of containers transported by road to Katherine from Alice Springs. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Carrick</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Transport has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>I understand that no delays are being experienced in the movement of full container loads from Alice Springs to Katherine. However small consignments have been delayed in the past at Alice Springs while they are being consolidated into larger consignments before being forwarded to Katherine. Arrangements to overcome this situation have recently been completed with Co-ord Pty Ltd and smaller containers will now be used for this traffic which will be on a regular weekly basis, leaving Alice Springs on Mondays and arriving in Katherine on Thursdays. This should overcome the problem raised by the honourable senator. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Pension Eligibility: House Rent (Question No. 1091)</title>
          <page.no>1133</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>7V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Georges</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>Will the Minister be specific on the way in which income for pension eligibility is to be assessed from 1 1 November 1976. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>If a person has a weekly income of $40 derived from renting a house, will the gross amount be regarded as means or will rates and taxes be deducted first. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Have specific guidelines yet been given to officers of the Department of Social Security. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) and (2) As a general rule, one-third of gross rent for a house will be allowed as a deduction from income to cover rates, taxes, repairs and other outgoings. A larger amount than one-third may be allowed where the pensioner produces evidence to show higher expenditure. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Yes. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Incident at Daly River (Question No. 1096) </para>
        </answer>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1133</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Northern Territory, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Is the Minister aware that an incident involving police and two pensioners, aged 54 and 60 respectively, recently occurred in Daly River and that both pensioners are now inmates of the Darwin Hospital. If so, did the police concerned use firearms and were the pensioners assaulted by the police. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Was a police inquiry held into the incidents. If so, was any action taken against the policemen concerned. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Has the Minister ordered a &#39;top level&#39; inquiry into what appears to be a totally unjustified assault. If not, will he initiate such an inquiry. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1134</page.no>
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The Minister for the Northern Territory has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Yes. An incident involving Police and three persons, namely, Alfred Allan Hargrave, Pensioner; Nelson Lyle Lewis, Pensioner, and Patrick Bernard St or an Plant Operator, did occur at Daly River on 20 August 1 976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Alfred Allan Margrave and Nelson Lyle Lewis received medical treatment in Darwin after the incident; neither is currently an inmate of the Darwin Hospital. </para>
          <para>The Police concerned did not use firearms. The police officer concerned denies he unlawfully assaulted any person. It is alleged that a number of Aboriginals who were with the police officer at the time assaulted Hargrave, Lewis and Storan </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>A Police Inquiry led by an Assistant Commissioner of Police was conducted into the incident. The Policeman concerned has been served with four departmental charges arising out of breaches of the Regulations under the Police and Police Offences Ordinance 1923-75. These charges have not been dealt with to date. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>No. See (2) above. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Normeat Meatworks, Katherine (Question No. 1101)</title>
          <page.no>1134</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1134</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Is the Minister aware that the company which took over the Nor meat meatworks at Katherine has reduced freezer pack size from 60 lb to 30 lb. If so, does this increase the handling and associated costs to a meatworks that is already in some degree of financial difficulty. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Does the company, in addition to exporting prime beef, also export offal and brisket, and is the company subsidising the export of brisket to something of the order of 10 cents per pound. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Will the Minister investigate the matters referred to with a view to encouraging more effective management in a meatworks badly needed in this part of the Northern Territory to provide both killing facilities for local beef producers and to sustain the economic and employment situation in a very isolated area. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1134</page.no>
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Cotton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Primary Industry has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) The company to which the honourable senator refers, Nor west Beef Industries Pty Ltd, have advised me that they are packing some edible offal in 30 lb cartons at the request of the buyers concerned, but packaging of all other offals and meats is in the usual 60 lb cartons. The net effect of variations in pack size would depend upon the price received for the product as well as any change in operating costs. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>I understand that the company engages in the export of brisket and edible offal, as well as in the export of car toned beef which is the principal revenue earner for the company. The meaning of the honourable senator&#39;s reference to subsidisation of the brisket exports is not clear to me. In any case, decisions concerning the day to day operations of Katherine meatworks are a matter of commercial judgment for the company responsible for its management. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>I must emphasise that the Government considers it important to ensure the continual availability of adequate killing facilities in the Northern Territory. This view was reflected in a decision of the Government earlier this year to accede to a request by Northern Meat Exporters Pty Ltd to vary the repayment schedule of the Government&#39;s loan of $ 1.4m to enable the company to operate Katherine abattoir under a joint venture arrangement with Nor west Development Corporation, the managing company for Wyndham abattoir, Western Australia. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>It is also relevant that the Bureau of Agricultural Economics is currently engaged in a study of the relationships between the requirements of cattle producers and the slaughtering facilities in the Top End and northern Western Australia. </para>
          <para>Wheat: Damage by Galah Populations (Question No. 1114) </para>
        </answer>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1134</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Mulvihill</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry, upon nonce: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Does the Department have in its possession information which would enable wheat farmers to control galah populations without having to resort to their widespread destruction. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1134</page.no>
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Cotton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Primary Industry has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>No. Information available to my Department from expert sources indicates that there is no method which would enable wheat farmers to control galah populations without resorting to destruction of the birds. Some work has been carried out overseas on bird repellents but they are not very effective and their use in wheat production appears impracticable. </para>
            <para>This species has extended its range and probably its numbers. Although the need for destruction of birds is regrettable, it appears well able to withstand the level of control operations practised at present. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">Audit of University Funds </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers:</inline>On 8 September 1976 <inline font-style="italic">{Hansard,</inline> page 453) <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Harradine</inline> asked me, as Minister representing the Prime Minister, a question without notice regarding the procedures adopted by the Auditor-General&#39;s Office to ensure that public moneys made available to universities are spent in an authorised fashion. I undertook to seek the information for the honourable senator and have now been provided with the following information by the Acting Auditor-General: </para>
        <quote>
          <para>With the exception of the Australian National University, grant moneys made available by the Commonwealth in the normal course for the purposes of universities are provided under the various States Grants (Universities) Acts and Universities (Financial Assistance) Acts, which are administered by the Universities Commission. The grants are paid to the universities through the State Treasuries. </para>
          <para>In addition to examining the regularity of grant payments by the Commonwealth, the Auditor-General&#39;s Office examines the certificates received by the Universities Commission from the auditors of the various universities (either State Auditors-General, or private auditors in the case of South Australian universities and colleges of residence generally) in relation to the application of grant moneys by the universities, and the reconciliation of such certificates with Commission records. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>The audit certificates are furnished pursuant to arrangements made between the Commonwealth and State authorities in accordance with the general requirements imposed by the relevant legislation on the responsible Commonwealth Minister to be satisfied that the conditions applicable to the &#167; rants, as set out in the Acts, have been fulfilled by the tates. </para>
        <para>Moneys are made available by the Commonwealth to the Australian National University from a special appropriation under the Australian National University Act and also from annual appropriations. The Auditor-General has been appointed the auditor of the University by the Treasurer under the provisions of the last-mentioned Act. Normal audit procedures apply in relation to the examination of expenditures of the University. </para>
        <para class="block">Australian Coastguard </para>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- On 9 September 1976 <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Devitt</inline> asked me a question regarding the progress being made and the likely date of setting up an appropriate coastguard or some similar organisation. The Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs has now provided me with the following information in answer to the honourable senator &#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>As the honourable senator will recall the question of whether a coastguard should be established in Australia has been raised on a number of occasions previously. No firm decision has been taken by successive Governments for the establishment of a coastguard. </para>
            <para>A good deal has been done to improve the surveillance which is undertaken in Australian waters particularly in the far north. For some years now interested departments together with representatives of the defence Services have examined ways of improving routine surveillance and specific surveillance in relation to particular activities, for example, surveillance associated with a particular smuggling operation. </para>
            <para>Apart from these activities Customs resources in the north have been strengthened by the provision of seagoing patrol launches. Moreover aircraft and other vehicles are chartered as required to cater for the needs of specific operations. </para>
            <para>In short I would inform the honourable senator that I cannot say whether or not a coastguard will be formally established in Australia. However, I can say that for Customs and other purposes arrangements are progressively being improved, particularly in the far north, to provide some of the services one normally expects a coastguard to give. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <para>Employment: New South Wales Building Industry </para>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- On 14 September 1976 <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Baume</inline> asked a question without notice concerning the degree to which the present employment difficulties in the building industry in New South Wales are a legacy of the actions of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Mundey</inline> several years ago. The Acting Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations has provided the following information in answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>No detailed statistics of industrial disputes arising from green bans are maintained by the Department of Employment and Industrial Relations. However, it is known that the green bans imposed in New South Wales had an extremely disruptive effect on the building and construction industry in that State. They were responsible for increases in costs, reduction in productivity and a general dislocation of forward planning by a number of building enterprises. Accordingly it is reasonable to assume that the green bans would have made a significant contribution to the employment difficulties now being experienced by the industry. However, in the absence of statistical data, it is not possible to quantify the precise impact which those green bans did in fact have. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Unemployment Benefit: Prosecutions (Question No. 1002)</title>
          <page.no>1135</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>How many persons were prosecuted for improperly obtaining unemployment benefit in Queensland for each calendar month since July 1 970. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197610122_28_0.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Department of Primary Industry: Statutory Authorities (Question No. 942)</title>
          <page.no>1135</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ISW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wriedt</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry the following question, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Which statutory authorities come under the control of the Department of Primary Industry. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What is the name, occupation, date and term of appointment, and remuneration of each holder of public office of each authority. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>1135</page.no>
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Cotton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Primary Industry has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>The Australian Apple and Pear Corporation, the Australian Canned Fruits Board, the Australian Dairy Corporation, the Australian Dried Fruits Control Board, the Australian Egg Board, the Australian Honey Board, the Australian Meat Board, the Australian Tobacco Board, the Australian Wheat Board, the Australian Wine Board, the Australian Wool Corporation, the Australian Wool Testing Authority. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Salaries for the positions listed are set out in the Remuneration Tribunal&#39;s 1976 Report. The other details sought by the honourable senator are provided in the following table: </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197610122_29_2.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197610122_30_3.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197610122_31_4.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
  </answers.to.questions>
</hansard>