
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1976-09-21</date>
    <parliament.no>30</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>2</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>773</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1976-09-21</day.start>
      <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Condor Laucke)</inline> took the chair at 2.30 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS</title>
        <page.no>773</page.no>
        <type>ministerial arrangements</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>773</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>DV4</name.id>
            <electorate>Western AustraliaLeader of the Government in the Senate</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role>Minister for Administrative Services</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I inform the Senate that the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations, the Honourable A. A. Street, left Australia on 18 September to attend the Sixth Conference of Asian Labour Ministers to be held in Teheran. He is expected to return to Australia on 30 September. During his absence the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs, the Honourable John Howard, will act as Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations and will assist the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Malcolm Fraser)</inline> in Public Service matters and women &#39;s affairs. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>I also inform the Senate that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, the Honourable Andrew Peacock, will leave Australia today to attend the United Nations General Assembly and to visit Brussels and Jakarta. He is expected to return to Australia on 1 1 October. During his absence the Minister for Primary Industry, the Honourable Ian Sinclair, will act as Minister for Foreign Affairs. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PETITIONS</title>
        <page.no>773</page.no>
        <type>petition</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Australian Broadcasting Commission</title>
          <page.no>773</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>773</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>RG4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIETZELT, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIETZELT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I present the following petition from 1 1 citizens of Australia: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>To the Honourable  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that the Australian Broadcasting Commission belongs to the people and not to the government of the day whatever political party. </para>
            <para>Your petitioners most humbly pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled should: </para>
            <list type="decimal-dotted">
              <item label="1.">
                <para>Eschew all means, direct or indirect, of diminishing the independence of the Australian Broadcasting Commission. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="2.">
                <para>Reject all proposals for the introduction of advertising into ABC programs. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="3.">
                <para>Develop methods for publicly funding the Commission which will prevent the granting or withholding of funds being used as a method of diminishing its independence. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="4.">
                <para>Ensure that any general inquiries into broadcasting in Australia which may seem desirable from time to time shall be conducted publicly and that strong representation of the public shall be included within the body conducting the inquiry. </para>
              </item>
            </list>
            <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>Petition received and read. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Family Planning</title>
          <page.no>773</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>773</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3A</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I present the following petition from 10 citizens of Australia: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled: The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
            <para>That the Family Planning Association and similar organisations throughout Australia contribute to the welfare and well-being of a great proportion of the Australian people both in family planning and in an advisory capacity on the prevention and control of social diseases. </para>
            <para>Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that urgent consideration be given to a favourable decision on the continuation of Federal Government finance to enable the activities of the Family Planning Associations and like organisations to proceed unimpaired throughout Australia. </para>
            <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>Petition received and read. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>773</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CLERK, The</name>
              <name role="display">The Clerk</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- A petition has been lodged for presentation as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Social Security Matters</title>
          <page.no>773</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">To the Honourable the  President  and Members of the Senate, and the Honourable the  Speaker  and Members of the House of Representatives in Parliament assembled, the petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth: </para>
        <para>That distress is being caused to social security recipients by the delay in adjusting pensions to the Consumer Price Index months after prices of goods and services have risen, and that medications which were formerly pharmaceutical benefits must now be paid for. </para>
        <para>Additionally, that State housing authorities&#39; waiting lists for low rental dwellings for pensioners grow ever longer, and the cost of funerals increase ever greater. </para>
        <para>Your petitioners call on the Australian Government as a matter of urgency to: </para>
        <para>Adjust social security payments instantly and automatically when the quarterly Consumer Prices Index is announced. </para>
        <para>Restore pharmaceutical benefits deleted from the free list. </para>
        <para>Update the State Grants ( Dwellings for Pensioners) Act of 1974, eroded by inflation, to increase grants to overcome the backlog. </para>
        <para>Update Funeral Benefit to 60 per cent of reasonable cost <inline font-style="italic">of funeral.</inline> (This benefit was 200 shillings, 20 dollars, when introduced in 1943. It was seven times the 1943 pension of 27 shillings a week.) </para>
        <para>And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.  by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Baume.</inline></para>
        <para>Petition received. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</title>
        <page.no>773</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LOAN RAISING BY TELECOM AUSTRALIA</title>
          <page.no>773</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>773</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ISW</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIEDT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct a question to the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications. He will be aware that Bain and Co. is one of the joint underwriters for the  loan being raised by Telecom Australia and that Hill Samuel Australia Ltd is the financial adviser to Telecom in connection with that loan. Is it correct, or has the Minister any knowledge, that Geoffrey Bain of Bain &#38; Co. is a member of the Liberal Party and a fund raiser for that Party? Is the Minister aware that Ernest Owens, the  Chairman  of Hill Samuel Australia Ltd, is also a member of the Liberal Party and a former Treasurer of the New South Wales branch of that Party? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Federal Affairs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I think the Leader of the Opposition has his facts wrong. A James Bain, Jim Bain, of Bain and Co., who is known to me is, I think, a branch member of the Liberal Party. The original Bain of Bain and Co. is now dead. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Owens</inline> from Hill Samuel Australia Ltd was never, to my certain knowledge, a treasurer of the Liberal Party. I am unaware whether he has been at any time a branch member of the Liberal Party, but that is quite possible. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FEDERALISM POLICY</title>
          <page.no>774</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8H</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Andrew</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Will the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Federal Affairs assure the Senate that the reduction in income tax through indexation will not reduce the amount of money received by the States through the federalism policy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I give that unqualified assurance. At the Premiers Conferences held earlier this year a clear undertaking was given by the Commonwealth Government that the figure of 33.6 per cent, which was finally fixed for revenue sharing, would be fixed after adjustments to tax had been made and after the Commonwealth Government had agreed to forgo no less than $ 1 ,050m by way of income tax to be retained in the pockets and purses of the public. Not only did that arrangement not affect the States but they were also given first of all a guarantee that never in the next 4 years would their revenue fall below the amount that the Whitlam Government formula would have yielded. I am happy to say that this year the revenue for the States based on the 33.6 per cent formula will, in fact, exceed the Whitlam formula by more than $89m. That, of course, is in addition to the extra amount given to local governments. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NEW ZEALAND ALL BLACKS RUGBY TEAM</title>
          <page.no>774</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEEFFE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I preface my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport by reminding him that on 9 September this year I asked a question concerning the transport of the New Zealand All Blacks rugby team from South Africa to New Zealand. The Minister will&#39; also recall that I raised the possibility of Qantas Airways Ltd acting as the carrier between the 2 countries. I remind the Minister that he promised to obtain the appropriate information from the responsible Minister but to date I have not obtained this information. Is the Minister aware that the All Blacks team landed in Perth this morning and will arrive, or has already arrived, in Melbourne this afternoon? Can the Minister indicate to the Parliament whether the policy of his Government has changed from opposition to apartheid as practised in South Africa to one of support? Does this indicate also that his Government approves of the race violence in South Africa? Lastly, does this mean that the Minister for Transport is merely another Minister who has lost control of his Department and that the international relations section of his Department is now able to make new policies without reference to the Minister or the Government? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-As to the first point, I regret that the answer to the question asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Keeffe</inline> on 9 September has not been given to him. I shall see whether I can get that for him as soon as possible- hopefully today. As to the second question, no, I am not aware that the All Blacks landed in Perth, but I accept the assurance of the honourable senator that they did. As to the third question, no, the Commonwealth Government has not changed its policies in opposition to apartheid. As to the fourth question, no, we do not support race violence anywhere in the world. Unlike the Labor Party, we are not selective as to countries in which we support or oppose race violence. It ought to be made quite clear that our opposition is not selective, whilst that of the Labor Party is. As to the question about loss of control, that is a silly question and I reject it. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>VIETNAMESE REFUGEES</title>
          <page.no>774</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>774</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ME4</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAUME, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BAUME</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Will the Minister representing the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs confirm that refugees from Vietnam recently have arrived in ports around the Gulf of Siam and are not allowed to land at those ports? Is there any information on whether these refugees are without supplies of food or medical attention? Can the Minister advise whether Australia has extended, or intends to extend, to some of these refugees the asylum it offered 22 others from Vietnam who recently were allowed to come here after fleeing from that country by ship? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that a considerable number of refugees from Vietnam are in vessels in waters off the South-East Asian coast. I understand also that many of these refugees have limited supplies of food and that medical attention may not be available if they need it. The scale of this problem requires an international effort to enable all the refugees on these vessels to be resettled. I can assure the honourable senator that Australia is participating in discussions with this objective. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SAFETY HELMETS FOR MOTOR CYCLISTS</title>
          <page.no>775</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MULVIHILL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs. Will the Minister inquire as to who was the Australian importer responsible for imposing on Australian motor cyclists a Japanese manufactured helmet which caused the death of Stephen Agnew and which resulted in a strong condemnation by a coroner? If the offender-the Australian importer- is detected, will punitive action be taken against him? In regard to long range policy, will Australia impose a more stringent quality check on such imports? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Repatriation</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I can assure <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Mulvihill</inline> that the attention of the Minister has been drawn to the newspaper reports to which he referred relating to an unsafe motor cyclist helmet which was strongly condemned by the Sydney coroner. 1 am informed that in November last year an import control was introduced to ban the importation of motor cyclist helmets not complying with the stringent requirements of Australian standard 1698. My colleague the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs has directed that inquiries be made into the circumstances of the importation of this particular helmet. I shall advise the Senate when those inquiries are completed. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TERTIARY EDUCATION ASSISTANCE SCHEME</title>
          <page.no>775</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKD</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JESSOP, Donald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator JESSOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Education. Is it a fact that at present the Government exempts from the means test the first $350 of the education allowance to primary and secondary students from geographically isolated areas? Is it also a fact that the present tertiary education assistance scheme imposes a means test on the excess allowance of $600 per annum for tertiary students in this category? As the Minister is considering making a statement on this scheme shortly, will he consider waiving the means test to avoid what appears to be discrimination against tertiary students from these areas? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It was because there were some 10 different schemes, because they overlapped and because anomalies were sometimes created that the Commonwealth Government set up an interdepartmental committee to look at all these matters, especially the matter of isolated children. It is matters such as those which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> raised that are being given consideration. I shall draw the attention of the committee and my Government to the points which he has made. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MEDIBANK LEVY</title>
          <page.no>775</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K6F</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAVANAGH, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CAVANAGH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask a question of the Minister for Social Security in her capacity as Minister for Social Security or as Minister representing the Minister for Health. Will a person on sickness benefit who has a wife and a child and who receives $88 a week, which is $6 in excess of the amount above which Medibank contributions are not payable, be charged 2.5 per cent of his sickness benefit for the payment of the Medibank levy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Lists have been made of those who are eligible to pay the Medibank levy. The only exemptions made to the present time by the Government are those who qualify for the pensioner medical service card. I shall investigate the matter raised by the honourable senator and see what information I can give him on it. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HEALTH INSURANCE</title>
          <page.no>775</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>775</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1Y</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BISHOP, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BISHOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Social Security in her dual capacity as Minister for Social Security and Minister representing the Minister for Health. It refers to Medibank and health insurance. She will be aware that whilst a considerable amount of printed information has been distributed at present, and more is promised, to members of Parliament and to members of the public, many thousands of citizens do not yet know the procedures which ought to be adopted in order to exercise their options. I understand from information given to me that in each of the 3 departments concerned special officers are assigned to study the matter and to make that information known to the public. Would the Minister consider discussing with the Minister for Health the need for a wide television campaign which would make known to the ordinary citizen the options which are available and upon which he should decide, so that more could be aware of the action which they should take to complete their obligations? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I shall draw to the attention of the Minister for Health the matter raised by the honourable senator. He referred to the lack of information in some areas. It is understood that there has been for some time a campaign to advise people of the options and benefits now available either in the Medibank or the private health insurance systems. Booklets have been prepared, leaflets have been made available. The telephone service has been made available for this purpose in many parts of Australia. I understand that television advertising and information were also part of this education campaign. However I shall draw to the Minister&#39;s attention the matter which has been raised to see what can be done to ensure that the widest information possible is available so that people can determine the benefits which they require. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EAST TIMOR</title>
          <page.no>776</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUU</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MISSEN, Alan</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MISSEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs. I refer to the new announcement by Indonesia that it has closed off waters around East Timor and that it will fire on any trespassing foreign ships. I refer to recent reports in London and Australian newspapers of continued heavy fighting in East Timor, new atrocities, and casualties and unrest in the Indonesian armed forces engaged in fighting the Fret i lin forces. Does this Government&#39;s inquiries indicate that these statements are correct? Are substantial teri tories and a substantial part of the population still under the control of&#34; the Fret i lin Government? In the circumstances, does the Government intend to reinforce its previously expressed attitude towards the invasion of East Timor, the removal of Indonesian forces, the need for a genuine act of free choice by the inhabitants and the humanitarian need for the immediate presence of the impartial International Red Cross and other aids to the suffering population? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-The first 2 questions concern matters of fact on which I shall have to seek information from my colleague in the other place. As to the third question, I think that the Government&#39;s policy on this issue has been clear from the time that it was first enunciated by the Honourable Andrew Peacock. He enunciated the Government&#39;s stance on it a number of times and I am quite certain that that is still the policy of the Government and will remain the policy of the Government. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EUCALYPT DISEASE</title>
          <page.no>776</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>RG4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIETZELT, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIETZELT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry whether he is aware of the threat to much of Australia&#39;s natural eucalypt forests, particularly in Victoria, Western Australia and Tasmania, caused by the fungal disease phytophthora cinnamon and the disastrous effect it could have on the export wood chip industry, the paper manufacturing industry and our national forest heritage. Will the Government agree to conduct an urgent study into the extent of the disease and its long-term effects on the industries mentioned and on the environment? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Industry and Commerce</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I think that the honourable senator will find that both the Commonwealth and State forestry departments are aware of this problem and that it is under urgent investigation. Eucalypt forests do not normally suffer from these sorts of problems, although this particular disease has occurred. I am not sure whether its source has been identified. Softwood forests are much more prone to these problems of devastation than are eucalypt forests which have learnt to survive through the normal activities of Australian man against his environment. This area is of great interest and importance. Occasionally there is an odd devastation phase in the eucalypt forests. One such period was called the plasmid insect phase when plasmid insects about 5 inches long almost defoliated the eucalypt forests of the eastern tablelands. Had that problem recurred a second year we would have almost lost the eucalypt forests of the eastern seaboard. What the honourable senator has said is important. I know that it is being looked at and I shall obtain more information for him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>VOLUNTARY WELFARE ORGANISATIONS</title>
          <page.no>776</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPV</name.id>
              <electorate>ACT</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KNIGHT, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KNIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I wish to ask a question of the Minister for Social Security concerning government co-operation with voluntary welfare organisations. I refer to the statement in the speech by the Governor-General on the opening of the Thirtieth Parliament that &#39;the Government will assist voluntary bodies by placing public service resources at their disposal through improving opportunities for transferability of staff between the government and the non government sector&#39;. Can the Minister indicate whether action has been taken towards implementing that undertaking? If so, what measures have been taken? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>776</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government has been looking at ways and means of achieving the transferability of staff between the government and the non-government sector. I am able to advise that in a limited number of instances we are very close to achieving this but I have no announcements to make at this stage of any particular instances. As a matter of interest, I inform the Senate that it was drawn to my attention this morning that we ought also to be arranging this sort of transferability on an international basis as there are many agencies and bodies in other countries which would benefit from the work that our officers could do for them and which likewise would enrich the experience of our officers. This matter is receiving constant attention. In a limited number of cases I believe that I am close to achieving some transferability. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LOCAL GOVERNMENT FINANCE</title>
          <page.no>777</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>777</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question is addressed to the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Federal Affairs. Has he seen a report that the local government and shires associations of New South Wales are urging the Australian Government to adhere to revenue sharing principles by making the local government allocation equal to 1.6 per cent of the finally allocated figure, as the Government undertook to do in the last Budget, which would mean another $2.7m for New South Wales? Is the report correct? Have the associations also urged the Australian Government to lift the allocation to at least 2 per cent, which is considered by the associations to be an absolute minimum if there is to be any effect on rates? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>777</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have seen reports from municipal and shire authorities requesting the Commonwealth Government to adopt a figure of 1.6 per cent both retrospectively as applying to this year and prospectively. I must correct <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Douglas</inline> McClelland &#39;s statement that in the Budget the Government undertook to give 1.6 per cent. That is entirely wrong. What happened was that the Government at the Premiers Conference, with the full understanding of that Conference, decided that it would announce the amount, as distinct from the percentage, to apply to this income year and to make that announcement in early June before the full amount of income tax for the year, then incomplete, was known. The Government, in order to do so, announced an amount of $ 140m for this year. So I say emphatically that for this year it is an amount and not a percentage. Some people- not the Government- represented the amount on the figures known as being 1.6 per cent. In fact, purely fortuitously, it turned out to be 1.52 per cent when the full amount was taken in. The 1.6 per cent was an informal figure raised by others in their figuring. The Government never said that that was to be the figure for this year. The amount for this year is $ 1 40m. It is true that there have been representations by local government in the past suggesting that the future figure should be 2 per cent. That is a matter for the future. I find it quite elevating that the Australian Labor Party, which provided only $79.9m last year, should be advocating that we provide more money after we have increased its grant by 75 per cent. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING COMMISSION: RUGBY UNION INJURY</title>
          <page.no>777</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>777</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9I4</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MESSNER, Tony</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MESSNER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications. I refer to the serious injury suffered by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator John</inline> Knight while gallantly defending Parliament, playing rugby against the Australian Broadcasting Commission last Sunday. I ask: Would the ABC entertain a claim for compensation or would this be regarded as evidence of political pressure? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>777</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In this chamber I have been made aware, largely by honourable senators opposite, of the dangers inherent in tangling with the Australian Broadcasting Commission. I did not know previously that the dangers were overt and traumatic on a rugby field. I hope the game was Rugby Union because I want to be sure that the correct code was played. I am not aware of this matter. At the risk of appearing partisan, because it was such a worthy cause and because no doubt the injury was incurred in full frontal display before the ABC without censorship, I shall bring the matter to the attention of the Minister concerned. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PURCHASE OF TRACTORS</title>
          <page.no>777</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>777</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WALSH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question, which is directed to the Minister representing the Treasurer, refers to an advertisement which was published in the <inline font-style="italic">Merredin Mercury</inline> on 2 September last and to a nearly identical advertisement published in the <inline font-style="italic">Countryman</inline> of 16 September of what is euphemistically called a study tour of the John Deere factory at Moline, Illinois, United States of America, being available to anyone who buys a John Deere 8430 or 8630 tractor before the end of December this year. These tractors cost about $50,000. The advertisement states that all expenses, including ground and air travel, meals and accommodation, are included. I ask the Minister: Would this overseas junket be subsidised by the Australian taxpayer through depreciation allowances and especially the 40 per cent investment allowance? If so, is it the intention of the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Government that the investment allowance be used in that way? If not, what steps will the Treasurer take to protect the revenue? </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I am not an avid reader of the <inline font-style="italic">Merredin Mercury</inline> and I do not suppose the Treasurer is either. I am quite sure he will be delighted to have his attention drawn to the advertisement. I think the assumptions the honourable senator makes about this matter are probably totally incorrect. One ought to check out the matter for the honourable senator and I shall do so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FOOD PRESERVATIVES AND COLOURING AGENTS</title>
          <page.no>778</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8R</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">TOWNLEY, Michael</name>
              <name role="display">Senator TOWNLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Health. No doubt the Minister is aware that some people are allergic to artificial colouring and preservative agents used in food. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>778</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JUH</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DEVITT, Donald</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Devitt</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Especially red. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>778</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K8R</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">TOWNLEY, Michael</name>
                <name role="display">Senator TOWNLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Especially red, as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Devitt</inline> mentioned. Also the Minister will be aware of the doubt that has been voiced recently about the safety of some of the colouring and preservative agents as they may prove to be cancerous. Some of the red I can think of would be cancerous. When does the Government intend to legislate to require manufacturers to list on the label the ingredients of any edible food so that those people who wish to choose foods free from certain ingredients will be able to do so? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that in many instances State government legislation would be required to achieve what the honourable senator seeks. However, I shall draw this matter to the attention of the Minister for Health and obtain an answer as soon as possible. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TASMANIAN RAILWAYS</title>
          <page.no>778</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYA</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">O&#39;BYRNE, Justin</name>
              <name role="display">Senator O&#39;BYRNE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport. Will he give an assurance that in the transfer of the Tasmanian Government Railways to the Australian Government the rights of railway employees, including the right of choice of superannuation fund, will be preserved? Further, will the Minister provide the Parliament with the date for the transfer of the Tasmanian Railways to the Australian Government? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- If my memory serves me correctly, I answered a similar question to that asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O</inline> &#39;Byrne a week or two ago. That question was asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bishop</inline> and related primarily to the South Australian Railways. The rights, particularly superannuation rights including transferability, of employees is an important matter and, as I am not aware specifically of the date of transfer, I shall seek information in answer to both questions for the honourable senator and let him have that information. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TIMOR</title>
          <page.no>778</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPO</name.id>
              <electorate>NORTHERN TERRITORY</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KILGARIFF, Bernard</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KILGARIFF</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs. In the past I have made representations on behalf of&#34; Timorese people in the Northern Territory to the Federal Parliament. My question now is along similar lines to that asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Missen.</inline> The Indonesian Government announced during the weekend that, because of continued fighting in Timor between the Timorese people and the Indonesian Army, the borders of Timor have been sealed off by Indonesia and the coastline of Timor is being patrolled. It is reported that there is a further large number of casualties in Timor and that the death rate apparently is increasing rapidly. In view of these disturbing reports and the fact that many Timorese are being killed unnecessarily, will the Government renew its endeavours with the Indonesian Government with a view to bringing about a cessation of hostilities and so allowing communication between Timor and Australia in order to permit the transfer of refugees and/or much needed aid? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I can assure the honourable senator that these matters are continually under notice not only by the Minister for Foreign Affairs but by the Government as a whole. However, in view of the honourable senator&#39;s special interest in this problem I certainly shall bring his question to the notice of my colleague in the other place. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AIR FORCE BASES</title>
          <page.no>778</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTJ</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCINTOSH, Gordon</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McINTOSH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Defence: Can the Government inform the Senate whether any discussions have been held between Australia and the United States of America on the proposed utilisation of the Learmonth air force base in Western Australia? Further, have there been any discussions with the United States in relation to the reported usage of the Cocos (Keeling) Islands for an air force base designed to provide an air link between Guam and Diego Garcia? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>778</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I shall have to seek the answer to the first question. However, if my memory serves me correctly, recently I gave an answer to the second question in reply to a question on notice. I shall check the records and let the honourable senator know, but I am quite certain that recently I answered a similar question which was placed on the notice paper. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LOCAL GOVERNMENT</title>
          <page.no>779</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JUH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DEVITT, Donald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DEVITT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I should like to pursue with the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Federal Affairs the question on local government which was first posed by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Douglas</inline> McClelland. 1 ask: What was the substantial basis of the Minister&#39;s frequently repeated statement that municipal rates would not need to rise by more than 5 per cent in the current rating year? What reason does the Minister give for the fact that these expectations represent only about 20 per cent and sometimes much less than the actual figure? Where did the Minister miscalculate? What can he do to correct the situation which has obviously got out of hand and which in many instances is now at an intolerable level? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The substantial source of the information was the federal body of the Local Government Association of Australia which made public, after the announcement of our $ 140m, the statement that as a result of that action it would not be necessary for local government to raise rates by more than 5 per cent. Therefore I regret that it was not necessary for me to miscalculate at all. Let me refresh the honourable senator&#39;s memory because he seems to be a little tender about the need for local government to put up its rates. In the 3 years in which the Labor Party was in office local government bodies increased their rates by the order of 30 per cent, 35 per cent and 40 per cent. This was due to inflation created by the Labor Government and the relative lack of funds from the Labor Government which meant that local government was not permitted to carry out its basic works without increasing rates. Therefore the history of the Labor Party in federal power is a tragic one for local government in that every local government body was forced to cut back its basic services and to put up its rates merely to survive. I am delighted to be able to say that, due to an increase in federal untied grants to local government, for the first time in 4 years there will be a major abatement in rate increases throughout local government and the Local Government Association has indicated that this will be so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SHIPBUILDING</title>
          <page.no>779</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>CAK</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RAE, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RAE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Minister for Industry and Commerce. Is it a fact that approval was recently given by the Minister and the Government for a bulk carrier to be built in Japan for Bulk ships Ltd, an Australian shipping company? Is it a fact that shortly thereafter Bulk ships Ltd entered into a contract to have the ship built in Australia by Carrington Slipways Pty Ltd at a price very much in excess of that quoted by the Japanese shipyard? Was that in any way as a result of any action by the Government in either withdrawing or making subject to conditions the approval which was given, or was it totally at the choice of the Australian company, Bulk ships Ltd. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It was natural that someone like myself and the Government would be trying to keep whatever shipbuilding activity we could within Australia. This was a contract to build a ship on behalf of Bulk ships Ltd by a Japanese shipyard. There was an Australian tender by Carrington Slipways Pty Ltd at Newcastle that was above the price that was able to be paid, allowing for the 35 per cent subsidy. I engaged in talks with the people at Carrington Slipways and others about this whole matter. After a period of negotiation between the buyer and the shipbuilder it was possible to have the ship built in Australia but in the 35 per cent subsidy range, with no delay in time or delivery. Much of the ability to do so was due to the company buying the ship, Carrington Slipways that is to build it and the unions concerned. It was very much to the credit of all those involved that they could get to the position where the building of the ship is to stay in Australia. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HEALTH INSURANCE</title>
          <page.no>779</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Cotton</inline> in his capacity as the Minister representing the Treasurer. Can the Minister assure the Senate that persons who have not lodged health insurance levy exemption forms with their employers by today, and who subsequently purchase private health insurance on or before 1 October, will not have to make an extended loan to the Taxation Office if the levy is deducted from their salary? Will the Minister also confirm that a working wife whose husband is paying the levy at the family rate will not have the levy deducted from her salary and be forced to make a similar loan to the Taxation Office? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not take upon myself personal tax liabilities on behalf of the Treasurer but I shall direct the question immediately to him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INDIAN OCEAN</title>
          <page.no>779</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>779</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1M</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRIMMER, Cyril</name>
              <name role="display">Senator PRIMMER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Has the Minister representing the Prime Minister seen the report in today&#39;s <inline font-style="italic">Canberra Times</inline> of the Prime Minister&#39;s address to the 61st Returned Services League Conference wherein the Prime Minister is reported to have said in part: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>If the concern we have expressed on the basis of evidence before us is misplaced- and the evidence is much more substantial than the public evidence . . . </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I ask: Does this mean that those public servants from the Joint Intelligence Organisation, the Department of Defence and the Department of Foreign Affairs who have been before the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence in recent months to give evidence on the Indian Ocean reference have withheld information from that Committee? </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I have not seen the report. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MEDIBANK PRIVATE</title>
          <page.no>780</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COLSTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is the Minister representing the Minister for Health aware that <inline font-weight="bold">Dr John</inline> Herron, the  Chairman  of the Australian Surgeons Association in Queensland and- if one can believe the Brisbane <inline font-style="italic">Telegraph-</inline> the leading contender to replace <inline font-weight="bold">Mr John</inline> Moore as Queensland State  President  of the Liberal Party, has publicly advised people not to join Medibank Private? In view of the widespread publicity given to <inline font-weight="bold">Dr Herron</inline> &#39;s attack on Medibank Private at a crucial time when all Australians are reaching their decisions regarding personal health insurance, will the Minister take this opportunity to repudiate <inline font-weight="bold">Dr Herron</inline> &#39;s warnings on what he has referred to as &#39;the long term implications&#39; of Medibank Private? Finally, will the Minister also advise the public of the advantages and security obtained by insuring with Medibank Private? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It would be understood that Medibank Private is in existence because this Government introduced it as an extension to the Medibank services. This Government supports the operations of Medibank Private. As an alternative, it gives choice to people if they wish to insure with private health funds. Both of these options are open. As I said earlier today in reply to a question, we should like as much authentic information as is possible to be available to the people of Australia. Persons in particular positions may hold personal views but I believe that the availability of substantial information to enable people to make their own personal choice is the way in which this Government should like to see this matter develop. I shall examine the other matters raised by the honourable senator and refer them to the Minister for Health. As far as the long-term implications of Medibank Private are concerned, it would be understood that it was this Government&#39;s policy to introduce Medibank Private insurance and we support its objectives. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TERTIARY EDUCATION ALLOWANCE SCHEME</title>
          <page.no>780</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>GD5</name.id>
              <electorate>ACT</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RYAN, Susan</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RYAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Education. It refers to a report in the <inline font-style="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</inline> yesterday- that is, Monday, 20 September 1976- that the Minister had informed the Liberal Party conference during the weekend that there would be no increase in tertiary allowances until the beginning of 1 977 and that there would be no retrospectivity. In view of the great interest in this matter by the thousands of students experiencing hardship under the present tertiary education allowance scheme levels, can the Minister confirm yesterday&#39;s report? Is the Minister prepared to expand at all on the information as reported? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-In answer first to the honourable senator&#39;s last question- yes, I am willing to expand on the matter. The reason why there is no increase in student allowances for 1976 is that the former Whitlam Government, of which she was a supporter, made a deliberate attempt and a deliberate decision not to increase tertiary allowances or other student allowances for the calendar year 1976. Any Labor senators who try to argue at this moment that there is a need to increase allowances for this year are in fact scolding their own former Government for a failure in its last Budget. I am willing to dilate upon that. It is true that in all statements on allowances the Fraser Government has made it clear that it will make decisions on this matter no later than early October which will apply from the calendar year 1977- the first calendar year for which this Fraser Government has responsibility. It very much regrets that the Whitlam Government used figures based on the June 1974 cost of living in determining its 1975 Tertiary Education Allowance Scheme allowances and then did nothing to up-date them for 1976. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PACKAGED BEER PRICE CUTTING</title>
          <page.no>780</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>780</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>4F4</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BUTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I ask the Minister representing the Attorney-General whether the Government has received advice from the Attorney-General&#39;s Department regarding the proposed legislation of the Victorian Parliament outlawing price cutting for packaged beer. I further ask the Minister whether such advice was received before the Prime Minister made a statement- I think it was described as a philosophical statement- regarding this matter on Sunday. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>781</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KUU</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MISSEN, Alan</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Missen</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It was about religion, of course. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>781</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>4F4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
                <name role="display">Senator BUTTON</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I am sorry; <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Missen</inline> corrects me. It was a religious statement. I did not know that he was so keen about the Prime Minister. The third pan of the question is this: Does the Minister regard it, as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Carrick</inline> has indicated in answer to other questions, as the responsibility of State governments to provide employment and encourage consumer spending? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not able to say what advice has been received from the Attorney-General&#39;s Department in respect of the consideration being given by the Victorian Government to some price fixing on beer. I understand from what I have read and heard that the matter is under consideration today in Melbourne. I think that probably the most appropriate thing for me to do is to say that this matter should certainly await any final decision in Victoria. However, I shall pass the matter on to the Attorney-General to see whether he is able to give any advice to the honourable senator who asked the question. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>781</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>4F4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
                <name role="display">Senator BUTTON</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I wish to ask a supplementary question, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President.</inline> As <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Durack</inline> indicated, the question was in 3 parts. He has failed to deal with the third part. I ask him to do so. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>781</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>8G4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
                <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I could not see the slightest relevance of that question to any ministerial responsibility I have. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>UNEMPLOYMENT FIGURES</title>
          <page.no>781</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>7V4</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GEORGES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Can the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations state whether the Government intends to continue the practice of issuing the recently reformed seasonally adjusted figures on unemployment? Is the Government aware that the figures issued using the new seasonal adjustment, which perhaps he can explain to me if he has time, show that the level of unemployment during August was 4.8 per cent? Was it the intention of the Government to show that this level of 4.8 per cent is the highest on record for the month of August? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government made it quite clear in a recent statement that it was ceasing to issue other than the actual figures for unemployment and that it certainly was not issuing seasonally adjusted figures, as was the previous practice. That statement was made by the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations following a meeting of the Ministers for Labour of all States, including the 3 Labor Party Ministers. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">The decision to cease the publishing of seasonally adjusted figures for unemployment was made following that meeting and was based on advice given by the Commonwealth Statistician that seasonally adjusted figures were not useful. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>TASMANIAN WOMEN&#39;S SHELTER</title>
          <page.no>781</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>UJ4</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WALTERS, Shirley</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WALTERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Has the attention of the Minister for Social Security been drawn to the statement by the Minister for Welfare in Tasmania that the Federal Government has avoided all its responsibilities in respect of the women &#39;s shelter in that State? Is this not a distortion of the facts, as the Government already has allocated $2.5m to the State for community health services and women&#39;s shelters come within that category? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is a fact that in this year&#39;s Budget the Government gave block grants to the State governments for projects which had been developed under the community health program. In giving block grants to the States the Commonwealth Government announced that it places emphasis on the development of community based health services. At the same time the Commonwealth Government expressed its concern to promote its policies in an environment where it wants Commonwealth involvement in the supervision of the expenditure of money by the States kept to a minimum. In the field of health care the Government believed that there was room for a major devolution of responsibility and, as a consequence, gave the block grants that I have mentioned. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>I understand that the Prime Minister has written to a State Premier advising him that the Commonwealth Government is concerned that assistance should be made available to those in distress, including women in crisis situations and those who use the women&#39;s refuges and other projects which have been developed under this program. I will check whether the Prime Minister has written to the Premier of Tasmania in the circumstances mentioned by the honourable senator to see whether the Premier of Tasmania is able to make available to those organisations which give assistance and support to those in distress and in emergency circumstances finance from the funds which were provided by the Commonwealth Government. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ASSISTANCE TO HOMELESS PERSONS</title>
          <page.no>781</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>781</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3A</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BROWN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Social Security. The Minister recently announced that since January 1976 $3m had been allocated in grants under the homeless persons assistance program. I understand that only $1.6m of the amount allocated was spent in the 1975-76 financial year. Does this mean that $ 1.4m of the 1976-77 Budget allocation of $2.8m already has been allocated to capital grants and recurrent operating costs? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not sure that I have at hand all the details mentioned in the question. I am aware that it was suggested that some funds provided in last year&#39;s Budget for this program were not used. I recall seeing today an answer to a question on notice dealing with this matter. It referred to the fact that during the last financial year some organisations which were in the process of developing plans for projects were not able to call on the funds. An explanation of the details of this program for last year will be provided in an answer to a question on notice. I shall obtain for the honourable senator some information on the specific matter that he has raised. The general explanation is that funds were available but the organisations concerned were not ready to call upon those funds before the end of the last financial year. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FREIGHT EQUALISATION SCHEME FOR TASMANIA</title>
          <page.no>782</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>CAK</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RAE, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RAE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport. I refer to the mid-year statement in which it was announced that a freight equalisation scheme would be introduced for Tasmania and to the fact that the northbound freight equalisation scheme is in operation already. Can the Minister indicate to the Senate when the other part of the scheme- that is, the southbound freight equalisation scheme- is likely to be able to be implemented? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I fully appreciate how significant the freight equalisation scheme can be to Tasmania, particularly when one considers that State&#39;s current difficulties concerning gross unemployment. I am aware that the northbound equalisation scheme is now operative. I have no details as to when the southbound equalisation scheme will apply. I shall pass the question on to my colleague the Minister for Transport and seek from him an answer to the question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MINING</title>
          <page.no>782</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEEFFE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister representing the Minister for National Resources aware of a mining warden&#39;s hearing at Gladstone on 24 November 1 975 concerning the proposal by the Darra Mining Company to mine for limestone and clay in the Mount Lar com district? Can the Minister verify that the Australian Legal Aid Office aided the mining protest group&#39;s objection financially? Have the mining warden&#39;s recommendations been released? If not, why not? Would it be true to say that the Queensland Government has suppressed the publication of the mining warden&#39;s recommendations because they recommend against mining? Can the Minister advise the Parliament of those recommendations as soon as possible? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Occasionally I hardly seem to be aware of national events let alone a hearing somewhere in a warden&#39;s court. No, I am not aware of it. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>782</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KPG</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- This Government is involved. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>782</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I only represent the Minister. The honourable senator came in here and asked me whether I am aware of something of that order and whether the Australian Legal Aid Office assisted people. No, I am not aware of those things and I do not see why I should be. He went on to make a series of allegations about the Queensland Government. If he wants information I will get it for him but if he wants to come here and ask rude and insulting questions about the Queensland Government I have no intention of helping him. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NAVAL RESERVE CADET UNITS</title>
          <page.no>782</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9I4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MESSNER, Tony</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MESSNER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is the Minister representing the Minister for Defence aware of public concern being expressed at reports that funds for the provision of buses for naval reserve cadet units will soon be reduced? Can the Minister confirm that this action is contemplated? If it is not contemplated, will he urge his colleague to make an early statement to that effect? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I shall seek the information for the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EAST TIMOR</title>
          <page.no>782</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>782</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>RG4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIETZELT, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIETZELT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Leader of the Government in the Senate who represents both the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Prime Minister. To some degree it follows upon questions asked by his colleagues <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Missen</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Kilgariff.</inline> Is the Minister aware that in today&#39;s Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline> it is stated that the Indonesian Foreign Minister, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Malik,</inline> claims that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Peacock,</inline> in April this year assured him that the Australian Government understood that Indonesia had to annex East Timor? Does the Minister know that the article also states that the Prime Minister&#39;s impending visit to Indonesia leads the Indonesian Government to believe that the Australian Government accepts Indonesia&#39;s position in East Timor? In view of the Minister&#39;s reaffirmation- I welcomed it, as I am sure the Opposition welcomed it- of the Government&#39;s stand for self-determination for the Timorese people, will the Minister ask the Prime Minister to repudiate <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Malik&#39;s</inline> statement and again ask the Indonesian Government to withdraw its troops from East Timor in accordance with the decisions of the United Nations? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I certainly shall pass the request along to the Prime Minister. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>RAINFALL MEASUREMENTS</title>
          <page.no>783</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>4F4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BUTTON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BUTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I  address my question to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster,</inline> the Minister for Science.  I  refer him to the fact that rainfall of 28 millimetres was measured in Melbourne yesterday.  I  wonder whether the Minister can tell us in simple terms how many millimetres there are in an inch. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role>Minister for Science</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-To be perfectly honest  I  would be unable to determine how much rain there was in inches. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>783</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>ISW</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Wriedt</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- What? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>783</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KAS</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I shall secure the information for him. Apparently <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wriedt</inline> knows. He was caught in the storm yesterday and asked me whether the eclipse had occurred. We seem to have some misunderstanding in the Senate. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>OIL REFINERY DISPUTE</title>
          <page.no>783</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MULVIHILL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations.  I  refer to the current oil dispute in New South Wales where some refinery operators work under a State award and are members of the Australian Workers Union while others in other refineries are covered by a Federal award and are in the Federated Engine Drivers and Firemens Association. The gist of my question is that the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commission is attempting to stop AWU members being heard in a State court. Am  I  to understand that in view of this Government&#39;s policy of creative federalism it is going to stand idly by or is it going to give unions the right to determine whether they remain under a State award or a Federal award? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Senator Mulvihill &#39;s question relates to one of the most vexed problems in the conciliation and arbitration area.  I  shall pass the question on to the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations and endeavour to obtain an early reply for him. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FUNDS FOR ABORIGINES</title>
          <page.no>783</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K6F</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAVANAGH, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CAVANAGH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs. In the Budget Speech the Treasurer promised more money for Aboriginal affairs after consideration of the Hay report and inquiries. As any additional expenditure would need the approval of this Parliament, will the Minister, in order to get development restarted in Aboriginal affairs, speed up consideration of the report and make a statement indicating that the necessary appropriation will be permitted this session and this year? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Department of Aboriginal Affairs and a committee which is looking at matters with regard to projects for Aborigines are working as speedily as possible to determine programs which will be able to be developed for Aborigines. I agree with the honourable senator that it is necessary to have the approval of this Parliament for expenditure. I draw his attention to the Treasurer&#39;s Advance which may be used for new projects and to the fact that many projects at present in the Department&#39;s budget will enable a great deal to be achieved immediately. Those new programs which are able to be developed or those housing associations which are worthy of special consideration are certainly being treated as matters of urgency. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING COMMISSION</title>
          <page.no>783</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COLSTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is the Minister representing the Minister for Post and Telecommunications aware that it has been reported that at last Wednesday&#39;s joint Government parties meeting in Queensland, during discussions on the Cedar Bay raid, a senior Liberal backbencher moved that the Queensland Government hold an inquiry into the Australian Broadcasting Commission for alleged bias against the police and that the move was postponed for further consideration? While I appreciate that a newspaper report of an incident at a party meeting could be lacking in accuracy and while I assume that the Minister would not contemplate discussing matters emanating from a closed party meeting will he confirm that a State government has no jurisdiction over the affairs of the ABC and that the Federal Government would never condone or allow a State government to initiate such an inquiry? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>783</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-As to the first part of the question, I have no knowledge of what may or may not have gone on in a party room or in a joint party room in a State parliament, nor would </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">I comment if I had. I am delighted that there should be some seeking of information as to jurisdiction over the Australian Broadcasting Commission, because it is now perfectly clear that what the Australian Labor Party had in view last Wednesday was not proven by the Thursday. I am able to tell the honourable senator that the Australian Broadcasting Commission is a statutory corporation and the creature of Federal legislation. Its legislative origin and its head of power are Federal matters. Therefore there would be no State intervention in the Commission. I know nothing about the substance of the honourable senator&#39;s question. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MEDIBANK LEVY: LONE PARENTS</title>
          <page.no>784</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3T</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Donald Newton</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DONALD CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Will the Minister representing the Treasurer ask the Treasurer to advise senators and the public of the level of income at which a lone parent is required to pay the Medibank levy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Yes, I shall. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEVALUATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN DOLLAR</title>
          <page.no>784</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry aware that leading spokesmen for primary industry stated in Canberra last week that unless the Government devalued the currency without delay Australian primary industry would be in a desperate situation by early 1977? Can the Minister say whether any promises were made to primary industry representatives in Canberra last week about the question of devaluation being under consideration by both the Australian and New Zealand governments? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-If it has been said once, it has been said many times. It is not on. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>FEDERALISM POLICY</title>
          <page.no>784</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WALSH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. It refers to widespread Press reports in the last 2 days that the Government has blocked <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Charles</inline> Court&#39;s attempts to raise overseas loans outside the Loan Council and has threatened the Government of Victoria with the Trade Practices Act? Are these reports incorrect? If not, has the Government realised the folly of the fragmentation of economic power, and has it abandoned the notions of State autonomy which are central to its federalism policy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>784</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I do not know from where <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Walsh</inline> gets all these imaginings. He must read some obscure newspapers. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Walsh</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The <inline font-style="italic">West Australian.</inline></para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-That is a fairly obscure newspaper. I do not even read it myself. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>7V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Georges</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- You will not even get your funeral notice in it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-I should hate to get my funeral notice in it because some of you fellows might support a motion of condolence, and I could not bear the hypocrisy, even in another place. These sorts of allegations are always floating around. As I said before, I am surprised that with all the money that the Government spends on providing research assistance, honourable senators cannot come up with something original. If there should be a newspaper strike in this country for 48 hours we would not have a question in the Parliament for a week. I suggest that honourable senators opposite do a little bit of original work. I know that most of their questions are devised by their research assistants from reading newspapers but, for goodness&#39; sake, they should show a little bit of originality and start to earn the money which they think they deserve. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>7V4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GEORGES, George</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Georges</name>
              </talker>
              <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">- Mr President,</inline>I rise to order. I think that those last remarks of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers</inline> were insulting to all honourable senators and, being sensitive, I take the insult personally. I ask that he withdraw the remarks because he is Leader of the Government in the Senate and Minister for Administrative Services, and we take very much to heart the criticisms that he makes of his fellow parliamentarians. Recently he has been doing that constantly and on this occasion I suggest that he withdraw those disparaging remarks. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>784</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>DV4</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- If the honourable senator takes offence at the remarks I shall certainly withdraw them. Actually, I thought I was flattering him. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ASSENT TO BILLS</title>
        <page.no>784</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Assent to the following Bills reported: </para>
      <quote>
        <para class="block">Loan Bill (No. 3) 1976 </para>
        <para>Administrative Changes (Consequential Provisions) Bill 1976 </para>
        <para>Aged Persons Hostels Amendment Bill 1976 Foreign Takeovers Amendment Bill 1976 Telecommunications Amendment Bill 1976 </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE</title>
        <page.no>784</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>784</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>DV4</name.id>
            <electorate>Western AustraliaMinister for Administrative Services</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators I present details of special Royal Australian Air Force flights for the period 15 July 1976 to 31 August 1976. This supplements the information I presented to the Senate last Wednesday, 15 September. Due to the limited number available, reference copies of this document have been placed in the Senate Records Office and the Parliamentary Library. I hope that sufficient copies can be made available for members of Senate Estimates Committee A, who have a particular interest in this matter. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I seek leave to move a motion in respect of the paper presented by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers.</inline></para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>785</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <motion>
          <para class="block">That the Senate take note of the paper. </para>
        </motion>
        <para class="block">I seek leave to continue my remarks. </para>
        <para class="block">Leave granted; debate adjourned. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY</title>
        <page.no>785</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>2U4</name.id>
            <electorate>New South Wales Minister for Education</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
            <name role="display">Senator CARRICK</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators and pursuant to section 33 of the Australian National University Act 1946 I present the report of the Council of the Australian National University for the calendar year 1975. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEPARTMENT OF SOCIAL SECURITY</title>
        <page.no>785</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>C7D</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Pursuant to section 148 of the Social Services Act 1947 I present the annual report of the Department of Social Security for the year ended 30 June 1976. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>9V4</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GRIMES</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I seek leave to move a motion. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>785</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GRIMES</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <motion>
          <para class="block">That the Senate take note of the paper. </para>
        </motion>
        <para class="block">I seek leave to continue my remarks. </para>
        <para class="block">Leave granted; debate adjourned. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SHIPBUILDING</title>
        <page.no>785</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>8G4</name.id>
            <electorate>Western AustraliaMinister for Repatriation</electorate>
            <party>LP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
            <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators I present the Industries Assistance Commission report on shipbuilding dated 20 September 1976. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K1Y</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia </electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">BISHOP, Reginald</name>
            <name role="display">Senator BISHOP</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-I seek leave to move a motion. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>785</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>785</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1Y</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BISHOP, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BISHOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <motion>
          <para>That the Senate take note of the paper. </para>
        </motion>
        <para class="block">I am sorry to have to comment upon the fact that, as I understand it, neither the Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Wriedt),</inline> his <inline font-weight="bold">Deputy (Senator Keeffe)</inline> nor any of the shadow Ministers have been given a copy of the report. It is a very important report to which everybody in the Senate looked forward because it concerns the position of shipbuilding in South Australia, Newcastle and elsewhere. I presume that this is the Industries Assistance Commission report on shipbuilding which was expected to come down this week. Nobody on this side of the chamber knows what recommendations are contained in the report; nor do we know what action the Government intends to take in relation to the recommendations of the Industries Assistance Commission. I hoped that there would be some statement by the Minister for Repatriation <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Durack).</inline> I expect that in the other place the shadow Minister was told about the matter and that some statement was made by the Government in relation to the recommendations. </para>
        <para>As is well known, the industry in my State of South Australia is likely to close down within a couple of years. In addition, I understand that the Premier of South Australia, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Dunstan,</inline> has made some positive recommendations to the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Malcolm Fraser)</inline> and others. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Cotton</inline> admitted that. I understand that since that time the Premier of New South Wales has made important contributing recommendations affecting shipbuilding. I hope that if the Minister can add something to the report he will do so at this stage. I seek leave to continue my remarks later. </para>
        <para>Leave granted. </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator DURACK</inline>(Western AustraliaMinister for Repatriation)- I seek leave to make a short statement. </para>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>785</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>785</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It was not the intention of the Government to make any statement in relation to the report today. The report was tabled as soon as it was received. For the reasons <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bishop</inline> has indicated, the importance of the report dictated that. But when a report is simply tabled it is not the practice for a copy of the report to be made available to the Opposition within a period of time prior to the tabling of that report. If the report had been accompanied by a statement, that would have been done. I would have been concerned had that not been done. But that is not the practice in these circumstances. I appreciate the importance of the matter. I certainly will draw <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bishop&#39;s</inline> remarks to the attention of the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Howard),</inline> whom I represent. No doubt the Government will make an early statement in regard to the matter. I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <motion>
          <para>That the resumption of the debate be made an order of the day for the next day of sitting. </para>
        </motion>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTE OF MARINE SCIENCE</title>
        <page.no>786</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>786</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KAS</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NCP/NP</party>
            <role>Minister for Science</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WEBSTER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of honourable senators I lay upon the table explanatory notes relating to the estimates of expenditure for 1976-77 for the Australian Institute of Marine Science. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SENATE ESTIMATES COMMITTEES</title>
        <page.no>786</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>786</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate>Western AustraliaLeader of the Government in the Senate</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WITHERS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <motion>
            <para>That the sitting of the Senate be suspended until 10. IS p.m., or such time as the  President  may take the chair, to enable Estimates Committees De and F to meet. </para>
          </motion>
          <para class="block">Estimates Committee D will meet in the Senate Chamber; Estimates Committee E will meet in Senate committee room No. 5; and Estimates Committee F will meet in Senate committee room No. 3. </para>
          <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
          <para>Sitting suspended from 3.43 to 10.15 p.m. </para>
        </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>FAMILY LAW AMENDMENT BILL (No. 2) 1976</title>
        <page.no>786</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Durack)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>786</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>786</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate>Western AustraliaMinister for Repatriation</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DURACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <motion>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </motion>
          <para class="block">I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>786</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows:</inline>
          </para>
          <para>The purpose of this Bill is to make amendments to the Family Law Act 1975. Honourable senators will recall that a number of amendments were made to the Act by the Family Law </para>
          <para class="block">Amendment Act 1 976, which was passed by Parliament in the last sittings. The main purpose of this much shorter Bill is to amend the Act to enable regulations to be made imposing court fees, as announced by the Treasurer <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr Lynch)</inline> in the Budget Speech. The fee to be imposed will be $60 payable on the filing of each application for divorce from 1 October. Under the Budget proposals, no fees will be payable in respect of any ancillary applications such as maintenance or custody applications. The Bill does not itself specify the amount of the fee. Clause 7 enables the fee to be prescribed by regulations. </para>
          <para>The Government decided to impose this fee in order to provide funds which will contribute to meeting the rising cost of legal aid. Some 80 per cent of Commonwealth funds appropriated for legal aid matters referred to private practitioners is in respect of matters arising under the Family Law Act. In this year&#39;s Budget, a total of $9.5m has been provided for payment to the private profession for legal aid. Approximately 80 per cent of this figure therefore will represent payments for family law legal aid. The increased expenditure allowed in this year&#39;s Budget for legal aid, other than Aboriginal legal aid, is $3.7m. The Government regards it as reasonable that applicants for dissolution who are able to do so should be required to pay a fee of $60. It is normal to pay a fee for being married, sometimes in excess of $30. Having in mind the facilities provided by the Family Court, a fee of $60 is not regarded as excessive. The proposed amount of $60 is also in line with the amount of fees formerly imposed under the Matrimonial Causes Act when due allowance is made for price movements since they were abolished in 1973. The total expected to be derived from these fees is $2.8m over a full year. This may be compared with $ 16.2m which is the total estimated Commonwealth expenditure on legal aid, other than Aboriginal legal aid, over the same period. It is anticipated that in the present financial year the total number of divorce applications will be 48 000. Because the fee is a once-only imposition, it is not expected that the comparative cost of collecting it will be large. </para>
          <para>The Bill includes a provision permitting the regulations to provide for exempting persons from paying the fee. It is proposed that the regulations will provide for automatic exemption from payment of the fee where a person produces satisfactory evidence that he or she is receiving legal aid for the divorce proceedings from a Commonwealth, State or Territory legal aid scheme. Registrars of courts will also have power to exempt payment where they are satisfied that it would impose hardship on an applicant. Honourable senators will, of course, have the usual opportunity to scrutinise regulations made under the provisions of the Bill. In the case of applications filed in a State Family Court -at the moment only the Family Court of Western Australia- the Bill provides that the fees are to be paid to the State. This has been done for administrative convenience so that the fees collected will not constitute Commonwealth revenue and, as such, have to be subject to Commonwealth Treasury and audit supervision. Negotiations are being undertaken with the Western Australian Government for adjustments to be made between the 2 governments to take account of the receipt of this additional revenue by Western Australia. </para>
          <para>The remaining provisions of the Bill are of a clarifying or formal nature. Recent litigation has thrown some doubt on the extent of the provision enabling a court, in special circumstances, to make a maintenance or custody order in respect of a child who has been put into care under State welfare legislation. The Bill clarifies the relevant provision. At the request of Western Australia, the Bill will enable the Commonwealth Attorney-General to delegate his power of intervention in proceedings to the Attorney-General of a State having a State Family Court. </para>
          <para>The proposed amendment to section 105 will facilitate the enforcement of court orders, particularly maintenance orders. This section enables any court to enforce an order made under the Act by any other court, but a prerequisite to the enforcement of an order is the registration of the order. A problem arises where a person is arrested in, say, Townsville, on a warrant issued in Sydney. The court in Townsville cannot deal with the matter until the order has been registered, and this may take some days. What is needed is a provision whereby the person arrested in Townsville can be released on bail pending the registration of the order. The amendment would enable the regulations to make a suitable provision. Honourable senators will recognise that the number and complexity of the amendments contained in this Bill are not great, and I therefore ask them to give their early and speedy consideration to it. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Grimes)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>HEALTH INSURANCE LEVY ASSESSMENT BILL (No. 2) 1976</title>
        <page.no>787</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <para>Bill (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Guilfoyle)</inline> read a first time. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Second Reading</title>
          <page.no>787</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>787</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Social Security</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GUILFOYLE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I move: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <motion>
            <para>That the Bill be now read a second time. </para>
          </motion>
          <para class="block">I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline></para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>787</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="italic">
            <inline font-style="italic">The speech read as follows:</inline>
          </para>
          <para>This Bill, together with another that I shall introduce shortly, seeks Parliament&#39;s agreement to some changes in the health insurance levy arrangements that were approved earlier this year. The essential features of the arrangements are being retained but some desirable reforms are proposed. There is to be a limit- or as it has come to be called, a ceiling- on the amount of levy payable. This will replace the earlier arrangement under which people had to pay a premium to Medibank if they wished to set a limit on their contributions towards standard Medibank benefits. The Bill will also provide an authority to make regulations to confer exemptions from the levy. This authority will be exercised to exempt pensioners who are entitled to pensioner health benefits. Such people will thus be given an exemption comparable to that provided for repatriation beneficiaries and members of the defence forces. It is also proposed by the Bill to remove the requirement under the earlier arrangements for private insurance funds to give their contributors end-of-year certificates for lodgment with income tax returns. </para>
          <para>As honourable senators know, the levy is to be imposed at a basic rate of 2.5 per cent of taxable income. For this year, 1976-77, the levy will apply only for the last 9 months of the year, so that the effective rate will be 1.875 per cent instead of 2.5 per cent. It follows that the maximum amounts of levy payable will be reduced by one-quarter for 1976-77. We have set the maximum amount- the ceiling- on a full year basis at $300 for a taxpayer with dependants and $150 for a person who has no dependants. These amounts will be reduced for 1976-77 to $225 and $112.50 respectively. Under the original arrangements, anyone who wished to pay no more than this towards standard Medibank benefits had to pay a premium to Medibank. If the premium was paid the person was exempt from the levy. On re-examination, this arrangement was found not to be the best available. </para>
          <para>For example, under it people had to commit themselves at the beginning of a year, and before they knew what their income for the year would be, whether to pay the premium or stay subject to the levy. By providing a ceiling on the levy itself, the amount of anyone&#39;s levy liability is fixed by what his or her income for the year turns out to be. Where a husband and wife are both taxpayers, it is proposed that their individual levy liabilities are not, in total, to exceed the family ceiling of $300. The husband will be assessed to levy on the basis of his own taxable income, but subject to the ceiling of $300. The levy on the wife&#39;s separate taxable income will be reduced, or eliminated, so far as necessary to ensure that her liability does not take the total liability of the couple above $300. The levy ceilings will be appropriately reduced for defence personnel and repatriation beneficiaries who have dependants who are not entitled under defence or repatriation arrangements to free medical treatment. Thus, to conclude my introductory references to the ceiling arrangements, a serviceman with a family will pay no more levy than $ 1 50. </para>
          <para>In introducing the levy we have been anxious to protect the position of low income earners. We have freed the levy, or have given a reduction in levy, to people whose taxable incomes are below the points where, ordinarily, income tax becomes payable. For example, people whose only income is the age pension are not called on to pay levy. As already indicated, however, levy relief for pensioners is to go further than that. Pensioners who have an entitlement to pensioners health benefits will, like people covered by repatriation and Defence Force arrangements, be freed from the levy. Age pensioners entitled to pensioner fringe benefits, as well as repatriation beneficiaries are Service personnel, will thus continue to receive the special consideration that has long been extended to them in the field of health care. </para>
          <para>In deciding to dispense with the requirement that private insurance funds issue levy relief certificates we accepted their point about the cost burden that this would put on some funds and, indirectly, their contributors. People who have opted for private insurance will instead make a claim to that effect on their annual tax returns. The private funds will be expected to provide the Taxation Office with information to check such claims, and the Bills make that quite clear. There will be sanctions against people who falsely claim to be privately insured. Other parts of this Bill will result in <inline font-style="italic">de facto</inline> spouses being treated in the same way for levy purposes as legally married spouses. This is, of course, the case for certain income tax purposes. </para>
          <para>These are the main features of the Bills, the ceiling arrangements being dealt with in the Bill I am about to introduce and the other matters being the subject of this Bill. The Bill also makes changes of a more technical kind, which I do not think I need discuss in this introductory speech. A memorandum explaining the Bill in detail is being circulated to honourable senators. I commend the Bill to the Senate. </para>
          <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Grimes)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>HEALTH INSURANCE LEVY BILL</title>
        <page.no>788</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>(No.  2) 1976 </para>
      <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives. </para>
      <para>Ordered that the Bill may be taken through all its stages without delay. </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>First Reading</title>
          <page.no>788</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Guilfoyle)</inline> proposed: </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Bill be now read a first time. </para>
        </quote>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>788</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I want to raise again a matter I have raised many times in this chamber, that is, the provision of a television service for Leigh Creek in South Australia. I think the last time I raised it was during the debate on Appropriation Bill (No. 3) 1975-76 on 25 May this year. I thought that my remarks on that occasion would have settled the matter for good because I was under the impression then that the residents of Leigh Creek were going to be provided with a television service. But I was disturbed to have drawn to my attention over the weekend an article which appeared on 1 5 September in the <inline font-style="italic">Transcontinental,</inline> which is a newspaper printed at Port Augusta in South Australia. The article was headed: &#39;Just so much politics&#39;. It read: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>The suggestion made by the Premier that the State Government &#39;would go it alone&#39; in relation to providing a television service to Leigh Creek was just so much politics, said <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> this week. </para>
            <para>He said advice had been received from the State Manager of Telecom Australia that the Leigh Creek Station would commence operation by the end of April 1977. </para>
            <para>The Commonwealth Government promised it would make funds available, and as a result of their undertaking, Leigh Creek would get television &#39;, said <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop.</inline></para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline>is endeavouring to rehash something of which we have been aware since the Labor Party was in government, that is, that Leigh Creek was going to get television. When <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Douglas</inline> McClelland was the Minister for the Media he gave that undertaking after receiving many deputations from myself, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Cameron</inline> and Laurie Wallis, the honourable member for Grey. Everything was agreed to while we were in government. Of course, we got the sack at a minute&#39;s notice and were not able to go ahead with the venture at that stage. </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline>is a past master at this kind of thing. During the election campaign I had occasion to phone him after he had put out a Press release. I told him that he reminded me of a cuckoo; he waited until a bird built a nest and then he crawled into it to lay a rotten egg. That is just what he did. I took the opportunity during the debate on an Appropriation Bill in this Parliament to quote chapter and verse for the work that had been done by various members of Parliament to bring about a television service for Leigh Creek. I thought that I had been very charitable to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> in my remarks on that occasion because I did refer to what he had done in the years gone by. </para>
          <para>I want to repeat what I said in this chamber on 25 May during the debate on Appropriation Bill (No. 3). My speech is reported at page 1890 of Senate <inline font-style="italic">Hansard</inline> of that day and at page 1 89 1 my remarks about a television service for Leigh Creek are recorded. I had to go through chapter and verse to put on record the work that had been done by Labor supporters of a Labor government to ensure that the people of Leigh Creek had a television service. I intend at this stage to repeat a lot of what I said because apparently the work that was done has not yet sunk into the mind of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> and he is still trying to claim credit for this television service. This is quite obvious from his Press statement which stated that the Commonwealth Government promised it would make funds available. He did not go on to say that it was the Commonwealth Labor Government that made that promise after many months of hard work. He is trying to claim credit for the present Government. As I pointed out on 25 May, the Prime Minister of the day, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Fraser,</inline> had put out a Press statement indicating that Leigh Creek was going to be axed. That is why I rise to bring the matter again to the attention of the Senate. A lot of hard work had to go on to get this matter put back on the stocks. </para>
          <para>During the election campaign <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Withers</inline> put out a Press statement- I shall quote from it before I finish my speech- aimed at winning the support of many people in the far northern areas. He said in it that they were going to get television. As <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O</inline> &#39;Byrne points out, this had similar ramifications to the telegram sent by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Ellicott</inline> except that it did not go quite so far. </para>
          <para class="block">However, it did say that television was promised and it gave certain facts which I will relate later. When the cut came in funds for broadcasting the residents of Leigh Creek had to go through the trauma again. The possibility of television for Leigh Creek was to be pushed again into limbo. These are the sorts of promises made by honourable senators opposite. When I rose on 25 May I had need to refer to a promise made by the Prime Minister in his policy speech. I quote from the <inline font-style="italic">Hansard</inline> record what the Prime Minister said: </para>
          <quote>
            <para>Australia needs a government of integrity and responsibility. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">All honourable senators on this side agree that Australia does need a government with those qualifications. It also needs senators with integrity and responsibility and that is the reason why I rose tonight. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> is wide of the mark in that respect. He made that statement and did not give credit to the previous Government for laying the foundations for television at Leigh Creek. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>789</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KAS</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I take a point of order. The honourable senator implied that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> lacked integrity and- what was your other word? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>789</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
                <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- You are taking the point of order. I am not going to help you. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>789</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KAS</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It is sufficient that any honourable senator should make a comment such as that but one would expect it to come from <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLaren.</inline> I ask that he withdraw his remark about my friend. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>789</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>
              <inline font-weight="bold">- Senator McLaren</inline>did not reflect in any way upon a fellow senator and I ask him to continue. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>789</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
                <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I did not think that I reflected on him but I did quote a passage from the Prime Minister&#39;s speech during the election campaign in which he said: &#39;Australia needs a government of integrity and responsibility&#39;. I went on to say that we should also have senators opposite with the same qualifications and I felt that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> was running far wide of that mark when he issued a recent Press statement. If <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster</inline> thinks that in that way I reflect on <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> then so be it, but I did not think that was the case. If I were to take on <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster</inline> and go back through some of the old copies of <inline font-style="italic">Hansard</inline> since I have been in this place- I might do this one of these days- I could reveal some very derogatory remarks and reflections on members of this Party and in particular on the former Prime Minister. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>790</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Order! I ask you to carry on your speech without referring to the matters to which you are now referring. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>790</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
                <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Until I was rudely interrupted by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster</inline> I was trying to lay the foundation for what I am going to say about what had happened and all the problems that had arisen in connection with getting a television service for Leigh Creek. I am going to quote from <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> &#39;s Press statements to show how he has endeavoured to imitate a cuckoo, to wait until somebody else does the work of building the nest and then he gets into it to lay the egg. I told him that personally. He issued a Press statement on 15 September and yesterday the Minister - </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>790</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KKD</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">JESSOP, Donald</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Jessop</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have not read it yet. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>790</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
                <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Well, I have read it for the honourable senator. The editor of the <inline font-style="italic">Transcontinental</inline> will not be too pleased when he reads the statement by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Jessop</inline> that he sent Press releases expecting them to be published in that newspaper and then admitted in this Parliament that he did not read the paper. That does not say much for what he thinks of the <inline font-style="italic">Transcontinental</inline> its editor. Yesterday <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Eric</inline> Robinson, the Minister for Post and Telecommunications, issued another statement. It was a repeat, just like <inline font-style="italic">Blue Hills.</inline> It appears that this matter goes on forever. I shall read this Press statement by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Robinson.</inline> It is headed &#39;Television for Leigh Creek&#39; and states: </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <quote>
            <para>The Minister for Post and Telecommunications, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Eric</inline> L. Robinson, announced today that Leigh Creek in South Australia would be given a television service. </para>
            <para>
              <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Robinson</inline>said the station would be constructed by Telecom Australia and would be operated by the Electricity Trust of South Australia. Recorded programs are to be provided by the Australian Broadcasting Commission. </para>
            <para>The Minister said that the station would be established by Commonwealth Government funds with the assistance of a contribution of $65,000 from the Electricity Trust of South Australia. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>Debate interrupted. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>790</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Use of Taxis in Australian Capital Territory </para>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>790</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Order! In accordance with the sessional order relating to the adjournment of the Senate, I formally put the question: </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>790</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">- Mr President,</inline>I shall not be infringing upon Standing Orders because I have another matter that I wish to raise in this debate on the motion for the adjournment of the Senate. It is a matter which I raised here in the adjournment debate on 15 September relating to the use of taxi cabs in the Australian Capital Territory in lieu of Commonwealth Government cars. I have noticed that it is a practice on the part of Ministers in this Government to write letters in answer to questions raised in relation to government policy so that in many cases there is no record in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline> In this case I have to take the time of the Senate to have recorded in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard</inline> a letter I received from <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Webster,</inline> the Minister for Science, in response to a question I asked him during the adjournment debate in respect of the use of taxi cabs in the Australian Capital Territory. This letter came from the Minister for Science, Parliament House, Canberra, and is dated 15 September. It states: </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para class="block">Dear <inline font-weight="bold">Senator,</inline></para>
          <para>I have received further information from the Department of the Capital Territory in response to matters raised by you in the Senate adjournment debate on 25 August 1 976. </para>
          <para>A copy is attached. </para>
          <para>Yours sincerely, </para>
          <list type="upperalpha-dotted">
            <item label="J.">
              <para>J. WEBSTER </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">The answer covers 3 pages and I ask that they be incorporated in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard</inline> rather than that I take up the time of the Senate in reading them. </para>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>790</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Is leave granted? There being no objection, leave is granted. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para class="italic">
          <inline font-style="italic">The statement read as follows:</inline>
        </para>
        <quote>
          <para>ANSWERS AND RESPONSES TO MATTERS RAISED DURING THE SENATE ADJOURNMENT DEBATE ON 25 AUGUST 1976 </para>
          <para>DEPARTMENT OF THE CAPITAL TERRITORY </para>
          <para>USE OF TAXIS IN LIEU OF COMMONWEALTH CARS </para>
          <para class="block">
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLaren</inline>
          </para>
          <para class="block">Hansard Reference- Pages 337 to 339 </para>
          <para class="block">Comment  . . it would appear that 20 per cent of the Commonwealth fleet- that is, 30 out of 1 50 vehicles- is off the road for service. This seems to be a very large proportion. &#39; </para>
          <para class="block">Response </para>
          <para>There are 151 vehicles in the Ministerial and Passenger Car Fleet. Whilst it is true that an average of 20 per cent or 30 of these vehicles are off the road, this is not an unreasonable figure. About 15 of these vehicles are off the road for periodic servicing and the balance are under-going repairs for mechanical breakdown or accident damage. </para>
          <para class="block">Question </para>
          <para>I would like clarification of the amount of $ 1 8,4 1 6 paid for the hire of taxis during May 1976. In particular I would like to know whether that figure includes any amount for bookwork and accounting. </para>
          <para>Answer</para>
        <para>The hire charge to clients for the use of taxis/hire cars in May 1 976 was $18,4 1 6 and was comprised of: </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_18_0.jpg" />
        </para>
          <para>Comment</para>
        <para>Although we are told of the cost of hiring taxis, there is no mention of the cost of hire cars . . . &#39; </para>
          <para>Response</para>
        <para>The cost of hire cars for the month of May 1976 was included in the figures provided. </para>
          <para>Question</para>
        <para>Does the Department insist that the same rest requirements between shifts which apply to its own drivers apply also to taxi drivers who carry Members of Parliament and Public Servants? </para>
          <para>Answer</para>
        <para>The Department, when it uses taxis to supplement the number of Commonwealth cars available, does not hire particular vehicles. It requests the taxi company to provide transport for a certain number of specified trips so it is thus the responsibility of the taxi company to establish the fitness of drivers selected. </para>
          <para>Question</para>
        <para>How many Ministers are using taxis to be conveyed to their home when the House gets up at night? </para>
          <para>Answer</para>
        <para>Very few Ministers use taxis to travel to their residence after the House rises. Ministers are entitled to use the &#39;V (VIP) service of chauffeur driven Ford LTD &#39;s and Galaxies. </para>
          <para>Comment</para>
        <list type="lowerroman-dotted">
          <item label=".">
            <para>. there are 151 vehicles with 111 active drivers. Thirty of the vehicles are idle in the garage awaiting service. That still leaves another 10 cars available, according to those figures, to be used at any period of time if the drivers are available.&#39; </para>
          </item>
        </list>
          <para>Response</para>
        <para>It is true that there are some ten Commonwealth cars that are not used on a regular basis. The cars are held in reserve so that drivers who log their cars in either for service or repair, have a reserve vehicle. </para>
          <para>Comment</para>
        <para>If the Government wants to keep up the morale of Government drivers surely if there is any overtime available they are the people to whom it should be given; not drivers of taxis . . . &#39; </para>
          <para>Response</para>
        <para>The Department does give overtime to car drivers whenever practicable. Taxis are normally only used when demands exceed capacity. </para>
        <para class="block">Senators McLaren and Keeffe </para>
          <para>Hansard References- Pages 338 and 339</para>
          <para>Comment</para>
        <para class="block">The senators commented on the transfer of car drivers back to the bus fleet. </para>
          <para>Response</para>
        <para>Commonwealth car drivers normally join the Department initially as bus drivers and are transferred at a later date to drive Commonwealth cars. Because of staff ceilings, there is a need to deploy staff to meet particular demands. They are not involuntarily transferred back to bus driving. </para>
		</quote>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>791</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLAREN, Geoffrey</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLAREN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I thank the Senate for its courtesy. That concludes my remarks. </para>
          </talk.start>
          </continue>
		  <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
        </speech>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>791</page.no>
        <time.stamp>22:32:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para>Senate adjourned at 10.32 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
  <answers.to.questions>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</title>
        <page.no>792</page.no>
        <type>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="block">The following answers to questions were circulated: </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Medical Benefits Costs (Question No. 718)</title>
          <page.no>792</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Grimes</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>How much of the estimated rise in medical benefits costs for 1976-77, compared with 1975-76, is due to (a) an increase in the number of services rendered and (b) increased rates of medical benefits. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="loweralpha">
            <item label="(a)">
              <para>In estimating total medical benefits costs for 1976-77 an allowance for an increase of approximately 4.5 per cent in the total cost of services was made to cover increases in population and the number of services per person covered. Against this increase were offset reductions in the cost for services which will not be eligible for medical benefits as a consequence of the changes made in the health insurance arrangements to apply from 1 October 1976, e.g., services to overseas visitors to Australia, workers compensation, motor vehicle third party insurance. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(b)">
              <para>The increases in the rates of benefits for medical services and optometric al consultation to apply from 1 January 1977, and for which benefits are claimed and paid in 1 976-77, are estimated to cost $22m. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Medical Benefits Services (Question No. 719)</title>
          <page.no>792</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Grimes</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>What estimates had the Government made in Budget forecasts for 1976-77 of: </para>
            <list type="loweralpha">
              <item label="(a)">
                <para>the number of services rendered; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(b)">
                <para>the value of benefits for these services; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(c)">
                <para>the number of services Medibank would have paid; and </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(d">
                <para>) the value of the services Medibank would have paid. </para>
              </item>
            </list>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="loweralpha">
            <item label="(a)">
              <para>and (c). At the time of preparing figures for the 1976-77 Budget, no estimates were made of the number of services rendered, or the number of services Medibank would have paid, the estimates being based on the amounts of medical benefits expected to be paid, taking into account the various factors which would vary these amounts as compared with the previous year. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(b)">
              <para>and (d). On the basis that medical benefits costs for 1976-77 refer to services rendered in that year (whether or not benefits are claimed and paid in that year), the total value of medical benefits was estimated as being $907m. Of this amount it was estimated that Medibank would be liable to pay benefits of $666m for these services whether claimed in 1976-77, or subsequently, and the registered medical benefits insurance organisations $241m. It was estimated that medical benefits, including liability for benefits carried forward from 1975-76 and excluding carry forward into 1977-78, of $7 10m would be paid by Medibank in 1976-77, and $ 1 86m for registered organisations. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Mineral Deposits (Question No. 740)</title>
          <page.no>792</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for National Resources, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What are the main economic minerals found in the following mineral provinces: (a) Kimberly, (b) Tennant Creek, (c) Mt Isa-Cloncurry, (d) Charters Towers, (e) Pilbara, (f) Amadeus Basin, (g) Alligator River, (h) West more land Mcarthur River, (i) Georgetown, (j) Chillagoe Herbert on, and (k) Bowen Basin. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What are the ore reserves for individual mineral deposits in each of these provinces, for each of the main prospective minerals found in each province. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>What company, or group of companies, owns or controls the various deposits in the various mineral provinces. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(4)">
              <para>What deposits have reached, or will reach, by 1977, the production stage. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(5)">
              <para>What are the main problems holding back the development of deposits in each province. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>792</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for National Resources has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) and (2)I refer you to the map series &#39;Atlas of Australian Resources- Mineral Deposits&#39;, which is available in the Parliamentary Library and to the Australian Institute of Mining and Metallurgy Monograph Series, which can be obtained for you by the Parliamentary Library. The relevant monographs are: </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>No. 5- Economic Geology of Australia and Papua New Guinea- 1 . Metals edited by C. L. Knight (1975) </para>
          <para>No. 6- Economic Geology of Australia and Papu&#39;a New Guinea-2. Coal edited by D. M. Traves and D. King (1975) </para>
          <para>No. 7- Economic Geology of Australia and Papua New Guinea- 3. Petroleum edited by R. B. Leslie, H. J. Evans and C.L. Knight (1975). </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>and (4) The table below gives information with the provinces named in part ( 1 ) of the question on major mining operations which are in production or may achieve production by 1977, also the names of the operating companies. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_19_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_20_2.jpg" />
        </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>There are many factors which a company would take into account in deciding whether or not to develop a mineral deposit. Basically the three main, and invariably interrelated, factors are whether development is economically viable, whether markets are available for the output of the project and whether the developing company can raise the necessary capital. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Factors determining economic viability include the current and anticipated price for the output and current and anticipated costs which in turn are influenced to a large degree by the location, size grade and the geological and physical configuration of the deposit. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Physiotherapy Charges: Medibank Agreements (Question No. 793)</title>
          <page.no>793</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>793</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ME4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAUME, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Baume</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Do only three of the State Governments allow charges, on private patients in standard wards, for physiotherapy rendered by private practice physiotherapists for patients who are privately insured against medical costs. If so, is this in any instance due to differing interpretations of the CommonwealthState Medibank agreements in different States. If so, how is this matter interpreted in the different States and what can he done to seek some uniformity in interpretation, if necessary by modification of the agreements made between the Commonwealth and the States. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>794</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>The honourable senator will be aware that the CommonwealthState Medibank Agreements to which he refers were found to be invalid. The Government is presently engaged in negotiating new Agreements with the State Governments, to operate from 1 October 1976. </para>
            <para>These new Commonwealth-State Hospital Cost Sharing Agreements will be based on the Commonwealth&#39;s policy of allowing each State Government to determine and follow its own practice with regard to charges in its public hospitals. The Agreements will therefore reflect decisions taken by State Governments, and agreed to by the Commonwealth, on charging policies in relation to inpatient accommodation and medical services, and to outpatient facilities. </para>
            <para>It is the general intention that the public hospital inpatient charges will be &#39;all-inclusive&#39; of extra services and facilities (including physiotherapy). It is of advantage for the inpatient to be aware of the charges to be made and to have adequate hospital insurance cover. It is possible that circumstances might arise in which a particular public hospital was unable to provide the services of a physiotherapist to a private patient requiring such services and therefore a private therapist would provide the services direct. The provision of services for private patients in this manner, would be viewed by the Commonwealth as being a matter of State Government policy, outside the terms of the proposed cost sharing arrangements. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Volatile Anaesthetics (Question No. 794)</title>
          <page.no>794</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>794</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ME4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAUME, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Baume</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>What action has been taken to inform the appropriate personnel in hospitals under Commonwealth control of the possible risks associated with volatile anaesthetics and pregnancy, as set out in the answer to Senate Question No. 4 1 . </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>794</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Notices have been given to all staff employed in the operating theatres of Commonwealth hospitals informing them that exposure to volatile anaesthetics could present a risk during pregnancy. Literature and information on the subject has also been made generally available to all other hospital personnel. Hospitals have advised staff that they may decline duties in operating theatres if they wish, and that if they do so, alternative duties will be arranged. In hospitals experiencing staffing problems, every effort is being made to ensure rosters allow staff the maximum breaks possible from the theatre environment. </para>
            <para>Additionally, in a number of Commonwealth hospitals scavenging and anti-pollution devices to remove exhaust gases have either been installed in operating theatres, or are being installed as finances permit. Tests are also being carried out with a view to reducing pollution in operating theatres to safe levels for all staff </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Social Welfare Benefits (Question No. 833)</title>
          <page.no>794</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>794</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What is the average waiting time between application for and receipt of (a) supporting mother&#39;s benefit, (b) child endowment, (c) student endowment, (d) orphan&#39;s pension, (e) maternity allowance, (0 handicapped child &#39;s allowance, (g) tuberculosis allowance, and (h) domiciliary nursing care benefit. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What percentage of initial applications are found on investigation not to justify the payment of benefit in each of the eight categories listed in ( 1 ). </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>794</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>I am advised that: </para>
            <list type="decimal">
              <item label="(1)">
                <para>(a) For supporting mother&#39;s benefit, the average time between lodgment of claim and payment is 25 days. There is a statutory qualifying period of 6 months during which claimants are eligible for State Government welfare payments. State authorities advise claimants to apply to my Department well in advance of the expiration of this period. Claims are investigated in the intervening period and, except in rare cases, transfer from State to Commonwealth benefit is effected without any interruption in payments. For persons not in receipt of State benefits, provision exists for immediate payments where claimants are experiencing special hardship. (b), (c) and (e). In the case of child endowment, student endowment and maternity allowance, the average waiting time between lodgment of claim and payment is 11 to 13 days. Most claims are paid within a few days, the higher average waiting time being brought about by claimants providing insufficient information on their claims. </para>
                <list type="loweralpha">
                  <item label="(d)">
                    <para>For double orphans pension, the average waiting time between lodgment of claim and payment is 19 days. Investigation necessary to verify the death of the child&#39;s parents or whereabouts of the surviving parent is undertaken in this period. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(">
                    <para>f) For handicapped child &#39;s allowance, the average waiting time before payment is made is IS days. Medical investigations are often necessary to determine whether the degree of incapacity of the child necessitates the claimant providing the child with constant care and attention. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(g)">
                    <para>In the case of tuberculosis allowance, the average waiting time between lodgment of claim and payment is 15 days. This time factor can be influenced by the fact that a medical examination is necessary to assess eligibility or because the claimant provides insufficient information in support of a claim. </para>
                  </item>
                </list>
              </item>
              <item label="(2)">
                <para>(a) The estimated percentage of claims for supporting mother&#39;s benefit where payment is not justified is 20 per cent. In many of these cases, the claim is withdrawn on marriage of the applicant, while in others the claim is lodged too soon to be held until the expiration of the six month qualifying period. These claimants are invited to reapply at a later date. Many are found to qualify for payment on reapplication. (b), (c) and (e) For child endowment, student endowment and maternity allowance, the percentages of claims where payment is not justified are negligible, being less than half of one per cent. </para>
                <list type="loweralpha">
                  <item label="(d)">
                    <para>and (f) Approximately 16 per cent of claims for double orphan&#39;s pension are found not to justify payment of benefit, while for handicapped child&#39;s allowance, the estimate is 13 per cent mainly on the results of medical investigations. </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(g)">
                    <para>For tuberculosis allowance, 10 per cent of claimants are ineligible for payment, mainly on the grounds that the earnings of the applicant&#39;s spouse preclude payment under the means test applied. </para>
                  </item>
                </list>
              </item>
            </list>
          </quote>
          <para>The following details concerning domiciliary nursing care benefit have been supplied by my colleague, the Minister for Health: </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>(h) For the Domiciliary Nursing Care Benefit, the average time between receipt of a claim in the Department and the issue of the first payment is three weeks. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>I might add by way of explanation that this benefit is paid on a &#39;per fortnight&#39; basis commencing from the beginning of the first pay-period following the date of receipt of the relevant application in the Department of Health and continuing until the end of the pay-period in which eligibility ceases. While this procedure may contribute to delays in the issue of initial payments, it does avoid confusion and reduces the likelihood of overpayments. </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>(h) Of all applications received since the introduction of the scheme in March 1973, 21.6 per cent have been rejected because payment was not justified. However, of those received in the last 9 months only IS. 7 per cent have been rejected. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Governor-General&#39;s Personal Staff (Question No. 840)</title>
          <page.no>795</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Prime Minister, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What is (a) the name, (b) designation and (c) salary and entitlements, of each member of the Governor-General&#39;s personal staff. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Have there been any resignations or departures from the Governor-General&#39;s personal staff since II November 197S. If so, for what reasons have the resignations or departures concerned taken place. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Prime Minister has provided the following information for answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>- </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr D.</inline>I. Smith, C.SU. Official Secretary $27,306 per annum, $200 per annum entertainment allowance, $ 100 per annum clothing allowance. * </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr M.</inline>R. Wilmot, Administrative Secretary $18,231 per annum. </para>
          <para>Air Commodore D. W. Colquhoun, D.F.C., A.F.C., RAAF (retired), Comptroller $16,963 per annum. </para>
          <para>Miss J. Lester, Private Secretary to Her Excellency $12,745 per annum, $883 per annum allowance in lieu of overtime.* </para>
          <para>Captain R. C. Aley, RASC Army Aide-de-Camp $ 1 5,838 per annum, $2 10 per annum uniform allowance. </para>
          <para>FI. Lt. R. J. Fox, RAAF, Air Force Aide-de-Camp $ 1 7,338 per annum, $210 per annum uniform allowance. </para>
          <para>Lt. R. Cason, RAN, Navy Aide-de-Camp $15,838 per annum, $2 10 per annum uniform allowance. </para>
          <para>* In addition a clothing outlay allowance was paid in 1974 to <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Smith</inline> and Miss Lester following their appointment to the Governor-General &#39;s staff. </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>There have been no resignations from the Governor-General&#39;s personal staff. Departures have consisted of defence force officers returning to their Services at the completion of their normal periods of duty. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Personal staff* has been interpreted to mean those staff normally selected personally by the Governor-General. Domestic staff and office staff have not been included. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Aboriginal Land Rights: Borroloola (Question No. 877)</title>
          <page.no>795</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Northern Territory, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Is Mount Isa Mines Holdings Limited to be allocated land at Borroloola which is at the present time part of the land claimed on the basis of tradition by the Aborigines living at Borroloola. If so, will the Company acquire this land before the Aboriginal Lands Rights Bill 1976 is considered in Parliament? </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for the Northern Territory has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>The Government is currently negotiating with Mount Isa Mines Holdings Limited in relation to mining tenures to be granted under the Mining Ordinance for lands within the McArthur River, Taw allah and Spring Creek Pastoral leases. The Company is not being allocated lands which fall within any known traditional claim by Aboriginals at Borroloola. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Sugar (Question No. 909)</title>
          <page.no>795</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Overseas Trade, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What percentage of the total annual world sugar production does Australia&#39;s production represent? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What percentage has Australia&#39;s production represented for the past 10 years? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>When was the International Sugar Agreement first ratified by Australia? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(4)">
              <para>What were the reasons for the establishment of the Agreement? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(5)">
              <para>What has been the total world production of sugar for each of the past ten years? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(6)">
              <para>What has been the average world sugar price for each of the past ten years? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>795</page.no>
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Cotton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Overseas Trade has provided the following information in answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>Australia&#39;s sugar production in I97S represented an estimated 3.5 per cent of total world production. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Australian sugar production as a percentage of total world production in the ten years 1966-75 was as follows: </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_22_3.jpg" />
        </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>Australia ratified the first International Sugar Agreement of 1937 and has been a member of all subsequent agreements i.e. those of 1953, 1958, 1968 and 1973. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>International cooperation designed to stabilise the world sugar market dates back to 1 864. Early efforts failed to achieve the objective of raising price levels and balancing production and consumption. A major problem was insufficient coverage of importing and exporting countries. Because of continued depressed prices, exporting countries pressed the World Monetary and Economic Conference of 1 933 for an effective international agreement. This initiative resulted in the International Sugar Agreement of 1937, the effectiveness of which was never tested because of the outbreak of World War II. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para class="block">Post-war agreements have operated with varying degrees of success since 1953. The reasons behind the negotiation of successive International Sugar Agreements is perhaps best illustrated by the objectives of the 1968 Agreement which is the most recent Agreement containing economic provisions. The objectives of that Agreement were: </para>
        <list type="loweralpha">
          <item label="(a)">
            <para>to raise the level of international trade in sugar, particularly in order to increase the export earnings of developing exporting countries; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(b)">
            <para>to maintain a stable price for sugar which will be reasonably remunerative to producers, but which will not encourage further expansion of production in developed countries; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(c)">
            <para>to provide adequate supplies of sugar to meet the requirements of importing countries at fair and reasonable prices; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(d)">
            <para>to increase sugar consumption and in particular to promote measures to encourage consumption in countries where consumption per caput is low; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(e)">
            <para>to bring world production and consumption of sugar into closer balance; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(">
            <para>f) to facilitate the co-ordination of sugar marketing policies and the organisation of the market; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(g)">
            <para>to provide for adequate participation in, and growing access to, the markets of the developed countries for sugar from the developing countries; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(h)">
            <para>to observe closely developments in the use of any form of substitutes for sugar, including cyclamates and other artificial sweeteners; and </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(i)">
            <para>to further international cooperation in sugar questions. &#39; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(j">
            <para>) World sugar production in the years 1 966- 1975 was as follows: </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_23_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para>Note: Annual averages are average of monthly average prices. </para>
        <para>Source: International Sugar Organisation. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Accidents Suffered by Earners and Non-Earners (Question No. 916)</title>
          <page.no>796</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>796</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>9V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GRIMES, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Grimes</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Has the Minister&#39;s Department made any estimates of the number and cost of accidents, excluding traffic accidents, in Australia to (a) earners outside work hours, and (b) nonearners. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>If these estimates are available, will the Minister provide them with a comment on the accuracy of the statistics. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>If the figures are not considered accurate, what steps are currently being taken to improve them. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>796</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>and (2) No adequate data exists on the number and cost of accidents occurring to earners outside work hours and to non-earners. Comprehensive information on injuries requiring inpatient treatment in hospital is available in the hospital morbidity statistics published by the Deputy Commonwealth Statistician in Queensland, Western Australia and Tasmania. These separate traffic accidents but not work injuries. It is understood that the special tabulations were provided by the Deputy Commonwealth Statistician in Western Australia and Tasmania to the National Rehabilitation and Compensation Inquiry (the Woodhouse Committee) which separated work, road and other injuries. A useful summary of information on non work injuries is at paragraph 19 to 32 of Pan 3 of Volume 3 (the Compensation) of the Woodhouse Committee&#39;s Report. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>I am informed that the Australian Bureau of Statistics has investigated the feasibility of conducting an accident survey in conjunction with one of its quarterly population surveys. Unfortunately technical reasons concerning the length of the recall period necessary to obtain reliable results forced the Bureau to abandon this particular approach to the collection of accident statistics. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>MyDepartment is having discussions with State officers concerning possible options for a national compensation program and in the course of these discussions attention will be given to the need for suitable statistics relating to accidents. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Leather Goods, Carpet and Freezer Industries (Question No. 918)</title>
          <page.no>796</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>796</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUU</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MISSEN, Alan</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Missen</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Have complaints been made that the viability of the leather goods, carpet, and freezer industries appear to have been severely jeopardised by New Zealand imports and that the New Zealand commodities are imported under most advantageous conditions created by the exchange rate and export incentives. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Can the Minister give an assurance, in view of the recommendation of the Industries Assistance Commission for a tariff protection made over a year ago, that the Government will give immediate attention to this inequitable situation. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>797</page.no>
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The following information is provided in answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) The Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs has received complaints from the leather goods industry that its viability has been jeopardized by imports of New Zealand commodities entering under advantageous conditions created by the exchange rate and export incentives. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>No similar complaints have been made to the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs with respect to the carpet or freezer industries. </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Industries Assistance Commission in its report of 10 June 1975 on leather and leather substitute products recommended that the rate of duty on leather wallets of New Zealand origin be increased from the present 6 per cent to the general industry rate of 25 per cent unless a mutually acceptable agreement on trade can be reached between Australia and New Zealand. The Government has the Commission &#39;s report under consideration and expects to announce its decision shortly. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>The Textiles Authority within the Industries Assistance Commission reported on 7 February 1 975 on certain textile floor coverings. As a result of the Government&#39;s decision on this report and following consultations between officials and industry representatives in both countries, tufted and axminster carpet piece goods with a maximum wool content of 80 per cent were included in Schedule A of the New ZealandAustralia Free Trade Agreement on 1 July 1975. Trade between Australia and New Zealand in such goods is regulated in accordance with the agreement reached between the two governments at that time and is subject to review as required. </para>
          <para class="block">Indications are that the arrangement which has been in operation for over 12 months is working satisfactorily. </para>
          <para>Following consideration of an interim report from the Industries Assistance Commission of 7 July 1976 on certain chest freezers, the Government announced on 10 August 1976 that temporary protection by way of global import licensing for a period of twelve months had been introduced in respect of chest freezers of up to 350 litres capacity. Licensing applies to all imports of such freezers other than those under existing special trading arrangements provided for in the New Zealand-Australia Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). As imports from New Zealand under NAFTA have always been subject to separate administrative procedures, such trade will continue to be administered separately. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Social Welfare Benefits: Appeals (Question No. 922)</title>
          <page.no>797</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>797</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>How many appeals relating to (a) unemployment benefit, (b) sickness benefit, (c) age pension, (d) invalid pension, and (e) supporting mothers&#39; benefit were dealt with in each State by Social Security Appeals Tribunals in (i) the March Quarter 1976 and (ii) the June Quarter 1976, and what are the detailed results of the appeals in question corresponding to the headings provided in the Minister&#39;s answer to Senate question No. 130, vide Senate Hansard, 4 May 1976, page 1515. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>797</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_24_6.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_25_7.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_26_8.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_27_9.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Commonwealth Employment Service (Question No. 925)</title>
          <page.no>800</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>800</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Has a decision been made not to proceed with the installation of a computer job-allocation system for the Commonwealth Employment Service. If so, (a) when was the decision taken, and for what reason; (b) what assistance would the installation of a computer job-allocation system provide in the functioning of the Commonwealth Employment Service; (c) what would have been involved; and (d) when, if at all, is it planned to proceed with the installation of a computer job-allocation system. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>800</page.no>
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="loweralpha">
            <item label="(a)">
              <para>A decision not to proceed with the installation of a computer job-allocation system for the Commonwealth Employment Service was taken by the previous Government in July 1 975 pending a review of cost benefit aspects in the light of capital expenditure and developmental costs involved. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(b)">
              <para>The proposed computer system would provide all offices of the Commonwealth Employment Service with immediate access to information about applicants seeking employment and vacancies notified by employers in any given geographically defined area. The proposed system would also supply a wide range of statistical information relating to the labour market and Departmental administration. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(c)">
              <para>The system would involve linking all offices of the Commonwealth Employment Service through a nationwide network of computers and terminal equipment. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(d)">
              <para>There are no firm plans to proceed with the installation of a computerised information system in the Commonwealth Employment Service. It is expected that the need for such a system will be reviewed during a forthcoming review of the operation of the Service. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Regional Employment Development Scheme (Question No. 928)</title>
          <page.no>800</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>800</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>What funds have been allocated under the Regional Employment Development scheme to each Shire Council in Queensland since the inception of the scheme. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>800</page.no>
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>The total of approved grants under the Regional Employment Development Scheme to sponsors in each local government area in Queensland since its inception are shown below: </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_28_10.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_28_11.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Brisbane Airport (Question No. 933)</title>
          <page.no>801</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>801</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>PF4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLSTON, Malcolm</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Colston</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Transport, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>With relation to part (2) of the minister&#39;s answer on 1 June 1 976 to Senate Question No. 253 </para>
            <list type="decimal">
              <item label="(">
                <para>1 ) What are the individual projected increases of international and domestic components making up the total projected increase. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(2)">
                <para>What are the projected increases in numbers of passengers involved in international and domestic travel. </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(3)">
                <para>Are direct services from Sydney and Queensland ports, other than Brisbane contemplated. If so, what are the details of the services planned. </para>
              </item>
            </list>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>802</page.no>
              <name.id>2U4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CARRICK, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Carrick</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Transport has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) International flights at Brisbane airport are expected to grow somewhat faster than domestic services, with flights to major overseas destinations projected to grow at a little over 5 per cent per annum, and services to Papua New Guinea at around 4 per cent. Domestic services comprise the bulk of jet services and are projected at 3 per cent. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>The most recent forecasts indicate that around 850 000 international passengers will use Brisbane airport in 1985. This reflects an expected growth of slightly under 1 1 per cent per annum. Domestic passenger traffic is projected to grow at a rate around 9 per cent to a total of around 5 million by 1985. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Around 30 per cent of domestic passenger traffic at Brisbane is in transit, transferring between flights to Queensland centres, and those to southern ports. It is only to be expected that, in time, demand on some of these routes, on an origin-destination basis, would warrant the introduction of commercially viable direct flights. This is a matter for the airlines to determine, but direct flights from Sydney to cities such as Townsville and Mackay are now offered in peak holiday periods, and these routes appear to offer the greatest likelihood of being able to support regular direct services within about the next ten years. The current downturn in domestic passenger traffic levels would appear to preclude any such expansion of the route network in the short term. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Statutory Authorities (Question No. 939)</title>
          <page.no>802</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>802</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ISW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wriedt</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for National Resources, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Which statutory authorities come under the control of the Minister. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What is the name, occupation, date and term of appointment, and remuneration of each holder of public office of each authority. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>802</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for National Resources has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Five, as follows: </para>
              <list type="loweralpha">
                <item label="(a)">
                  <para>The Australian Atomic Energy Commission </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(b)">
                  <para>The Joint Coal Board </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(c)">
                  <para>The Pipeline Authority </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(d)">
                  <para>The River Murray Commission </para>
                </item>
                <item label="(e)">
                  <para>The Snowy Mountains Hydro-electric Authority </para>
                </item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>The names, occupations, dates and terms of appointment are as shown below. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>The most recent figures for the remuneration of the office holders are to be found in the 1976 Review of the Remuneration Tribunal, released in July 1976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_29_12.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_30_0.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Statutory Authorities (Question No. 960)</title>
          <page.no>803</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>803</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>ISW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIEDT, Ken</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wriedt</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Science, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Which statutory authorities come under the control of the Minister. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What is the name, occupation, date and term of appointment, and remuneration of each holder of public office of each authority. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>803</page.no>
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) The following statutory authorities are responsible to the Minister for Science: </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Anglo-Australian Telescope Board </para>
          <para>Australian Institute of Marine Science </para>
          <para>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation </para>
          <para>Metric Conversion Board </para>
          <para>National Standards Commission. </para>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Details relating to remuneration of holders of public offices are contained in the Remuneration Tribunal&#39;s 1976 Review. Other details requested by the honourable senator are as follows: </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_30_1.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_31_15.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_32_16.jpg" />
        </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Communications Aid Project in Indonesia (Question No. 963)</title>
          <page.no>805</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>805</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>TJ4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WALSH, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Walsh</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Have any Australian aid funds been used to support a microwave communications project in Indonesia. If so, how much Australian aid has been spent in support of the Indonesian microwave project in (a) 1973-74, (b) 1974-75, and (c) 1975-76. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Has any inquiry been made of the Indonesian Government by Australian officials about the degree of duplication of facilities that will occur now that Indonesia has installed a domestic communications satellite system. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Will there be any duplication of facilities between the two communications projects. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(4)">
              <para>If no inquiry has been made of the Indonesian Government, will the Minister arrange for the information to be obtained. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(5">
              <para>) When was a decision taken to set aside Australian aid funds to support the Indonesian microwave project. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(6)">
              <para>When the decision to support the Indonesian microwave project was taken, was it known that the Indonesian Government also intended to install the domestic communications satellite system. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>805</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Foreign Affairs has provided the following answers to the honourable senator&#39;s questions: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Yes. The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development agreed to provide loan funds for a microwave system from Jakarta to Medan if the Indonesian Government was able to make suitable arrangements for supervision of the contracts. At Indonesia&#39;s request, Australia undertook this task. In addition, Australia agreed to provide equipment and technical support to upgrade the telephone exchanges and related cable distribution to be connected to the microwave system. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>Approximate Australian expenditure in support of the microwave project (with total Australian expenditure on the telecommunication project shown in brackets) was: </para>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_32_17.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="069232197609212_32_18.jpg" />
        </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>Yes. Inquiries were made in August 1974 by members of the Australian Telecommunications Mission in Bandung, on behalf of the Australian Development Assistance Agency, when the first reference to the satellite system came to notice. Since that time the Mission has been assisting Perumtel, the responsible Indonesian authority, on co-ordination of the satellite system with the Trans-Sumatra microwave system. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>The satellite system is capable of providing telephonic and television communications to any location in Indonesia at which a ground station is located and, from a ground station, over microwave or cable facilities to other locations. The Trans-Sumatra microwave system provides telephonic and television communications to most major cities in Sumatra. Satellite ground stations have initially been established at five Sumatra cities. At these locations the satellite system complements, rather than duplicates, the microwave system. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>Inquiries have already been made- see answer to Question 2. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>Approval for Australian involvement in the supervision of the installation of the Trans-Sumatra microwave system and in the upgrading of the telephone exchange system in Sumatra was given on 27 May 1970. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(6)">
            <para>No. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Aged Persons Homes: Western Australia (Question No. 977)</title>
          <page.no>805</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>805</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>5V4</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Coleman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) Is the limit for subsidy for aged persons homes a statewide limit of $ 10,200 per single unit and $ 1 1,850 per double unit with a possible land subsidy of up to $ 1 ,920. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Are building costs in the north-west of Western Australia about 80 per cent higher than for the Perth area. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>Will the Minister review subsidy allowances so that organisations can receive a higher subsidy for aged persons homes in the north-west of Western Australia. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>805</page.no>
              <name.id>C7D</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GUILFOYLE, Margaret</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Guilfoyle</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question is as follows: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para />
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Building costs in the north-west of Western Australia are often higher than the Perth area. However, it is difficult to generalise as building costs are influenced by many factors including location of project, proximity to transport, tender climate, local availability of materials and method of construction used. Furthermore, higher building costs in country areas are usually offset by lower land prices. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(3)">
              <para>The Government recently examined the question of introducing zone loadings on maximum subsidy Limits for aged persons&#39; homes and hostels to offset the higher building costs often encountered in remote areas. However, it was decided that it was not appropriate, at this time, to introduce such loadings. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>The question of zone loadings will be kept in mind for possible implementation in the future when circumstances permit. </para>
          <para>As previously announced by the Treasurer on 20 May 1976, for the first time the maximum subsidy limits will be reviewed quarterly to ensure that they keep abreast of movements in building costs. </para>
          <para>As the honourable senator is aware, the Government announced an increase in the subsidy limits payable under the Aged or Disabled Persons Homes Act, from $9,360 for a single unit of accommodation to $10,200 and from $10,920 for a double unit of accommodation to $1 1,850, as from 20 May 1976. </para>
          <para>The grant limit under the Aged Persons Hostels Act was increased from $ 1 1 ,700 to $ 1 5,300 from the same date. </para>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Consumer Organisations: Grants (Question No. 980)</title>
          <page.no>806</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>5V4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLEMAN, Ruth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Coleman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) What is the amount paid to each organisation which has received a grant for consumer matters in 1 975-76. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>What amount has been appropriated for future grants. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <name.id>8G4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DURACK, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Durack</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The following information is provided in answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) In 1975-76 a grant of $70,000 was made to the Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations (AFCO) for the year 1975-76. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>A grant of $75,000 has been made to Afro for the year 1976-77. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Department of Foreign Affairs: Journalists (Question No. 1036)</title>
          <page.no>806</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(">
              <para>1 ) How many journalists were employed in the Minister&#39;s Department, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, when the administrative arrangements of 22 December 1975 were made. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>How many journalists were employed in the Department of Foreign Affairs, and in commissions and statutory bodies under the Minister&#39;s control, at 1 September 1 976. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <name.id>DV4</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WITHERS, Reg</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Withers</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Foreign Affairs has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal">
            <item label="(1)">
              <para>Four. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(2)">
              <para>Four. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Administrator of Northern Territory (Question No. 1071)</title>
          <page.no>806</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2U</name.id>
              <electorate>NORTHERN TERRITORY</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ROBERTSON, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Robertson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Northern Territory, upon notice: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>Has the Government purchased a car for the personal use of the wife of the Administrator of the Northern Territory. If so, will the Minister indicate the details of the purchase, price paid, and whether the transaction was handled under Tender Board procedures. </para>
          </quote>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>806</page.no>
              <name.id>KAS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NCP/NP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WEBSTER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Webster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for the Northern Territory has provided the following answer to the honourable senator&#39;s question: </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>No. </para>
          </quote>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
  </answers.to.questions>
</hansard>