<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <session.header>
        <date>1937-06-18</date>
        <parliament.no>14</parliament.no>
        <session.no>2</session.no>
        <period.no>1</period.no>
        <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
        <page.no>43</page.no>
        <proof>0</proof>
    </session.header>
    <chamber.xscript>
        <para class="block">Senate. </para>
        <business.start>
            <day.start>1937-06-18</day.start>
            <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon. P. J. Lynch)</inline> took the chair at 11 a.m., and read prayers. </para>
        </business.start>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>VOLCANIC DISTURBANCES AT RABAUL</title>
                <page.no>43</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>43</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - Serious volcanic disturbances took place at Rabaul, capital of the Mandated Territory of New Guinea, on the 29th May, 1937, and the following days. Vulcan Island, in Rabaul Harbour, erupted at 4 p.m. on Saturday, the 29th May, emitting dense volumes of smoke, and covering Rabaul with volcanic dust. Matupi, about 2 miles from Rabaul, also erupted on the 30th May. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>The population of Rabaul - European, Asiatic and native - was evacuated to Kokopo, about 20 miles away. Both volcanoes continued their activity until the morning of the 3rd June. Heavy deposits of pumice dust and mud fell on Rabaul, breaking countless trees and blocking streets, which became quagmires, whilst the harbour became impassable owing to a thick layer of floating pumice. Most of the buildings in Rabaul are intact and unharmed, but are covered thickly with volcanic dust. </para>
                    <para>Both volcanoes arc now quiescent, and the harbour is clear and available for shipping. The cleaning of the town is progressing rapidly, and Government departments have returned to resume their ordinary activities. Some of the commercial activities have also been resumed in the town, and permission was given for the European residents and the Chinese community to take up residence in Rabaul again as from the 10th June. </para>
                    <para>One European has been missing since Saturday, the 29th May, and search has failed to locate him. The deaths of natives definitely known at present number less than twenty. The Administrator has been asked whether his inquiries to date disclose any further deaths or that any number of natives has not been accounted for. I have learnt to-day that Mr. Victor Costner, the wireless operator of the American vessel <inline font-style="italic">Golden Bear,</inline> is also reported missing. He was last seen on the wharf at Rabaul on the day of the eruption. </para>
                    <para>The first reports received from the territory of the eruption indicated that a serious situation had arisen at Rabaul, and that, in consequence of the evacuation of the population, an acute food shortage was imminent. H.M.A.S. <inline font-style="italic">Moresby</inline> was diverted from survey work in the Gulf of Carpentaria and instructed to proceed immediately to Rabaul, and the motor vessel <inline font-style="italic">Malaita,</inline> of the Burns, Philp line, which was then at Brisbane, was commissioned to proceed to Rabaul with all speed with medical stores, provisions and other necessaries. The women and children who wore resi dent at Rabaul at the time of the eruption were offered passages to Australia, and 75 of them left by the SS. <inline font-style="italic">Montoro,</inline> which is due in Sydney on the 19th June. </para>
                    <para>The question of the retention of Rabaul as the capital of the Territory of New Guinea is receiving consideration. Inquiries have been made with a view to obtaining the services of a qualified scientist who could proceed to the area and examine and report upon the volcanic and seismic dangers to the inhabitants and the administrative and commercial activities. On the receipt of his report the advisableness of appointing a committee to examine the question of the suitability of Rabaul as the capital, and the possible selection of another location, will be considered. </para>
                </speech>
        </debate>

        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>REGIME OF THE STRAITS CONVENTION</title>
                <page.no>44</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>44</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party>UAP</party>
                        <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - I lay on the table - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>Regime of the Straits - the Straits of the Dardanelles, the Sea of Marmora, and the Bosphorus - Copy of Convention signed at Montreux on the 20th July, 1936. </para>
                </quote>
                <para class="block">Notice of His Majesty&#39;s ratification of the Convention in respect of the Commonwealth of Australia was deposited with the French Government on the 15th September. The Convention came into force on the 9th November. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>EDUCATIONAL FILMS</title>
                <page.no>44</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Convention for Facilitating International Circulation</title>
                    <page.no>44</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - I lay on the table - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>International circulation of Films of an Edu- cational Character - Text of Convention drawn up at Geneva, 11th October, 1933, at conference held under the auspicesof the League of Nations. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">Accession in respect of the Commonwealth of Australia, including the territories of Papua and Norfolk Island, and the Mandated Territories of New Guinea and Nauru was registered with the League of Nations on the 23rd December, 1936, and came into force 90 days after that date. </para>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LEAGUE OF NATIONS</title>
                <page.no>45</page.no>
                <type>report</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">17th Assembly:report of Australian Delegation. </para>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>45</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party>UAP</party>
                        <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEOEGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - I lay on the table of the Senate the report of the Australian delegation to the 17th Assembly of the League of Nations which met at Geneva in September and October of last year, and move - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>That the paper be printed. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>Australia was represented at the Assembly by the Eight Honorable S. M. Bruce, C.H., M.C.; F. L. McDougall, Esq., C.M.G.;Raymond G. Watt, Esq.; and <inline font-weight="bold">Mrs. E.</inline> A. Waterworth, O.B.E. It is interesting to note that 52 nations were represented at the Assembly, and that among the representatives were three Prime Ministers and 26 Foreign Ministers. So far as Australia is concerned, the most important discussions at the Assembly related to the reform of the League, nutrition, and trade barriers. </para>
                <para>The failure of collective security to prevent the conquest of Abyssinia had led to considerable criticism of the machinery of the League for the prevention of aggression. The British Foreign Minister ascribed the failure of the League in that dispute to the lack of more energetic action and effective League intervention in the early stages of the crisis. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Eden</inline> suggested that machinery should be devised as soon as possible to improve the working of the Covenant. </para>
                <para>Various proposals were discussed at the Assembly for strengthening the provisions of the Covenant in regard to collective security, but some delegates, including those from Canada, held that formal amendment of the Covenant at that time was neither possible nor necessary. The New Zealand delegate insisted that sanctions would be ineffective in the future, as in the past, unless they were immediate and automatic. He said that the League had lapsed into futility as the result of the vacillation of governments, and not by reason of indecision on the part of the people. </para>
                <para>In his address to the Assembly, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce,</inline> acting on instructions from the Commonwealth Government, suggested that the conflict in Abys sinia had demonstrated conclusively that, a non-universal League, particularly one which did not include three of the greatest Powers of the world - the United States of America, Germany and Japan - could not prevent, or bring about the immediate cessation of, aggression by the overwhelming nature of financial, economic or military sanctions, and that, in the circumstances, for the League to have endeavoured to operate the Covenant in full might have been to increase the danger by spreading the area of the conflict instead of ending it. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> pointed out that whilst, its non-universality was the most obvious reason why the League had. not achieved all that was hoped of it, there had been other Causes, but to review them would serve little purpose at that stage. In his opinion,- the wisest course for final achievement was a full and honest recognition of the facts as they existed, and a determination to establish the greatest measure of co-operation possible in the circumstances. The Commonwealth Government,he said, did not propose any amendment of the Covenant, but merely suggested some changes of interpretation, although it would welcome the introduction of certain&#34; amendments. </para>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline>
                    added that the Commonwealth Government unreservedly supported the views expressed by the British delegate as to the necessity formore effective intervention in the earlier stages of disputes by an improvement of the working of Article 11 of the Covenant. In this manner it would be possible for the League to intervene before disputant nations had gone so far that national prestige rendered any retirement extremely difficult. The Commonwealth Government favoured regional pacts and, as regards general obligations in respect of financial and economic sanctions,&#34;
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline>
                    stated that the Commonwealth Government considered that the existing practice, whereby economic and financial sanctions under Article 16 of the Covenant are not automatic but are applied only after a meeting of, and full consideration by, the members of the League, should be fully maintained. He considered that the strength and pressure of world public opinion would grow progressively until statesmen would be. compelled to act justly whenever world peace was endangered by the act of an aggressor,
                </para>
                <para>In regard to nutrition, a subject which had been raised by the Australian delegation at the previous assembly, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> declared that nutrition was the focal point of the movement to substitute a policy of production for one of restriction. He said that Australia continued to attach the utmost importance to the economic issue, believing that a solution of it would open the way to world peace and the removal of social unrest. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> urged that a special committee should be set up by the Council for the investigation of economic problems. He suggested that the first steps should be taken by the great powers, especially the creditor nations. He also advocated the rejection of the fearful negative policy which had emerged from the World Economic Conference in 1933, namely, that prosperity should be achieved by restricting instead of increasing production. This doctrine, he submitted, would ultimately drive impoverished millions to revolt. </para>
                <para>The Assembly adopted a resolution commending the Currency Agreement between Great Britain, France and the United States of America, and invited the co-operation of all States, whether members of&#34; the League o&#39;r not, in the direction indicated by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce.</inline> The Assembly urgently recommended States as an. essential condition of final success, to organize, without delay, determinate and continuous action to ensure the reduction of excessive obstacles to international trade and communications, and, in particular, to abolish the present system of quotas and exchange control. </para>
                <para>The Assembly requested the Council to appoint a committee to inquire into the question of equal commercial access for all nations to raw materials. A committee of experts was duly set up in January. It met. in March and, after a preliminary discussion, agreed that for any study of the accessibility of raw materials to be adequate it must, not he limited to consideration of. the raw materials for industry, hut must include also foodstuffs and fodder. Although many raw materials are admittedly derived from colonial and mandated territories, it had been pointed out that most raw materials are produced wholly, or to a great extent, in sovereign, countries. The committee, therefore, further agreed that raw materials ought to be taken into consideration, whatever their origin. </para>
                <para>Another matter of some importance dealt with by the Assembly was that of terrorism. It will be recalled that part of the settlement by the League of Nations of the dispute between Yugoslavia and Hungary in connexion with the assassination at Marseilles of King Alexander of Yugoslavia was the framing of two international conventions intended to secure co-operation&#39; between governments against terrorism. Two draft conventions have now been drawn up, one for the prevention and repression of terrorism, and the other for the establishment of an international criminal court to try any person brought before it by a contracting party. These drafts will in the ordinary course come before either a later Assembly or a special conference for formal adoption and signature. The Commonwealth Government has already informed the League that it agrees in principle to the adoption of a convention for the repression of terrorism, but does not favour the proposed international, criminal court. </para>
                <para>The usual reports from the technical and other organizations of the League on the work carried out during the preceding year came before the Assembly. These indicate that in the field of social and humanitarian activities the League is carrying out all that could be expected of it in the circumstances. I commend the report for perusal by honorable senators. </para>
                <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings)</inline> adjourned. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>INTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE</title>
                <type> report </type>
                <page.no>46</page.no>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>MARITIME Sessions: REpORT of Australian Delegation. </para>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>46</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party>UAP</party>
                        <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>.- I lay on the table* - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>International Labour Organization of the League of Nations - Twenty-first and </para>
                    <para>Twenty-second (Maritime) Sessions, held at Geneva, October, 1936 -Reports of the Australian Delegates. </para>
                    <para>Draft Conventions and Recommendations adopted at - </para>
                    <list type="decimal">
                        <item label="(1)">
                            <para>Twenty-first (Maritime) Session, 6th to 24th October, 1936; and </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="(2)">
                            <para>Twenty-second (Maritime) Session, 22nd to 24th October, 1936.  and move - </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para>That the paper be printed. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>The reports which I have tabled of the Australian delegates to the 21st and 22nd (Maritime) sessions of the International Labour Conference which were held at Geneva in October last, have appended to them the texts of the draft conventions and recommendations adopted. Representation at the International Labour Conference, as honorable senators are aware, consists of government and non-government delegates. The non-government delegates represent respectively the employers and the workers, and are chosen in agreement with the industrial organizations concerned. The Government delegate was <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. L.</inline> F. East, I.S.O.; the employers&#39; delegate, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. C.</inline> B. L. Filmer, D.S.C., and the workers&#39; delegate, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. J.</inline> A. Tudehope. The Conference discusses matters on the agenda, and may by a two-thirds majority, adopt international regulations in respect of social and industrial matters in the form of draft conventions, which are subsequently submitted to governments for consideration with a view to ratification and implementation. </para>
                <para>The second session in October was necessary to comply with certain constitutional requirements in connexion with the revision of an existing convention. </para>
                <para>The Conference was attended by the representatives of 83 States, of which 29 were maritime countries possessing in the aggregate 84 per cent, of the merchant shipping tonnage of the world. The United States of America and the Union of Soviet SocialistRepublics took part in the Conference for the first time. </para>
                <para>The Conference adopted draft conventions concerning - </para>
                <list type="decimal">
                    <item label="(1)">
                        <para>The eight-hour day principle under the three-watch system and providing for a systematic organization of work on board  ship ; </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(2)">
                        <para>The liability of the ship-owner in case of sickness, injury or death of seamen; </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(3)">
                        <para>Sickness insurance for seamen; </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(4)">
                        <para>Certificates of professional capacity for masters and officers; and </para>
                    </item>
                    <item label="(5)">
                        <para>Annual holidays with pay. </para>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <para class="block">In addition, the convention of  1920  concerning the minimum age for employment at sea was revised so as to raise the age from fourteen to fifteen years. Recommendations were adopted in regard to hours of work and manning, and seamen&#39;s welfare in port, whilst other resolutions called for the study generally of certain questions with a view to their being placed on the agenda of a future maritime session of the Conference. </para>
                <para>It is claimed that the draft conventions and recommendations adopted at these maritime sessions of the Conference, combined with those adopted at the earlier maritime sessions in  1920, 1926  and  1929,  now provide an international labour code for seamen in accordance with the spirit of the general regulations already accepted for workers as a whole. The Commonwealth Government has ratified all the earlier maritime conventions with the exception of one relating to the repatriation of seamen. The provisions of this particular convention  are  in practice being fully complied with by the Commonwealth. The law regarding the repatriation of seamen from places abroad, other than the United Kingdom, is contained in the British Merchant Shipping Act, and the United Kingdom has postponed ratification, pending ratification by at least six of the principal maritime powers, of which so far, only three have ratified the convention. </para>
                <para>The provisions of three of the new conventions, namely those relating to the manning of ships, the liability of the shipowner towards sick arid injured seamen, and the establishment of minimum requirements of professional capacity for masters and officers, are already covered by the Commonwealth Navigation Act, but some minor amendments will be necessary to bring Australian legislation strictly in conformity with the conventions in question. The matters of hours of work and holidays with pay are covered by various industrial awards relative to officers and most, if not all, of the ratings employed on our coastal fleet. These provisions&#39; are in many respects more liberal to seamen than are those of the new conventions. </para>
                <para>The conventions and recommendations adopted at the 21st and 22nd sessions of the Conference have been referred to the several State governments and are now under consideration by the Commonwealth departments concerned. </para>
                <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings)</inline> adjourned. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTION</title>
                <page.no>48</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TELEPHONE SERVICES</title>
                    <page.no>48</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Tatana Rural Automatic Exchange. </para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K3L</name.id>
                            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SAMPSON, Burford</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SAMPSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon</inline><inline font-style="italic">notice</inline><inline font-style="italic">-</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Does his department intend to proceed with thu installation nf a rural automatic telephone exchange ;it  Tatana  to serve the interests of West Tamar fruit-growers and others? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Has thu automatic equipment originally intended for &#39;lutana been diverted to Waddamana? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>If not, is lie in a position to state, if and when the &#39;lutana rural automatic exchange will lie an accomplished fact? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions are as follows : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Yes. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>No. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>The exchange equipment is on order and delivery is expected shortly. The installation w ill lie effected with the least possible delay. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>WIRELESS BROADCASTING</title>
                    <page.no>48</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>North- Western Queensland Regional Station - Talks by Mr. C. R. Badger - Station 4RN - Perth Facilities. </para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JQP</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COOPER, Walter</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COOPER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Can the Postmaster-General give any information regarding the proposal to erect a regional wireless station in North-Western Queensland? </para>
                    </quote>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is not possible to give any undertaking at the present juncture concerning the erection of a regional broadcasting station to serve the area referred to. The national broadcasting system is being developed in accordance with a comprehensive scheme which contemplates a reliable radio service for all populous areas in the Commonwealth, but a plan of such magnitude can only be realized in stages. The current stage includes&#39; the construction of stations in areas where improvement is badly needed, but later the region under notice will receive attention. Moreover, the department has established the short-wave broadcasting station SLR to provide the programmes of the national service to areas such as this, and reports received from these localities show that a useful service is &#39;being given. The department intends further to improve its short-wave facilities in the near future. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Why permission was refused by the Australian Broadcasting Commission to Mr. C. K. Badger of Perth to broadcast the second  of his series of talks entitled &#34; Michiavell mid Modern Dictators&#34;? </para>
                    </quote>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Inquiries will be made from the Australian Broadcasting Commission. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Is  anything being done to improve the situation in North-west Queensland regarding the reported poor reception from 4RN &#34; A &#34; class wireless station? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>ls it a fact that the reception is so poor that listeners are obliged to fall buck on a -s B &#34; class station, 4L&#167; Longreach? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>Can lie give any satisfactory reason as to why the &#34;News Bulletin&#34; from 4BN,  originally  put on the air at 7 a.m., was altered to (i.30 a.m.? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Inquiries are being made and a reply will be furnished to the honorable senator as early as possible. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KP8</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">JOHNSTON, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator E B JOHNSTON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>When it is intended to commence the erection of the second National Broadcasting Station promised for Perth ? </para>
                    </quote>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator will be furnished with a reply to  his inquiries as early as possible. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>WHEAT MARKETING</title>
                    <page.no>48</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>48</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KP8</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">JOHNSTON, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator E B JOHNSTON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Prime Minister, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What is the effect of the recent referendum on the Wheat and Wheat Products Act 1935? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If this act is invalid, what steps are being taken to secure to Australian wheat-growers a home consumption price for wheat, in the event of its price falling in the open markets? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Acting Prime Minister has supplied the following answers: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>The act is rendered inoperative. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>This matter is under consideration. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>CUSTOMS DUTIES ON OREGON</title>
                    <page.no>49</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTX</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator JAMES McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Trade and Customs, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Is itafact that owing to an increase of duty on oregon logs, much high priced machinery is compelled to remain idle and employees usually engaged in sawing are out of employment? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Is it a fact that the duty is giving Canadian sawnoregon an advantage of 2s. per 100 super, feet? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>If so, will the Government give the matter early consideration? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>If not, will an inquiry be madeinto the ma tter by the Tariff Board ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Minister for Trade and Customs has supplied the following answers: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1">
                            <para>. No. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>No. </para>
                            </item>
                            <item label="3 and 4."> 
                                <para> In view of recent rises in c.i.f. prices of bothoregon logs and sawnoregon, departmental investigations were commenced last week with a view to ascertaining what price advantage  Oregon  logs have over imported sawnoregon. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TROPICAL HYGIENE</title>
                    <page.no>49</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What is the present position regarding the work previously carried on at Townsville by the Division of Tropical Hygiene? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>What operations, if any, are now being carried out  in  this connexionby the Commonwealth Health Department or any other federal department? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K2Z</name.id>
                            <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Minister without portfolio assisting the Minister for Commerce</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BRENNAN, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BRENNAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Minister for Health has supplied the following answers :  - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>The work previously carried  on  at Townsville is being continued and has been extended. The laboratory at Townsville continues local investigations and the staff of the School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine at Sydney are carrying out general investigations into tropical medicine and visiting Northern Queensland for the purpose of reinforcing the investigations being locally made by the Townsville laboratory. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>See answer to No. 1. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>DUKE OF WINDSOR</title>
                    <page.no>49</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Censorship of Wedding Films</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6P</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BROWN, Gordon</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BROWN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Trade and Customs, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Has the Government taken any step that will have for its effect the practical censoring of the moving pictures of the Duke of Windsor&#39;s wedding? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If any action was taken or is contemplated what is the form of such action? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Minister for Trade and Customs has supplied the following answers: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>No. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>The films will be dealt with by the Censorship Board in the same manner asany other imported films. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>NUTRITION</title>
                    <page.no>49</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KS9</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party>ALP; FLP from 1932</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, John Valentine</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator J V MACDONALD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Whether it is correct, as alleged to be stated by Dr. Nott ex-M.H.R., now of Canberra, &#34;That 40 per cent, of the babies born during the regime of the Lyons-Page Government are suffering from malnutrition &#34;, and if so, what action does the Government propose to take to remove such a state of affairs? </para>
                    </quote>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>49</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K2Z</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BRENNAN, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BRENNAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Minister for Health has supplied the following answer :  - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The information desired by the honorable member is being obtained. </para>
                    </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>DAYS AND HOURS OF MEETING</title>
                <page.no>49</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the days of meeting of the Senate, unless otherwise ordered, be Wednesday, Thursday and Friday of each week; and that the hour of meeting, unless otherwise ordered, be three o&#39;clock in the afternoon of Wednesday and Thursday, and eleven o&#39;clock in the forenoon of Friday. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERNMENT AND GENERAL BUSINESS : PRECEDENCE</title>
                <page.no>49</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, on all sitting days of the Senate during the present session, unless otherwise ordered, Government business shall take precedence of all other business on the notice paper, except questions and formal motions, and except that general business take precedence of Government business on Thursdays, after8 p.m.; and that unless otherwise ordered, General Orders of the Day take precedence of general notices of motion on alternate Thursdays. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>FRIDAY ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, during the present session, unless otherwise ordered, at four o&#39;clock p.m. on Fridays the  President  shall put the question - That the Senate do now adjourn, which question shall not be open to debate; if the Senate be in committee at that hour, the  Chairman  shall in like manner put the question - That he do leave the chair and report to the Senate; and upon such report being made the  President  shall forthwith put the question - That the Senate do now adjourn, which question shall not be open to debate: Provided that if the Senate or the committee be in division at the time named, the  President  or the  Chairman  shall not put the question referred to .until the result of such division has been declared; and if the business under discussion shall not have been disposed of at such adjournment it shall appear on the business-paper for the nest sitting day. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SUSPENSION OF SITTINGS</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, during the present session, unless otherwise ordered, the sittings of the Senate, or of a committee of the whole Senate, be suspended from 12.45 p.m. until 2.15 p.m., and from 0.15 p.m. until 8 p.m. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SESSIONAL COMMITTEES</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Standing Orders Committee</title>
                    <page.no>50</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a Standing Orders .Committee be appointed, . to consist of the  President,  the  Chairman  of Committees, Senators Brown, Crawford, Hardy, Herbert &#39;Hays, Johnston, A. J. McLachlan, and Plain, with power to act during recess, and to confer with a similar committee of the House of Representatives.. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Library Committee</title>
                    <page.no>50</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEoRGI</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a Library Committee be appointed, to consist of the  President,  Senators Collett, Collings, Dein, Duncan-Hughes, James McLachlan, and Millen, with power to act during recess, and to confer or sit as a joint committee with a similar committee of the House of Representatives. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>House Committee</title>
                    <page.no>50</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a House Committee be appointed, to consist of the  President,  Senators Brand, Cooper, Foll, Grant, J. V. MacDonald, and Uppill, with power to act during recess, and to confer or sit as a joint committee with a similar committee of the House of Representatives. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Printing Committee</title>
                    <page.no>50</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a Printing Committee be appointed, to consist of Senators Badman, Cox, Hardy, J. B. Hayes, Leckie, Allan MacDonald, and J. V. MacDonald, with power to confer or sit as a joint committee with a similar committee of the House of Representatives. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LEAVE OF ABSENCE</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>leave of absence</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Foll)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That Senators Duncan-Hughes, Guthrie, Plain and <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Walter</inline> Massy-Greene be granted two months&#39; leave of absence on account of absence overseas. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PUBLIC WORKS COMMITTEE</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That in accordance with the provisions of the Commonwealth Public Works Committee Act 1913-1930 the following senators be appointed members of the Parliamentary Standing Committee on Public Works, viz., <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Brand, Senator Brown</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Cooper.</inline></para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LONDON NAVAL TREATY BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That a message be sent to the House of Representatives requesting the House of Representatives to resume consideration of a bill intituled &#34; A bill for an act to enable effect to be given to a Treaty signed at London on behalf of His Majesty and certain other Powers &#34;, which was transmitted to the House of Representatives for its concurrence during last session of the Parliament, the proceedings on such bill having been interrupted by the prorogation of the Parliament. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>INTER-STATE COMMISSION BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That leave be given to introduce a bill for an act to make provision for the Inter-State Commission and for other purposes. </para>
            </quote>
            <para>Bill brought up, and read a first time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GENEVA CONVENTION BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>50</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That leave be given to introduce a bill for an act to enable effect to be given to Article </para>
                <para class="block">Twenty-eight of the International Convention for the Amelioration of the Condition of the Wounded and Sick in Armies in the Field, signed at Geneva on the twenty-seventh day of July. One thousand nine hundred and twenty-nine, and for purposes connected therewith. </para>
            </quote>
            <para class="block">Bill brought up, and read a first time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>BRITISH SHIPPING PROTECTION BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Brennan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the consideration of the British Shipping Protection Bill, which lapsed by reason of the prorogation, be resumed at the stage it had reached during last session. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SEAMEN&#39;S COMPENSATION  BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Brennan)</inline> agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That leave bo given to introduce a bill for an act to amend the Seamen&#39;s Compensation Act 1911. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>TRANSPORT WORKERS BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Brennan)</inline> agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That leave be given to introduce a bill for an act to amend Section 12 of the Transport Workers Act, 1928-1929. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>THERAPEUTIC SUBSTANCES BILL 1937</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Brennan)</inline> agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That leave be given to introduce a bill for an act relating to Therapeutic Substances and for other purposes. </para>
            </quote>
            <para class="block">Bill brought up, and read a first time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>REGULATIONS AND ORDINANCES</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Standing Committee</title>
                    <page.no>51</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>51</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have to inform the Senate that I have received the following letters: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>The Senate, Canberra, 17 June, 1937</title>
                    <page.no>51</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Mr. President,</title>
                    <page.no>51</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>In accordance with Standing Order 36a I hereby nominate Senators Abbott, Collett, Duncan-Hughes, and McLeay as members of the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances. (Sgd.) G.F. Pearce. </para>
                <para>Leader of the Government in the Senate. </para>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>The Senate, Canberra, 17 June, 1937</title>
                    <page.no>51</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Mr. President,</title>
                    <page.no>51</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>In accordance with Standing Order 36a I hereby nominate Senators Brown, Cooper, and J. V. MacDonald as members of the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances. (Sgd.) J. S. Collings. </para>
                <para>Leader of the Opposition in the Senate. </para>
                <para>Motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances be appointed, to consist of Senators Abbott, Brown, Collett, Cooper, Duncan-Hughes, J. V. MacDonald and McLeay, such senators having been duly nominated in accordance with the provision of Standing Order 36a. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
                <page.no>51</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Address-in-Reply. </para>
            <para>Debate resumed from the 17th June (vide page 19) on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline> - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the following Address-in-Reply to  His Excellency  the Governor-General&#39;s opening Speech be agreed to: - may it please your excellency: </para>
                <para class="block">We, the Senate of the Commonwealth of Australia, in Parliament assembled desire to express our loyalty to our Most Gracious Sovereign and to thank your  Excellency  for the Speech which you have been pleased to address to Parliament. </para>
            </quote>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>51</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                        <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - Very early in the speech delivered by the Governor-General yesterday, His Excellency referred to the portions of Australia which he had so far had an opportunity to visit, and to the fact that everywhere he was confronted with undoubted proof of the loyalty of the Australian people and a splendid spirit of confidence in the future of the Commonwealth. Although these imported gentry - these expensive gentlemen - have to be financed out of the taxation levied by the Parliament, I agree with the expenditure incurred until it exceeds the limits of decency. I do not refer to the more than adequate salary paid to the Governor-General, to the very fine perquisites he receives, or to the palace at Canberra, all of which are justified, but I do object to the fact that official residences are provided in other capital cities for these gentry. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. P. J. Lynch).</inline> - Order! To whom is the honorable senator referring? </para>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There is no need for mo to particularize. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>52</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- If the honorable senator is referring to the Governor-General, he is distinctly out of order in using his name disrespectfully in debate. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I am referring to the action of this Government in providing more than one official residence for the Governor-General. I have protested against its action in this respect on more than one occasion. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator also referred to the remuneration of the Governor-General. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Yes ; I approved of it. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator must know that he is not entitled to reflect upon the Governor-General. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If you, sir, can direct my attention to any remark of mine which can be construed as a reflection upon the Governor-General, I shall withdraw it; but I object to being accused of using words which I did not utter. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K09</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PAYNE, Herbert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Payne</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator referred to &#34; imported gentry &#34;. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KS7</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP; LP from 1944</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, Allan</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ALLAN MACDONALD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If that is not a sneer, I do not know what it is. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the honorable senator to withdraw the offensive remark. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- You are placing me in a difficult position. I did not refer to the gentleman himself. What do you wish me to withdraw? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable <inline font-weight="bold">Senator, referring</inline> to  His Excellency,  sneeringly  used the term &#34; imported gentry &#34;. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I included His Excellency in the general term &#34; imported gentry meaning imported gentlemen. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the honorable senator to withdraw the offensive remark. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In deference to you, sir, I withdraw it. I dislike doing anything that is disorderly. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There must be an unqualified withdrawal. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>52</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I withdraw the remark, because if I decline to do so I shall be prevented from concluding my speech. 1 do not know what degree of loyalty the Governor-General expected to find when he was on tour. I hope that he was not surprised, because Australians are notably not lacking in loyalty. I am just wondering whether the splendid spirit of confidence to which  His Excellency  referred is shared by the Government, because, judging by this Speech and by Ministerial actions, I am afraid that, it has very little confidence in the future of Australia. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">His Excellency</inline>
                    also referred to the disaster which occurred at Rabaul. I congratulate everybody concerned on the way in which that misfortune has been handled, and I draw attention to the fact that once again in a time of emergency private enterprise was very promptly superseded by Government control; in this way the very difficult position at Rabaul was quickly ameliorated.
                </para>
                <para>Later in his Speech the Governor-General made the following comment concerning the financial position: - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>The public credit in Australia has been maintained at a very high level with corresponding advantages to interest rates generally while the conversion of our overseas indebtedness to lower interest rates has been steadily carried on, as loans mature, with most satisfactory results. . Business generally is once more vigorous and expanding and the future may, therefore, be looked to with wolffounded optimism. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>In passing I draw attention to the fact that to-day Australia is paying more for its loan money than is being paid by most of the other countries which are using borrowed money for the development of their territories.  His  Excellency&#39;s Speech contains this further interesting statement : - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>Recorded unemployment which in 1932 had reached the previously unknown level of 30 per cent., has progressively fallen until to-day it stands at less than 10 per cent, a state of affairs which compares favourably with that existing before the depression. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>I say definitely that those figures are absolutely and totally unreliable; the claim that such a wonderful result has been achieved by this Government is neither true nor creditable to the authors of. it. The statement does say, of course, that they are &#34; recorded &#34; figures ; but </para>
                <para class="block">I point out that the only recorded figures are the numbers of registered unionists who happen to be unemployed at a particular date. No notice is taken of the thousands of our young people who are leaving school and to whom at present no possibility of securing a job presents itself. The Government is entitled to take credit for achievements resulting from its own policy, but in this instance it is taking credit to itself undeservedly. The Governor-General&#39;s Speech continues - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>My Advisors desire to repeat that this recovery would not have been achieved as quickly as it has been without the patriotic cooperation of the people as a whole and -the patient endurance of those who were the greatest sufferers from the depression. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>In face of all that has occurred and is still occurring, I have never listened to worse piffle in a speech from the King&#39;s representative. That statement is untrue; every one knows that the suffering was forced on the people affected, and they were neither patriotic nor patient in enduring it. In dealing with this Speech I propose to impeach this Government; I do not intend to let .it get away with grandiloquent language designed to deceive the people and to enable it to shirk responsibility for all the evils that are occurring in this country. </para>
                <para>Paragraph 3 of the Speech informs us that the Prime Minister and two other Ministers have been participating in the important deliberations of the Imperial Conference, and I understand from intimations given to honorable senators yesterday, that the result of those deliberations will be placed before us later. In passing, I shall only say, ihat everybody in this country with a mentality developed beyond the infantile stage, knows perfectly well that the Imperial Conference has been a dud,, and that the time occupied in its deliberations has been totally valueless to Australia. That is the only conclusion we can draw, if the information that has percolated to .Australia through the syndicated press- in which, by the way, I have very little confidence - and the syndicated _ wireless, which is controlled by the syndicated press, can be taken as reliable. This information shows that the conference has been a complete and tragic dud. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>53</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JUD</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DEIN, Adam</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Dein</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-  Did not the conference achieve anything of importance? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>53</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Ye3;  but those things could have been achieved without this conference. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>In paragraph- 14 of the Governor.General&#39;s Speech, the Government again takes great credit to itself for the fact that that magnanimous combination of captains of industry, the Shipping Confer^ once, has agreed very belatedly to make a reduction of freights to the amount of &#163;500,000 annually, the benefit of which, we are told, will be reaped mainly by primary producers who are obliged to use this transport. I am not in a position to question the accuracy of this estimate. My pleasure in reading this announcement was qualified by this further passage in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>With a view to reducing the costs to shipping, the Com mon wealth Government proposes to reduce light dues from Gd. to (id. per ton on all overseas shipping visiting Australian ports. The State governments have been asked to co-operate with a view to reductions in harbour charges. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>What a magnanimous gesture has been made by the shipping companies ! First the Government tells them that they are taking too much toll of the primary producers of this country, and they must cease doing so, but having made the companies see that they have been charging, excess freights to the extent of &#163;500,000 annually, it says in effect, to them, &#34;We do not want to soak you too hard, so we will give you a rebate of &#163;65,000 annually in respect of light dues.&#34; On examining the relevant figures I find that from 1932 to 1935-36 the total revenue collected from light dues was &#163;7S1,000, or an average of &#163;195,250 annually, and a third of that figure, &#163;65,000, the Government proposes to present to the shipping companies. These shipping magnates, numbers of whom were interested in the sabotaging of the Commonwealth Government line of steamers, should have been properly dealt with long ago. </para>
                <para>In paragraph 17  of the Governor-General&#39;s Speech, it is intimated that an amendment of the Seamen&#39;s Compensation Act, designed to bring the provisions of that legislation into line with modern conditions, will be introduced. As I do not know what will be the exact  nature of the amending measure, I cannot criticize it, but I hope that steps will be taken to deal effectively with those gentry who control our shipping and who, as an Australian judge said recently, &#34;have been sending coffin ships to sea.&#34; I hope that the Government will take notice of the representations made by members of the Opposition in this chamber to the effect that every vessel engaged on the Australian coast, and over which the Commonwealth has control, should be compelled to carry modern wireless apparatus in order to safeguard the lives of those on board. </para>
                <para>According to paragraph. 19 of the Governor-General&#39;s Speech, the Government proposes to push ahead with the ratification of the Statute of &#34;Westminster. Its action in this respect is very belated ; but better late than never. With this remark I conclude my references to the precious document presented to this chamber yesterday in the form of the Governor-General&#39;s Speech. </para>
                <para>I asked earlier whether this Government shared the confidence in the future of Australia that was expressed by the Governor-General. I suggest that the Government&#39;s approach to national problems - it does occasionally awake from its legislative sleep-walking and discover something wrong somewhere - and the method by which it proceeds to handle such problems, provide evidence of its tragic failure to understand the basic causes of those problems. It merely interferes and tinkers with the festering sores on the body politic, and glosses over its incompetence with statements praising the patriotism and enduring patience of the people, but never attempts to root out the diseases. I regret that I am unable to congratulate either the genius who compiled the Governor-General&#39;s Speech or the honorable senators who were given the difficult task of submitting to this chamber the Address-in-Reply. All parties to this document have my sincere sympathy; they have done their best to make bricks without straw. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Why did the workers apply to the Federal Arbitration Court for an increase of the basic wage by 12s. a week? They based their claim on the ground that industry was able to pay the increased amount. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall not attempt an explanation, but I know that the decision of the electors in the Gwydir division, in which by-election campaign <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Hardy</inline> was most prominent, clearly indicated their dissatisfaction with the present Government. I recognize, of course, that in the ramifications of our present system of parliamentary government there is such a thing as window-dressing for election purposes. I suppose that every government and every party feels that it has a right to do something in this direction. At all events I do not deny the right of the Government to do a bit of honest legitimate window-dressing, provided there is a sincere purpose behind it. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K08</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARKINS, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Arkins</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Provided also that the goods are on the shelves. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Political window dressing is legitimate only when the goods are on the shelves. If, on the other hand, they are all in the window, the results to the people may be disastrous, and I suggest that just as the street vendor or barrowman is by law punishable if he &#34; tops &#34; up his sales by substituting inferior quality goods for those displayed, so also should a government be punished if it indulges in window dressing for election purposes and does not subsequently redeem its election pledges by legislative enactment. This Government because of its failure to honour its promises will be so punished when the polling booth juries next assemble to record their verdict. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable gentleman had better watch his step or he may meet his Waterloo. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>54</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If I meet my Waterloo at the next election the loss to this chamber will be greater and more tragic than if half a dozen leaders of the Country party mat their Waterloo. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>This Government is not only bankrupt of legislative ideas, but, in this chamber at all events, is also suffering from mental pernicious anaemia, as is evidenced by its lack of supporters capable of adequately explaining even the feeble apology for constructive statemanship which has been submitted to us for consideration. </para>
                <para class="block">During its waking moments it babbles about national insurance to the press - but never to Parliament. In a newspaper statement published on the 22nd September, of last year the Federal Treasurer &#34;referred to inquiries now being made by British experts &#34;. The Governor-General&#39;s speech which was placed in our hands yesterday, also referred to &#34; inquiries now being made by British experts &#34;. Apparently we have to go to some other country which has made a tragic failure of social services, for experts to advise us in respect  of  national insurance, because, so the Government believes, no Australian is capable of giving sound advice with respect to this essentially Australian problem. The newspaper statement continued that the Treasurer &#34; considers that the investigation will enable them to provide the Government with a comprehensive report&#34;. We have been at the report stage for the last 20 years. It is positively dishonest now for the Government to say &#34;we are prepared after the elections to do something with regard to national insurance &#34;. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-  How long has national insurance been on the Labour party&#39;s platform? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- This Government also sent its delegates to the Geneva Labour Conference with instructions to support proposals for a 40-hour working week in respect of certain industries.. It is to our discredit that in nearly every other country employees have for long enjoyed a 40-hour week in some industries. If this Government had been sincere in its desire to do something, it could have provided for a 40-hour week for the whole of its employees, including those on public works, and thus set an example to the governments of the States and the world generally. In this connexion I am proud to say that Queensland has for many years had a statutory 44-hours working week. We are now waiting for the National Parliament to extend this system to its employees. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-  Read the Constitution and see if this Parliament has authority to do that. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- This Government talks of health and nutrition, and gives the little Minister a roving commission to ramble over Australia and entertain amused audiences with circus antics on the platform until they are like the old lady at the zoo, who, confronted with the elongated giraffe, declared in her bewilderment &#34; there ain&#39;t no sich animal &#34;. What does this Government care about the health and nutrition problems which are rampant in every working class home? So serious is the situation that a census taken recently in Victoria of the children attending public schools in that State, disclosed that only 19&#163; per cent, were without physical defects. The Government is still chattering about health and nutrition, but so far its only contribution to a solution of the problem is the appointment of commissions and boards of inquiry. Every one knows that all that is required is to give the working men and women decent homes to live in, and reasonable wages for the work which they perform. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-  Does the honorable senator forget that there was a Labour Government in power in 1931? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator need not be concerned about what was done or . said by the Labour Government in 1931.  His  present preoccupation should be the political avalanche that will put a Labour Government in power at the next elections. In the Prime Minister&#39;s Policy Speech in 1934  -  and the statement was broadcast from hundreds of platforms - this Government promised that it would, forthwith, deal with the unemployment problem by putting in hand the work of standardizing the railway gauges throughout the Commonwealth. Some years have elapsed, but not one steam-tractor nor a single steam-scoop has been set to work; not a shovel or pick has been placed in the hands of idle Australian workmen to get on with the job. We are still waiting. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-  What is the present percentage of unemployment in Australia ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>55</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Hardy</inline> would refrain from asking absurd questions, he would probably be able to absorb some of the facts which I am placing before the Senate, and, with  his colleagues, might then soon be kneeling at the political penitent&#39;s form seeking salvation. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>This Government sends nervous old women of both sexes shivering to bed for fear of the bogy of an invasion through the vulnerable north of Australia by hordes of Japanese or others. At the same time it has unpatriotically imported an alleged patrol boat, which in its first exploit and after much expensive repair work had been done to it, has to be re-discovered from the air and ingloriously towed back to its base by the enemy prize ship which it had so heroically captured! What a wonderful achievement ! </para>
                <para>This Government has discovered, through its experts, both imported and indigenous, what every good. Australian already knew, namely, that there are within the confines of this continent vast coal and shale deposits and immense indications of potential flow oil. Yet it has not exploited any of them. It proposes to hand over this business to private enterprise. It talks of &#34; empire &#34;, of &#34;loyalty&#34;, of &#34;patriotism&#34; and &#34; defence &#34;. It scarifies the  Opposition  with baseless charges of disloyalty, but its only outstanding contribution so far, to the adequate defence of Australia, is to evolve plans for firmly establishing in this young democracy in the southern seas thieving, private-enterprise, profiteering armament manufacturers, that cancerous world scourge which has made Europe a seething cauldron of war, or inspired in the peoples there the paralysing fear of it. With all the opportunities available to it and with the full knowledge that manufacture of armaments by private firms is responsible for the apprehension that exists in the world to-day, this Government proposes to hand over the business to private enterprise. There would be le3s likelihood of war if there were not private manufacture of arms, and certainly there would bo  no prolonged war if there were not profit in the business of -armament making. </para>
                <para>This Government has also discovered that there are in Australia vast iron ore deposits and huge quantities of scrap iron, and its criminal contribution to Australia&#39;s defence problem, should a national crisis ever unfortunately arise, is to allow the export of both products from Australia. It has not the excuse that it did not know of what was being done, because in season and out of season, I have asked questions concerning proposals by foreign companies to exploit our iron ore deposits, and I have received all kinds of answers, tie purpose of which was to discredit my information. I was told first that the Government had no knowledge of such proposals, but later ministers admitted that a scheme had been formulated, but said that Brasserts Limited, the company concerned in the negotiations, was an. English concern and that English capital was behind the venture. On one occasion you, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. President,</inline> took me to task because I doubted the sincerity of the Government in respect of the answers given; but what I then said is now common knowledge. Practically every newspaper in the land is taking the Government to task for allowing the exportation of this valuable Australian raw material, and to-day we have the spectacle of a scientific representative of one nation actually supervising arrangements for the exportation of our fabulously rich iron ore deposits as fast as the ore can be taken out of the country. Honorable senators may be a little surprised at my earnestness upon this and other subjects which I have discussed from time to time; but I take the view that no good Australian with the capacity to think and a voice to express his thoughts can remain silent regarding the inactivity of this Government with respect to such matters. </para>
                <para>This Government knows that the nations of the world stands aghast at the fearful prospect of another world war ; yet it contemptuously sneers at those in this chamber, who, like myself, advocate an active policy of peace and goodwill at home and abroad, who. plead. for support of a universal language and demand legislation having world peace as its goal. </para>
                <para>I have no doubt that when the defence estimates come before us for consideration, we shall hear repeated some of the statements made by a representative of this Government during the Gwydir byelection. That gentleman, in a public address during the campaign, said, in so many words &#34; Ladies and gentlemen : I shall not mention the Labour party&#39;s defence policy, because it is well known to everybody that it has not got one.&#34; But what of this Government&#39;s policy? Fiscally it assaults and insults certain foreign nations and then sends its political head, whom it hates but dare not destroy, to the Imperial Conference, there to jibber, in a masquerade of statesmanship, of a Pacific pact! It permits hordes of aliens to come into Australia, while hypocritically professing its loyalty to the Australian national policy of a White Australia. It &#34; monkeys &#34; with the generally accepted policy of Australian protection, so that every session sees more and more reduction of the protective nature of the tariff, each reduction resulting in some Australian being forced into the ranks of either the unemployed, or that unhappy army which must perforce accept the dole. It talks grandiloquently of its great love for the primary producer but annually treats him as a mendicant, using his often appalling economic misery as a means of securing votes at election time. That brings me back to the statement which I made at the commencement of my speech - the Government is incapable of distinguishing between cause and effect. It either does not know the basic causes of Australia&#39;s national problems, or it does know them. If it does know those causes, why is every attempt to solve those national problems concerned only with the effects, rather than the causes? </para>
                <para>By some of the things that it has done, the Government stands condemned. But I cannot- blame it nearly so much for its acts of commission as for its acts of omission. The things left out of the Governor-General&#39;s Speech speak much more eloquently than do those which are in it. I say, further, that some of the things which are in it are childish; they are things which no self-respecting Government would have submitted to the gaze of the electors of this nation. The Government ought to have been ashamed to include in the Speech the unemployment figures to which I have already referred and then to refer to the patriotic and patient way in which the Australian people endured the misery of the depression years. It ought also to have been ashamed to take to itself credit for all the improvements mentioned in the Speech. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K09</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PAYNE, Herbert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Payne</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Government has not taken credit for all the improvements. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay,</inline> speaking with a sob in his voice, said last night- </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- He is not so good a &#34; sobber &#34; as is the Leader of the Opposition. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have more justification for my tears than the Leader of the Country party has for his laughter. Last night, with tears in his voice, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline> said : &#34; Surely honorable senators have not forgotten the depression years and what this Government inherited.&#34; He went on to say that in- flation, nationalization and repudiation were the main ingredients of the policy of the Scullin Government. In a moment of inspiration he used those three terms : &#34; inflation, nationalization and repudiation,&#34; but he forgot how to apply them to his argument. I shall take advantage of this opportunity to fill in the gap left by the honorable senator. First, I shall deal with inflation, a term which is supposed to scare us all when it is mentioned. But if the Government relies on a denunciation of inflation to win the next election, it will not succeed. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable gentleman still believes that the Commonwealth Bank should be controlled politically. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I believe that the Commonwealth Bank, like every other Government Department, will carry out the policy of the successor to the present Government as loyally as it has carried out the un-understandable policy of the mesalliance known as a composite Government. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- A Labour Government would interfere with the currency. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>
                            <inline font-weight="bold">- Senator Hardy</inline>
                            probably knows no more about inflation than he does about currency. He is on dangerous ground. Every owner of a motor car knows that if the tyres of his vehicle are deflated the only remedy is inflation.
                        </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K08</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARKINS, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Arkins</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- He must first mend the puncture. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>57</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Mending the puncture is merely a part of the process of inflation. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline>
                    proceeded to inveigh, against nationalization. I commend to the honorable senator and to those who hold his views, a book entitled
                    <inline font-style="italic">Business in Government,</inline>
                    which may be obtained from the Parliamentary Library. It is most informative, although it contains only what public men ought already to know, namely, that because of the decadence of the capitalistic order of society, governments in every country of the world are forced to adopt to an increasing extent a policy of nationalization. Private competitive enterprise has proved a tragic failure, and, therefore, governments everywhere, irrespective of their political beliefs, are obliged to take over more and more control. In other words, they adopt nationalization, a term which
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline>
                    mentioned as though it should strike terror into the minds of his hearers. Having declaimed against inflation and nationalization, the honorable senator proceeded to deal with the term &#34;repudiation&#34;. If the Government is relying upon a campaign in which &#34; repudiation &#34; is the key-word in order to win the next election, I sympathize with it. Its spokesmen last night did not improve a bad cause; they did not have even the capacity of members of the Ministry for making a good case out of a bad job. Only once in Australia has repudiation raised its head; and then a Labour Government scotched it at birth.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator is frequently to be seen in the company -of those who have advocated repudiation. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Evidently <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Hardy</inline> is concerned that I shall always be found in good company. I am sorry that I cannot compliment him on the company that he keeps, for during the Gwydir by-election campaign I frequently saw him with doubtful political associates. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- &#39;Does the honorable senator refer to &#34; Jack Lang &#34; ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline> is a thick and thin supporter of the Government, probably because he does not want to incur the disapproval of the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Pearce).</inline> While the honorable senator was speaking last night I could not help sympathizing with his leader, because frequently during his speech, and also during that of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marwick,</inline> the Government&#39;s case was given away. When <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline> &#39; referred to the 40-hours&#39; week I fully anticipated that he would proceed to tell the Senate of the Government&#39;s intentions in that connexion. He stated with all the force of which he was capable that &#34; a 40-hours&#39; week is on everybody&#39;s tongue &#34;. It is true that his voice was no louder than mine, but its lack -of volume was due to physical, rather than to mental, causes. He endeavoured to show that a working week of 40 hours is now within the realm of practical politics, and, as the mouthpiece of the Government, in that he was chosen to move the Address-in-Reply to the Governor-General&#39;s Speech, he argued that the determination of this subject should be left to the arbitration courts of this country. I should like to know when the honorable senator, and the Government for which he spoke, were converted to the policy of arbitration and conciliation. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KNZ</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HARDY, Charles</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hardy</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have supported it all my life. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>58</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Hardy</inline> is a .young man who does not remember the strenuous days when the Australian Labour party, at the cost of much sacrifice and energy, first advocated a policy of arbitration, until, in time, its enthusiasm had converted public opinion. The result Ls seen in the fact that young fellows like Senators Hardy, McLeay and Marwick now believe that the determination of working conditions should be left to the arbitration courts. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline>
                    then announced another wonderful discovery that he had made. Speaking as the one selected by the Government, from the galaxy of talent and beauty among its supporters, to act as its mouthpiece, he said: &#34;We learned during the depression that, when the primary producers suffer, everybody suffers.&#34; The depression to which he referred began in 1929 or 1930 and continued for some years. Not until then did the honorable senator learn the great truth which he enunciated ! In this connexion there is one further truth that he must yet learn - although I doubt his capacity to appreciate it - that when the workers of this country - all those who wrest the national wealth from the soil of this country and create it into commodities and articles required by the people - suffer, every other section of the community suffers also. Even that section of the community which the honorable senator has singled out for his special attention suffers. When one stratum of society is in trouble every other stratum is affected, although in respect of the upper strata, the incidence is not so tragic as in the lower grades.
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay</inline>
                    did not know that fundamental fact until 1929. I realize that he could not have learned it as- early as I did, for I am a much older man than he is; but now that he has acquired the knowledge, I hope that he will retain it for many years. With the . air of a Solomon, or a pundit, he went on to say that what the wage earner requires is not more leisure, but more money. What a discovery!
                </para>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>59</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                        <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                        <party>NAT</party>
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- And less gas. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>59</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The inference from that interjection is that I am getting rid of some gas at the moment. The sooner the honorable senator develops the capacity to spread a useful gas instead of the politically poisonous tear gas, with which he usually endeavours to envelop the Senate, the better.  His  gas does not mean anything, but it befogs and discomforts us, because we cannot see how to meet the attack. The honorable senator&#39;s remark is not clever. Talk is all that we can do in this chamber. We are sent here to talk, not to chop wood. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>Senators McLeay and Marwick, in moving and seconding the Address-in-Reply last night, undertook an almost impossible task. I listened most carefully to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marwick,</inline> and I hope that he will not misunderstand me when I say that the only pearl of wisdom he dropped was his reference to the tragedy of unemployed youths. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>59</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JUD</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DEIN, Adam</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Dein</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- We have not had any from the honorable senator yet. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>59</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is because I refuse to cast my pearls before swine. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marwick</inline> is sympathetic towards them; he wants to ensure that something is done for the relief of that tragic product of the depression, the workless youth. I can understand that, but I cannot understand why he has allied himself politically with a- muddling group of do-nothings. He referred to the apprenticeship laws, and said &#34; We shall have to do something about . them &#34;. Apparently he had in mind a man who, seeking a job and asked if he were a member of the union, and whether he had served an apprenticeship, had to reply in the negative. The honorable senator complained that many persons were unable to obtain jobs because they had not served an apprenticeship, and that the unions limit the number of apprentices in proportion to the number of journeymen or tradesmen. The same charge has been voiced from time to time by my honorable friend <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Payne,</inline> who is a picture of funereal gloom   when he refers to apprenticeship laws, and charges those whom we on this side of the Senate represent with having strangled employment. Senators Marwick and Hardy know nothing of the past because they .suffer the handicap of youth, but some honorable senators, the greybeards of this chamber, know that the restrictions about which my honorable friends complain had to be introduced in order to curb the rapacity of private employers. Those restrictions were made for the same reason as every other regulation is made, namely, to prevent some evil or solve some problem. For instance, in the interest of safety and comfort, traffic regulations exist. If <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marwick</inline> does not know the origin of the apprenticeship laws I should like to take him under my paternal wing and school him in political economy. In the Parliamentary Library he may read of the horrors of labour exploitation that have prevailed,  and in some industries still prevail, in this country and Great Britain. I believe that if I coached <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marwick</inline> and others like him in the political and industrial history of their own land, they would see the error of their ways, and understand the problems which afflict this nation. They would realize that this Government cannot be effective, because it is incapable of understanding the basic causes of our troubles, and of distinguishing them from the mere outward and visible signs of the disease which afflicts the body politic. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>On the 12th November, 1936, I asked a question in this chamber relating to the distribution of financial assistance to the pearl shell industry. The question and answer are reported on pages 1728-9 of <inline font-style="italic">Hansard,</inline> Volume 152. On receipt of the information I proceeded to make investigations, the result of which forces me to express the hope that in any further distributions of largesse which this Government finds itself able to make it will see that the money goes to those who deserve it, and not to those who are not in financial need. My investigations brought forth the following facts regarding some of the beneficiaries: - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>Farquhar&#39;s Proprietary Limited, &#163;6911s. 6d. - The proprietors of this concern live on Thursday Island and are reputedly well-to-do. </para>
                    <para>Wyben Pearling Company Limited, &#163;32811s. 4d.- Originally Burns, Philp &#38; Company. Found their fleet of nearly twenty boats too cumbersome to be bandied in connexion with their merchandise and shipping agencies, and the Wyben Pearling Company was formed to take over the fleet. It is an offshoot of Burns, Philp and Company, and is understood to have paid handsome dividends, as high as 40 per cent, in one year. </para>
                    <para>Bowden Pearling Company Limited, &#163;269 2s.8d- Herbert Bowden, the original owner and now principal, left Thursday Island over 30 years ago to manage the affairs of Bowden Brothers and Company Limited, Sydney, in their large operations in Japan. Bowden has retired from business and is reputed to be a wealthy man. He has been a frequent traveller to Japan, Europe and America. </para>
                    <para>Charles Sinclair, &#163;70 8s. 6d.- This man was born in Torres Straits, his father having been one of the first white divers. He is the only pearler who is not financially strong.. Had the whole of the &#163;1,500 distributed on Thursday Island been given to him it might have been justified. </para>
                    <list type="upperalpha-dotted">
                        <item label="E.">
                            <para>J. Hennessey, &#163;106 18s. 5d.- This pearler has sold his fleet and is about to retire south. He stated he had received &#163;200 without expecting anything. He was so pleased, evidently, that he exaggerated the amount. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para>Morey and Company, &#163;177 13s. 3d. - <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Morey</inline> retired to Brisbane about twenty years ago, and has carried on no business since. He has now a working partner. </para>
                    <list type="upperalpha-dotted">
                        <item label="J.">
                            <para>B. Carpenter and Sons Limited,. &#163;91 9s. 2d.- <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Walter</inline> and William are both well off and reside in Sydney. It is said the former gave &#163;25,000 to Imperial funds to get the &#34; <inline font-weight="bold">Sir &#34;.</inline> They, or William, received also some of the grant for boats at Port Darwin (&#163;88 12s. 8d.). </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para>Austral Diving and Pearling Company Limited, &#163;24 0s. 9d. - This is a new concern I can ascertain little about, but I understand Walter Carpenter has formed it. </para>
                    <para>Cleveland and Vidgen Limited,. &#163;186 15s. 6d. - Both these pearlers reside on Thursday Island, but can hardly be deserving of public charity. </para>
                    <para>Wanetta Pearling Company Limited,. &#163;131 17s. 7d. - This company was owned by the late Reg. Hockings, who also had a coco-nut plantation on Aru Island under the Dutch. His estate should have been valued at about &#163;50,000. His two cousins now run the fleet and no doubt own it. They are both well-to-do. Reg. Hockings was a bachelor. </para>
                    <para>Aboriginal Company Boats, &#163;4311s. 2d. - These are under the Protector of Aboriginals. The natives own about 30 boats, but they are nearly all skin or swimming divers, who, apparently, were not considered worthy of much of the &#163;1,500. </para>
                    <para>In nearly all the cases the fleets were owned by one or two men who, on their retirement, formed companies to relieve their private accounts of any risks. </para>
                    <para class="italic">
                        <inline font-style="italic">Sitting suspended from 12.45 to 2.15 p.m.</inline>
                    </para>
                </quote>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>60</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- This morning I referred to the patrol boat operating in northern waters, and I understand that since the incident, which I mentioned the Government has been faced with a legal problem of whether the claim for towage charges made by the prize ship should or should not be paid. On previous occasions I have expressed my opinions concerning the activities of the Government, which, in endeavouring to increase its territory, may involve Australia in serious international complications. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>I also had something to say regarding the magnanimity, alleged more than real, of the shipping companies, which are reducing freights to the amount of approximately &#163;500,000 per annum. I showed quite conclusively that these reductions are not what they appear to be. Since speaking on the subject I have perused a report in a Brisbane newspaper, which supports this Government, and which prompts me to ask the Government if it is prepared to institute inquiries before extolling further the virtues of certain shipping companies which are alleged to have reduced freights. I should like it to inquire into what ha3 been done regarding the claim of the shipping companies for greatly increased freights for the carriage overseas of zinc concentrates from the Mount Isa Mine. If the Minister studies the report he will find that there is a good deal more in this subject than appears on the surface. </para>
                <para>On previous occasions I have referred to the long periods during which this Parliament is in recess. The last recess extended for about six months, -and, naturally, I, in common with other representatives of the people, strongly object to the closing of Parliament in this way. We are not permitted to carry out the work we are paid to perform. In December last the Prime Minister promised quite definitely that Parliament would reassemble before the Australian delegation left for the coronation and the Imperial Conference. We were told that we. would have an opportunity to discuss the policy to be supported by the Australian delegates at the Imperial Conference which has just concluded its sittings; but no such opportunity was afforded. </para>
                <para>I do not intend to elaborate what I said &#34;this morning concerning the syndicated press, except to say that the press of Australia is doing a great dis-service to those who undertake the national work in this country by continually belittling this and other Parliaments. You, sir, have, on more than one occasion, very eloquently directed attention to the serious state of affairs which exists. Whatever may be the opinion concerning the value of the services of individual public men, it is a national dis-service on the part of the pres3 to be continually belittling the efforts and credit of men in public life. The Australian press never misses an opportunity to ridicule this Parliament, and particularly this chamber. You, sir, have pointed out that the time which the Senate sits is not the important factor; what counts i3 the value of the work which it performs. The problems confronting Federal and State parliaments are now so involved and intricate that members are entitled to more consideration than they receive from the press of this country. I  believe  that the time is approaching when governments will have to take some measure of control over the press in order ihat politicians may be given &#34;a fair spin &#34; and also to ensure that the information which Australia is allowed to receive regarding happenings overseas may be more complete, instead of in the ridiculous and restricted form in which it is supplied at present. </para>
                <para>I repeat what I have said on previous occasions concerning the control of wireless broadcasting. I am wondering how long the Postmaster-General <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator A. J. McLachlan),</inline> who is closely associated with the Australian Broadcasting Commission, will allow the present state of affairs to continue. For some time I have been asking for a B class broadcasting licence for the Trades Hall in Brisbane, but have always been told in a perfectly courteous way that, according to the experts, a suitable wave length is not available. I do not pose as an expert, but I know that powerful A and B class stations are being erected in different parts of Australia, and I should like to know why a station cannot be made available to the Labour party in Queensland. Why should there he this monopoly of the air? The Australian newspapers are privately controlled, and, consequently, Labour cannot expect any consideration from them, but there is no reason why one political party should be excluded from the air. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>61</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K08</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARKINS, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Arkins</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Our party is in a similar position in New South Wales. The Labour party has a broadcasting station in that State, but we have not. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>61</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The party to which the honorable senator belongs has unlimited funds at its disposal, and is able to pay for whatever propaganda it desires. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>61</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K3L</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SAMPSON, Burford</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sampson</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Our party is without funds. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>61</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If I were permitted to peruse the balance-sheet of the United Australia party I could dispute the honorable senator&#39;s statement. The large sums made available to that party enable its representatives to remain in occupation of the Treasury Bench. In New Zealand, where there is a Labour Government in control, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Savage,</inline> the Prime Minister, has established the most powerful broadcasting station in the Southern Hemisphere. In opening that station some months ago, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Savage</inline> said that the country and the Government intended to be independent of wireless transmitting stations controlled by a biassed press. A governmental station has been established in that Dominion for the dissemination of reliable information to the people of New Zealand and, in fact, to the world, as to what the Government is doing, why it is doing it, and what it expects to achieve. In Japan the wireless broadcasting of advertisements is prohibited. It is atrocious to realize that in Australia we cannot enjoy the privacy of our homes without being bombarded with a nefarious propaganda and endless advertisements. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>62</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K08</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARKINS, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Arkins</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is incorrect. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>62</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Does the honorable senator suggest that the privacy of our homes is not interfered with by advertisements ranging from beer to &#34;B.O. &#34; soap? I again ask the Postmaster-General whether the technical objections which now exist in respect of a B class station for the Labour party in Queensland are to prevail indefinitely or whether there is a prospect of our request being complied with? The Labour party has insufficient funds to enable it to pay for the use of B class transmitting stations already on the air. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>Of course, the Address-in-Reply will be carried by an overwhelming majority in  this chamber, and conveyed to.  His Excellency  with a great show of pleasure. But the Speech itself does not mean anything at all. I have dealt with some portions of it and also with points raised by the mover and seconder of the motion for the adoption of the Address-in-Reply. I have also endeavoured to reply to some of the disorderly interjections of honorable senators opposite, who take such an unholy delight in entering the arena when I am speaking. A few days ago I read a facetious comment to the effect that politicians possess two hats - one to throw into the ring and another through which to talk. I realized this morning how fully the hats through which some talk were being used. </para>
                <para>I now direct attention to the encroachment being made upon the accommodation provided in this building for the use of members of Parliament. This building is supposed to be a temporary structure, but a long time will elapsebefore a permanent Parliament House is erected. Unfortunately, through the trespass of Government departments, Parliament House is becoming merely a huge secretariat. In the interests of Australia, and of all concerned, the Parliament should take cognizance of the situation and reserve the accommodation provided in this building for the work of Parliament and those associated with it. The Prime Minister&#39;s Department alone has established a hive of industry in this building, and many of its officers conduct a good deal of their work here. Accommodation should be provided for them by the construction of the necessary administrative buildings. </para>
                <para>In moving around this Capital City I have noticed, with pleasure, the development which has taken place during the recess. Whatever government is in power, Canberra should be developed as rapidly as circumstances permit. I do not know whether honorable senators are aware of the building activity and general trade expansion that is taking place in Queanbeyan, only eight miles away. Hotels are being extended, new shops are being erected, and additional housing accommodation is being provided. That development should be in Canberra instead of in Queanbeyan, which is deriving most of the benefit from the wages paid to artisans in Canberra. In addition to building houses in Canberra for public servants, the Government should be erecting house for a resident artisan population. Many men who are employed in Canberra are compelled to live in Queanbeyan owing to the inability to obtain housing accommodation here. Additional Commonwealth departments should be established in Canberra at the earliest possible moment. The Government has failed in not having evolved a scheme of cheaper housing for the building artisans and others working for wages in this </para>
                <para class="block">Federal territory. It is not making sufficiently rapid provision for the housing of even those officers who are employed in the departments already transferred to Canberra. Thus it is doing two evil things at once; not only is it enabling a neighbouring town to reap the advantage of such development as has been carried out, but it is also establishing, on the part of public servants, an ever-increasing vested interest in Melbourne and making the task of bringing them to Canberra more difficult. One of the first things which the Government should do in developing this city is, not to embark on new buildings such as one which has been recently forecast in the press, but to extend the housing accommodation so that the transfer of government departments may be completed without delay and the artisans and others who earn their living in Canberra may reside here and by their expenditure help to build up this city. We shall never have cheap building in Canberra until we have a resident artisan population. To continue the present neglect is to fail not only to develop this wonderful capital as we hope to see it developed, but also to do justice to lessees in the Territory, to public servants who cannot get accommodation except at hotels, and to other employees who ought to be here but whom the Government dares not invite to come here because it cannot house them. As this Government has the necessary funds for this work - it says it has another surplus - there is no reason why it should not allocate all the money necessary for putting men into re-productive employment in Canberra and thereby increasing the great asset we possess in this wonderful capital. </para>
                <para>I sincerely hope that the matters which I have raised will not be passed by merely as points mentioned in a speech in this chamber and recorded in <inline font-style="italic">Hansard,</inline> or placed in departmental archives never to be referred to again. Even if my suggestions be not acted upon, it would be to the advantage of the Government and. the Commonwealth as a whole if they were given some attention, and not treated as being unworthy of consideration merely because they emanate from a small Opposition, or regarded only as excuses for ribald wit on the part of honorable senators supporting the Government, who apparently are themselves unable to advance any worthwhile proposals. </para>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>63</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party>UAP</party>
                        <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>&#91;2.34&#93;. - I congratulate the mover and seconder of the Address-in- Reply on their businesslike and pithy speeches. Their remarks had the merits of being brief and to the point and of dealing strictly with the subjects under consideration. But how can I describe the speech of the Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Collings)</inline> ? Not having at my command the honorable senator&#39;s wealth of language I am obliged to fall back on borrowed phrases, and I recall a verse from Goldsmith which may be very appropriately applied to the oration to which we have just listened - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>While words of learned length and thundering sound </para>
                    <para class="block">Amazed the gazing rustics ranged around, </para>
                    <para class="block">And still they gazed and still the wonder grew </para>
                    <para class="block">That one small head could carry all he knew. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    seems to be worried because unemployment is decreasing ; that fact seems to rob him of one of his favorite texts upon which he expounds the gospel of labour. To-day he has no alternative but to question the figures; he really doubts, he says, whether the figures, which are given on the authority of the Commonwealth Statistician, supply a true picture of the employment situation in Australia.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>63</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I contend that they are not all-inclusive. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>63</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I propose to deal with that point. I have here the latest bulletin issued by the Commonwealth Statistician, which was made available to the press on the 17th April last. That bulletin deals with the very point which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> has raised in respect of the figures certified by the trade unions. Incidentally, I assume that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> does not question the genuineness of those figures.. The unions certify them as being correct, and we must assume that, being stalwarts of the Labour party, they would not publish false data. The question arises as to whether these figures can be taken as a reliable guide to the volume of unemployment. There are three ways in which this point can be examined. One is to compare the census figures with the unemployment statistics based on the trade union returns at the time the census was taken. These will be found to tally within a point or two, showing that the unemployment figures at the time the census was taken truly reflected the employment situation. But there are other means of checking the accuracy of these figures, and, in this respect, I invite <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> to look at the following very interesting statement contained in the Statistician&#39;s bulletin: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <quote>
                    <para>Working from the basis of the census of the 30th June, 1933, and from compilations made from returns of employers in remitting wages tax and returns collected from Government Departments, the Government Statistician of New South Wales has prepared an index of employment and unemployment covering all persons dependent on employment in New South Wales. </para>
                    <para>Honorable senators will notice that this statement deals with all persons dependent on employment. Of course, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> will probably say that the Government of New South Wales is not a Labour Government and for that reason its figures are open to doubt. In this respect, I am reminded of an occasion when a well-known political figure in New South Wales challenged the figures published in Coghlan&#39;s <inline font-style="italic">Year Booh.</inline> When figures from that authority were placed before him he asked where the book was printed and, on being told that it had been published by the Government Printer, he replied, in effect: &#34; There you are ; that is a Government publication; you cannot rely upon those figures &#34;. However, I shall now refer to an authority whom <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> will not question. In his bulletin the Commonwealth Statistician says: - </para>
                    <para>The Director of the Bureau of Industry in Queensland publishes an index of employment mid unemployment among men wage and salary earners. The data for this index are derived from information relating to unemployment insurance contributions and other sources. The results are given below. </para>
                    <para>I do not propose to give these figures in detail, but I shall refer to a relevant section of them. It is shown on the authority which I have quoted that in March, 1937, under the heading &#34; Excluding as employed the full-time equivalent of part-time men engaged on relief work &#34; the percentage of unemployment in New South Wales was 8.1 per cent. That is leaving out those who are employed on part-time employment; if those are included the figure is 6.S per cent. In respect of Queensland, under the heading &#34; Employment and unemployment among men wage and salary earners (in terms of full-time employment and unemployment, excluding normal seasonal variations)&#34; the figure for March is 8.6 per cent. Now we turn to the figures issued by the Commonwealth Statistician to see how they compare with the Queensland and New South Wales figures, the Commonwealth figures being based, of course, on trade union returns. For the March quarter of 1937 we find that the New South Wales figure for unemployment is 11.8 per cent. Thus, if the <inline font-style="italic">Commonwealth</inline> Statistician&#39;s figures err at all, they err in the direction of exaggerating the volume of unemployment, because the figures taken from all sources by the New -South Wales Statistician is S.l per cent. The Queensland figure for the March quarter of 1937, compiled from trade union returns, is 7.7 per cent., as compared with 8.6 per cent., the figure compiled from all sources by the Queensland Government. If <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> will study the publications which are issued from time to time he will find that he is on very unsound ground when he challenges the statement of unemployment as revealed in the report of the Commonwealth Statistician. </para>
                    <para>The honorable senator is unfortunate also in another respect. Despite his tale of woe and his attempt to paint a picture of widespread destitution and misery in this country, he will find that some of his own friends have been saying just the opposite. At the present time the trade unions are applying to the Federal Arbitration Court for an increase of the basic wage. What have the leaders of Labour in that sphere to say about the prosperity of this country? They have placed their arguments before that court, and from press reports it appears that the basis of their claim for an increase of the basic wage is that Australia is now fully restored to prosperity. I suggest to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> that he had better have a few words with some of the gentlemen in the army behind him, and tell them that when he is going to tell a tale of poverty and depression in this chamber, they should not give him the lie direct by their claims before the Arbitration Court. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>The honorable senator described the Imperial Conference as a dud. Only about three months ago, together with the Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives and other leaders in the Labour party, he was denouncing the Imperial Conference, by drawing a terrible picture of Australia being drawn into the spider&#39;s web, and being committed to all sorts of imperialistic policies behind the back of Parliament. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I did not say that. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.Perhaps not in those words.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Nor in any other words. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.The honorable senator was among those who tried to create the impression that real danger lurked in the mission undertaken by the Australian Ministers now visiting London. Was not that one of the reasons which they advanced in support of their contention that Parliament should be called together before the Prime Minister
                    <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons)</inline>
                    and his colleagues departed on that mission, so that Parliament might be told what they intended to do at the Imperial Conference? To-day, when the imperialistic tricks that Labour critics predicted have not taken place, and schemes to drag Australia at the tail of the United Kingdom have not eventuated, the honorable senator and his colleagues say that the Imperial Conference has proved a dud. Considered as a point for the coming election the conference certainly has proved a &#34; dud &#34; for
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    and his party, because the things which he said were going to happen have not happened. The honorable senator also remarked that the. Governor-General&#39;s Speech was so much window-dressing, but he had to admit that, as dressed, the window looked rather attractive. Consequently, he appeared to be somewhat perturbed. He told us that he had no objection to a little window-dressing for election purposes, but apparently his concern now is that the results are so good.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- What I complain of is that the Government is merely &#34;topping off&#34; its sales to the electors. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable gentleman to-day had the opportunity of a lifetime to point out to the electors which of the goods in the Government&#39;s shop-windows were in his view, spurious or defective. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is what I did. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.Oh no. The Leader of the Opposition had very little to say about the quality of the goods so displayed. As a matter of fact he scarcely referred to a single item in the shop-window, his remarks being directed mostly to the goods that were not shown in it. And that, I repeat, is his present trouble. That is why he objects to this window-dressing.  His  one concern now is that it i3 altogether too attractive for his liking; he fears that it will appeal to the electors.
                </para>
                <para>I come now to the subject of national insurance. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> this morning raised objections to the employment of two experts from the United Kingdom to advise the Government on thi3 important subject. Since national insurance is an issue of great magnitude, affecting all sections of the community, every precaution should be taken to see that any scheme we may propose is based on sound principles. We have not hitherto had experience of such a system in Australia. There has been unemployment insurance in Queensland for some years, but no system of national insurance. The United Kingdom, on the other hand, has operated some forms of national insurance for over 20 years. In the circumstances was it unwise on the part of the Ministry to seek the advice of two men who had actually been administering the British scheme and had a practical knowledge of its working? </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>65</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KS7</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP; LP from 1944</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, Allan</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ALLAN MACDONALD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- They have been identified with the scheme from its inception. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.That is so, and knowing its advantages and disadvantages, they were in a position to advise this Government with reference to the inauguration of a similar scheme in this country. What did these two men do when they came to Australia ? They immediately visited every state which is operating measures of social policy, in order to inform their minds of what is being done in Australia. Surely
                </para>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    will admit that before any well thought-out scheme can be introduced, those who recommend the form which it should take must know all about the operations of social legislation in the various States, in order to avoid waste of money and duplication of services.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- My objection is that these investigations have been going on for over 20 years. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.There has been no similar prior investigation of this particular phase of social legislation. I am aware, of course, that
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    has been so busy preparing his speech on the Address-in-Reply that he has not yet had time to read the report presented to the Government by
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Ince,</inline>
                    one of the British experts to whom reference has been made ; but I am sure that when he does read it he will find that
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Ince</inline>
                    has given careful consideration to all that has been done by the various States up to date.  His  report indicates to what extent State social legislation at present in operation will be rendered unnecessary in the event of the institution of a Commonwealth scheme. I am astonished that any one who wishes to see such a system inaugurated should object to the introduction of experts to assist us in formulating an effective scheme.
                </para>
                <para>As regards the 40-hour working week, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings&#39;</inline> desire seems to be that this matter should be dealt with, not by the Arbitration Court, but by legislation. If he holds this view so strongly, why does not the honorable gentleman appeal to <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forgan</inline> Smith, the Premier of Queensland, to enact State legislation along these lines? There is nothing - not even an Upper House - to prevent <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forgan</inline> Smith from introducing legislation enacting immediately a 40-hour working week in Queensland. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Leader of the Senate knows the reason. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I assure the honorable gentleman that I do not. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Commonwealth Parliament has not the constitutional authority to legislate for a 40-hour working week. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.As my colleague has reminded me, this
                </para>
                <para>Parliament has not complete powers to legislate on this subject. </para>
                <para>The Leader of the Opposition also went on to say that the Governor-General&#39;s Speech was, in many respects, a bed-time story.Well, I have listened to many bed-time stories over the air, and I confess that I have found some of them quite interesting. I cannot say the same of the speech delivered by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings.</inline> To me, his remarks rather resembled a horrible nightmare. The honorable gentleman did refer to some matters mentioned in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech, but I regret to state that his interpretation of them was quite incorrect. He kept referring to the policy speech delivered by the Prime Minister at the last election, and asked what the Government had done since then. For example, he told the Senate that nothing whatever had been done about the standardization of railway gauges. I am afraid the honorable gentleman has been asleep. Has he never heard of the construction of the Red Hill to Port Augusta railway on the standard gauge? This work was carried out in accordance with the recommendation of the commission which inquired into the standardization of gauges. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Is that work completed? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It will be completed shortly. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>66</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is about all that has been done. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.At any rate, it is something, and
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    said that nothing had been done.
                </para>
                <para>The Leader of the Opposition also criticized the Government&#39;s proposals to promote the extraction of oil from shale.  His  opinion seemed to be that, instead of coming to an agreement with <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Davis,</inline> who submitted a scheme to develop the Capertee deposits, it should undertake the work as a State enterprise. I remind honorable gentlemen that at various times many State enterprises have been undertaken in Australia, and some are still in operation. One is the State coal mine at Wonthaggi in Victoria. That venture, I understand, involves the State Government in heavy financial loss annually, and for the last twelve months its history has been one of almost continuous industrial disturbance. That, I suggest, is not very encouraging to the Government. I suppose .that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> would like us to know that the State coal mine in Queensland is being operated at a profit. It is true that it shows a profit, but this is earned by compelling the Queensland Railways Commissioners to buy the coal at a cost above its economic value. </para>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    had a good deal to say about the projected export of iron ore from Yampi Sound in Western Australia. That subject, also, does not appear in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech. Concerning it, all I have need to say is that the granting of mining leases is a matter within the sole jurisdiction of the State Government; in this instance the Commonwealth Government is concerned only with the export of the iron ore and the admission of people to be engaged in connexion with its purchase. Honorable senators are aware that H. A. Brasserts and Company Limited formed an Australian operating company to work the iron deposits at Yampi Sound on the understanding that the Nippon Mining Company would take the whole of the output. The scheme provides for the sale of the ore at the company&#39;s works at Koolan Island and not on delivery in Japan, so that it is necessary for a limited number of Japanese experts to remain on the island to satisfy themselves as to the proper grading and analysis of the ore, thereby eliminating difficulties and possibilities of disagreement. These experts, to be four in number, will not be engaged in development work of any kind, and the position in regard to them is to be reviewed at the end of twelve months with a view to determining whether the work of grading and inspection can be satisfactorily carried out by Australians. There is also to be one interpreter. The entry of these Japanese experts and interpreter for this purpose is on all fours with the admission into Australia of representatives of other countries for the purposes of inspecting, evaluating, and purchasing the wool clip. It is estimated that eventually 500 or 600 Australians will be employed in this enterprise.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    will see from this that the granting of the lease is a matter entirely for the Labour Government of Western Australia. It is no concern of the Commonwealth Government. The Leader of the Opposition suggested, but did not -say so straight out, that we ought to prevent the export of this iron ore to Japan. If that is his view, I ask him does he propose to stop there ? What has he to say about the export of ore produced from Mount Isa? Will the honorable senator urge that that should not be exported? Surely, if it would be right to prevent the export of iron ore from Yampi. Sound, it would be equally right to prevent the export of ore from Mount Isa. But if we did this, what would happen? I understand that if we prevented the export of ore from Mount Isa we should render unemployed about 10,000 men who are directly or indirectly connected with that enterprise.
                </para>
                <para>I am afraid that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Colling&#39;s</inline> knowledge of even the political history of Australia is somewhat shaky. He appears to be under the impression that the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Act was placed on the statute-book by the Labour party. I happened to be a member of the Labour party when that measure was passed by this Parliament. I know all the circumstances that led up to its introduction and adoption. I was a member, as you were, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. President,</inline> of the Labour party in Western Australia when the Arbitration Act was passed by the State Parliament, so it may not he out of place to remind <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> that the Labour party cannot claim the credit for that legislation. The Commonwealth act was introduced by the late,Mr. C. C. Kingston, a well-known Liberal in his day. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>67</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>NAT</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator A J McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Kingston</inline> had also piloted through the State Parliament a similar law. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.Mr. B. R. Wise, another Liberal, introduced an arbitration bill into the New South Wales Parliament and succeeded in getting it passed, and
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Sir John</inline>
                    Forrest introduced the Western Australian measure. Therefore, it is not true to say that we owe all our arbitration laws to the advent of the Labour party in the Commonwealth or State spheres, and it would be well if
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    were sure of his ground before he indulges in criticism regarding the initiation of social legislation.
                </para>
                <para>Another point raised by the Leader of the Opposition, but one not mentioned in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech, was the distribution of the grant to those engaged in the pearling industry at Thursday Island. Honorable senators are well aware that the grant was made because the pearl shell industry generally was then in a distressful condition. It was represented to the Government of the day that a grant should be made to them in order to keep the industry going. It was feared that, otherwise, it would fall entirely into the hands of the Japanese. Accordingly the grant was made, and it may be that some wealthy men shared in. its distribution. But the money was not paid to- them because they were wealthy. </para>
                <para>The honorable senator also referred to the patrol vessel in Northern Australian waters. I admit that for some of the work which it is called upon to do the <inline font-style="italic">Larrakia</inline> is unsatisfactory, but I remind the Leader of the Opposition that when that vessel was ordered it was not intended that it should be employed on patrol work at all. Honorable senators will remember that when the air mail service between Australia and Singapore was inaugurated it was operated by land planes. About that time there had been a number of air  catastrophies  in different parts of the world, where land planes had fallen ii.to the sea, and it was thought that it would be unfair to ask pilots to take similar machines across the sea unless speedy assistance could be given to them in an emergency. Australia&#39;s obligation was to look after that portion of the route between Timor and Darwin, and the vessel now used as a patrol boat was obtained for the purpose of going speedily to the rescue of aviators who had fallen into the sea. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>68</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It was not capable of doing even that without repairs and alterations. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>68</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That is not so. The Government has always recognized the unsuitability of the vessel for patrol work, and some time ago it ordered another vessel which is nov? under construction. In the meantime, the <inline font-style="italic">Larrakia</inline> has been impressed into the patrol service. In addition to the <inline font-style="italic">Larrakia</inline> there is a customs vessel now at Darwin; it arrived there within the last fewdays. Although a larger and more powerful vessel, it has not the speed of the <inline font-style="italic">Larrakia,</inline> but for the work for which it will be used it should prove reliable. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>The honorable senator complained that Parliament has been closed for six months. From his remarks one would imagine that a crime had been committed. It is extraordinary that honorable senators now find fault with a practice which has continued without complaint for 50 years in the State parliaments of this country. Since long before federation it has been the ordinary practice in every State for the parliament to sit for about six months and to be in recess for a similar period each year. No one found fault with that practice; but now that the Federal Parliament, the members of which are gathered, not from within the borders of one State, but from all over Australia, follows the same practice, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> and others are loud in their denunciation of it. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>68</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BROWN, Gordon</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Brown</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Prime Minister promised that Parliament would meet in March. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.Finally, I shall refer to the remarks of
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    in relation to party funds, and I do so as a warning to the honorable senator, because he is on dangerous ground. I have the confidence of the Nationalist party in Western Australia, and I. know that the experience there is that the party never has a feather with which to fly.
                </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>68</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator has made some good flights. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE.Yes, but not because of ample party funds. My only object in mentioning this subject now is to warn
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline>
                    of the danger of an inquiry being instituted into the source of the funds of the Labour party. I can tell him how the- funds of that party are raised in Western Australia. The most powerful trade union in that State, as in some of the other States also, is the Australian Workers Union. In Western Australia thousands of men who were out of employment were offered relief work; but a condition imposed by the Labour Government of that State is that each man before he becomes eligible for employment shall take out a ticket in the Australian Workers Union.
                </para>
                <para>SenatorCollings. - The right honorable gentleman is wrong. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>69</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The membership fee is 25s. per annum. If the relief workers have not sufficient money to pay the fee in a lump sum - and many of them, being on the verge of starvation, cannot do so - they are permitted to spread the amount over four payments. Obviously, the money represented by those fees is not necessary for carrying out the administration of the Australian Workers Union, because the union carried on successfully before the new system . was inaugurated. The balance-sheet of the Australian workers Union in Western Australia shows that approximately the equivalent of the fees obtained from relief workers is expended on political organizing in that State. In other words, the Labour Government of Western Australia, through its powers of administration, has financed the Labour party out of public funds. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>69</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KS7</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP; LP from 1944</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, Allan</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ALLAN MACDONALD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>-It has used public officers to collect the money. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>69</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- IfI were asked to say which is the more decent way to raise political funds - a voluntary contribution from those who support a political party, because they think its policy is best in the interests of the country, or a compulsory levy from those who, through unemployment, destitution and starvation are obliged to accept relief work - I would choose the former method. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Hardy)</inline> adjourned. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PAPERS</title>
                <page.no>69</page.no>
                <type>papers</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>The following paper was presented :  - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>Sent of Government Acceptance Act and Seat of Government (Administration) Act - Ordinance No. 7 of 1937 - Canberra Community Hospital (Inquiry). </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>69</page.no>
                <type>special adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the Senate at its rising, adjourn till Tuesday next at 3 p.m. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>69</page.no>
                <type>adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>69</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
                        <party>UAP</party>
                        <role>Minister for External Affairs</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - I move - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
                </quote>
                <para>This morning <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Johnston</inline> asked the following questions; - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>With reference to the sum of &#163;12,000,000 voted for adjustment of farmers&#39; debts under the provisions of the Loan (Farmers&#39; Debt Adjustment) Act 1935 - </para>
                    <list type="decimal">
                        <item label="(">
                            <para>1 ) How muchhas been paid to each State to date, under the terms of this act; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="(2)">
                            <para>What is the reason for the delay in making any balances due available to the States; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="(3)">
                            <para>When may the States expect to receive any balance of the amounts authorized for payment to the farmers under this act? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </quote>
                <para>The answer was not. available this morning but the Acting Treasurer has since supplied the following answers: - </para>
                <para class="block">
                    <graphic href="153332193706182_26_0.jpg" />
                </para>
                <list type="decimal">
                    <item label="(2)">
                        <para>and (3). The question of the provision of funds for this purpose is bound up with that of raising money for carrying out State public works. The amount which the Commonwealth is authorized to raise for farmers&#39; debt adjustment is determined by the Loan Council, which consists of representatives of the States and the Commonwealth. In coming to its decision, the Loan Council must have regard to the requirements of the several governments for their works purposes, and to the total amount of loan money available to the Loan Council on reasonable terms and conditions. The sum unanimously authorized by the Loan Council for the financial year 1930- 37 was &#163;1,500,000, and, with the exception of some small amounts yet to be drawn before the 30th June, 1937, it has all been paid to the States. No delay has occurred in advancing to the States the sums which the Loan Council has unanimously authorized the Commonwealth to raise for this purpose. The amount to be provided for 1937-38 will be determined by the Loan Council at its next meeting, to be held in July. </para>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <adjournment>
            <adjournmentinfo>
                <page.no>69</page.no>
                <time.stamp>15:11:00</time.stamp>
            </adjournmentinfo>
            <para>Senate adjourned at 3.11 p.m. </para>
        </adjournment>
    </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>