
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1948-09-03</date>
    <parliament.no>18</parliament.no>
    <session.no>2</session.no>
    <period.no>1</period.no>
    <chamber>REPS</chamber>
    <page.no>83</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para class="block">House of Representatives. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1948-09-03</day.start>
      <para>
        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline>Deputy Speaker <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr.</inline> J. J.  Clark) took the chair at 10.30 a.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PARLIAMENTARY PROCEEDINGS BROADCASTING COMMITTEE</title>
        <page.no>83</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline> Chifley) - <inline font-style="italic">by leave -</inline> agreed to - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That, during the absence of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Holt, Mr. Hutchinson</inline> be temporarily appointed in his place as a member of the Joint Committee on the Broadcasting of Parliamentary Proceedings. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>83</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SNOWYRIVER SCHEME</title>
          <page.no>83</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>83</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate>ROBERTSON, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Will the Prime </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Minister inform the House of the position in regard to the Snowy River water conservation scheme? Has anyagreement been reached between the Australian Government and the Governments of New South Wales and Victoria in relation to the scheme? Will the right honorable gentleman give to the House what information he has of this great scheme and an estimate of when it is likely to be implemented ? </para>
          <para>Mr.Chifley. - The Minister for Works and Housing will answer the question. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>83</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L0X</name.id>
              <electorate>FORREST, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Works and Housing</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LEMMON, Nelson</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LEMMON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Preliminary examination of the scheme indicated to the engineers of the Department of Works and Housing that it was worthy of further examination. At a conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers held in  1947  is was decided to establish a committee, representative of the Commonwealth and the Governments of New South Wales and Victoria to examine the engineering aspects of the scheme. The committee is to present its report to the three Governments concerned. It is anticipated that the report will be submitted to the Prime Minister early in November. I trust that when it is received it will be considered by the two States purely from the standpoint of the national value of the scheme. A great source of power remains untapped in the waters of the Snowy River and it is hoped that when the report is discussed by the three Governments the scheme will be considered without bickering between the. States and solely from the point of view of the benefits its implementation will confer upon Australia as a whole. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>83</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MOTOR VEHICLES</title>
          <page.no>83</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">Left-hand Drive. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>83</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KEP</name.id>
              <electorate>FRANKLIN, TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FALKINDER, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Mr FALKINDER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct a ques tion to the Minister for Transport. Is it a fact that the recent conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers discussed a proposal to ban the use in Australia of left-hand drive motor vehicles? What was the attitude of the Commonwealth towards that proposal? Was consideration given to the fact that large numbers of American Army jeeps are now  being used by Australian primary producers who would be placed in an unfortunate position if such a ban were imposed? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Mr.WARD- At the recent conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers, the subject of left-hand drive motor vehicles was raised at the instance of the Premier of Queensland, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hanlon.</inline> Attention was drawn to the great danger to public safetycaused by the increasing number of such vehicles on our roads. Some of the States have already taken action in the matter and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hanlon</inline> was anxious that a uniform practice be adopted in all States. After having expressed their opinion that no more of these vehicles, other than those imported by the consular services for their own use, should be registered, the conference expressed a desire that the subject be referred to the Australian Transport Advisory Council for consideration. That course will be taken. The problem will be listed for discussion at the next meeting of the council. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>84</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>POSTAL DEPARTMENT</title>
          <page.no>84</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Female Postal Assistants</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JPL</name.id>
              <electorate>BOURKE, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BLACKBURN, Doris</name>
              <name role="display">Mrs BLACKBURN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-In view of the  accepted Labour policy favouring the civil equality of men and women, will the Minister for Labour and National Service explain why women postal assistants now receiving 75 per cent. of the male rate of wages are to have their rate cut to a lower percentage? As these women are doing exactly the same work as men, carrying the same loads, making rounds of the same size, and working the same hours, will the honorable gentleman show how the proposed reduction can be justified? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KHL</name.id>
              <electorate>MELBOURNE, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>FLP; ALP from 1936</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HOLLOWAY, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Mr HOLLOWAY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not able to say whether or not such a reduction can be justified. That is a matter for determination by the Commonwealth Public Service Arbitrator to whom the ease has been submitted. I do not know whether a final decision has yet been made. I shall discuss the matter with the PostmasterGeneral and inform the honorable member in due course. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>84</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DISTILLATE AND POWER KEROSENE</title>
          <page.no>84</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate>RICHMOND, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ANTHONY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct a question to the Minister representing the Minister forShippingand Fuel. I have received letters and telegrams from farmers&#39; organizations in the northern part of New South Wales, notably in the Tweed district, who are anxious to increase production of primary commodities. They say that their members areunable to obtain supplies of distillate and power kerosene because of a restriction placed by the Department of Shipping and Fuel on the oil companies delivering these fuels. In these communications the oil companies arc accused of having oversold their quotas and it is alleged that because of this no further supplies will be made available to them until the 1st October. The worst consequence of that, of course, falls not upon the oil companies but upon the farmers, who are precluded from carrying out their preparations for spring sowing. Therefore, I ask whether the requisite fuel can be made available to the farmers, irrespective of what the oil companies may or may not havedone. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate>MACQUARIE, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Prime Minister</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- This matter has been the subject of a great deal of consideration. I shall not go into all the details regarding overselling, but it is completely clear that there has evenbeen propaganda in favor of the unrestricted selling of various petroleum products that are in short world supply.I do not know anything of the particular matter mentioned by the honorable member, but I can easily appreciate that, if  Prime  companies have been over-selling their quotas, farmers, through no fault of their own, may not be receiving essential supplies of fuel. In view of that, I shall make it my business to get in touch with the Minister for Shipping and Fuel and ask him to have an immediate inquiry made. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>84</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>CIVIL AVIATION</title>
          <page.no>84</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Missing Passenger Aircraft</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K0K</name.id>
              <electorate>GRIFFITH, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CONELAN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CONELAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Civil Aviation any information to impart to the House about the report that a passenger aircraft is missing between Brisbaneand Sydney? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>84</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KCM</name.id>
              <electorate>MARIBYRNONG, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Air</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKEFORD, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DRAKEFORD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have some information. I regret that it is not satisfactory. An Australian National Airlines liner, VH-ANK, left Brisbane for Sydney at 5.35 p.m. yesterday and was due at Mascot airport at 8.55 p.m. At 7.53 p.m. the crew of the  aircraft reported its position as being over Williamtown, the nearest airport to Newcastle, at a height of 6.000 feet, and it was cleared to come down to 4,000 feet. At 8.12 p.m. Mascot aeradio was in touch with the aircraft and everything appeared to he normal. <inline font-style="italic">No</inline> further message was received from the machine. At 9.15 a.m. to-day, a message was received from officers of the <inline font-style="italic">Caldare,</inline> a coastal vessel, that at 8.20 p.m. yesterday an aircraft was seen two miles off the coast at Terrigal, opposite Gosford, flying at 200 feet and apparently losing height. This position would be on the course of the missing aircraft. A Catalina flying boat has been diverted since that mews was received to search the area in addition to the other aircraft that have been searching since daylight  this  morning. I hope that news will come to hand soon and I trust, as I am sure all honorable members dp, that it will be of such a nature that it may relieve the anxiety of everybody concerned. It is understood that the aircraft had a complement of ten passengers and a crew of three. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>85</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN NAVY</title>
          <page.no>85</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Dreger Naval Base - -Medical Officers</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>85</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L0G</name.id>
              <electorate>FLINDERS, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RYAN, Rupert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr RYAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Parliamentary delegation which .has just returned from Japan, and of which I was a member, visited the Royal Australian Naval personnel .at the naval base of Dreger in New Guinea and inspected .the installations and amenities provided. Generally speaking, the conditions &#39;for both officers and ratings are satisfactory, but there is a shortage of electric fans. Only approximately 40 fans are provided at the base. &#34;Will the Minister for the Navy inquire into the position with a view to providing additional fans at an early date ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>85</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZ9</name.id>
              <electorate>KENNEDY, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for the Navy</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RIORDAN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr RIORDAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I shall have inquiries made and inform the honorable member of the position. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>85</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZR</name.id>
              <electorate>BALACLAVA, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Several surgeons and other medical officers are still retained in the Royal Australian Navy, although they enlisted merely for the duration of hostilities, and should have been demobilized soon after the termination of the war. As three years have elapsed since the cessation of hostilities, the chances of their re-establishing themselves successfully are rapidly diminishing. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>85</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DEPUTY SPEAKER, Mr</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Does the honorable member wish to make a speech on the subject? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- No,- I am merely making an explanation. The Minister for the Navy knows very well that representations for the release of these medical men have been made to him by relatives and by other honorable members. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DEPUTY SPEAKER, Mr</name>
                <name role="display">Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Order ! </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr WHITE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- As the Army demobilized its medical officers long ago, will the Minister for the Navy undertake that justice will be done to medical officers still in the Navy who enlisted only for the duration of the war, so that they will not be penalized because of their patriotism and loyalty? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZ9</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RIORDAN, William</name>
                <name role="display">Mr RIORDAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I thank the honorable member for his explanation of the background to his question. Had he paid attention during question time in days gone  by,  he would have heard other honorable members ask similar questions. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- -It is a pity the Minister does not do something to rectify the position. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <para>Mi:. RIORDAN. - The honorable member would have heard the reason for the retention .of some doctors in the service of the Navy. Certain medical men who still are retained in the Navy were enlisted as &#34; hostilities only &#34; which meant for the duration of the war and a period  thereafter.  Legally, they can be retained, but the Navy Department is most anxious to release those who desire to leave the service. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- What is preventing their release? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>85</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZ9</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RIORDAN, William</name>
                <name role="display">Mr RIORDAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- From time to time, I have been in communication with the British Medical Association on &#34;the matter, and only a fortnight ago spoke to <inline font-weight="bold">Dr. Hunter</inline> about it. I also had discussion last week with the Director of Medical Services, with a view to investigating the possibility of obtaining for the navy service medical officers from overseas, so as to release medical men still retained in the Navy. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>86</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>WHEAT</title>
          <page.no>86</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KWP</name.id>
              <electorate>WIMMERA, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">TURNBULL, Winton</name>
              <name role="display">Mr TURNBULL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture inform me whether the growers&#39; representatives will control policy and sales under the Government&#39;s scheme to stabilize the wheat industry, or will the Minister continue to do so? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KYC</name.id>
              <electorate>BALLAARAT, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Commerce and Agriculture</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">POLLARD, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Mr POLLARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government plan, which is subject to agreement by the States, provides for an Australian Wheat Board. Policy will not be affected by the plan because full and effective control over overseas markets is vested in the Commonwealth, and that provision will not he altered. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYV</name.id>
              <electorate>HUME, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FULLER, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Mr FULLER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I preface a question which I wish to ask the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture by quoting the following report which I have taken from the <inline font-style="italic">Daily Advertiser</inline> of the 28th August last:- </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Lockhart Farmers and Settlers Supports Wheat Stabilization. </para>
          <para class="block">Lockhart, Friday: At the Farmers and Settlers&#39; Association meeting to-day, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Kendell,</inline> M.L.A., for Corowa, said that notwithstanding some faults, he was going to support the federal wheat stabilization plan for the sake of young men taking up blocks. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DEPUTY SPEAKER, Mr</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Order ! What is the honorable member&#39;s question ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYV</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FULLER, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Mr FULLER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Minister inform the House of the progress being made by the various State governments in introducing legislation to give effect to a stabilization plan on a national basis? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KYC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">POLLARD, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Mr POLLARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have not any authentic information on the matter raised by the honorable member. I understand that the Government of Western Australia is taking a ballot of the wheat-growers of that State to ascertain whether they are in favour of the Commonwealth plan, and that similar action is being taken in Victoria and South Australia. I have no definite information about the desire of the growers in New South Wales, but I know that the Government of that State has indicated that it is in favour of the Commonwealth plan. In Victoria there are divided counsels, the Liberal section of the composite Government in that State being strongly in favour of the Commonwealth plan whilst the Country party section of that Government is rather indifferent to it. I understand that a similar situation exists in Western Australia. So far as the wheat-growers themselves are concerned, my information - and information leaks through to me from various sources - is that there has been a marked swing among them in favour of the Commonwealth plan. I am also informed that 75 per cent. of the wheatgrowers in Victoria are likely to vote in favour of the Commonwealth plan. I understand that a similar vote is likely in South Australia. I am not unconscious of the fact that this marked swing towards the Commonwealth plan, and the notable silence of members of the Australian Country party, has some association with the fact that world prices for wheat are falling, so that many people are anxious to get in out of the wet, and to obtain the benefits of the Commonwealth stabilization plan. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>86</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>METROPOLITAN PORTLAND CEMENT COMPANY LIMITED</title>
          <page.no>86</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>86</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KZJ</name.id>
              <electorate>REID, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LANG, John</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LANG</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Treasurer inform me: (1) Whether a permit was issued recently to the Metropolitan Portland Cement Company authorizing that company to import cement manufacturing machinery to the value of $950,000 from the Ford Motor Company of the United States of America, which involved a total expenditure of $1,189,110 to cover complete charges? (2) Who made the request for the release of such a large amount of dollars, and who made the recommendation for the grant? (3) Was the permit issued prior to the flotation of the company? (4) Was a portion of land owned by the Commonwealth near the Warwick Farm racecourse also sold to the company as a factory site? (5) Prior to the issue of the permit to expend such a large number of dollars for the purchase of machinery, were any inquiries made as to whether suitable machinery was not, in fact, lying idle in Australia? (6) Was the Government informed that two of the largest cement manufacturing plants in the Commonwealth were not in production? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>87</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think that the honorable member for New England <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Abbott)</inline> raised this matter, without mentioning the name of the company concerned, during the last sessional period, and he has since written letters to me on the subject. Indeed, I owe him an apology for not having answered his letters until after I returned from my recent visit abroad. The history of the flotation of the company to which the honorable members have referred has been considered by the Capital Issues Board. That body is, as every honorable member knows, a most reputable one, and the  Deputy  Governor of the Commonwealth Bank presides over its deliberations. I understand that a number of applications for the flotation of new capital have been refused by the board. I particularly inquired into this matter because of the attention paid to it by the honorable member for New England. As I say, the board has to deal with a great number of applications, and in many cases it has to point out to applicants that their applications do not conform to the board&#39;s requirements. The proposal is often amended to meet the criticism of the board and is approved in the amended form. My recollection is that that occurred in the case of this par:ticular company. The question of importation also arose, but that was a different matter, because it concerned the Treasury and the Commonwealth Bank. When a large sum of dollars is involved, the matter is referred to the Treasury and myself directly, particularly if there is any doubt as to whether the grant of dollars is warranted. In this instance, an application was made for an allocation of dollars for the purchase from the United States of America of secondhand plant for cement-making. I do not remember all the technical details of the type of plant that was sought. I asked Treasury officials, who are especially qualified for this work, to examine the whole proposition. After they had done so, it was decided to make dollars available for the purchase of this plant. It may be true, as the honorable member for Reid has said, that some cement manufacturing plants in Australia are not now in full production. In my own electorate, there are some which are not producing to full capacity. The reason is not lack of plant but lack of labour. Indeed, the development of new processes in the industry in recent years has enabled fewer men to manufacture greater quantities of cement. After the matter had been fully examined, I agreed to the granting of dollars, as I have done in hundreds of other cases. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>87</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JLL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Abbott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The application had to come before the right honorable gentleman? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>87</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>A48</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Yes, but I make it clear that not every application comes before me. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>87</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JLL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Abbott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I understand that; but this particular application did come before the right honorable gentleman? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>87</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>A48</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- An application for a large sum of dollars comes before me. For instance, applications by newspaper proprietors for dollars with which to purchase newsprint, and by the proprietors of the paper manufacturing plant at Boyer, in Tasmania, involved a large sum of dollars, and, therefore/ they came to me for consideration. In approving of the grant of any dollars, I have in mind that great developments are required in this country in connexion with our public works programme. The present programme involves an expenditure of nearly &#163;600,000,000. At the moment, there is not sufficient labour to man all the works, or undertake all the projects that we should like to begin. Of course, one can always question a judgment or opinion in this matter, but I did not see any reason why, all other things being in order, and in view of the report of Treasury experts, dollars should not be granted for the purchase of this cementmaking plant. Naturally, because of the dollar stringency, I grant any application with the greatest reluctance. In the matter to which the honorable member for Reid has referred, the importation of the plant did seem to me to make a contribution towards fulfilling Australia&#39;s cement requirements and, even more important, the sale of supplies in excess of local requirements will enable us to earn dollars. We could sell large quantities of cement, if it. were available, in the dollar area. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>88</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JLL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Abbott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Have we sufficient shipping for the purpose? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>88</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>A48</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I understand that some of the countries which urgently require cement, would provide the necessary shipping. We have granted an application by the management of the Boyer newsprint organization for a considerable amount of dollars, in the same way as we have provided a large amount of dollars for the Broken Hill Proprietary Company Limited, to establish a tinplate mill, which will save dollars. As I believe that the dollar stringency will continue for a long period, any expenditure of dollars which Will ultimately save dollars or earn dollars in the future always seems to me a matter which deserves earnest consideration. I have outlined the broad circumstances of the purchase of the cement-producing plant, but if any honorable member desires further details, I am always prepared to supply them. However, I make the qualification that I always endeavour to avoid&#39; divulging to the public intimate details of any business, because I do not think that that is proper unless a charge of corruption has been made. The information is given in confidence, and the confidence should be respected. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>88</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>RE-ESTABLISHMENT LOANS</title>
          <page.no>88</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>J7U</name.id>
              <electorate>DARWIN, TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYONS, Enid</name>
              <name role="display">Dame ENID LYONS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-- In view of the decreased purchasing power of Australian money since the legislation was framed to permit of the granting to ex-servicemen of re-establishment loans up to &#163;1,000, and having regard to the fact that the allowable amount of a loan for home-building has recently been increased, will the Minister for Repatriation recommend to Cabinet an increase of the allowable amount of re-establishment loans ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JNX</name.id>
              <electorate>BASS, TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Repatriation</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The matter of reestablishment loans is one aspect of government undertakings which I administer for the Department of Post-war Reconstruction. I shall examine the points raised by the honorable member to see what merit there is in the claim she has made, and will let her have a reply in due course. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>88</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HOUSING</title>
          <page.no>88</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>6V4</name.id>
              <electorate>MARTIN, NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DALY, Fred</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DALY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It has been brought to my notice that representatives of the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>New South Wales Housing Commission complain from time to time that some defence establishments, such as air force camps and army hutments, are at present not occupied by officers or men, yet are withheld from the State Government,, thus preventing their use as emergency housing. Is the Minister for Works and Housing aware of any service establishments which could be made available to the State governments? Are they being held for any particular purpose, or is there no foundation for the statements that have been made concerning them?&#39; </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L0X</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LEMMON, Nelson</name>
              <name role="display">Mr LEMMON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The policy of the Government has been to make available to all State housing authorities any surplus hutments, and any naval, army or air force establishments capable of conversion into temporary civilian housingaccommodation. New South Wales has fared extremely well under this policy,, for more hutments have been made available to it than to all the other States combined. I do not know of any establishments which are now surplus and could be made available </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>RABBIT SKINS</title>
        <page.no>88</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>88</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KDA</name.id>
            <electorate>WILMOT, TASMANIA</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">DUTHIE, Gilbert</name>
            <name role="display">Mr DUTHIE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I point out to the Prime Minister that the Australian rabbit has earned for Australia many dollars, which could be devoted to the purchase of wire netting for use in combating the menace, which is increasing, owing to the prices of skins falling. In view of the fact that production of wire netting in Australia is at present 4,000 tons annually, which is less than the 1938-39&#39; production- </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>88</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">DEPUTY SPEAKER, Mr</name>
            <name role="display">Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Order ! The honorable member is giving a great deal of information. I understood he intended to ask a question. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KDA</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DUTHIE, Gilbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DUTHIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am endeavouring to help the Prime Minister. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DEPUTY SPEAKER, Mr</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Order! The honorable member is not helping himself by his. attitude. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>88</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KDA</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DUTHIE, Gilbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr DUTHIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the great and continuing increase in the demand for wire netting by many primary producers of Australia who wish to utilize it to combat the rabbit menace, will the Prime Minister give earnest consideration to the possibility of importing certain quantities of this material from the United States? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>89</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Chifley</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Commerce and Agriculture will answer the question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>89</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KYC</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party>ALP</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">POLLARD, Reginald</name>
            <name role="display">Mr POLLARD</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- The Australian rabbit has been a prime earner of dollars in recent years. It is recognized, however, that it would be better to do without the rabbit and earn dollars by selling more primary produce. It is also recognized that, due to several years lag in the production of wire netting and to the great demand for it at the present time, many primary producers have difficulty in obtaining their needs. However, the question of the importation of wire netting from dollar areas or from any other source involves not only the question of dollar shortage but also the question of what would be an economic price which the farming and grazing community could afford to pay for the imported article. There is an organization in Sydney which has been busy for some months&#39; circularizing primary producers and primary producers&#39; organizations urging them to bring pressure to bear on the Government to import wire netting from dollar areas. This organization includes in its propaganda an order slip, but it studiously refrains from informing the primary producer what would be the landed cost of the wire netting. According to the latest information I have, the landed cost of No. 8 plain wire imported from the United States of America would be in. the vicinity of &#163;4 a cwt., compared with 28s. a cwt. for plain wire manufactured in Australia - although I admit there is an insufficiency of Australian-made wire. The landed cost of wire netting from the United Kingdom, according to the latest information I have, is about &#163;5 15s. peT cwt. for a 42-inch coil .of 1-i-inch mesh wire. Those costs  are  high and it is doubtful, even if there were a free flow of wire from overseas, whether primary producers could afford to &#34;buy it. For the information of -the honorable member and other interested parties, I .am obtaining figures showing the landed .costs of wire netting from the United States .of America and from other world  sources </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>89</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COTTON</title>
          <page.no>89</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>89</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLR</name.id>
              <electorate>MARANOA, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ADERMANN, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ADERMANN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that the matter of increasing the guaranteed price for cotton was discussed at the recent conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers and that the Prime Minister informed the Premier of Queensland that he would consider the subject further following that discussion. As the planting season is now about to commence, can the Prime Minister say definitely by how much the guaranteed price for this season&#39;s cotton will be increased? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>89</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is true that the Premier of Queensland, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hanlon,</inline> raised the matter of cotton production at the recent conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers. At that conference T pointed out to him that after the 20th of this month the fixation of prices will rest with the States. As I see it at the moment, there is no reason why, should the Queensland Government believe it to be desirable, the price of cotton should not rise to world parity. That is a matter for determination by the State Government in conjunction with the Queensland Cotton Board. One of the great difficulties in the fixation of a price for cotton which will provide an adequate net return to growers in Queensland is that certain charges are made by the Queensland Cotton Board in respect of its commitment to its bank. With the production of cotton at present at a low level, the charges to which I have referred amount, I understand, to 7d. per lb. Thus, whatever price might be obtained, about 7d. per lb. has to be deducted in order to enable the board to meet its commitments .in respect of certain&#39; advances. What I said to <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hanlon</inline> was that following on whatever happened after the 2Q.th September in respect of prices control, &#39;and probably before the end of this year., I would ask the Australian Government to examine the whole question of cotton prices.  I did not promise <inline font-weight="bold">.Mr. Hanlon</inline> that anything could be .done immediately, and I cannot make such a promise now ; but, certainly, something will be done within the next few months. In ,the meantime, it appears that for .this .season and, perhaps, for the next season, the cotton-growers could be amply .covered by ruling prices., if the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">State government and the Queensland Cotton Board allowed them to rise to world parity. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>90</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>IMMIGRATION</title>
          <page.no>90</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KFQ</name.id>
              <electorate>HENTY, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GULLETT, Henry</name>
              <name role="display">Mr GULLETT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Many of the migrants who come to Australia are qualified in various professions and trades, but they are unable to practise here because their qualifications are not  recog&#39;nized  by the authorities. This fact tends to discourage the migration of qualified persons to Australia. Will the Minister for Immigration confer with the State trade examining bodies and university authorities with a view to inducing them to set up a council to examine migrants on their merits regarding academic and trade qualifications, so that they will not have to do the whole course again, but will be given credit for the qualifications which they acquired abroad? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>BV8</name.id>
              <electorate>MELBOURNE, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Immigration</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CALWELL, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CALWELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I should be very glad if the State authorities would take a broad view regarding the recognition of degrees acquired abroad, and of the technical skill which many migrants possess. I think the honorable member, when asking his question, had in mind alien migrants rather than those of British birth, but there are complications regarding these also. I am not sure that Canadian medical degrees are recognized by Australian universities under any reciprocal arrangement, and we have no reciprocal arrangement with any foreign countries in this respect. When war broke out, the only two foreign countries with which we had an arrangement for -the recognition of medical degrees were Italy and Japan. There was no .reciprocal arrangement with university authorities in Holland, Austria, Germany, Belgium or France, for instance, and I do not think that there was any disposition on the part of the authorities in those countries to recognize Australian medical degrees. Why that should be, I do not know, because the standard of medical training in Australia is as high as in any part of the world. Indeed, Australian university standards in all faculties are particularly high. I am glad that the honorable member asked his question, because it might serve to shake some people out of their lethargy. At present, </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Australia is losing the benefit of the knowledge and skill acquired by immigrants during years of study. These people, who have come to make their homes in Australia must, under the present arrangement, begin <inline font-style="italic">de novo</inline> if they wish to acquire degrees in Australian universities. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>90</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SUBSIDIES</title>
          <page.no>90</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K0K</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CONELAN, William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CONELAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that the 12th September has been fixed as the date upon which the payment of subsidies upon imported cotton goods will cease. Can the Prime Minister say whether the subsidy will be payable on goods carried in a ship which arrives at Fremantle before the 12th September, but which does not unload the goods until it reaches its final port of call three or four weeks later ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Instructions covering this matter have been issued, apart from the general order in relation to subsidies. So that there will be no confusion, I shall arrange for the release at an early date of a statement giving exact particulars. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>90</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COAL</title>
          <page.no>90</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Employment of Polish Miners</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2A</name.id>
              <electorate>BENDIGO, VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RANKIN, George</name>
              <name role="display">Mr RANKIN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Immigration whether it is true that the miners&#39; federation has declined to allow Polish and other immigrants to work with members of that federation in Australian mining projects? If so, what reason has been given for the ban imposed upon these immigrants? Will the Government take suitable action against the federation to ensure that the Government&#39;s policy of giving immigrants a reasonable opportunity to be absorbed into the Australian population shall prevail? Has the Minister read a statement by the secretary of the Victorian branch of the Australian Labour party, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Lovegrove,</inline> that action taken by the miners&#39; federation against the Polish miners is part of the Communist cam,paign? Does the Minister agree with that statement? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>90</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>BV8</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CALWELL, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CALWELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I was expecting this question to be asked yesterday, and had begun to think that I should . have to wait until next Tuesday for it. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">
            <inline font-style="italic">I</inline>have seen the resolution of the council of the miners&#39; federation. I think that it is a most unfortunate resolution. I notice, however, that it says that members of the federation offer no objection to the employment of any person because of race, colour, or creed, and in that respect I believe that the federation is on firm ground. There is considerable misconception on the part, of the council of the miners&#39; federation regarding the types of -immigrants coming to this country. It is untrue to say that Poles are not accustomed to a democratic way of life. Many Polish ex-servicemen and displaced persons were members of social democratic ^parties in their own country. They wore not fascists or supporters of totalitarian refimes and their only desire in coming to Australia is to find an opportunity for a free and full life among democratic people. Of the Poles employed at Glen Davis, seven worked in British coal mines and were members of the miners&#39; federation of Great Britain, which, as the Prime Minister said last night, is a Communistcontrolled union. They have discharges from that union. These Poles at present are removing the over-burden or doing certain other work above ground. The miners have a legitimate reason for objecting to the employment underground of Poles who cannot speak English. They are entitled to some assurance that such Poles will not endanger the safety of other men. I think, however, that this legitimate fear on the part of the miners is being exploited. As no useful purpose can be served by wrangling with the council of the miners&#39; federation in the press or in other ways about this matter, I have asked the  president  and secretary of the federation to come to Canberra to talk the matter over with me. I am satisfied that if there are any valid grounds for criticism of the employment of Poles underground, we can remove those grounds. If the miners fear that the Government will bring Poles to this country to disturb industrial conditions, they may set their minds at rest. We have no intention of disturbing the mining industry; but the fact remains that in the last twenty years the number of men employed in that industry in Australia has fallen from 24,000 to 17,000. </para>
          <para class="block">We have been no more successful in securing sufficient miners in Australia than the people of England have been in getting enough miners from their own ranks. In the United States of America, the disposition of workers to undertake mining has changed to such a degree that the average age of American miners is now 42 years. We intend to bring to this country people from displaced persons camps and also - Poles who served with the British forces, particularly those who fought alongside Australians in the defence of Tobruk. . All these people will be found employment in this country. We cannot get too many of them. They are excellent types, and the Government will not be intimidated or told by anybody that migrants are not to work, here, there or anywhere else. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>91</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>WOOL</title>
          <page.no>91</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">Re-sales bt FOREIGN Countries. </para>
        <para class="italic">
          <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Abbott</inline>
          <inline font-style="italic">having earlier addressed a disallowed question to the Prime Minister,</inline>
        </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>91</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLL</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ABBOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Prime Minister read in the press the statement that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Robert</inline> Schuman, the French Foreign Minister, has taken strong exception to the allegations of the Australian Minister for External Affairs that France had re-sold Australian wool to the United States of America at a price below that paid to the Commonwealth? As France takes 90 per cent, of Australian sheep-skin exports, will the Prime Minister request the Minister for External Affairs not to imperil this market by making rash statements? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>91</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>A48</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
              <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have seen certain press statements but, of course, I cannot accept them as accurate reports of the conversations between <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Schuman</inline> and the Australian Minister for External Affairs. It has been clear for some time that Australian wool and other commodities have been re-exported from certain European countries in return for dollars which properly should have come to this country.  That  matter has been taken up at a high level. I have been in touch with the British Chancellor of the Exchequer, and he has broached the matter with the countries concerned. I have made a statement on the position  emphasizing that no governments had been concerned in the re-exporting of Australian commodities to dollar areas, but that this had been done by getrichquick business people who had been able to sell the goods at a discount, receiving half of the dollars back on the free market and making their profit out of those dollars. The honorable member for New England will understand that </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>92</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JLL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Abbott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Not the Prime Minister&#39;s explanation of it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>92</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>A48</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CHIFLEY, Ben</name>
                <name role="display">Mr CHIFLEY</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Again I say that no government has been engaged in this business. Most of the wool bought by France is purchased,, I understand, with credits arranged by Lazard Brothers under certain guarantees, I assume. As this is a revolving account, there is no suggestion that the French Government has used it to re-sell Australian wool for dollars. The honorable member for New England has mentioned a protest, by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Schuman</inline> against certain statements: made by the Minister for External Affairs. I should have imagined that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Schuman</inline> would have repudiated any suggestion that his Government had engaged in the re-selling of Australian commodities, and I have made it clear to the French Minister that no such suggestion has ever been made by me. I have spoken to the British Chancellor of the Exchequer about the matter because it concerns the Empire dollar pool. As one of the governments concerned was in the course of formation at that time, and it would have been unwise to have allowed this practice to develop, the Australian Government took action through the Commonwealth Bank which administers exchange control. This control will be administered stringently to ensure that we shall receive the dollar earnings to which we are entitled, and amy one who. seeks to break the regulations willbe dealt with drastically. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DAYS AND HOURS OF MEETING</title>
        <page.no>92</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chifley).</inline> agreed to - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That, unless otherwise, ordered, this House shall meet for the despatch of business on each Tuesday at 3 p.m.; on each Wednesday and Thursday at 2.30 p.m.; and on each Friday at10.30 a.m. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY REPRESENTATION BILL (No. 2) 1948</title>
        <page.no>92</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Johnson)</inline> - <inline font-style="italic">by leave -</inline> agreed to - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That leave be given to bring in a bill for an act to provide for the representation of the Australian Capital Territory in the Parliament, of the Commonwealth. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
        <page.no>92</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="block">Address-in-Reply. </para>
      <para class="block">Debate resumed from the 2nd September <inline font-style="italic">(vide</inline> page 83), on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thompson</inline> - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the following Address-in-Reply to the Speech of  His Excellency  the Governor-General be agreed to :  - </para>
      </quote>
      <para class="block">MayitpleaseYourExcellency: </para>
      <quote>
        <para>We, the House of Representatives. of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia, in Parliament assembled, desire to expressour loyalty to our Most Gracious Sovereign, and so thank Your  Excellency  for the Speech which you have been pleased to address to Parliament. </para>
      </quote>
      <para class="block">Upon which <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Lang</inline> had moved, by way of amendment - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the following words, be added to the Address: - &#34; and to inform Your  Excellency  that, because the Communist party, as an agency of a foreign power, admits it owes no allegiance to the Commonwealth of Australia, and because its avowed objective is the overthrow of constitutional government in Australia, with force if necessary, this House is of the opinion that your advisers should be asked to take the followingoption to deal with the grave emergency rapidly developing within the nation to threaten its security: - </para>
        <list type="loweralpha">
          <item label="(a)">
            <para>The Communist party and itsauxiliaries should be declared illegal, organizations and necessary legislation should be submitted to this Parliament to deal with them as treasonable agencies; (b)No Communist should be employed by the Commonwealth in any position involving the security of this country; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(c)">
            <para>The appointment&#39;s of all Communists on Government board&#39;s and agenciesshould be terminated immediately; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(d)">
            <para>All newspaper and newsprint licences of the Communist party and its auxiliaries should&#39; be withdrawn, and the despatch of its publications through the Post Office should be prohibited; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(e)">
            <para>All premises occupied by Communist organizations (including Marx House, Sydney) should be declared illegal premises, and all telephone facilities should be withdrawn by the Postmaster-General ; <inline font-style="italic">\f)</inline> Legislation based on the New  South  Wales Consorting Act should be introduced, making it illegal for members of the Communist party to consort together ; (i&#39;l That the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Act should be  amended to make it an offence for any registered trade union to pay any of its funds into any Communist party organization.&#34; </para>
          </item>
        </list>
      </quote>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>93</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>L1A</name.id>
            <electorate>Robertson</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I atn pleased indeed to have this opportunity to say a few words about the Speech delivered by the Governor-General upon which  His Excellency  has been so warmly congratulated by members of this House. I should like to add my congratulations to those already voiced both for the manner in which the Speech was delivered and also for the substance of it. The Speech opened with a reference to the Government&#39;s intention to donate &#163;10,000,000 to the United Kingdom Government. I am sure that every person in Australia will be pleased that the Government has expressed its intention to give this additional &#163;10,000,000 which, with the &#163;25,000,000 provided last year by this Parliament, makes a total gift to the people of Great Britain of &#163;35,000,000. We, in Australia, cannot do too much to assist the people of Great Britain who suffered so greatly and endured so many privations during the war in order that we might still be free. It is heartening to find the Australian Government co-ordinating so wholeheartedly with the United Kingdom Government in the relief of distress in Great Britain. A great opportunity is at hand for Australia to grow more food and so help to relieve the distress of the starving people on the other side of the world. Recently, I had the honour of leading a parliamentary delegation to Queensland. The members of the delegation, who were the guests of the Queensland Government, were taken to Capella, in central Queensland, where they witnessed a remarkable sight. The Queensland Government has started there a project which must appeal to the imagination of every Australian who wants to see our great country develop. At Capella, the Queensland Government has acquired a great property known as the Peak Downs Station, comprising 73,000 acres, and has in view the resumption of additional areas of land .until eventually it will have at least 500,000 acres under the plough. To witness the great tractors ploughing thousands of acres in a very short time, each giant machine ploughing a swathe as wide as this chamber, is indeed an inspiring sight. This project envisages the production of food in the grand manner such as has been employed in the United States of America for many years. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>93</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  And Russia, too. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>93</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Some honorable members opposite, like the honorable member for Richmond <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Anthony),</inline> are prepared to condemn any methods merely because they are similar to those adopted by Stalin. We do not care what Stalin is doing in that respect. Surely there ie nothing wrong in adopting good methods from Russia. I am sure that the Opposition members of the delegation applaud the methods adopted by the Queensland Government, which is operating in conjunction with the British Overseas Food Corporation, in implementing this project. The Queensland Government and the corporation have signed a joint agreement under which the former is to acquire the land. Of the &#163;2,000,000 to be invested in the project, &#163;1,500,000 will be provided by the corporation and &#163;500,000 by the Queensland Government. A. special body of men will be appointed to oversee this great project and to bring to fruition as soon as possible the sorghum crops that have been planted, and the sunflower crops from which oil will be extracted for the manufacture of margarine and the provision of much-needed cooking oils for the people of Great Britain. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>93</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  What is the principal crop ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>93</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In the main, sorghum will be grown for pig feed. It is planned to produce 500,000 pigs annually, which will be fed on sorghum grown nearby. These pigs will be slaughtered and shipped to Great Britain. Every person who has been to Capella has applauded most highly this great undertaking. When we view projects such as this we cannot but feel that those who  conceived them deserve the greatest credit. It is hoped that the rainfall in the Capella district this year will be up to average so that the project may have a successful beginning. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>The Governor-General referred in his Speech to the economic stability of this country. &#34;When one moves around Australia and talks to people in all parts of this vast continent, one finds that there is general agreement that the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Chifley)</inline> deserves the greatest credit for the economic and stabilization policies carried out by his Government, and it is usually given to him. Had not a firm hold been kept on the economic affairs of this country both during the war and in the post-war years, Australia would now have been in the shaky condition that many other countries are in to-day. The economy of Australia is an object lesson to the whole world, and the people in other countries envy us. We are proud of our Prime Minister.- We are proud of the way in which he has directed the affairs of this country, and our opponents, even the millionaires of Australia, must be thankful in their hearts that our economy has been kept so stable and that our assets are safe and sound to-day. They are, in fact, safer than they have ever been. Doubtless some people, in their desire for gain, are anxious to displace this Government, but I am sure that the average men and women of Australia who have given a little thought to these matters will be content to allow this Government to remain in control for many years to come. </para>
        <para>Reference was made in the GovernorGeneral&#39;s Speech to the defence of Australia, and we have heard a great deal of comment about this passage from members of the Opposition. No doubt we shall hear a great deal more from them in the same strain in the future. However, we can all remember what happened to Australia during World War II., when honorable members opposite were in power. When the war began, they were fighting amongst themselves, their parties were torn to tatters, and they could not produce a stable government to make this country safe for even one hour. They threw in the reins of government and the Labour party came into office. We all remember how quickly it stimulated the courage of the people and marshalled the whole nation behind it. That is history. In the light of. those facts, it is laughable for members of the Opposition to talk now about this Government neglecting the defence of Australia. I am sure that the people who have heard the criticism by honorable members opposite will hope that, should the world be so unfortunate as to be embroiled in another global conflict, a Labour government will still be in office in this country. The Labour party has a splendid record. It ha3 been kept in office by the people, who have great faith in it. There is little to be gained by raking over ancient history now, but I am impelled to do so when honorable members opposite condemn this Government and try to persuade the people that it has no policy for the defence of Australia. Their attacks inevitably bring to mind the events of a few years ago, when the people looked to a Labour government to save their country in its hour of peril. The people of Australia know that this Government stands side by side with the Governments of the United Kingdom and the United States of America, acts in close co-operation with them, and has the advantage of the advice of their experts as well as that of its own experts. Naturally the public cannot be told every detail of the nation&#39;s defence plans, but I am happy to place myself in the hands of this Government and its advisers,- and I have no doubt that a majority of Australians will be confident to do so also. </para>
        <para>The Governor-General referred in his Speech to the fact that, in view of the result of the recent referendum, controls over prices and land sales are being handed by the Commonwealth to the State governments. That is a very good thing. Further, I consider that the sooner we can throw overboard all war-time controls, the better it will be for the nation. We found it necessary after the termination of hostilities to keep certain emergency controls in operation for some time. As 1 have previously said, it was a good thing that we retained those controls, but as. we are returning to peace-time normality it would be a. good thing if we could get rid of them altogether. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>95</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- But did not the honorable member urge the people to vote * Yes &#34; at the referendum ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>95</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I did, but apparently the honorable member cannot understand that, when we asked the people for power to exercise those controls, we also told them that we would use the power only if necessary. Those controls have now gone back to the States, which have power to keep them in operation for ever if they want to do so. I say that such controls should not be permanent. They should operate only in special circumstances, and the special circumstances which led to their introduction will soon cease to exist. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>The Governor-General also made reference to coal production in Australia. Everybody realizes that, if our national development is to proceed, we must have increased coal production. I hope honorable members will forgive me if I refer again to central Queensland and to the coal deposits at Blair Athol, near the Capella district, which I mentioned earlier. There is a tremendous coal deposit at Blair Athol. It is not a coal seam in the ordinary sense of the word; it is a mountain of coal. It is covered by an overburden of about 30 feet of earth. When that overburden is removed, one can stand on pure coal. The deposit extends downwards for a distance of 90 feet .in some places, but the general depth is between 40 feet and 60 feet. It would be possible to supply the whole of Australia with coal from Blair Athol if we could open up a good railway system to the coast. Having seen coal being mined at Blair Athol, I urge the Government to develop open cut mining in Australia wherever possible. We must congratulate the Hanlon Government in Queensland upon its enterprise in obtaining overseas capital and concluding an agreement with a British company to lay down a new railway line from Blair Athol to the coast, the probable terminus being Mackay. When the line is completed, it will be possible to transport to port vast quantities of coal that are waiting to be mined. At present, Blair Athol is served only by a light railway running to Rockhampton about 250 miles away. It is impossible to transport the coal won at Blair Athol, which amounts to approximately 1,400 tons a day, over a light railway. The English company which is directing the project will require approximately five years to get its railway into operation, so that the southern States of Australia cannot look to Queensland to provide any quick relief of the situation brought about by the shortage of coal. Of course, we hope that the railway line, which is estimated to require five years to complete, will be ready for use in a far shorter time. However, I mention the exploitation of the coal deposit at Blair Athol as an instance of what a government of men of imagination can do, and to illustrate the results that follow from attracting overseas capital to Australia. There are many large financial institutions overseas which are ready to invest money in Australia and to assist us in developing our great continent. If we were in a state of war the railway line which I have mentioned would, no doubt, be constructed in a much shorter time, but in times of peace, when there is no conscription of labour and people are free to work when and where they like, all we can do is to endeavour to attract labour to the jobs where it is most needed. I shall say something later concerning that aspect of the matter. </para>
        <para>The Governor-General&#39;s Speech mentioned the subject of industrial arbitration. When the important measure which amended the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Act was debated in the Parliament last year a great deal of discussion took place on its merits, and the Government emphasized that its purpose was to &#34; stream-line &#34; the arbitration machinery of the country so as to avoid strikes. The leaders of the Government have continuously counselled the workers of this country to adhere to arbitration, and I take this opportunity to say to the workers that if they do not heed that advice they stand in great danger of losing the advantage which they have already acquired. I repeat that it is of the utmost importance to Australian workmen that they should heed the advice offered to them by the Labour Government, in the election of which they played so large a part. The tenor of that advice is that in adhering to the system of industrial arbitration they should obey the awards of the Conciliation Commissioners who were appointed by the Government. The men who were appointed Conciliation Commissioners were in most instances Labour men, of considerable experience of industry, who will be fair and sympathetic to the workers. I do not like to read reports of strikes following decisions of the Conciliation Commissioners, because those officials were appointed by the Government for the very purpose of conciliating industrial disputants. I can only say that I join with the leaders of the Government in their appeals to the workers of this country not to bring about chaos in industry by disregarding awards of the Conciliation Commissioners. The Australian Labour party has always favoured industrial conciliation and arbitration; in fact, it not only fostered the principle of arbitration, but over the years it has actively developed that principle. I realize tha.t the average worker has great faith in arbitration and desires to abide by decisions of the arbitration tribunals, but unless there is real unity between the industrial workers of this country and the present Government they stand in great danger of losing all the privileges that they have gained. If the present Government went out of office, to-morrow it is safe to say that the 40-hour week would not last fourteen days. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTY</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Archie</name>
              <name role="display">Mr ARCHIE Cameron</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I hope that it would not. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My friends opposite certainly hope that it would not, and they concede the truth of my statement. If the workers of this country want to hold the concessions which the present Government has given them- </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L0G</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RYAN, Rupert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Ryan</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government did not give those concessions to them; the 40- hour week was awarded by the Arbitration Court. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I repeat that if the workers want to continue to enjoy a 40-hour week it is up to them to support the present Government. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Are the farmers of Robertson working a 40-hour week? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The farmers of Robertson are very anxious that continuity of work shall prevail. They certainly do not want strikes; they want industrial peace. My friend the honorable member for Richmond <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Anthony),</inline> however, is very happy when strikes occur. He was most jubilant on the eve of the State by-election in Kogarah, because it was impossible, owing to the shortage of coal, for Sydney householders to have fires in their homes or for housewives to cook meals. Because of the plight of Sydney people at that time he was able to gain a miserable  political advantage, of which he ought to be ashamed. He certainly does not want to see industrial peace in this country, but the farmers, like every other sensible person in Australia, certainly desire that there shall be peace in industry. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANTHONY, Hubert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Anthony</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Do the farmers work a 40-hour week ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>96</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L1A</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLIAMS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Mr WILLIAMS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I know that the honorable member does not work a 40- hour week, and probably never will. 1 have spoken of the need to develop our great country, because we all realize that unless we can obtain additional population we cannot properly develop Australia. The truth of that observation is borne out when one travels over the vast distances of this country, sees its rich lands, and realizes its- enormous potential productivity. Undoubtedly, we have a vast territory, hut we must remember that its very vastness-is a temptation to other nations of hundreds of millions of people, who envy our possession of such a magnificent heritage. If we do not take positive steps to populate and develop our country we shall certainly have to reckon with those over-populated nations. Bearing in mind those considerations, I congratulate the Minister for Immigration <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Calwell)</inline> on the magnificent work which he has done in bringing migrants to Australia. For his achievements the Minister has been commended, not only by honorable members on this side of the House, but also by the Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Menzies).</inline> A recent report in the Melbourne press stated that the Leader of the Opposition paid a fine tribute to the Minister. The right honorable gentleman is reported to have said, &#34; <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Calwell</inline> has made as good a fight as possible. This country could take 20,000,000 people&#34;; and I agree with the right&#39; honorable gentleman. It is not often that I find myself in agreement with him, but I emphasize my complete agreement with him in this matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>The northern part of Queensland contains vast tracts of country which await development, and I consider that more migrants should be directed there. The migrants who come to this country should not be directed to the overcrowded  cities;  their proper place is in the rural areas, where they can play an active part in primary production. Furthermore, I believe that we should direct them to the most remote parts of the States, because those are the areas which are most in need of people to develop them. In any event, I should like the Minister for Immigration to direct more migrants to the northern part of Queensland. </para>
        <para>As a security precaution - world conditions are uncertain to-day - we must have more people. Northern Queensland has wonderful productivity, but it has not yet been properly developed. The more quickly we can settle people in that part of the Commonwealth to open up the rich country there, the better it will be for Australia. We must remember that northern Queensland played a tremendous part in World War II. From air strips at Mareeba, Townsville, and other centres aircraft took off to fight in the battle of the Coral Sea. Had it not been for the good work of cane-cutters and. cane-growers in providing labour and machinery for the rapid construction of air strips, those aircraft could not have struck such decisive blows in the battle. We should not forget the importance of northern Queensland in&#39; another world war, and the Australian Government must do everything in its power to develop that area. We in this Parliament are nationally minded. State boundaries do not mean very much to us. In our outlook, we are not narrow-minded or partisan. An honorable member who represents a Victorian constituency must atta-ch as much importance to the development of northern Queensland as he does to the development of his own State. I have no doubt that the honorable member for Barker <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Archie Cameron),</inline> who possesses a large mind, is anxious that Australia shall be developed on a national basis. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>97</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>U&#93;</title>
          <page.no>97</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>I now desire to refer to the PostmasterGeneral&#39;s Department, and the necessity for the development of telephonic communications in outlying areas. The Postmaster-General <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Cameron)</inline> has stated that an amount of &#163;42j000;000! will be expended under a three-year programme on the development of postal facilities. The sooner we can develop those facilities, the more quickly we shall relieve the distressed people who live in places other than the large cities. I should like to see the complete overhaul of postal facilities in the Wyong and Gosford districts, and, indeed, in other centres in my electorate. The farmer should be given some priority in telephonic communications, and a proportion of the cost of connecting a farm to the telephone line should be borne by taxpayers generally. In my opinion, the cost of connecting a farm to a telephone line is often extortionate, and a farmer should receive some relief from the present heavy charge. I know that the Postmaster-General&#39;s Department is suffering from the handicap of lack of materials and labour, but the PostmasterGeneral informs me that, as conditions improve, he will take all steps necessary to improve facilities in country districts. </para>
        <para>The people of Australia are anxious to see the country develop along the lines that I have mentioned. They want to know why great public works such as water conservation are not completed in a short time; why roads and bridges are not being constructed; and why new railway lines are not being laid, new rollingstock manufactured and existing rollingstock repaired. The reason lies in our lack of population. In simple terms, we have not sufficient people to do all the necessary work, and, in addition, we have not sufficient materials available for those works. Last month, the National Works Council approved an almost staggering programme, and made &#163;91,000,000 available to the States for expenditure on great undertakings such as railways and water conservation. That allocation was made on the basis of a survey of what the States could expend if man-power and materials were available for public works. The States have great developmental programmes, but we do not seem to be able to get the work done. Before we can make substantial progress, we must increase our population. I believe that the Government is doing its utmost to bring more migrants to Australia. Wl&#34;-&#34; &#39;Tip Pr;~p  Minister  visited London recently, he discussed this problem with  I .lie  ou. i.ea  Kingdom authorities </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>98</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate>Mr. Burke</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata" />
              <name role="display">Mr ACTING DEPUTY SPEAKER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Order! The honorable member has exhausted his time. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>98</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>L0G</name.id>
              <electorate>Flinders</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RYAN, Rupert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr RYAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>.- If I do not reply to the speech of the honorable member for Robertson <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Williams),</inline> the reason is not that I agree with his views or approve of his remarks. I rise to participate- in this debate for an entirely different purpose. Last night, the honorable member for Parkes <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Haylen)</inline> told the House something of the story of Australian members of the British Commonwealth Occupation Force, and I now desire to continue that account. I do so with great enthusiasm. The people of Australia, among whom I include members of this Parliament, have suffered for a long time under a grave misapprehension about the quality of our troops in Japan and the role that they are playing in that country. I must confess that when I went to Japan I was under the same misapprehension. From what I had read in the press and heard from other sources, I had a feeling in the bottom of my heart that perhaps our troops in Japan were nothing more than a bunch of bandits or a crowd of evil-doers and evil-livers. I suppose that that idea was somewhat excusable, because for a long time, the press had been giving a most unfavorable account of what had been taking place in Japan. Never at any time in this House have I heard a vigorous defence of our troops put forward by the people who should defend them. I refer to members of the Government, and, above all, the Minister for the Army <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Chambers).</inline> It is true that on occasions the Minister for the Army has called for a report, and has read it to the House, but so far as my recollection goes, he has never said what he should have said, namely, that we have in Japan what I consider to be the finest body of troops, in pearc-time, that now exists in the world. Therefore, I welcome this opportunity, which is the first that I have had, to inform this House of the exact position,, and to tell the people of Australia about it. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>As a delegation, we had five weeks in J apan. Of that period, we spent approximately three weeks in the British Commonwealth Occupation Force area. Originally, the British Commonwealth Occupation Force consisted of troops from Great Britain,. Australia, India and New Zealand, and  numbered  approximately 40,000 men. The withdrawal of the British and Indian troops, and, later the New Zealand troops, reduced the strength of the British Commonwealth Occupation Force to a comparatively small figure. Nonetheless, the remaining troops in Japan do represent not only Australia -but the British Commonwealth of Nations. That is of great importance to the Empire and ourselves,, and perhaps to the world as a whole. While we were in Japan, we were given opportunities to see everything that was to be seen there. We spoke not only to. officers but also to the non-commissioned officers and men of the various units in different areas, as well as in Tokyo. Consequently, we were able to form a good idea of what was taking place, what our troops were doing and thinking, and how they liked conditions in Japan. Having been a professional soldier, I can claim with justification to possess some knowledge of armies. In the course of my life, I have seen the armies of many countries in war-time as well as in peacetime, and, therefore, I am able to form a reasonable opinion of the value of our troops compared with those of other countries in the past and at the present time. For bearing, efficiency, discipline and morale I have seen no better troops in the world in peace-time, and I consider this is a reasonable interpretation of the position in Japan. </para>
          <para>The honorable member for Parkes mentioned, amongst other things, the picturesque ceremony of the changing of the guard in Tokyo, which takes place there twice a week. It has come to play an important part in the life of Tokyo itself. The troops assemble just off one of the main streets and, headed by a very good band, march for about a quarter to half a mile into the square in front of the </para>
          <para class="block">Emperor&#39;s Palace, -where the ceremonytakes place. Even now, after about three years, the ceremony is viewed by quite a number of Japanese, as well as others.  It  occupies about half an hour. The number of troops taking part is not now so large as previously, but, nevertheless, the spectacle is imposing. It brings the greatest honour to the troops themselves and to the people of Australia. Over the years, I have seen parades of the Brigade of Guards in London - the trooping of the colours, and other performances. I have seen my old regiment, the Royal Horse Artillery, which we always considered to be the best regiment in the British service, perform some outstanding exercises, yet, the display by our men that I saw in Japan recently was at least as good as the best show put on by the Guards Brigade, or my own regiment, and that is saying something ! This is due to the quality of the troops, and very largely to General Robertson, an able and efficient officer, who has learned, during the course of his own experiences, how to deal with and train troops. Great credit is due to him and to the fine body of officers he has under his command. I have not the time to mention all of their names, but they are an able and extremely keen body of men, who are doing a great job for Australia. I say this from my own knowledge, and the other members of th&#171; delegation can confirm this view. </para>
          <para>We interviewed General MacArthur, the Supreme Commander, several times. On the last occasion we were with him for two hours. Towards the end of the talk, he mentioned the Australian Army of Occupation in Japan, and, while L cannot quote his exact words, they made an impression on my mind. The General said that he had had experience of Australian troops in battle and knew them as fighting men second to none in the world. He had heard that in peacetime Australian troops did not make good garrison troops, that they were wild, undisciplined and unsuitable to perform peace-time duties in an occupied country. The General went on to say that after he had been with them in Japan for something like three years, those views had proved to be entirely wrong, as he had found that the Australians were the best troops under his command from the point of view of discipline and bearing. He said, in conclusion, &#34; They are a magnificent body of men, of whom Australia should be proud &#34;. Those words of General MacArthur confirm in every way what the members of the delegation saw in Japan. </para>
          <para>I wish also to pay a very short tribute to a body of men in our army known as the Field Security Police. They are mostly non-commissioned officers and are scattered right&#39; throughout the British occupied area, being sent in threes and fours to the larger towns, mainly in the back country, where there are no troops. It is their job to keep in touch with the Japanese and to find out what they are doing. Those men are performing splendid work. They send in returns as to the feeling in the  country  and, in addition, they give advice to the Japanese on a number of matters connected with the democratic way of life. We have every reason to be proud of them; they are extremely keen and intelligent. </para>
          <para>Coming now to the Air Force, we spent two days with Group-Cap tain Brian Eaton and his command at Iwa  Kuni  and had an opportunity to see the field exercises at  Takamatzu  on Shikoku Island, where they were carrying out tactical operations in co-operation with an American bombing squadron. There was with them a squadron of the Royal New Zealand Air Force. We were all impressed by the efficiency displayed, and particularly with the nature of the operations they were carrying out. It is true to say that at the present moment there are no squadrons of air forces anywhere else in the world better than these. They would be ready to go into action on 24 hours&#39; notice. </para>
          <para>I shall touch also on the administrative service. No army, either in peace-time or in war, can Garry on without an efficient administrative service. The members of the delegation took the opportunity to see everything possible of various administrative units in Japan and we inspected the barracks, messes and supply service activities. We also saw the Army and Air Force workshops at Kure and Iwakuni, all of these impressed us. </para>
          <para class="block"> Another matter of great interest, and importance to the people of Australia, is the excellent educational service which is being carried on in the command. The training courses last for a month, and there are classes in woodwork, painting, metal-work, languages and commercial science. A great many of the troops are taking advantage of this opportunity. In the course of a month they are able to get a good grounding in a subject. It is evident, therefore, that the men&#39;s education is not being neglected whilst recreational facilities are excellent. At the barracks which the Australian troops occupy in Tokyo right in the heart of the city, there is even a swimming pool, and there are also tennis courts. In addition, scattered in various parts of Japan, there are leave hostels where troops may stay for a week-end or for a week. We visited several of these hostels, and found that they were very well run. They enable the troops to get away from the routine of barrack life, and to obtain a change of air and scenery. Excellent work is also being done by such voluntary organizations as the Young Men&#39;s Christian Association the Young Women&#39;s Christian Association and the Red Cross, which, at their establishments, provide facilities for refreshment and amusement. </para>
          <para>There has been a good deal of talk in Australia about the families of Australians serving in the Australian forces in J apan. I am able to say that practically all of them are very happy. They are well housed, and are provided with servants. The only drawback is the cost of living. They live on a somewhat higher standard than they would in an Australian city, and this, naturally, entails greater expense. Thus, a private or a non-commissioned officer, with a wife and children to provide for, finds living very expensive, and I believe that something should be done to help them. These families are filling a very important role in Japan. They invite private soldiers and others to their houses, and provide a taste of home life to men who lack the normal female society to which they were accustomed in Australia. Moreover, the families are provided with Japanese servants, who come to them straight from their own Japanese homes. They observe the manner of living of the Australians, and carry back to their own people their impressions of men and women who have been reared in a democratic atmosphere. This indoctrination of the Japanese by their own people, who are brought into contact with members of the occupation forces, is going on all the time. Nearly 18,000 Japanese are employed by the armies of occupation, and all of them are brought into daily contact with the privates, non-commissioned officers and officers of the forces. Thus, they absorb unconsciously much information about the democratic way of life as practised by civilized people in other countries. For that reason, I believe that the families of soldiers in Japan play a very important part in bringing about a better mental attitude among the Japanese. </para>
          <para>I have discussed the quality of our troops in Japan, and the question naturally arises as to the purpose of their presence there. They are members of an occupying force. At the end of the war we, in common with the people of all the allied countries, felt that as we had succeeded in crushing our deadly enemy, we should keep our foot on his neck by maintaining a force of occupation in Japan. However, as time goes on, the opinion of people changes. The belief is now held by many people in Australia that the occupying force should be withdrawn. I do not propose to discuss that point at length now, though I shall seek an opportunity to do so later. In the meantime, it is sufficient to point out that our troops in Japan are filling a very important role as part of the army of occupation. It is the first time that Australian troops have formed part of an occupying force in any part of the world, and we are to-day setting standards for ourselves, and, perhaps, for the world generally, regarding what a force of occupation ought to do, and how it ought to behave. We are also creating a precedent for our own permanent army, and laying down the lines upon which it is to develop. Methods of organization and administration are being tried out in Japan, and valuable experience is being gained in regard to services and amenities. The people of Japan are observing the conduct and bearing of our troops, whose behaviour must have an important influence upon the J apanese, who are setting out upon the long and arduous road to democracy. </para>
          <para>I am glad to take this opportunity to discuss our forces in Japan because of the misapprehensions entertained by whole sections of the Australian public regarding the conduct of the troops, and the conditions under which they live. Fantastic stories have been told about the troops, just as fantastic stories have been told about the activities of the parliamentary delegation in Japan. Such stories are the result, partly of exaggeration, partly of invention, and partly of pure lying. For instance, we were told that the troops were being mentally and morally neglected. Nothing could be further from the truth. We were also told that Australian troops were engaged in blackmarketing on a large scale. It is true that some black-marketing occurred among some of the troops, if that is the proper way to describe it, but it was understandable in the circumstances. The temptation to indulge in black-marketing was very strong. At first, the yen was valued &#39;at 200 to the &#163;1,. and very little could be bought for 200 yen. For a packet of cigarettes it was possible to buy a great deal. Since the exchange is now at a more reasonable rate, being 1,090 yen to the &#163;1, the situation has altered. However, what black-marketing did take place was mainly a matter of a man selling a packet of cigarettes, or a bar of chocolate of his own for which he got much better value outside. Black-marketing means getting goods in an unauthorized way and selling them at unauthorized prices. That never happened on a large scale in Japan. </para>
          <para>The press has been trying to instil into our minds the idea that our troops in Japan are riddled with venereal disease. Many people in Australia, including some honorable members, believe that. I shall not deny that there is venereal disease among our troops in Japan, but there has never been an army, or an occupying force, in which that disease has not existed. It exists among troops even on home stations. Those who make this charge against our occupation forces should look round and ask themselves how much venereal disease exists in Australia. These stories, however, are gross exaggerations. Let us consider the facts: First, 80 per cent, of Australian troops who have passed through Japan have never had venereal disease; secondly, the monthly rate of venereal disease among our troops in Japan at present is 1 per cent, per month. Perhaps, that percentage is too high; but&#39; it is not so high as that among occupation forces elsewhere, and I believe that the rate among our occupation troops is decreasing. This story is a .bogy which should be laid to rest at once. These stories of neglect of our troops, black marketing and venereal disease are doing a great deal of harm at home as well as lowering the prestige of our soldiers in the eyes, perhaps, of the world. I talked with hundreds of men- during my visit to Japan, and I assure honorable members that the first question which half of them asked me was, &#34; Why are we being maligned in Australia? Why are we being maligned, above all, by the press? What have we done to deserve it ? &#34; These men stand as a credit to Australia, and deserve better treatment.&#39; The position is even worse than that. No less than six private soldiers approached me and told me that they had received letters from their fiancees in Australia, in which they were told, &#34;I will never marry a man of the type you &#39; appear to be &#34;. I know that there are a great many more similar instances. The honorable member for Perth <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Burke)</inline> told me of the case of a woman with a family, in Western Australia, the wife of a soldier now serving in Japan, who had a mental breakdown because she believed these reports and believed that her husband was living this terrible life. Such reports are entirely unfounded. The press as a whole is responsible for these stories; it is not so much the correspondents who earn their daily bread by sending in sensational reports to their newspapers, as the editors and managers who control those newspapers. They have the heavy responsibility of not belittling our troops, or allowing these lying statements to be made about our occupation forces. They should tell the facts; and the facts bring honour not only to our occupation troops but also to Australia, the country that bred them. </para>
          <para>In conclusion, I am very glad to have this opportunity to state the facts to the House and through it to the people of Australia. I want to allay the anxiety which exists among sections of our people with respect to the behaviour and moral worth of our troops in Japan. As an Australian, I am proud of the troops I have seen and proud to belong to their race. They are an absolutely magnificent body of men who are doing a splendid job. I only wish that all Australians could go to Japan and see for themselves what fine troops they are. I hope that the Australian leaders who are responsible for them will, in the future, receive some recognition at the hands of the Government. I hope even more earnestly that all those troops to whom, to-day, I pay this tribute will have given to them in the name of the Australian people and from the press of this country the recognition which is their due. </para>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>102</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JNX</name.id>
              <electorate>Bass</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Repatriation</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. -  .The House and the country are indebted to the honorable member for Parkes <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Haylen),</inline> and the honorable member for Flinders <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Ryan)</inline> for the forthright and considered approach which they have made to the problem that arises from reports which have been published in the press from time to time with respect to our occupation forces in J apan. The speeches of both honorable members were absolutely free from political bias, a rare occurrence in this  House.  Each of them made his speech in a very temperate way after giving the matter mature consideration following the visit of a delegation- to Japan during the recent parliamentary recess. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>102</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KHL</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">HOLLOWAY, Edward</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Holloway</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  They are two big Australians. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>102</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I agree with the Minister for Labour and National Service <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Holloway).</inline> The honorable member for Flinders, prior to his election to the Parliament, was a permanent  soldier.  He served with distinction in World War I., and he knows something about soldiering.  His  survey of the posi tion in Japan, the behaviour of our troops, the very high esteem in which they are held and the admiration that is felt for them by those who see them from day to day, is a tribute which, I am sure, all of us keenly appreciate. I should like to say that as a Minister I appreciate greatly what the honorable member said this morning, as I appreciated what the honorable member for Parkes said on the subject last night. The speeches of those two honorable members should do something at least to allay the fears of our people at home who have been led to believe the statements that &#39;have been made from time to time in the press about the conduct of our boys in Japan. <inline font-style="italic">i</inline> propose to make a few observations on the Speech delivered by the GovernorGeneral. The ceremony of opening the parliamentary session- was performed in keeping with the traditional practice of the Mother of Parliaments. I believe that we should continue to follow that tradition with which is associated a temperate measure of display and pomp appropriate in a democratic community. The Australian people recognize the value of our democratic system of government and the principle accompanying it, and all honorable members agree upon the necessity for its continuance. That system shows the world that here is a body of free people who may assemble without let or hindrance, with no secret police force or soldiers required to guard the GovernorGeneral as he enters this Parliament. That is something which all Australians, perhaps very quietly and without fuss, accept as their due and as a part of a system whose continued operation we all desire. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>The Speech of the Governor-General surveyed the activities of the Government during a considerable period, and also foreshadowed legislation which the Government proposes to introduce during the current session. There has been some criticism of it because it did not contain a reference to this, that or the  other subject, but the Governor-General&#39;s Speech is necessarily a brief survey of the past and an indication of the Government&#39;s future programme. On this occasion the Speech covered several pages, which His Excellency had the patience to read to members and which was broadcast to the people outside. The Government has been criticized because the Speech does not refer sufficiently to its future policy and programme. I am not much concerned about that because those who have any connexion with Parliament and parliamentary procedure know very well that one cannot cram into the GovernorGeneral&#39;s Speech all the programme envisaged for the session which the speech inaugurates. It is interesting to study the references that have been made by honorable members who have spoken concerning the Government, its activities, loss of prestige and failure to do certain things. I do not pay much attention to those utterances because after all political speeches are made from political angles. Naturally, members supporting a government say the things they believe about what has been done by the Government and express them in the best fashion possible. The Opposition criticizes the Government. But I have no complaint about criticism of .the Government by Opposition members. When the party to which I belong was in Opposition, I believed in criticizing the government of the day and I accept criticism from the present Opposition because it keeps the Government active. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JTY</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Archie</name>
                <name role="display">Mr Archie Cameron</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  Is the Minister feeling disappointed ? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I am not at all disappointed. I shall refer to matter published in the daily press, during the recess, touching the activities of the Government, and written .by individuals who have no political reason to make any observation at all about the soundness of the country&#39;s economy, the building of homes or building costs or any of various other matters. As a matter of interest, and because particular items do not appear in all the newspapers in Australia, and therefore may not be seen by all honorable members, I shall refer to a statement made by <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman</inline> Brookes which was published in the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline> of the 18 th August last. All I know of <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman</inline> Brookes is that he is an important man in the industrial life of Australia and has a high reputation in a number of other fields. The Melbourne </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para class="block">
            <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline>report of <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman&#39;s</inline> statement reads : - </para>
          <quote>
            <para>Australians might moan, hut their country was in a sounder economic position than any other country he knew, said <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Korman</inline> Brookes to-day. </para>
          </quote>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  Read out all he said, including his statement on taxation. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- If the honorable member will be patient I shall proceed. The statement continues - </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <quote>
            <para>Prices have been held down very successfully and even if there was a slump abroad Australia could withstand it. &#34;If only we can realize what a wonderfulposition  we  are in now and make the most of our opportunities, there should be no stopping us,&#34; said <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman.</inline> &#34; We can face the future with the greatest optimism.&#34; </para>
            <para>
              <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman,</inline>who is  chairman  of directors of Australian Paper Manufacturers Limited and Australasian Paper and Pulp Company Limited, returned a few days ago from a five-months&#39; business trip abroad. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">I do not propose to read the whole of  the  article. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  That is only a condensation of a long report. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- To please  the  honorable member for Balaclava &#34; <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr.</inline> White) I shall read the whole of  the  report. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-  It is still only a part  of  what he said. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>103</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The report continues - </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <quote>
            <para>Britain&#39;s economic position was far from satisfactory, he said. It was difficult to see how she would right herself, unless the Government organized an exodus of at least 10,000,000 people in the next few years. </para>
            <para>She might be able to feed 30,000,000 of her present population, but no more. It would have to be the policy of the Empire to spread her population in a way that would suit her economics. &#34; Personally, I think that Australia must take several million of the old country&#39;s surplus population in the next five years,&#34; said <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman.</inline> &#34; We need to make proper arrangements to take up to 10,000,000, if necessary - we have to see what we can do about ships, housing and employment. &#34; That should he the aim of any Government in office, no matter what its political flavour.&#34; </para>
            <para>
              <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Norman,</inline>who talked with <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Attlee</inline> and other Government lenders while in London, said that key men of the British Government seemed to be woefully lacking in &#34; Empire-mindedness.&#34; </para>
            <para> They hadn&#39;t travelled the Empire, and they knew little about Australia and our opportunities. </para>
            <para>Their present policy was wrong. They expected Britons to work harder than ever, yet the food provided, no matter how filling it was, was insufficient for hard work. </para>
            <para>He had been struck by the general lassitude of the people. They seemed to have lost the sting which was essential for any sort of progress. You could see that in their sport, as well as work. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">That is the entire article which appeared in the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald.</inline></para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>104</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KZR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">WHITE, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Mr White</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- That may be the entire article, but it is not a full report. The report is critical of the Government. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>104</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JNX</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">BARNARD, Herbert</name>
                <name role="display">Mr BARNARD</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I suggest to the honorable member for Balaclava <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. White)</inline> that any report critical of the Government would most certainly be published by the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline> in full. The article that I have quoted frankly states that the economy of this country is sound. The heading on the article is &#34;&#39; Australia Sound Economically &#34;. It is useless for the honorable member for Balaclava to endeavour to twist these statements to suit his own arguments. I assume that the <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline> has given a faithful account of the contents of the report in the belief that publication of that matter would be of advantage to the people of this country. The plain fact is that the. report is favorable to the Government and the honorable member for Balaclava does not like it. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>In the opinion of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. F.</inline> W. Fraser, Canadian Trade Commissioner in Australia, published in the press on the 6th August, this country is accomplishing the best job in price control of any country to his knowledge. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Fraser</inline> who had returned to Canada on leave said that prices in Australia were lower than in Canada, but that the dollar shortage was still a serious hinderance to trade with Canada. </para>
          <para>Interesting figures on housing costs have been given by another Australian who has been overseas recently. He is <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. C.</inline> E. Philp a Hobart architect who returned to Australia last month from San Francisco. I know this gentleman personally. In a press interview, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Philp</inline> stated that a two-bedroom weatherboard house at Lagoona  Beach, 60 miles south of Los Angeles, cost &#163;8,000 to build. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Philp</inline> also said that high prices in America included costs of central heating, refrigeration, stoves, and other modern needs. Wages were the chief factor. A carpenter in California earned &#163;6 a day. American workers received colossal salaries but living costs were equal to salaries. Many people with large incomes had to make their own clothes because they could not buy them. He added - </para>
          <quote>
            <para>I&#39;ve come back with more respect for price- fixing controls than when I went away. Australians should consider themselves lucky that inflation tendencies have been checked. </para>
          </quote>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Philp</inline>went to America to study modern architectural methods. </para>
          <para>These are the opinions of people who know something about conditions obtaining abroad to-day, and are able to make comparisons with conditions in Australia. Whilst there may still be room for improvement, it is clear that the economic policy of this Government has provided a sound basis for business enterprises. It is generally agreed that pricefixing in this country has guaranteed equity to the people of the Commonwealth, and has kept prices down much more successfully than has been the case in other countries. </para>
          <para>I was interested in the observations made last night by the Acting Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Harrison),</inline> who cited figures in an endeavour to belittle this Government&#39;s efforts. A review of the past is often amusing. I recall, for instance, that the Acting Leader of the Opposition was associated with successive governments which did nothing at all about housing. On many occasions while I was in opposition I voiced criticism of the housing situation in Canberra, which of course is the responsibility of the Commonwealth Government, but governments of which the Acting Leader of the Opposition was a supporter, and at one time, a Minister, took no action whatsoever, although hundreds of people were homeless in this city. The only contribution made by those administrations to a solution of Canberra&#39;s housing problem was to close the brickworks. No grants were made to the States for home construction. I shall not endeavour to answer in full the charges made by the Acting Leader of the Opposition, against this Government because I have not the figures, but I am sure that my colleague, the Minister for Works and Housing <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lemmon),</inline> will be able to tell the honorable gentleman just what has been done to alleviate the housing shortage throughout the Commonwealth. I referred to the matter briefly only because I realize that the Acting Leader of the Opposition knows quite well that he didnot state the facts. Everybody knows that more houses should be built. Any failure to provide homes has not been due to lack of finance. Ample funds have been made available by the Australian Government, both for the construction of homes and for the administration of housing schemes. </para>
          <para>I shall not deal with the Department of Repatriation at the moment, although the honorable member for Balaclava, as usual, had something to say about that matter. In the course of the budget debate, I propose to make a full statement on the activities of my department. To-day I am content to say that in the forthcoming budget financial provision for the care of ex-servicemen is more adequate than in any other budget in our history. I ask leave to continue my remarks. </para>
          <para>Leave granted; debate adjourned. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PAPERS</title>
        <page.no>105</page.no>
        <type>papers</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The following papers were pre sented :  - </para>
      <para>Commonwealth Public Service Act - Appointments - Department of Supply and Development - J . J. E. Glover, D. Johnstone. </para>
      <para>Lands Acquisition Act - Land acquired for Department of Supply and Development purposes - Hendra, Queensland. </para>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>105</page.no>
        <time.stamp>12:54:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para class="block">House adjourned at 12.54 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
  <answers.to.questions>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</title>
        <page.no>105</page.no>
        <type>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="italic">
        <inline font-style="italic">The following answers to questions were circulated: -</inline>
      </para>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Pharmaceutical Benefits</title>
          <page.no>105</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>105</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>F4T</name.id>
              <electorate>DARLING DOWNS, QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FADDEN, Arthur William</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Fadden</name>
            </talker>
            <para>nasked the Minister representing the Minister for Health, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>How many persons were engaged by the Government in connexion with its free medicine scheme ? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>How many of these persons are in receipt of &#163;500 a year or more? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="3.">
              <para>What are (a) their names, (b) designations and (c) salaries? 4.Upon what particular work are the persons mentioned in paragraph 3 at present engaged? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="5.">
              <para>What are the other employees doing? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>105</page.no>
              <name.id>KHL</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">HOLLOWAY, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Holloway</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Minister for Health has supplied the following information :  - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Provision was made for 117 positions,  of  which 61 are at present occupied. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>Twelve. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="198331194809031_22_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <para class="block">
          <graphic href="198331194809031_22_0.jpg" />
        </para>
        <list type="decimal-dotted">
          <item label="5.">
            <para>They are employed in the duties of their positions and assisting in the general departmental administration, in which there is a shortage of staff. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Australian National Airlines Commission</title>
          <page.no>105</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <question>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>105</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JLL</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ABBOTT, Joseph</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Abbott</name>
            </talker>
            <para>t asked the Minister for the Interior, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice-</inline></para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Did the Australian National Airlines Commission purchase a block of land in Elizabethstreet, Sydney, at the rear of its passenger office ? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>If so, who were the vendors? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="3.">
              <para>What price was paid for the land? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="4.">
              <para>Is it intended to use the property asa freight terminal? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="5.">
              <para>What is the estimated cost of alterations and other conversions being carried out on the site? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>106</page.no>
              <name.id>K9G</name.id>
              <electorate>KALGOORLIE, WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for the Interior</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">JOHNSON, Herbert</name>
              <name role="display">Mr Johnson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answers to the honorable member&#39;s questions are as follows . - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>No. The land referred to is part of a Commonwealth-owned property known as &#34; Phillip House &#34;, which is partially occupied by the Australian National Airlines Commission in connexion with its passenger and freight business. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>See answer to question 1. 3, 4 and 5. The information required is not available, but will be obtained. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </answer>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
  </answers.to.questions>
</hansard>
