<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <session.header>
        <date>1934-07-05</date>
        <parliament.no>13</parliament.no>
        <session.no>1</session.no>
        <period.no>5</period.no>
        <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
        <page.no>218</page.no>
        <proof>0</proof>
    </session.header>
    <chamber.xscript>
        <para class="block">Senate. </para>
        <business.start>
            <day.start>1934-07-05</day.start>
            <para>ThePresident <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator the Hon. P.</inline><inline font-style="italic">J.</inline> Lynch) took the chair at 3 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
        </business.start>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>218</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SENATE ADJOURNMENT</title>
                    <page.no>218</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>218</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Leader of the Senate say if there is any truth in the rumour heard in the lobbies of this chamber that it is the intention to adjourn the Senate to-night at 6.30 for seven days or possibly more? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>218</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There is no truth in the rumour, but probably the Senate will adjourn to-night until Wednesday next. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TOBACCO-GROWING</title>
                    <page.no>218</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Mareeba Experimental Station</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>218</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JRW</name.id>
                            <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">CRAWFORD, Thomas</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator CRAWFORD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council - (1) Is it the intention of the Government to vacate the tobacco experimental station at Mareeba? (2) Is it the function of the Commonwealth or the States to carry on experimental stations on the lines of Mareeba? (3) Can assurance be given that tobacco-growers in the Mareeba district will be provided with adequate instruction and assistance? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>218</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Minister in charge of Development and Scientific and Industrial Research</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Ianswered a similar question last week, but to clarify the position, I am now able to furnish fuller information, the honorable senator having given me notice of his question. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para> At a meeting in Hobart in February last of the Standing Committee on Agriculture, on which the States were represented by the permanent heads of the departments of Agriculture, agreement was reached unanimously that Commonwealth activities in respect of tobacco should be confined to research into disease and the conduct of tests of smoking quality, and that the States should assume full responsibility for field investigations into disease, selection, yield and quality improvement, and for instruction, demonstration, and field experimental work; further, that of the sum of &#163;20,000 per annum provided by the Commonwealth for instruction in connexion with the tobacco industry, &#163;15,000 per annum should be paid to the States and &#163;5,000 per annum to the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research. Queensland&#39;s share is &#163;3,750 per annum. In order that there should be no misunderstanding between the Comwealth and the State in regard to the conduct of the tobacco experimental station at Mareeba, the Prime Minister (Mr. Lyons) informed the Acting Premier of Queensland by telegraph onthe 26th June, 1934, that the station was not required by the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research for the conduct of the work allotted to it by the Standing Committee on Agriculture, and that, in these circumstances, advice would be appreciated as to whether it was considered that the station was of value from the point of view of the tobacco industry; also, if it was considered of value, why the Queensland Department of Agriculture declined to take it over, bearing in mind the functions allotted to the States and the funds provided from Commonwealth sources towards the cost of carrying out such functions. The Acting Premier replied by telegram on the 28th Juno as follows: - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Your telegram twenty-sixth connexion Mareeba tobacco experiment station, Department of Agriculture considers cost of maintaining station would be too great in relation to information to be gained therefrom which would be of value only to a limited number of growers even in Cairns hinterland. In view of wide variation in climate and soil types of tobacco lands in Queensland it is considered detailed information of greater value to growers generally and to individual tobacco-growing localities is to be obtained from our existing policy of extensive scheme of experiment plot work embracing trials in various districts and on the different soiltypes in each district. </para>
                    </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PRIVILEGE</title>
                    <page.no>219</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I  ask  you, Mr. President, as Chairman of the Joint House Committee, who authorized the locking of all doors and prevented access  to  the dining-rooms and lounge room for nearly three hours to-day? Was it for the purpose of excluding from those privileged places all members who did not desire to hear Mr. Latham&#39;s stirring story  of  his adventures during his jaunt to the East, at the expense of the Commonwealth? Will you see that members are not, in future, excluded from those privileged places in this building to suit the convenience of  any  Minister who desires to put over his &#34; thrillers&#34;- </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <speech>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>219</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Order ! </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- And will you compel them, if necessary, to &#34; strut their stuff &#34; in other places so that members will not be inconvenienced? Is the Attorney-General, by these mysterious meetings, trying to outdo Inspector Scott, of New South Wales? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator&#39;s questionis saturated with inferences and expressions of opinion. I therefore rule it out of order. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>WHEAT INDUSTRY</title>
                    <page.no>219</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KP8</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">JOHNSTON, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator E B JOHNSTON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the Leader of the Senate if it is the intention of the Government to pass, before the impending election, the necessary legislation for the assistance and preservation of the wheat industry? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- A  statement on this subject will be made at a later date. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PAPERS</title>
                <page.no>219</page.no>
                <type>papers</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>The following papers were presented :  - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>Lands Acquisition Act - Land acquired at Blacktown, New South Wales-For Postal purposes. </para>
            </quote>
            <para>Nauru Island Agreement Act - Ordinances of 1933- </para>
            <para>No.11 - Appropriation (Supplemental) 1932 </para>
            <para>No. 12 - Nauru Royalty Trust Fund Appropriation (Supplemental) 1932. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>FINANCIAL STATEMENT</title>
                <page.no>219</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Receipts and Expenditure, Consolidated Revenue Fund, 1933-34</title>
                    <page.no>219</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>219</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Assistant Treasurer</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>&#91;3.9&#93;. - I lay on the table the following paper: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para class="block">Statement of the receipts and expenditure of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, for the year ended 30th June, . 1934. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <list type="upperalpha-dotted">
                        <item label="I.">
                            <para>move - </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <quote>
                        <para>That the paper be printed. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para>When submitting the Supply Bill to the House of Representatives for consideration on the 28th June last, the Prime Minister informed members that he hoped to be in a position, within a few days, to submit a statement of the Consolidated Revenue Fund under various headings, showing the approximate results for the financial year 1933-34, which has just closed. </para>
                    <para>The financial returns for the year are not yet complete, but I am now able to give to honorable senators a statement showing the approximate results for the year. These results are subject to minor amendments when final returns come to hand. </para>
                    <para>The statement shows a balance of receipts over expenditure of &#163;1,301,616, as compared with the deficit of &#163;1,176,490 which was anticipated when the budget for 1933-34 was presented to Parliament. The results, therefore, indicate an improvement of approximately &#163;2,478,000 as compared with the budget estimate. The budget did not include &#163;3,045,000 provided during the year for relief to wheat-growers, of which &#163;1,254,000 was obtained from the flour tax temporarily imposed subsequent to the budget. The relief to wheat-growers thus absorbed &#163;1,791,000 of the ordinary revenue. Eliminating wheat relief expenditure and the flour tax, the total improvement in the budget may be set down at &#163;4,269,000. </para>
                    <para>This improvement is principally due to increases in revenue as compared with the budget estimate, the chief increases being :  - </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_1_0.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <para>The increased yields under all  these  heads of revenue are striking evidence  of  the general improvement of the conditions in Australia during the past year. In particular, the higher revenue from customs and excise, sales tax, and the post office, is a reflex of improved trade in many industries. The higher prices for wool also, of course, contributed  to  the general improvement. </para>
                    <para>The  total  expenditure for the year, including &#163;3,045,000 provided for  relief to  wheat-growers, was &#163;72,647,000, as compared with the estimated expenditure  of  &#163;72,801,000. The actual expenditure thus closely approximates the expenditure provided for in the budget. No payments were made during the year in respect of Australia&#39;s war indebtedness to the  Government  of the United Kingdom. The savings made by the conversion of  Commonwealth  debts in London in February last are not reflected in last year&#39;s  results,  whilst the full annual cost of  the  concessions made last year in respect of pensions, salaries, and taxation, was not borne by last year&#39;s budget. </para>
                    <para>When the budget is brought  down,  more detailed particulars of  last year&#39;s results  will be submitted  for the information of  honorable senators. </para>
                    <para>Question resolved in the  affirmative. </para>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>220</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>OTTAWA AGREEMENT</title>
                    <page.no>220</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Government, in interpreting the Ottawa agreement, consult beforehand with the States which would be affected by any decision it may make? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I  presume the honorable senator means the Governments of the States. It  would certainly be a departure from all previous practice for the  Commonwealth Government to confer with the government of a State in regard to a matter affecting, for instance, the tariff, which is wholly within the province of the Commonwealth Parliament. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Are not the various States sisters of the Commonwealth, and, in view of the fact  that  the Ottawa agreement is a unique compact, would not the Government be agreeable to a departure from the orthodox procedure ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is impossible to discuss a matter of this kind by means of questions and answers. I suggest that the honorable senator should take some other opportunity to put his views before the Senate. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I give notice of the question. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>FREMANTLE DOCKING FACILITIES</title>
                    <page.no>220</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7M</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLETT, Herbert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLETT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In considering any scheme for effective coastal defence, will attention be given by the Government to the necessity for the provision at Fremantle of adequate docking facilities? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>220</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- That matter has been the subject of correspondence between the Premier of Western Australia and the Prime Minister, (Mr. Lyons), and has been considered by the Government from the point of view of defence. An answer has been sent to the Premier of Western Australia pointing out that no defence moneys are available for that work at the present juncture. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LANG PARTY</title>
                <page.no>220</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>220</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Has the attention of  the  Leader of the Senate been drawn to the following letter in the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald</inline> of the 4th July last: - </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LANG PARTY IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA</title>
                <page.no>220</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">Leads in Vote at Australian Labour Patty Meeting. </para>
            <para>Perth, Tuesday. The desirability of the Federal Labour party making another attempt to effect a settlement with the Lang party of New South Wales was the subject of a debate lasting nearly three hours at a meeting of the State executive of the Australian Labour party at Perth Trades Hall last night. The result of the voting showed that the Lang element was in ascendancy. </para>
            <para class="block">Is the right honorable gentleman still of the opinion which he expressed last night that the mission of the honorable member for Dalley <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Rosevear)</inline> and myself to Western Australia &#34; fell flat &#34;? </para>
            <interjection>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>220</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                        <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                        <party>ALP; NAT from 1917; UAP from 1931</party>
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Yes </para>
                </talk.start>
            </interjection>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>MISSION TO THE EAST</title>
                <page.no>221</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Statement by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham</inline> - Cost of Trip. </para>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>221</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Has the attention of the Leader of the Senate been directed to the following item in the Sydney <inline font-style="italic">Sun,</inline> of the 5th July: - </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para> IN PRIVATE. </para>
                    <para>Lathamon the East. (From our Special Representative). </para>
                    <para>Canberra, Wednesday</para>
                    <para>Surprise has been caused by the actionof the Government in calling members of the Federal Parliament together for an informal private meeting to-morrow to hear a statement by the Attorney-General <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Latham)</inline> on the international situation in the East </para>
                    <para>It is stated that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham</inline> considers his statement should be imparted privately to members rather than be made on the floor of the House. </para>
                </quote>
                <para class="block">What is the right honorable gentleman&#39;s answer to those comments? </para>
            </speech>
            <talk.start>
                <talker>
                    <page.no>221</page.no>
                    <time.stamp />
                    <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                    <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                    <party>ALP; NAT from 1917; UAP from 1931</party>
                    <role />
                    <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                    <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                    <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                    <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                </talker>
                <para> My reply is that Mr. Latham will make a statement in the House of Representatives. </para>
            </talk.start>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>221</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- In view of the fact that the cost of the Australian political mission to the East, headed by the Attorney-General <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Latham),</inline> will have to be paid by the Australian people, why have not the reports of the mission been made public ! What were the nature and names of the declarations and titles bestowed on <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham</inline> and other members of the delegation by the Governments of the countries, including Japan, through which the mission passed ? </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>221</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- In referring to the delegation as a political mission the honorable senator is clearly expressing an opinion, and, therefore, his question cannot be allowed. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The delegation headed by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham</inline> was termed a diplomatic mission, but in the presence of the Sultan of Djokjakarta, and at other places at which it called, political speeches were made. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Order ! The honorable senator will be in Order in referring to the delegation as a diplomatic mission, but not otherwise. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I submit to your ruling, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. President,</inline> and substitute the word &#34; diplomatic &#34; for the word &#34; political. &#34; </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- As to the first part of the honorable senator&#39;s question I have already said that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham</inline> will make a report to Parliament. I ask the honorable senator to give notice of the second portion of the question. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTION</title>
                <page.no>221</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>NAVAL APPOINTMENTS</title>
                    <page.no>221</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister for Defence lay on the table of the Senate the written applications for positions in the Australian Navy forwarded to him during the last two and a half years by Senator Dunn? Will he also state how many, if any, of such applications have been successful? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para> The matter will receive consideration. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>RURAL REHABILITATION SCHEME</title>
                    <page.no>221</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7M</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLETT, Herbert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLETT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Government, in framing its rural rehabilitation scheme, consider the inclusion of measures to protect mortgagors from being sold up before the effective introduction of that plan? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator&#39;s question affects not only the policy of the Government, but also State legislation. It is not usual to make statements of policy in reply to questions. I can only say that the point raised in the question has not been overlooked. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>MARTIN BY-ELECTION</title>
                    <page.no>221</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- What was the reason for the concellation of the meeting at Hunter&#39;s Hill at which the Minister for Defence (Senator Pearce) proposed to deliver a political speech in favour of the United Australia party candidate at the Martin by-election? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>221</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- If the honorable senator shows as much industry in reading the newspapers tomorrow as he has exhibited to-day he will see the reason there. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>MARKETING OF AUSTRALIAN PRODUCTS OVERSEAS</title>
                <page.no>221</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Formal Motionfor Adjournment</title>
                    <page.no>221</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. P. J. Lynch).</inline> - I have received from <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> an intimation that he desires to move the adjournment of the Senate this afternoon for the purpose of discussing a definite matter of urgent public importance, namely, &#34; The marketing of Australian products in overseas markets, particularly in regard to trade relations with Great Britain&#34;. </para>
                <para class="italic">
                    <inline font-style="italic">Four honorable senators homing risen in support of the motion, &#39;</inline>
                </para>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>222</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ELLIOTT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>.- I move - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>That the Senate at its rising adjourn till to-morrow at 9 a.m. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">I do so because of the great uncertainty in the minds of the people of Australia, and even of members of this Parliament, in regard to the marketing policy of the Government, and the prospect of future markets in overseas countries, particu-1 larly the United Kingdom. That uht certainty  ha3  been increased, rather than lessened, by the recent visit of the High Commissioner, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce.</inline> Many Australians, including myself, followed closely the newspaper reports of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce&#39;s</inline> progress through Australia. Incidentally, I may say  that  most  men in  public life have come to regard newspaper reports of statements by public men as being like a child of which the  speaker  is the father and the reporter the mother. The child so often takes after the mother. Both in Western Australia and South Australia, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> emphasized the importance to Australia of the British market. He said that it represented practically the only overseas market for the things which Australia can produce. Those of us who hoped that his emphasis of the importance of that market would be realized by the governments of Australia, were disappointed when <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Bruce,</inline> speaking at Melbourne, advocated a policy of reduction of production and restriction of exports. He said a good deal about quotas in relation to imports into the United Kingdom.  Later,  at Brisbane, he advocated a standstill policy for two years. The vacillating nature of his remarks left us bewildered. A stand-still policy is a policy of retreat. No country or individual can stand still; there must be either progress or retrogression. I had hoped that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> would bring home to the people of Australia the urgency of the Commonwealth Government establishing the closest possible relations with the Government of the United Kingdom. But apparently, as a result of the visit of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce,</inline> on the 22nd June, the Hobart <inline font-style="italic">Mercury</inline> informed its readers that a representative of the Commonwealth Government had expressed doubt regarding the possibility of expanding our trade with the United Kingdom, and had indicated the intention of the Government to concentrate on foreign markets. That report caused a sinking feeling within me, because I had hoped that there would be a better understanding by the leaders of public thought in Australia of the spirit and opinion of the people of Great Britain. Summarized, the report in the <inline font-style="italic">Mercury</inline> reads - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>It is futile for lis to expect Great Britain to alter hor policy or to place our hopes in greater inter-Empire trade. I wish to refer to those who urge that Australia by some magical process should endeavour to foster greater Empire trade ... It sounds very simple, but it displays an utter disregard for three paramount facts. The first ia that if we permit the unrestricted import of manufactured goods, many employees in secondary industries will be put out of work because 55 per cent, of our primary products are consumed in Australia the greater proportion of it <inline font-style="italic">by</inline> persons dependent upon the prosperity of our secondary industries. The second point that is overlooked is the crux of the whole position. It is this: Great Britain has decided to encourage her agriculture to the highest possible pitch of production. She has, in the last two years, evolved elaborate marketing  machinery  directed towards this end, and  she  has determined to make herself as far as possible economically self-contained, and will not be deflected in the slightest degree from her- declared agricultural policy. The third point disregarded is that the United Kingdom has contracted obligations in her treaties with foreign countries which prevent her imposing severe restrictions upon foreign meat and dairy products unless she also imposes restrictions upon dominion products of the same kind. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para>He went on to say - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>These are not idle words because any one who has followed the trend of British thought in this direction must know that the present British Government is absolutely determined to pursue the course upon which it has embarked. Those who urge that the solution of our marketing difficulties is to be found in reduced tariffs for our secondary industries surely have forgotten what recently happened when New Zealand . . . made a similar proposal to Great Britain. Briefly, what New Zealand proposed was that in return for free  entry of British manufactures there should be free entry into Britain of New Zealand products - chiefly dairy products. That proposal, so similar to that which is being Canvassed in Australia to-day by a small section, was not accepted by the British Government. The utterances of British leaders within recent months show how futile it is for us to expect Great Britain to alter her policy or place our hopes in greater inter-empire trade. </para>
                        <para>What, then, was Australia to do? If Britain, the greatest consumer of Australia&#39;s primary products, flatly says, &#34; This much and no more,&#34; two courses were open to the Commonwealth. The first was one to which every reasonable person must be opposed - that of restricting exports. The Government was opposed to that course. The second course was to seek vigorously for foreign markets. This the Government was doing. </para>
                        <para class="block">To me that appears to be a hopeless statement so far as our trade with Great Britain is concerned, and is, I submit, a misinterpretation of public opinion in Great Britain to-day. Some honorable senators may 6ay that the New Zealand Government made a gesture to the British Government which waa rejected; but if they pursue the matter further, they will find that it was not an offer to Great Britain, but merely an inquiry submitted by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forbes</inline> to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs as to whether a proposal on such a basis would be considered by the British Government. I understand that a statement was made by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thomas,</inline> the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, to the effect that the British Government could not deal with the Dominion of New Zealand alone, and that, if it had to reopen the issue, similar gestures should be made by the other oversea dominions. In discussing the Ottawa agreement or intra-Empire trade generally, it has never been suggested that there should be unrestricted imports of British goods into Australia. It has always been distinctly laid down that the dominions should have the right to develop their own secondary industries. This was specifically dealt with in the Ottawa agreement. Instead of jeopardizing the position of thousands of employees in our secondary industries, as was suggested by the representative of this Government, their position will be jeopardized unless we can devise some means whereby the purchasing power of those engaged in primary production can be .increased. Unless the Government is fully alive to the situation and increases our trade with Great Britain, it will not be acting in the best interests of the Australian people. </para>
                        <para>In the House of Commons on the 16th May last, I find that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Neville</inline> Chamberlain said - </para>
                        <para>We shall have to adapt ourselves to new conditions and make up our minds to the fact that although we can still increase our export trade we cannot assume that we shall be able to export the quantity or value of goods which we did only a very short time ago. That being so there are two alternatives. One is a continued extension of the homo market. In my opinion we have not by any means at present reached the limit of the expansion of the home market. The other is to be found in the development of interImperial trade. </para>
                        <para class="block">That is the opinion of a most influential member of the British Cabinet. His words are almost an invitation to the Commonwealth and the other dominions to meet at a round table conference in an endeavour to develop trade between the Old Country and the dominions. He went on to say - </para>
                        <para>It is a very striking fact  that  while  our  exports to foreign countries have decreased so considerably during the last twelve months our exports to the dominions and to  the  countries of the Empire have increased. </para>
                        <para>The dominions were in a worse condition than we were at the time of the Ottawa Conference. They are beginning to show very great improvement in their position. The first thing they had  to do at that  time  wai  to find a better market for their own production. The result of that is already beginning to show, and it will continue  to  increase as they feel more confident and show greater ability in buying for themselves. </para>
                        <para>Maintenance and expansion of the home market, the development of the inter-Imperial agreements, began and only began at Ottawa, in these two directions this country (United Kingdom) will have to find its compensation for losing so much foreign trade, which  we  shall probably not be able  to recover  in  the  lifetime of most of us here. Toward that end the policy of the Government is directed. </para>
                        <para class="block">If  that  is not an invitation to Australia and to  the  other dominions to devise a means to cultivate our garden of empire, I do not know what it is. On the other hand, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. &#34;Walter</inline> Runciman, one of the  most able members of  the  British Government, on  the  7 th May, said  that - We have already made,  outside the  British Empire, trade agreements with nine foreign countries. We have seven more under negotiation  at  the present time, and I hope  that  before the end of this year there will be  no  important trading community in the world with whom we are not on more intimate terms than we are to-day. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">That is the other side of the question, and emphasizes the urgency of Australia establishing the closest possible relationship with the British market, and of adopting an attitude other than that to which so much prominence has been given in the press, and by some public men in Australia to-day. </para>
                    <para>During April, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Runciman</inline> struck another blow at the British and dominion farmers when the formal negotiations for a pact were resumed with representatives of the Dutch Government. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Runciman</inline> has apparently made up his mind to give the Dutch farmers a specified portion of the British market in cheese, poultry, eggs, tinned milk, cream and other primary products. Meanwhile Dutch primary produce is being imported into the United Kingdom at prices that give the British farmer no chance of successful competition. This also can be regarded as a challenge to Australia and to the other dominions to consult with Great Britain in problems which vitally affect them. Lord Winterton, speaking in the House of Commons, said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Empire trade is the ideal cherished by the vast majority of the Conservative party and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thomas</inline> gratuitously taxed it. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">There again, we see a fertile field for successful representation for the purpose of securing increased trade. In this connexion, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Amery</inline> said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Empire trade is being strangled by the black pact with the Argentine. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Herbert</inline>
                        Samuels, a gentleman whom we did not expect to express this opinion, stated -
                    </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The way out of the glut of goods is not to restrict and contract supply, but to ^develop Britain and the dominions, expanding&#34; purchasing power in the largest single unit in the world. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">Those remarks were cheered by members of the House of Commons, but they are diametrically opposed to the present policy of the Commonwealth Government. We find farmers throughout the United Kingdom passing resolutions, affirming that, in the United Kingdom market, the British farmer should take first place, the dominion farmer second place, and the foreigner what was left. As many as fifteen meetings of this character were held on one day in various parts of Great Britain, and at all of them there was unmistakable evidence of the attitude of the people towards this marketing problem. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. L.</inline> S. Amery, speaking in the House of Commons, on the 7 th May, with regard to the British trade pact with Argentina, said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>I regard the Argentine Treaty as one of the most disastrous events of my lifetime. I do not blame members of any particular Ministry, but I doubt if any conservative ca.n have any great confidence in negotiations conducted by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Runciman.</inline></para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Runciman,</inline>
                        the  president  of the British Board of Trade, has no sympathy at this juncture with the policy for which we stand. The debate in the House of Commons disclosed that in the view of Labour members, at all events, it was the foreign imports, and not the imports from the dominions, that had upset the British market for the home  producer. The people of the Mother Country are now alive to the fact that the quota system is of no particular advantage to the British consumer or the British producer. Neither is it helping dominions development, but there is definite evidence that the foreign producer is taking advantage of the quota to secure much higher prices for the smaller quantity of goods he is permitted to export to Great Britain. For this reason, the people of Britain are now advocating a new policy - the substitution of duties for quotas; a policy of natural development of production instead of one of restriction and quotas.
                    </para>
                    <para>My purpose is to emphasize the need to concentrate on the market that is ours - the market of the  United  Kingdom. It is open to us, and we should develop it. Last year, Denmark increased slightly her purchases from Britain. Whilst Britain sold to that country goods of a total value of &#163;15,854,000, Denmark sold to Britain goods to a value of &#163;34,606,000. At the present time, the Danish Government is negotiating a trade agreement with Germany, and to further those negotiations, refuses to grant to Danish merchants the necessary import licences to make purchases from Britain. Denmark, apparently, is prepared to grant extraordinary concessions to Germany, France, and other countries with which she is negotiating. </para>
                    <para>We have not had the vision to appreciate the possibilities of, and to live up to, the Ottawa* agreement. For the first four months of this year, compared with the same period of last year, the overseas dominions sent into Britain &#163;3,918,000 less grain and flour, whilst foreign exports of those commodities to the United Kingdom increased by &#163;2j074,000. For the first four months of this year, the imports of food, drink and tobacco into the United Kingdom were valued at &#163;18,253,065 more than for the corresponding period in 1913. </para>
                    <para>I think the Minister representing the Minister for Commerce will agree with me that, at this juncture in our affairs, we want trade, not politics. He will also, I hope, agree with my contention that agriculture is Australia&#39;s greatest industry, and that it is an efficient productive industry; but the key to agricultural prosperity is no longer skill in production, but ability to sell. Efficiency in production is no longer a protection against an overcrowded market. Rather is it a contributing cause. The battleground has been transferred from the farm to the market. &#34;We in Australia should awaken to the need for a marketing sense. &#34;There is not yet evidence of this in the community, or, I. fear, in the minds of the Australian Governments. </para>
                    <para>The solution of this problem is not to be found in reduced production, but in expanding markets. Where are we to find those markets? World markets are not going to be restored to us on the old international basis. International trade rests upon two rocks: firstly on the free exchange of commodities and money, and secondly on peace. The first has been shattered by economic warfare, and the second has been undermined by political dynamite. If we rely for our overseas trade upon foreign markets, our entire economic structure will collapse, and that will be a calamity* The British market presents the greatest field for the development of our industries. It should not be forgotten that it is the great market upon which converges the great bulk of the agricultural exports of the world. We are not alive to. its possibilities, nor do we realize the harvest that will be ours if we approach this business of developing the British market in a spirit of good will. Last year the </para>
                    <para class="block">Mother Country took from the dominions 80 per cent, of its butter imports, and 79 per cent, of its beef imports. The yearly food bill of the United Kingdom amounts to &#163;640,000,000, and, notwithstanding the development of British farming operations, following the encouragement given by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Elliot,</inline> the Minister for Agriculture, the farmers of the Mother Country produced only 40 per cent, of the requirements of the home market. Foreign nations contributed 39 per cent., and the colonies and dominions of the Empire only 21 per cent. Although last year Great Britain took 56 per cent, of our exports, we are only on the fringe of chat great market. What a harvest awaits us if we approach it in a spirit of give and take. In 1932, Canada increased its exports of foodstuffs to the United Kingdom by 50 per cent.; New Zealand advanced its figures by 13 per cent. ; but Australia, I regret to say, increased its exports of foodstuffs by only 5 per cent. </para>
                    <para>We should regard the Ottawa agreement merely as a foundation upon which to build an edifice of intra-Empire trade. But we must approach it with a determination to honour and live up to the spirit as well as the letter of that document. We shall have to abandon the policy of death and despair, referred to by one honorable senator as represented by those three horrible words - restriction, reduction, and quotas. It is hardly necessary to question the meaning of the first two words. We know what they mean, but have forgotten that nature takes a strong hand in interpreting them. What is still worse, it would mean governmental and departmental control of our great producing industries. If once we allowed this to happen, we should never be able to shake the governments off, and the days of greatness for our industries would be numbered. Anything that interferes with private initiative and enterprise destroys individuality and the very citadel of man&#39;s work. </para>
                    <para>Regarding the word &#34; quotas &#34; there is less understanding. Some Ministers and High Commissioners have described them as measures to restore prosperity to agriculture. They do nothing of the kind. The quota system is an iniquitous means of attempting salvation to stricken industry. Actually it will bind industry with  fettei&#39;3 of control more complete and unyielding than thi3 country has ever experienced. We have been told that it is necessary to develop agriculture in England. We have no objection to that policy. We support it, because a weak England means a weak British Empire. Those who have studied this subject intimately have come to the conclusion that Great Britain, under the best circumstances, could not produce more than 50 per cent, of its foodstuffs. This fact has, apparently, been overlooked by persons who are rather diffident about boldly approaching this great, problem. A self-contained Australia is a bankrupt Australia. One of my first lessons in economics was received from the present Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons)</inline> when . he was Premier of Tasmania. Speaking to me of the undeveloped forests and water resources of that State, he said, &#34;We hear these spoken of as assets, hut they are liabilities until they are converted into earning power.&#34; If the Governments of Australia would take that statement as their text, what a wonderful field of opportunity would open up for Australia in the markets of the British Empire ! </para>
                    <para>In order to convey to honorable senators a graphic survey of the position of the British markets, I have prepared several diagrams showing the average exports and imports of the United Kingdom for the years 3928-1932. The imports into Britain averaged &#163;879,684,000 a year. We are given the impression that, most of these goods came from British dominions or colonics, but that is not so, because goods to the value of &#163;628,000,000 were obtained from foreign countries, and only &#163;253,000,000 worth of goods was obtained from Britain&#39;s overseas Empire. The cost of foodstuffs imported from foreign countries was &#163;274,296,000, and &#163;136,000,000 was paid for foreign raw materials, all of which could be produced within the British Empire. Over the same period the total exports from Groat Britain amounted in value to &#163;513.966,000. of which only &#163;286,000,000 worth went to foreign countries, and &#163;227.000,000 worth to the overseas  Empire  n difference of only &#163;60,000.000. The total commodity balance in  favour of  the foreigner was &#163;341,500,000. </para>
                    <para class="block">The adverse balance against the overseas Empire was only &#163;24,000,000. We are told, sometimes, to remember the tremendous amount of British capital invested in foreign countries, as compared with the outer Empire. Well, let us see what it i3. According to <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Robert</inline> Kindersley,  writing in the <inline font-style="italic">Economic Journal</inline> for June, 1933, the nominal value in December, 1933, of investments in the overseas Empire, on which interest was payable in Britain, was &#163;2,187,000,000 which -returned &#163;109,000,000 a year in interest. The amount invested in foreign countries totalled &#163;1,538,000,000, and returned an annual interest of &#163;76,000,000. Over the period mentioned, the average quarterly adverse balance of British trade with the United States of America amounted to &#163;125,000,000; with Argentina, &#163;3S,000,000; with Germany, &#163;31,000,000; with France, &#163;13,000.000; with Belgium, &#163;17,500,000; and &#39;with Italy, &#163;1S,900,000. </para>
                    <para>I have made a survey of the &#34; black &#34; pacts, as the foreign agreements negotiated by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Runciman</inline> have been described. The countries which had negotiated commercial treaties with Britain are Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Argentina, Germany and Finland. The latest board of trade figures refer to the first quarter of this year and relate to a total trade of &#163;45,000,000 with those six countries. Britain has gained an additional trade of &#163;1,212,000 with them, compared with the first quarter of 1933, but they have increased their trade with Britain by &#163;3,230,000. Those foreigner? have gained nearly two and a half times the advantage which has come to Britain. Other foreign countries, realizing the advantages of concluding trade agreements with Britain are now negotiating for similar pacts. A trade agreement with Russia wa3 signed in February, and negotiations are now in progress with Poland, Latvia, Lithuania, France, Uruguay, Turkey, and Holland. A Dutch delegation was in London at the end of April. Holland&#39;s hope is to become a more formidable rival to British and Empire dairy farmers. Under the AngloDanish agreement, Britain guaranteed to Denmark annually a market for 2,300,000 cwt. of butter. In the first three months of this year, Denmark sent to Britain 594,366 cwt., compared with 545,474 cwt. for the same period of last year, at an average price of 16s. per cwt. less than last year&#39;s price. At the end of April Danish butter was 8&#39;2s. a cwt. in London. In Denmark the domestic consumption price is stabilized at 102b. a cwt. Owing to the depreciated currency the Danish exporter receives in addition b subsidy equivalent to 20 per cent, ou all produce shipped to England. The Dutch butter exporters receive a subsidy of nearly 100 per cent. They ere quoting butter to Dutch consumers at 190s. per cwt. But they are exporting it. to England at 50s. per cwt. at their own ports. </para>
                    <para>Argentina sells to Britain &#163;41,600,000 worth of goods a year, and Britain sells to Argentina &#163;13,000,000 worth. The disparity is remarkable. The advantages which Britain confers on Argentina are astonishing. </para>
                    <para>The position in respect of imports of foreign agricultural products into Britain is serious to Australia as is shown by the following figures: - </para>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>emphasize the importance of the governments of Australia attempting immediately to take advantage of the public opinion prevailing in Britain today, by showing that Australia is  ready  to help the Mother Country to promote the policy that <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Edward</inline> Grey laid down in 1911 &#34; To hold what we have, to develop it, and in developing it, lo make as few enemies as &#39;possible. That, gentlemen,&#34; he said, &#34; is th$ foreign policy of Great Britain &#34;. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>227</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator has exhausted his time. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>227</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role>Assistant Minister</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>&#91;3.57&#93;. - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> courteously advised me last night that he intended to move the adjournment of the Senate to-day in order to discuss the marketing policy of the Government. I have listened with interest to his remarks, and while I do not pretend to be in a position to reply offhand to the whirlwind of figures with which he has overwhelmed us, I may say that the Government finds itself in agreement with the principle of the policy advocated by the British and Scottish farmers. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> said that a motion had been carried at a meeting of farmers in Great Britain, who advocated that in trade Britain should come first, the Empire second. and foreign countries third. That is a very crude way of putting the position. The policy of this Government is to protect the people and industries of Australia first. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>227</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- That is recognized in Great Britain, </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>227</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Australia pioneered the policy of preference to British products. Tor more than a quarter of a century imperial preference has been advocated here, and it has found expression in the statute law of this country. Therefore, it cannot, be, alleged against this or preceding Governments that they have not adhered to the policy of promoting trade within the Empire. They have not advocated empire free trade, and the present Government, does not stand for that policy, but it does believe in trade reciprocity and trade preference, consistent with the protection and conservation of Australian interests. #1 wish to remove what appeared to me to be misunderstandings regarding the policy of this Government. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> is under a misapprehension as to the statements made by the High Commissioner. As a matter of fact, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> did not come to Australia to advocate any policy. That would not be within the scope of the duties and obligations of the High Commissioner. The policy of Australia is determined by the Government. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>227</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K1L</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BARNES, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Barnes</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- But he made a policy speech. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>227</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Did he not visit Australia as a British trade commissioner ? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>227</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Honorable senators may make facetious observations of that kind, but the High </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para class="block">Commissioner did not advocate  a  reduction of production, nor did he ask for  a  restriction of exports. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>228</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  I mentioned that that was the impression given .by the press. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir HARRY</inline>
                        LAWSONYes. The honorable senator stated, in effect, that
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce&#39;s</inline>
                        statements were fathered by the man who was supposed to be making them, and mothered by the newspaper reporters, and sometimes the father did not recognize his offspring. The High Commissioner did not advocate a reduction of production or a restriction of exports, but he did advise this country of certain developments that were taking place overseas which might ultimately have &#38;! adverse effect on the expansion of some of our industries, and he gave the Government the benefit of his advice and observation of the whole position. He made the Government acquainted with the &#34; atmosphere &#34; and the trend of events in European markets. He provided data and information as to negotiations of which he had a first-hand knowledge, to enable the Government to decide its policy and frame its course of action. I ask the Senate to accept this explanation as a true statement of the High Commissioner&#39;s recent visit to Australia.
                    </para>
                    <para>The Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons)</inline> has made definite statements as to where the Government stands in regard to the export trade. I asked my colleague the Minister for Commerce <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Stewart)</inline> for certain information, and he has furnished me with an interesting statement as to the general position. Time will not permit of my giving the whole of it, but one paragraph may advantageously be read. Referring to the visit of the High Commissioner, my colleague states - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The Commonwealth Government gave the most careful consideration to the whole matter and called the State Premiers and Ministers for Agriculture into consultation. Subsequently, the Prime Minister announced, in clear and precise terms, the Commonwealth Government&#39;s policy. On the 30th April, 1934, he carefully traversed the position and made the following declaration &#39;&#39;The Commonwealth Government has always  been  opposed, and is still strongly opposed, to the policy of restrictions on production and export.&#34; </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">We know that when matters of this kind were discussed at the World Economic Conference the High Commissioner declared that the reduction of production was a policy of despair.  The  statement by  the  Minister for Commerce continues - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>It Bees in such a policy the direct opposite to that which is desirable for Australia, viz., one of continued expansion and development. In the interests of Australian primary, producers, the Government will not institute regulation of the export of butter and meat, unless, and until, it is absolutely unavoidable. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">There can be no misunderstanding  regarding  the meaning of those words. Referring to the consideration which the Government was giving to the basis of consultation with the United Kingdom, the Prime Minister stated - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The Government of the United Kingdom has not yet made any proposal, nor has the Commonwealth Government. When the time &#39; comes for the consideration of quotas, the* initiative, as regards quantities, will actually rest with the United Kingdom. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">He then proceeded to indicate that the Government was considering the possibility of securing other markets, because the policy of the United Kingdom, while it might not cause a diminution of supplies from Australia, might impose a check on further expansion. The Prime Minister&#39;s words do not permit of misunderstanding. They were - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The future of Australian development depends, not on a static condition in regard to the volume of export, but on an enlargement of the demand. If, therefore, owing to the protection of British agriculture, and the commitments of the United Kingdom in her foreign treaties, Australia is to be limited in the British market, we must do our utmost to secure foreign markets. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para>On the 8th May, 1934, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Lyons</inline> amplified his statement in some respects. He then stated - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The best way to avoid the  necessity  to regulate the export of butter and meat is to expand foreign markets. In the past, Australia lias concentrated efforts chiefly on Empire markets, but must now seek an expansion of foreign trade. There is an ever increasing, disposition for countries to confine their pur chases to countries which buy from them. Australia will be forced to do the same. Foreign countries which do not buy freely from Australia cannot expect the continuance of Australia&#39;s custom. On the contrary, we must aim to improve the relative position of our good customers in our import trade. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">It is rather significant that the statement of the British Chancellor of the </para>
                    <para class="block">Exchequer, to which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> referred, in which he indicated three points of policy and urged that the Objective must be an increase of imperial trade, was made just after the declaration of the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons)</inline> in regard to this matter at Adelaide. These facts will enable honorable senators, to draw their own conclusions. Australia is knocking at the .door of Britain all the time, and asking for a greater share of the British market. It must not be assumed - and I hope that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> did not wish it to be inferred - that the Government has knocked with a palsied hand. Through the proper channels it has been pressing for a larger share of the British market, because it realizes that there ought to be an opportunity there for the disposal of more Australian produce. Honorable senators must, however, not lose sight of the fact that, notwithstanding the Ottawa agreement, and indeed, following that agreement, Great Britain concluded treaties with a number of foreign countries. Those treaties are an obstacle to the free development of our trade with Great Britain, and prevent us from obtaining a larger share of the British market. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>229</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- That is an admission. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir HARRY</inline>
                        LAWSON.The Government has nothing to hide in this connexion. It realizes that if we are to get the right view of the position, we must know the facts. It is well known that world marketing conditions have presented colossal difficulties during the last few years. During the world depression, countries which were formerly important markets for agricultural products, have severely reduced their purchases, and have limited imports by prohibitive duties, quotas, and other forms of restriction. This contraction of foreign markets, accompanied, in some cases, by increased production in Empire countries, resulted in greater quantities of foodstuffs being1 thrown upon the United Kingdom market. Increased supplies, combined with the lower spending power of consumers in the United Kingdom, led to a serious fall of prices. That was the position when the Ottawa Conference met. At that gathering^ as the result of the policy decided upon by this
                    </para>
                    <para class="block">Government, preferences were secured ou a wide range of agricultural products. The preference for dominion meat was secured by the imposition of quotas upon foreign supplies. Preference for dairy products took the form of customs duties on foreign supplies, while dominion products were guaranteed free entry for three years. The British Government reserved the right, in the interests of British farmers, to include dominion products in plans for import regulation, after the 30th June, 1934, in regard to meat, and after August, 1935, in regard to dairy produce. Wheat produced in the dominions was guaranteed free entry, while wheat produced in foreign countries was to pay a customs duty of 2s. a quarter, subject to the condition that wheat produced in the dominions should be offered for sale at world parity prices in the United Kingdom. A similar proviso was made in the case of preference on metals. Other preferences took the form of specific ad valorem customs duties. </para>
                    <para>At the time of the Ottawa Conference, it was made clear by the United Kingdom delegation that the protection of the domestic producer was a definite part of the British Government&#39;s policy. At the same time, subject to the limitations imposed by the preferences to the dominions, Great Britain retained freedom of action in regard to future relationships with foreign countries. Immediately after the Ottawa Conference the British Government commenced negotiations with foreign countries, and has since concluded trade treaties with a number of foreign primary-producing countries - Denmark, Argentina, Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russia - and negotiations are proceeding with &#39; Netherlands, Latvia, Estonia, Poland, Lithuania and Uruguay. At the time when the United Kingdom was negotiating with Denmark and Argentina, the Commonwealth Government, through the High Commissioner, expressed concern lest treaties with those countries should re-act to the disadvantage of Australia. Those treaties, however, were concluded, and were followed, by others with the countries I have mentioned. I desire to make it clear that the British Government had a perfect right to conclude those treaties, and that, in doing so, it lias not infringed the provisions of the Ottawa agreement. Let me emphasize, however, that Great Britain commenced to negotiate those treaties immediately following the Ottawa Conference. That action was merely an indication of the British Government&#39;s belief iu the importance of foreign trade, and of its determination to pursue &#38;&#38;- vantages in the markets of those foreign countries which were substantially dependent on the United Kingdom as an outlet for their produce. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>230</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The Commonwealth Government should have taken advantage of the strong public opinion in England against it. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>230</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I have already said that nothing has been, or will be, wanting on the part of the Government in vigorously urging the claims of Australia to a full and increasing share of the British market. I regret that time will not permit me to traverse in detail all the provisions of the foreign treaties made by the United Kingdom since the Ottawa Conference, but a brief reference to a few important products will be sufficient to indicate the general position. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>In the agreement with Denmark, the United Kingdom undertakes not to charge on Danish butter a higher duty than 15s. a cwt. - the duty provided under the Ottawa agreement - and, in the event of the imposition of restrictions upon the importation of butter, to allot to Denmark a quota of not less than 115,000 tons. If the total permitted import of butter exceeds 405,000 tons, the share of Denmark is to be increased proportionately. Tha.t agreement, which was signed on the 24th April, 1933, came into force on the 20fh June. 1933, and is to remain in force till the 20th June, 1936. Similar Undertakings have been entered into with other foreign countries. </para>
                    <para>In the agreement with Argentina, which was signed on the 1st May, 1933, and which is to remain in force till the 3 st May, 1936, the United Kingdom Undertakes not to impose restrictions on chilled beef below the imports in the year ended the 30th June, 1932, unless such Action is necessary to secure a remunerative level of prices in the United Kingdom  market  and no such restrictions will be maintained -if it appears that the imports so excluded are being replaced by increased imports of other kinds of meal, other than experimental shipments of chilled beef from other parts of the British Commonwealth of Nations. The position is that Great Britain has entered into certain obligations, and its markets are not absolutely free to us. If we. in Australia, can do anything to increase the sentiment in favour of Empire trade reciprocity, it will be to our advantage. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>230</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- We might prevent other pacts from being entered into. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>230</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- A development of Empire sentiment might have the effect of freeing the British market from the entanglements which now exist, and be of great advantage to Australia. I hope that I have removed certain misunderstandings from the minds of honorable senators. Surely there can be now no ground for misrepresentation regarding the attitude of the Government to these vital issues. The charge is that the proposal to obtain a footing in foreign markets is opposed to the spirit of Empire. The answer to that charge is that Great Britain, which is vitally concerned in any matter affecting Empire unity and development, has not found it inconsistent with the Empire spirit to conclude trade treaties with foreign countries. Britain has always relied largely on foreign trade. It may be of interest to honorable senators to learn that the Federal Graziers Association has urged the Commonwealth Government to conclude treaties with foreign countries in the interests of Australia&#39;s export trade in wool and wheat. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>230</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Dunn</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Did not that association specifically mention Russia ? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir HARRY</inline>
                        LAWSON.I am not advised on that point. Presumably, the Federal Graziers Association is also guilty of having disregarded Empire interests.
                    </para>
                    <para>In various quarters it has been urged that restrictions on imports from Australia have been imposed by various countries by way of reprisals against our tariff policy, and that if we were to slash into our customs tariff, Britain would respond nobly. In this connexion, 1 desire to quote from a document which will reveal to the Senate the negotiations which have taken place between the Governments of New Zealand and Great Britain. On the 25th October, 1933, the Governor-General of New Zealand sent to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, the following telegram:- </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>My Prime Minister has asked me to send you the following telegram: - </para>
                        <para>With reference to question of quantitative regulation of agricultural produce imported into United Kingdom, there is a widespread belief on the part of producers in New Zealand that if we undertook a drastic reduction or removal of New Zealand&#39;s protective tariff on United Kingdom goods  His  Majesty&#39;s Government in the United Kingdom would guarantee continuance of unrestricted entry of New Zealand primary products.  His  Majesty&#39;s Government in New Zealand would be grateful if  His  Majesty&#39;s Government in the United Kingdom would indicate their attitude towards this suggestion. - Bledisloe. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">The reply of the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, dated the 22nd December, 1933, was as follows :  - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Your telegram No. 78 of 25th October. Please convey following message to your Prime Minister: - </para>
                        <para>I much regret delay in replying to your message, which required careful consideration in consultation with my colleagues. </para>
                        <para>We desire in the first place to make it clear that the policy adopted by  His  Majesty&#39;s Government in the United Kingdom is, designed to promote the planned marketing of argicultural products in the interests of all concerned and involves where necessary control of home production as well as of home marketing.Its object is, by correlating supply with demand, to raise the price of the commodities concerned, and to maintain it at a level at which it will once more becomes remunerative to all producers supplying the United Kingdom market. </para>
                        <para>It is true that in present circumstances regulation is likely to involve a check to immediate expansion, but orderly increase of production, as demand increases, with due regard to maintenance of a remunerative price, is of course contemplated. </para>
                        <para>The suggestion in your telegram would involve modification of United Kingdom policy indicated above, and could hardly be considered with reference to New Zealand alone. Norwe think could an examination of such a question take place on the basis of a suggestion put forward by particular trade interests. For this reason we feel hardly in a position to give any further indication of our attitude than that outlined above, though we are. of course, at all times ready to givefull and sympathetic consideration to any proposals of the New Zealand Government for the development of the mutual trade of the two countries. - Thomas. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">Those cables supply an answer to the suggestion that the Australian tariff is an obstacle to increased intra-Empire trade. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>231</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thomas</inline> stated at the time that the Government of New Zealand was not prepared to submit a definite proposal. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir HARRY</inline>
                        LAWSON.The honorable senator has possibly studied this subject more closely than I have, but the cablegrams which I have quoted indicate the view of the British Government at that time. It has been said that Australia&#39;s tariff policy is prejudicial to more favorable marketing conditions in the United Kingdom. For many years Australia&#39;s tariff policy has included preference to the United Kingdom over a wide range of commodities, and we have received in return preference on. only a few items, which do not include our major export products. Preference by the United Kingdom to Australia was not realized until 1932, whereas Australia, one of the pioneers of the principle of Empire preference, has been granting preference to the United Kingdom for a quarter of a century. The value of the preference granted by Australia to the United Kingdom is demonstrated by the balance of payments. While Australia was a borrowing country, the balance was strongly in favour of the United Kingdom; but, since the cessation of borrowing, the value of Australia&#39;s exports to the United Kingdom has been sufficient to pay for imports and meet payments due in London for debt interest and various invisible items. I regret the necessity to emphasize these points; but I do so only to expose the disservice done to their country by those Australians who falsely represent their fellow citizens as members of a greedy and grasping community who wish to extract the utmost advantages from the Mother Country without making an adequate return. I am glad to have had the opportunity to present the case on behalf of the Government, to answer certain allegations and to remove wrong impressions and misconceptions. I desire to make it clear to the members of all political parties in this chamber that the Government is endeavouring in every possible way to increase production and find a profitable outlet for the products of our export industries, by developing our marketing activities, particularly in the direction so eloquently referred to by
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott.</inline>
                    </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>232</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  Will the Assistant Treasurer advise the British Government that that is the attitude of this Government? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir HARRY</inline>
                        LAWSON The British Government knows our attitude in this matter. We have to face the position as it is, and, if markets&#39; are not available, we cannot secure them. The Government desires to exploit every possible market open to Australia&#39;s producers, and to increase the activity of governmental marketing agencies. The Government can only encourage, inspire and advise private enterprise. It is not the duty of the Government to do more than that.
                    </para>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>232</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K1L</name.id>
                            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BARNES, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BARNES</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>.- Statements have appeared in the press, and have been made on public platforms, concerning intra-Empire trade, which lead some to believe that Australia has to be wet-nursed by the Mother Country. I intend to place on record what Australia has done for Great Britain. During the war the British Government contracted to purchase the Australian wool clip for the four years 1916-17 to 1919-20, at ls. 3&#189;d per lb.; this wool was eventually sold in London at 6s. per lb. The arrangement between Great Britain and Australia was that, in respect of any profits on wool sold for purposes other than military, one-half of the profits was to be paid to Australia. In addition to getting wool for naval and military requirements at one-quarter of its value, Great Britain made a profit of &#163;35,000,000. According to the budget statement delivered on the 16th September, 1920, the payment made for Australia&#39;s wool under the Imperial contract amounted to &#163;159,000,000. Had Australia received 6s. per lb., Australia&#39;s wool cheque would have been approximately &#163;735,000,000, instead of &#163;159,000,000, which represented a loss to Australia of over &#163;500,000,000, or more than our total war debt. In 1919, the present member for North Sydney <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Hughes),</inline> in referring to the sale of Australian wool, said - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Millions have been lost to this country on wool alone...... </para>
                        <para>Had I known before what I know now, 1 should never have sold wool other than for the period of the war. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para>In  connexion with the sale of Australian wheat, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Lough,</inline> a member of the  House of Commons, said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>I asked my friend, the Parliamentary Secretary to the Shipping Comptroller, whether he had not bought a great deal of cheap wheat, and he said &#34; Yes.&#34; </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">When that gentleman asked where  the  wheat was situated,  he said that it was  in Australia. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Prothero,</inline> president  of  the British Board  of  Agriculture, speaking in the House  of Commons, said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>We have made, in times past, an appeal to Australia to sell us their wheat at a lower price than they could get it in the world market, because we are their kith and kin, and they have done so. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">In the House of Commons, on the 4th August, 1922, <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Newton</inline> Moore asked certain questions regarding contracts for the purchase  of  Australian wheat, and <inline font-weight="bold">Sir. W.</inline> M. Thompson, parliamentary secretary to the Board  of  Trade, replied that &#34; the Government contract for the purchase of Australian wheat from 1916-17  to  1919-20 covered 5,000,000 tons. The contract was subject  to  a crude allowance  of  58,000 tons for loss and damage.&#34; The cost averaged 5s. 2d. a bushel f.o.b.  in  Australia, whereas the average price  of  wheat purchased elsewhere during the same period was 9s. 3d. f.o.b. in the country  of  origin. That meant  a  loss  to  Australian wheat-growers of &#163;37,000,000, and that much gain  to  Great Britain. </para>
                    <para>The position with respect  to  meat  is  also interesting. In the <inline font-style="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</inline> of  the 27th March, 1919, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline> Beale is reported  to have stated - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Had Australia obtained for her meat of high quality the same price as America received for hers of low quality, namely 150 per cent, more, about 13d. instead of 5d., the position in Australia to-day would be vastly better. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">It will be seen that again Britain made millions  of  pounds out  of  our meat industry. For electrolytic copper, the United States  of  America received &#163;163  a ton  from Great Britain as  against  &#163;108 a ton paid  to  Australia for the same product. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. G.</inline> H. Roberts,  the  British food  controller, stated that the Imperial Government was losing 10&#163;d. per lb. on homeproduced cheese, but the loss would be met by the profits on imported cheese. The average price received by Australia for its butter was ls. 6d. per lb., although it was realizing as much as 7s. 6d. to 10s. per lb. in London. For all our primary products, we received much less than any other country in the world. &#34;We lost millions of pounds, while Great Britain gained correspondingly. </para>
                    <para>For over twenty years Australia has granted tariff preferences to the United Kingdom, the value of which is estimated at from &#163;7,000,000 to &#163;8,000,000 per annum. These preferences have been given to Great Britain, without bargaining, in order to build up intra-Empire trade, and as a result, Australia became Britain&#39;s second best market. According to the ex-Minister for Trade and Customs, <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Henry</inline> Gullett, in 1929 the average margin of preferences granted by Australia upon goods of British origin was 15 per cent., and extended over almost the whole schedule. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Latham,</inline> the Attorney-General, when in London, referring to allegations concerning Australia&#39;s tariff, declared, &#34; Our British preferences are real, not illusory.&#34; The following table shows Australia&#39;s trade balance with Great Britain prior to the Scullin Government assuming office: - </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_15_2.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <para class="block">Under the Ottawa agreement, an endeavour was made to establish trade within the Empire upon a sound reciprocal basis. Great Britain secured conditions which enabled British goods to enter Australia, and to compete on equal terms with local products. Australia was to receive certain benefits from Great Britain with respect to the importation into that country of our primary produce, but while the benefits to Great Britain have materialized, we have not received a corresponding advantage. British manufacturers are now active competitors on an equal basis with Australian manufacturers. Some time ago, the Prime Minister said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The Government has reduced the rates of the British preferential tariff on two-thirds of the items to the level of 1928&#39;. There are 571 sets of duties which are lower than the comparable rates which operated Under the 1921-28 tariff. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">The Government has made concessions to Great Britain, to the detriment of our secondary industries. </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_15_2.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <para>We have also to remember that during the war, Great .Britain lent between &#163;1,500,000,000 and &#163;1,800,000,000 to its allies. The Prime Minister of Great Britain, speaking at Retford, said that Great Britain had written off 60 per cent, of the debts due to it. The original rate of interest paid by Great Britain to America on its war debt, was 5 per cent. ; but Congress concluded that that rate was too high, and it was subsequently reduced to 4^ per cent. Britain lent money to France at a very much lower rate of interest than it required Australia to pay. The Mother Country also backed French credit during the war and had good cause to regret it. Britain lent France &#163;65,000,000 when the franc stood at lOd. France repaid the loan when the franc was worth only 2d. Summarized, the position between Great Britain and Australia during and since the War is as follows: - </para>
                    <para>Australia lost over &#163;600,000,000 in connexion with the sale of primary products to the United Kingdom during the war. </para>
                    <para>Great Britain asked Australia to sell wheat to the United Kingdom at less than world price. Australia did so. </para>
                    <para class="block">Great Britain wiped off over one half of the war debt owing by foreign nations but did not reduce Australia&#39;s war debt by one penny. </para>
                    <para class="block">Great Britain funded its war debt with America at 3.3 per cent. and made Australia pay 5 per cent. </para>
                    <para class="block">For over 20 years Australia has granted preferences to British goods to the value of &#163;7,000,000 a year. </para>
                    <para class="block">Australia made further concessions to Great Britain under the Ottawa agreement which enabled British manufacturers to compete seriously with our secondary industries. </para>
                    <para class="block">It is but natural to think that, as Great Britain can produce only about 40 per cent. of its own food requirements, and as the Ottawa agreement was supposed to provide facilities for the development of intra-Empire trade, we should enjoy a greater share of the British market for primary products. The dominions are entitled to some portion of the 39 per cent. of imports of primary products from foreign countries into Great Britain. Australia has no apology to offer with regard to its preferential trade relations with Great Britain. All the facts show that for many years we have granted very important concessions to the Mother Country. We now feel that vre are justly entitled to a larger share of the British Market. </para>
                    <para>The High Commissioner a month or two ago endeavoured to persuade us that the proposals which he outlined would be of very great advantage to this country. The people generally were under the impression that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> was speaking entirely in the interests of people in Great Britain. I may be doing the High Commissioner an injustice in this matter, but I feel sure that 90 per cent. of the people of Australia are in agreement with me. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> spoke of the possibility of a further restriction of Australia&#39;s export trade to the Mother Country. Apparently that view was not held in Great Britain itself, because not long ago the Minister for Agriculture <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr.</inline></para>
                    <para>Elliot) in reply to <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forgan</inline> Smith, the Premier of Queensland, who visited Great Britain in connexion with the Queensland sugar industry, said that while it was true that Great Britain intended, if possible, to make itself economically self-contained, there was no thought of restricting Australian imports. It would appear, therefore, that the position was not quite as had been represented by the High Commissioner when he was in Australia. </para>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>234</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                            <party>ALP; LANG LAB from 1931</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - I congratulate <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> upon the wealth of detail with which he supplemented his remarks this afternoon. Altogether, his speech was a very fine effort. It was, no doubt, made with a view to his candidature for the Senate in September. The honorable gentleman, having control of a chain of newspapers in Victoria, obtains a wide circulation for his views, and his speech this afternoon was, I suppose, intended to tickle the ears of the farmers in his electorate. Let me again remind him that many farmers are in much the same position as many thousands of unemployed industrialists. They may have a job, but they want food. Above all they want some guarantee of security with reference to their production. Only recently representations were made to the Minister in charge of development <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator McLachlan),</inline> that an inquiry be made as to the possibility of extracting petrol from wheat. Fancy growing wheat to drive motor cars! </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>Prior to his visit to Great Britain, a year or two ago, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> was a firm advocate of the Ottawa agreement, the effects of which on our industries is now so clearly seen. At the annual conference of the Victorian Press Association, in Melbourne, the honorable gentleman delivered an interesting speech, in the course of which he warned his hearers that foreign countries were making insidious efforts to undermine the benefits conferred by the Ottawa Conference. He advised Australian producers and manufacturers to go to England to fight for their markets. Why should they have to do that ? During the last election the wealthy sections of our primary and secondary producers placed money at the disposal of government  candidates, and also representatives of the Country party. Surely they were entitled to expect some <inline font-style="italic">quid pro quo.</inline></para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>235</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The honorable senator does not understand any one being consistent in any cause. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>235</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Yes I do. It is the duty of this or any other Government to protect the primary producers and manufacturers of Australia. It should not be necessary for them to go overseas and fight for their markets. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> went on to say at that conference - </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <quote>
                        <para>England is the greatest market in the world to-day for Australia&#39;s products. If we do not realize the chances, they will be taken from us, because foreign countries are watching and waiting to get in. If they do get in it will be very difficult to get them out. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">Apparently what <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> then predicted is now taking place, and this Government is being asked to give its attention to the development of other markets. Only a few days ago the Graziers Association of New South Wales, in conference, carried a motion urging the Government to take steps to make a trade agreement with Soviet Russia - an agreement between a country that adheres to the principle of communism and a country under a democratic form of government. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> and his political friends are always ready to link my section of the Labour party with communism, and all that it stands for, yet they are willing to make a trade agreement with Russia for the sale of Australian wheat and wool. Great Britain is now committed to a policy of economic nationalism. So must Australia be. We have come to realize that the home market is the best market. It is only natural that, in common with other countries, we should seek the further development of this market, in the interests of our people. Under the regime of this &#34; prosperity &#34; Government, 400,000 men and women are unemployed to-day, or working only on dole relief. Here is a market right at our door. </para>
                    <para>We are reminded that &#163;500,000,000 of British capital is invested in Argentina. Does <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> imagine that those capitalists are concerned about Australia ? </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>235</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Those investments are now worth under &#163;200,000,000. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>235</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The only time Australia comes into the picture is when it is required to participate in the foreign wars of the Mother Country. To-day we find Britain entering into &#34; black &#34; pacts with six foreign countries, including Soviet Russia. According to the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald,</inline><inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> said that the Australian delegates at Ottawa were defeated on the meat question by the cleverness, and careful and intensive propaganda of their opponents. The honorable senator thus suggested that the representatives of the Lyons Government at Ottawa were politically stupid. Our delegates, he said, went in the wrong spirit - that of taking all and giving nothing. . On the same occasion, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> was also reported to have said that the meat quota which the Australian delegates obtained would &#34; get Australia nowhere &#34;, and that Argentina could more than make up its loss in the frozen meat trade by exporting more chilled meat. That was an admission from <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> himself that Australia has not much chance in the British meat market. <inline font-style="italic">The</inline><inline font-style="italic">Australasian</inline><inline font-style="italic">Manufacturer,</inline> of the 6th May, 1933, stated- &#34;Once more unto the breach, dear friends&#34; - the breach of the Ottawa agreement, committed by the British Government, first, in taking wheat from Russia when there waa ample wheat to be taken from the dominions; second, in taking meat from the Argentine, when all its requirements could have been taken from Australia; third, in giving an order for &#163;7,000,000 worth of butter to Denmark, when this country could have supplied the lot. The Russian wheat was cheaper than Australian wheat - but what about &#34; the spirit of the Ottawa agreement&#34;? British financiers have millions invested in the  Argentine  - but what about &#34;a self-contained Empire&#34;? Denmark trades with England - but in proportion to Australia&#39;s trade with England, Denmark&#39;s total is paltry. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <para>In the face of this wanton smashing of the agreement, in spirit if not in letter, England demands more and more concessions from the dominions - and especially from Australia. She demands that her manufactures., under the Scrap of Paper, shall enter this country without effective tariff restrictions on goods that can be made here. </para>
                    <para>It is this sort of behaviour that eventually caused England to lose America. The colonists there were a  long-suffering lot - as we are - but a point was reached at which further oppression was unbearable. The  fault  lay, of course,  not  with the English  people,  but with English statesmanship, which  is  forever the slave of financial interests that never hesitate  to  use British imperialism as  a  cloak for activities  that  are anti-Imperial. </para>
                    <para>So far as English statesmanship is concerned, the agreement is already a scrap of paper. So far as English industry is concerned, every advantage has been taken to use the agreement as an instrument to injure Australian manufactures. . . . </para>
                    <para>The Lyons Government, while it remains in power, will do nothing likely to annoy its overseas friends. . . . </para>
                    <para class="block">It would seem from this that the Ottawa agreement has been scrapped, and one reason is that the British financiers have millions invested in Argentina. Notwithstanding the fact that there has been a secret conference and agreement between the Country party and the Lyons Government, the tariff barriers of this country must be greatly lowered to enable the coalitionists to go to the country with promises that will please the electors. </para>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>236</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The honorable senator has exhausted his time. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>236</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. -  When the Assistant Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Lawson)</inline> was making his statement, I interjected that I should have something to say in rebuttal. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sampson</inline> then interjected, and from his words I. inferred that he meant that any statement by me in rebuttal would not be prompted by proper motives, but would be made for the purpose of sheer obstruction. There can be no doubt in my mind as to what the High Commissioner said when he was in Australia. I did not have to read press reports to know it; I got it definitely from <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> himself. Federal Labour members from Queensland were privileged to meet the High Commissioner in a friendly chat at the Bellevue Hotel, in Brisbane. Those present at that interview were the members in the House of Representatives for Kennedy <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Riordan),</inline> Oxley <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Baker),</inline> Brisbane <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. George Lawson),</inline> Herbert <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Martens), Senator Brown</inline> and myself. In a most informative talk <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> showed himself entirely familiar with the exports and imports of the different countries of Europe, and was able to tell us almost to a bushel the exportable surpluses of wheat held by those countries; but he definitely stated that Australia&#39;s way out was the restriction of its exports. At the conclusion of our interview <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> also said, just as definitely, that the policy he was advocating would not be a trump-card political policy. He remarked that, as he was no longer in Parliament, he was not concerned with politics, but with a policy of safety for Australia. I then asked <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> if the course he was advocating was not, at best, merely tinkering with the problem, and not touching its causes. I inquired whether it was not designed to prop up the capitalistic order of society, which everybody who takes an intelligent survey of world affairs knows to be tottering to its fall. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> replied, &#34; I agree with what you have said ; but I do not think capitalism is coming to an end this year, next year, or the year after. I am only concerned about seeing that Australia discovers a policy which will help it to escape the immediate danger that threatens her.&#34; Yet this afternoon the Minister told us that such a policy as restriction of production was not advocated by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce.</inline> I do not know what he said at the conference attended by the Minister; hut I do know what he said at the interview to which I have referred. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>It seems strange to me, if what the Minister said is correct, that so much correspondence by telegram should have taken place between the Acting Premier of Queensland, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. P.</inline> Pease, and the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Lyons)</inline> with regard to this very matter. I propose to read, in reply to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott,</inline> extracts from that correspondence which will show what actually occurred. During <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce&#39;s</inline> presence in Australia the Prime Minister called a Premiers Conference for the purpose of conferring with the High Commissioner. The conference was held <inline font-style="italic">in camera</inline> at Canberra, and after <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> had outlined the position, the Acting Premier asked him if the proposals he was placing before the conference had been sanctioned by the primary producers&#39; organizations of Great Britain alone, or whether the British Government had been consulted. </para>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline>
                        replied that the British Government had given its imprimatur to the quotas he had set forth. The Acting
                    </para>
                    <para class="block">Premier of Queensland reported the facts by cablegram to the Premier of that State, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Forgan</inline> Smith, who was then in London, and received the following reply :  - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Re your telegram outlining Bruce&#39;s statement at Premiers Conference; have seen <inline font-weight="bold">Major Elliott,</inline> Minister for Agriculture. He emphatically denies that Bruce had any authority to put forward any quota suggestions or similar matters of policy on behalf of. or at suggestions of, British Government. Advise me urgently exact term&#39;s Bruce&#39;s statement on that point. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">
                        <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Pease</inline>
                        immediately wired to the Prime Minister as follows :  -
                    </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>In cabling my Premier, Bruce&#39;s proposals, as set forth at Canberra, I stated those proposals were submitted with British Government&#39;s authority. You will remember 1 specially asked Bruce whether proposals as outlined by him submitted with British Government&#39;s approval, to which he replied &#34; Yes &#34;. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir George Pearce</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-The honorable senator has not quoted the whole of the correspondence. He should also give the Prime Minister&#39;s reply. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I should like to do so because it would confirm what I have already said, and show that the Minister does not know what is going on, but, unfortunately, I have not the Prime Minister&#39;s reply with me. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir George Pearce</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The Prime Minister gave a complete denial to the allegations of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Pease.</inline></para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- It may interest the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Pearce)</inline> to know that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> spoke to me in the following strain : &#34; Do you know, Collings, that at the World Conference I put Australia&#39;s position,&#39;, in relation to its primary products, and the need for an expansion of our export trade, very definitely, but of 66 nations represented at the conference, I could get only ten to support my proposals, and even their support was half-hearted, because they did not understand the position. What chance had I of making effective representations on behalf of Australia, in opposition to this policy.&#34; That is the policy which the Commonwealth Government denies that it ever advocated. A prominent newspaper put the position well when it asked whether <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> was Australia&#39;s High Commissioner or Great Britain&#39;s trade commissioner. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <para>To the remark of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> that a self-contained Australia would be a bankrupt Australia, I take the strongest exception. Does the honorable senator suggest that if Australia were cut off from supplies from other countries its 6,500,000 inhabitants would sit down and starve? There is nothing which is needed for the health, happiness, and prosperity of the Australian people which cannot be produced in Australia better than in any other one country. Australia with its six and a half millions of people has accomplished in little over a century a world&#39;s record, and a seeming miracle. No similar number of people in the world&#39;s history, in any country, has ever achieved such a wonderful record of splendid development and progress. It would appear that some honorable senators desire that this glorious country should become a vassal State of Great Britain. So long as I have breath in my body I shall fight any such proposal. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYH</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Robert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- No one has ever made such a suggestion. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>237</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- What does this policy of restriction of our exportable surplus mean? In my opinion, Australians are foolish to produce so much that they have a large surplus available for export. A sane policy for Australia would be to meet its own normal requirements, at the same time making provision for adverse seasons, and to refuse to send out of th&#187; country the best of our goods be sold abroad at half theprice charged for similar goods in Australia. If the proposal of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bruce</inline> is to be recognized at all, it means, as one writer has satirically suggested, that every wool-grower should be compelled to reduce the cut per sheep by 2 lb.; that no wheat-grower be allowed to produce more than 12 bushels on any acre; that the dairyman should shoot at dawn any cow that gives more than one billycan of milk; that the poultry-farmer should send to the meat market any hen that lays eggs on more than three days a week; that every orchardist should destroy any apple tree that bears more than two dozen apples each year; and that no live-stock be mated for the next three years. Honorable senators smile, but they know that in </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <para class="block">Tasmania and elsewhere fruit and livestock are destroyed, and production restricted, while thousands of persons live in a state of degradation, poverty and  starvation </para>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The honorable senator has exhausted his time. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>238</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - In supporting the motion, I appeal for greater consideration for our export industries. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> quoted <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> as having said that a self-contained Australia would be  a  bankrupt Australia. The world is troubled to-day because a policy of intense economic nationalism has been followed by many countries, including Australia. Indeed, Australia was one of the first nations of the world to preach the wild doctrine of economic nationalism and self-sufficiency. That policy has caused as great an interruption of commercial intercourse between nations as was caused by the Great War which preceded it. The experience of France, Germany, Italy, and other European countries during the war, led them to adopt a policy of more intense agricultural development in the interests of their own people. The result was that the wheat exporting countries found a restricted market for their produce. The average importation of wheat by France, Germany and Italy, for the years 1926 to 1930, was 206,000,000 bushels, whereas to-day not one bushel of wheat from Canada, Australia or Argentina enters those countries. Markets have been closed because European countries, like Australia, have adopted a policy of intense economic nationalism, and have endeavoured to become self-contained. The result of this policy in the countries mentioned is a greatly increased price for bread. In retaliation for Australia&#39;s high tariff, France has increased the duty on Australian wheat by 4s. 6d. a bushel above the rates which operate in regard to other foreign wheat. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Daly</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  What quantity of Australian wheat goes to France? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Even before the higher duties were imposed, our exports of wheat to France were not considerable. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Daly</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  Did not France purchase Australian wheat merely for blending? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Not necessarily. The exclusion of Australian wheat from the French market has resulted in Australia having a carry-over of 100,000,000 bushels of wheat at the end of the cereal year. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Daly</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  Is that carry-over due to the attitude of France? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- It is partly the result of our attempt to make Australia self contained. Australian over-production of wheat during the last five years is practically equivalent to the importation of wheat by France, Germany and Italy during the previous five years. That proves the fallacy of adopting a policy of economic nationalism. Other countries have followed Australia&#39;s example and have refused to purchase goods made outside their o.wnOWN boundaries. Economic nationalism caused the great financial depression from which the world has not yet recovered. Those who say that the depression would have come in any case do not wish to place the blame in the right quarter, <inline font-style="italic">and so</inline> they will not attribute it to the policy of high tariffs, embargoes and restriction of output, which is the real cause. Australia&#39;s unsound policy has had a boomerang effect. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Daly</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-. -  The honorable senator would sell South Australian wheat in exchange for motor bodies. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- As I have said, Australia&#39;s attempt to be self-contained caused the depression. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  Was the depression in Britain due to the same causes </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- It pains every true Australian to learn that the Government regards as futile any attempt to increase our exports to Britain. Only a small proportion of Britain&#39;s requirements is supplied by Australia. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  That is because Britain does not care about Australia. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>238</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Britain does care; but, unfortunately, Australians do not seem to realize the protection which Britain has afforded this country throughout its history. The great development which has taken place in Australia would not have been possible but for Britain&#39;s assistance. Nevertheless, I think that Britain should offer to Australia a larger share of its market. The average annual exports from Denmark to Great Britain are valued at &#163;46,000,000, while those from Australia are valued at over &#163;40,000,000, but Aus-&#39; tralia&#39;s purchases from Great Britain amount to &#163;7 5s. a head of our population, while the purchases made by Denmark are equal to only &#163;2 15s. a head of its population. In other words, Australia&#39;s purchases from Great Britain average &#163;23,000,000, as against purchases by Denmark amounting to &#163;10,500. 1 was interested to hear the Assistant Minister say that the policy of Commonwealth Governments has always been in favour of preferential trade with Great Britain; but what does that really mean? &#34;While foreign countries exporting goods to Australia have to surmount a high tariff wall, British products entering this country have also to pay heavy customs duties. I do not blame Great Britain for declining to concede all that we may wish; if we do not extend consideration to Britain, we cannot expect its assistance in matters of trade. If we arc to meet our financial commitments to Great Britain - our interest bill alone amounts to about &#163;28,000,000 annually - Great &#39; Britain must import large quantities of our produce. At present, owing to our high tariff, we have only one-way traffic between Australia and Great Britain. Wc export large quantities of wool and wheat to the United Kingdom, but owing to the high customs duties we impose, a comparatively small quantity of British goods is imported into Australia. This results in higher freights being charged. It is essential that we should export more of our produce to Great Britain than at present, and that can be done if the Government will urge the British Government to take larger quantities of those primary products which we can economically produce. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings</inline> said that Australia with a population of a little over 6,500,000 persons, has performed wonders, but we could not have made such progress but for the production of large quantities of wool and wheat. Objection, was raised in certain quarters to the imposition of a sales tax on flour to assist the wheatgrowers, hut that tax was rendered necessary owing to the high cost of producing wheat, due mainly to the excessive cost of agricultural machinery. Production costs have been increased by heavy customs duties. On behalf of the primary producers of Australia, whose life-blood  i3  being sapped, I urge the Government to oppose any restriction of exports from Australia, which would only aggravate the present serious position. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>239</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - I regret that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman</inline> has seen fit to attack the protectionist policy of Australia. My only criticism of the help which the present Government has afforded to our secondary industries is that the present tariff is not sufficiently protective. If Australia is to be a self-contained nation we have to consider what we can produce, and what we should import. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman</inline> may be interested to hear some interesting facts that were contained in a report presented by a commission appointed .by the Bruce Page Government, to which the honorable senator reverently referred. I may inform this champion of the primary producers that, under the tariff in operation when the Scullin Government came into power, sausage casings to the value of &#163;561,000 were imported into Australia. This great representative of the primary producers may also be interested to learn that under that tariff, &#163;116,000 worth of cheese also was imported. Apparently at that time it was considered easier to import cheese than to produce it. While a bounty was being paid on the production of dried fruits, the government of the day was so benevolent that in one year it allowed &#163;182,000 worth to be imported. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>239</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Badman</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  The honorable senator is referring to dates. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>239</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I am referring to dried fruits generally. Although we can readily produce sufficient vegetables to supply our requirements, preserved fruit and vegetables valued at &#163;236,000 were imported. Hides valued at &#163;795,000 also came into Australia. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>239</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Badman</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  What was exported during the same period? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>239</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>--We were exporting wool which was paid for with artificial silk. Perhaps honorable senators opposite will be surprised when&#39;. 1 tei&#93; them that during <inline font-style="italic">the</inline> same  period soap valued at &#163;101,000 was imported. This document was not prepared by the Labour party ; it was the product of a commission set up by the Bruce-Page Government as a warning to this so-called Country party. It showed rural producers that the Labour party and the Nationalist party were trying to put the Country party on the right economic track. I urge <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> to give serious consideration to the possible effect upon Australia of a lowering of the tariff. I. am not opposed to Empire trade. As a matter of fact, 1 believe we should do what we can to promote trade within the Empire. I am opposed to any alteration of our tariff to the detriment of Britain because I believe in the British Commonwealth of Nations; but any preferential arrangement should be reciprocal, and, as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> pointed out in his excellent discourse this afternoon, there is no doubt that Great Britain is not playing the game by Australia. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>240</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Neither is Australia playing the game by Great Britain. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>240</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- This discussion may give rise to serious thought as to the future development of British trade with Australia, and I hope also that it will receive the attention it deserves in other countries. We regard Australia as part of the British Empire, and we are anxious to improve our trade relations with our own kith and kin. But we want the Ottawa agreement to be interpreted, not so much in the letter as in the spirit of that document. In that respect we have fallen down,  because  hitherto we have been disposed to pay more regard to the letter than to the spirit of the  agreement  We have evidence of this in connexion with the motor body industry. I repeat that we should do what we can to observe the spirit of the Ottawa agreement, and as regards the motor body industry, I take this opportunity to say that I disagree entirely with the view of the representatives of the British motor body manufacturers who visited Australia recently and endeavoured to persuade us that, as British manufacturers could produce motor bodies more cheaply than Australian manufacturers, we should provide greater facilities for their importation and confine our attention to tha assembling of them in Australia. I wish British manufacturers to realize that, as one of the parties to the Ottawa agreement, we owe allegiance also to Canada, South Africa, and other dominions of the Empire. If the competition of any British industry displaced any considerable number of men employed in a like industry in Australia, the reduced purchasing power of our people, due to their unemployment, would, seriously affect the market enjoyed by other portions of the Empire. If we throw the Australian market open and allow it to be flooded with British goods, then because of unemployment the market for other customers will be reduced. An open market is valueless if it contains no purchasers. I would like <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman,</inline> and those who think as he does, to endeavour to realize the futility of lowering the tariff merely to enable farmers to reduce the cost of ploughing by, say, 2d. or 3d. an acre. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>240</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Badman</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Why ridicule the farmers ? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>240</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I am not ridiculing them. No one has exposed them to a greater amount of ridicule than their representatives in this  chamber  this afternoon. I have an intimate knowledge of the difficulties of the South. Australian farmers, and I can say definitely that they do not support <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman&#39;s</inline> anti-tariff views. For this reason, I am sorry that the honorable gentleman will not be called upon to face the electors in September. If he went before them simply as a representative of the Country party and without the support of the pair of crutches provided by the Liberal and Country League, his second preferences would go to the Liberal party. I have no fear about the next election so far as the tariff issue is concerned, because I know where the people of Australia stand. I advise <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman</inline> to take a keener interest in the welfare of the farmers. If he had sounder knowledge of their difficulties he would realize that their interests would not be served by the lowering of the tariff wall, and the wholesale admission into Australia of that class of goods in respect of which the Scullin Government was obliged to take action some years ago. This Government has authorized inquiries into many tariff items brought down by the preceding Administration, and we are informed that 60 reports by the Tariff Board have yet to be dealt with. I hope that the Ministry will not interfere with the protection given to Australian industries, which means so much to our industrial stability. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>241</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KP8</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">JOHNSTON, Edward</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator E B Johnston</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>-  The next Government will do that. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>241</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The next government will be one led by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Scullin,</inline> and we may rest assured that it will rectify some of the anomalies that have arisen out of the actions of this Government. I must say, however, that the task will be somewhat easier, because, be it said to the credit of this Administration, it has not done so much injury to Australian industry as was caused by the Ministry which held office immediately prior to the Scullin Government. I am not opposed to the motion, but I hope there will be full recognition by all parties in the Senate that the destiny of Australia rests, not so much upon markets overseas, as upon the preservation of the home market for Australian industries. The security of the home market will make possible the development of a true national life. By recognition of that fact the interests of Great Britain will be better served than they would he by the lowering of the tariff barrier to enable British manufacturers to flood the Australian market, only to discover that there was nobody in the market-place with the money to buy their goods. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <para>SenatorRAE (New South Wales) &#91;5.44&#93;. - I presume that we should not find fault with Great Britain for not giving us greater facilities in the British market, because the Mother Country is merely attempting to do what we also desire, namely, to become economically self sufficient. As, obviously, that is the intention of the British . Government, what are we going to do about it ? Our powers are limited, and however admirable may have been the sentiments expressed by other honorable senators, Great Britain is merely aiming to remedy evils of which we also complain. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Daly</inline> mentioned one point to which other speakers had not referred. The honor able gentleman reminded us that the greatest evil from which we are suffering is the curtailment of the local market, due to the lessened purchasing power of our people. A similar position has arisen in other countries, and, for reasons akin to those operating here, their governments are endeavouring to make them self-contained. The world war accentuated a position that had previously begun to manifest itself. The enormous destruction of the world&#39;s wealth during those four years merely brought things to a head. The purchasing power of the people in every country having been mortgaged for generations ahead, a keener struggle for existing markets is inevitable. While that condition prevails, high tariffs or low tariffs will not of themselves suffice to get the world out of its troubles. It must surely occur at times to every Australian of average intelligence that it is absurd to send overseas the very best of our produce to be consumed by others while weare obliged to pay higher prices for the second quality goods which we keep for our own use. This is a form of economic lunacy, which, apparently, is inseparable from the capitalistic system. I am afraid that until that system is abandoned, we shall be called upon to suffer increasing evils of the like nature. On this subject of Empire trade, I quote the following from the <inline font-style="italic">Canberra Times</inline> of this date: - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>It cannot be said that the immediate outlook is one that supports the view that an early election is a good move in political strategy. The next few weeks may see an intensification of conditions of serious menace to Australia. The position in Germany and the outlook of Germany towards imports of raw materials, such as wool, together with the impending action by Britain against German balances in Britain and elsewhere, render the future one of serious concern for the wool industry and therefore strike fundamentally at Australian prosperity. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">That refers to the fact that all sorts of influences may, at any time, affect the trade balances between the various countries. As regards the latest development of British policy, can any one blame the farmers of the Mother Country for endeavouring to secure a greater measure of protection for their industry against foreign competition ? If we cannot blame the English farmer or stock-raiser for  seeking greater security, neither can he logically blame us for desiring to protect our home market for our secondary industries. The policy operates both ways. If one nation attempts to benefit itself by a tariff, that nation has no logical ground for finding fault with any other nation that adopts the same policy. Therefore, the fact that some nations resolve no longer to trade with others is not due to any inherent wickedness in the government of any particular country. Its action is simply dictated by the belief that, in trade matters, there should be some measure of reciprocity. It is true that by our tariff policy we have to some extent estranged the goodwill of other countries. But what we have to do is to consider whether, on the whole, it is better for us to approve of a high tariff and accept the consequences, or in deference to the wishes of other countries, adopt a low tariff and become &#34;wood and water joeys &#34; for the re3t of the world. The policy of Australia, however, is to build up its secondary industries. I scarcely agree with <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Collings,</inline> who said that we could produce everything we required and exist in a state of perfect isolation. </para>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>242</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I remarked that wc would not starve. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>242</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K1Z</name.id>
                            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">RAE, Arthur</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator RAE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Of course, we could produce everything necessary for our sustenance, but I do not suggest that we could profitably produce everything we require. We could eat our own mutton, even if wc could not export any of it. We could find means of weaving our wool into clothing, and could consume Australian-grown sugar, even if we could not export the surplus. Twenty years ago, or more, I wrote an article in which I endeavoured to refute the common fallacy, which has survived to the present day, that unless we throw our ports open to the world, we are in danger of starvation and bankruptcy. If an enemy blockaded our ports, and prevented us from either importing or exporting goods, would we perish from the cold because of too much wool, or die of starvation because of too much foodstuffs? We all agree that it would be admirable if Britain would buy more of our primary products, but what steps can we take to bring about that result? If we must accept a flood of imports from Great Britain to enable us to export more of our primary products to the Old Country, we must either take the consequences of our tariff, or make wholesale reductions of duties. Whatever differences of opinion may prevail regarding the tariff, Australia&#39;s policy for many years has been the building up of its secondary industries. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman,</inline> I understand, said that Denmark sold &#163;23,000,000 worth of produce to Great Britain in a year, while Australia exported &#163;10,000,000 worth to the same market; but Britain has trade relations with many countries, and cannot afford to shut out their products to please Australia and Canada. We cannot expect to monopolize the British markets. An absurd amount of credit i3 given to Britain for having protected this country for over a century. That praise is founded upon a ridiculous assumption. Unless a country is prepared to be dominated by another, it cannot allow even a square foot of its territory to be annexed, by another power. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>242</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The honorable senator has exhausted his time. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>242</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KS9</name.id>
                            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, John Valentine</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MacDONALD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - I do not agree with <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> that restriction of production by government action is always detrimental. I remarked by way of interjection, during his speech, that government interference with the export of stud rams to foreign countries that compete with Australia in the markets of the world would be desirable. I am glad that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> has submitted this motion, for it has furnished an opportunity for the discussion of a most important subject. I am not so gloomy as <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Rae,</inline> who thinks that whatever is said in this chamber will have no effect. After all, the members of this Senate, in conjunction with the members of the House of Representatives reflect the opinion of the people of Australia. In listening to the address by the Attorney-General <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Latham)</inline> this morning, one realized that Australia is known in other countries, and I consider that the discussions in the Commonwealth Parliament will have some effect, even in London. It seems only a short time since members of this Senate expressed their views concerning the Ottawa agreement, yet it is nOw being thrown to the winds. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>243</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JY7</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DUNCAN-HUGHES, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Duncan-Hughes</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- By whom? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>243</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KS9</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MACDONALD, John Valentine</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator MacDONALD</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- For his answer, I ask the honorable senator to consider the treaties that have been made, by Britain with foreign countries since the conclusion of that agreement. The honorable member for Henty <inline font-weight="bold">(Sir Henry Gullett),</inline> in his speech on the agreement, said - </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The purpose of the  Imperial  Enonomic Conference at Ottawa was to review the question of preferential trade within the British Empire, and to endeavour to establish it upon a sound reciprocal basis. . . . The case for a comprehensive scheme of preferential trade within the Empire rests upon the belief first that such a scheme is practicable and economically round, and, secondly, that it will prove <inline font-style="italic">a</inline> most powerful influence in strengthening all the other bonds which hold the British peoples together. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">That was a sound argument, because at that time the policy of Empire nationalism was preached. Ours was to be a self-contained Empire, and Britain was to think first of Australia. Britain is undoubtedly the hub of the Empire, but London is the financial centre of  international  financial interests which extend to practically every part of the world. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott,</inline> in his references to reductions, restrictions and: quotas, merely proved the soundness of the arguments advanced in this chamber last year by senators on the Opposition side. To some extent, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Badman</inline> anticipated me in giving some of his views on this subject, hut he has a free-trade complex. When interviewed by a representative of a newspaper in one of the .southern capitals regarding the restriction of exports, he said - </para>
                    <quote>
                        <para>On an average, the Australian buys from Britain &#163;7 5s. worth of goods each year. The Dane buys &#163;2 15s. worth, and the American only 5s. worth. Yet we find that Great Britain has imported an average of &#163;46,715,000 worth of produce from Denmark during the past three years&#39;, while Australia&#39;s share has averaged only &#163;40,198,000. On the other hand, exports from Great Britain to Denmark have averaged &#163;10,184,000 a year; but exports to Australia have averaged nearly &#163;23j000,000 a year. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para class="block">Following the Ottawa Agreement, Britain concluded a treaty with Den mark, which shows that all the high-sounding phrases of the honorable member for Henty were so much hot air. Denmark exports much butter and other dairy produce to Great Britain, and this has a detrimental effect on the Australian butter trade. The agreements which Great Britain enters into with foreign countries, and which are of disadvantage to Australia, give us great concern. Argentina exports much chilled beef to Britain, and it has occurred to me that recent developments in regard to the Northern Territory should be closely watched. The attempt made last year to obtain control of that territory by means of chartered companies was due to the desire of British capitalists with international interests .to control our beef export trade, because, with the likely success of the latest process of chilling beef, the advent of Australian chilled meat upon the world&#39;s markets, was greatly feared by Argentina. The attempt has failed because, as evidenced by the deputation of the Australian Natives Association to the Leader of the Senate, the Government has been shown that public opinion is against it. It is well known that British financiers have invested approximately &#163;500,000,000 in Argentina, with the result that reciprocal trade within the Empire is seriously affected. Now that the proposal to develop the Northern Territory by &#39;means of chartered companies has failed, the problem of developing that vast area is being attacked from a different angle by those who were interested in seeking control of it. Instead of saying that the Northern Territory is a profitable field for the investment of British capital, the Gilruths and others now declare that it is of no value. What is the reason for this change of attitude? As one who would welcome a gradual progress towards a socialistic state, I would rather have this country developed with Australian capital than with money provided by outsiders. Probably the activities of international financiers, who desire to wreck the Australian meat industry so far as the export of chilled beef is concerned, have influenced <inline font-weight="bold">Dr. Gilruth</inline> and others. </para>
                    <para>Some honorable senators contend that Australia should always give way to Britain. The sacrifices which Australia made during the war, described by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Barnes</inline> as our free gift of &#163;600,000,000 to Britain, are overlooked. I well recall <inline font-weight="bold">Sir George</inline> Fairbairn diecussing in the Senate chamber in 1922 Australia&#39;s contribution to the British Empire during the war as represented by the sacrifices made in respect of the prices obtained for our primary products, and, though an imperialist, reluctantly admitting what <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Barnes</inline> has said to-day. A careful review will reveal that Australia has treated the Motherland generously. That policy of restriction of output and of quotas is entirely foreign to the spirit of the Ottawa agreement, and to the sentiments expressed by <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Henry</inline> Gullett on his return from Ottawa, when he said that he commended the agreement to the House in the interests of Australia, and of the Empire as a whole, and asked all to accept -it for the sake of the Australian primary producers. </para>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>244</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JY7</name.id>
                            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNCAN-HUGHES, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNCAN-HUGHES</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - &#39;Some questions asked recently in the House of&#39; Commons may be of interest to honorable senators, in view of the imputation that Great Britain has not done a fair thing by Australia in the matter of trade agreements. On the 15th May of this year, Captain Spencer asked the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs the date on which he first made representations to the Australian Government on the prohibition of the importation into Australia of British sheet glass, and what reply, if any, he had received. <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. J.</inline> H. Thomas replied that representations were first addressed to the Australian Government on this subject on the 25th January, 1933, and, although they had been repeated several times since then, no satisfactory reply had been received. Captain Spencer also asked that the British Government would continue .to urge upon the Commonwealth Government the necessity for action, and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thomas</inline> replied, &#34;I hope that the reply which I have given to-day will provide the necessary incentive.&#34; Captain Spencer then asked whether the Minister would name the articles of British manufacture, the importation of which into Australia had .been prohibited, or subjected to an increased duty since August, 1932, and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Thomas</inline> replied, &#34; I am sending the honorable member a list of five cases in which the duties in the Commonwealth of Australia on goods manufactured in the United Kingdom have been increased since August, 1932. In one case, namely that of plain clear sheet glass, importation Ls at present prohibited.&#34; When I spoke on this subject last year, I pointed out that, although we had received concessions from the Old Country covering a wide range of articles, all we had given in return was a general undertaking. I added that, unless we did our part, we would experience difficulty in getting these concessions extended or renewed. What I prophesied then is now coming to pass. The Minister stated that these quotas had no connexion with tariffs, but it stands to reason that, unless we fulfil our part of the bargain, it will be increasingly difficult to get any extension of these concessions. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>Motion - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - withdrawn. </para>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>244</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>DUTY ON FILMS</title>
                    <page.no>244</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>244</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K1L</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BARNES, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BARNES</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Trade and Customs, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What is the rate of duty on British-made Alms imported into Australia? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>What is the rate of duty on Australian-made films imported into the United Kingdom ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>244</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MCLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Minister for Trade and Customs has supplied the following answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Films the produce or manufacture of the United Kingdom and imported direct from that country are admissible free of customs duty, but aro subject to 10 per cent, primage. Such educational films of United Kingdom origin as aro admissible under by-law are free of both customs duty and primage. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>The rates of duty payable on Australian-made films imported into the United Kingdom are (o) positives, i.e., films containing a picture for exhibition, whether developed or not, per lineal foot of standard width of If inches, *d; (6) negatives, i.e., films containing a photograph, whether developed or not, from which positives can be printed, per lineal foot of standard width of If inches,  3 1/3d </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>FEDERAL CAPITAL TERRITORY</title>
                    <page.no>245</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Unemployment</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Interior, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What is the present number of unemployed males in the Federal Capital Territory? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>What is the number of their dependants? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>What was the nature and duration of the temporary employment provided in November oflast year? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>What employment, if any, has been provided during the already expired period of this current year, and what were the nature and duration of same? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="5.">
                            <para>What provision, if any, has been made for the balance of this year? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Sir George Pearce</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para> The Minister for the Interior has supplied the following answers: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>  716 are registered. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para> Recordsofalldependants are not available. Dependants of applicants for ration relief number 619.  </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>For those registered who were dependent on unemployment relief works, full-time employment was provided from the 27th November to 22nd December, 1933. Prior to this, during November, the allotment was one week in two to married, and one in four to single, men. The nature of the work may be summarized as road improvements, afforestation, and scrub destruction. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>The allotment of work from 8th January, 1934, fluctuated between one week in three to one in two for married, and from one in five to one in four for single men. From the 14th May, 1934, until the 29th June, 1034, married men were employed full time, and single men for one week in three - generally on works of the same nature as in 1933. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="5.">
                            <para>This is dependent upon the amount that may be provided by Parliament. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>ASSISTANCE TO FRUITGROWERS</title>
                    <page.no>245</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KP8</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">JOHNSTON, Edward</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator E B JOHNSTON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Commerce, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Under what conditions and to what extent was assistance given to fruit-growers in each State of the Commonwealth under the provisions of the Fruit Growers Relief Act 1933? </para>
                    </quote>
                    </question>
                    <answer> 
                    <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>245</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
     <para> The answer to the honorable senator&#39;s questions is as follows:- </para>
     </talk.start> 
                    <quote>
                        <para>The Fruit Growers Relief Act appropriated the following sums, to be paid to the States, for the benefit and assistance of necessitous fruit-growers who could satisfy an authority . nominated by the State that they had suffered losses in the export from Australia of apples and pears grown by them during the 1932-33 season :  - </para>
               
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_27_0.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <para class="block">The following sums have been advanced to the States: - </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_27_1.jpg" />
                    </para>
                    <para>The other States have not applied for any portion of the sums allocated to them. </para>
                    <para>Questions have arisen in regard to the interpretation of the word &#34; necessitous &#34;. In order to assist the States in dealing with applications, the Prime Minister advised the States, in May last, that the best course to pursue was to obtain such particulars as would enable an opinion to be formed, firstly, whether the claimant had suffered losses in export during the 1932-33 season, and, secondly, whether, as a result of those losses, he had been placed in a position of financial difficulty. </para>
                         </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>AERODROME IN SOUTHERN TASMANIA</title>
                    <page.no>245</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K3L</name.id>
                            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SAMPSON, Burford</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SAMPSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister for Defence, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice </inline> What action, if any, has been taken to provide southern Tasmania with an aerodrome in the vicinity of Cambridge? </para>
                   </talk.start>

                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>245</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- A site for an aerodrome to serve Hobart has been selected. The acquisition of the site by the Commonwealth will be notified in the Commonwealth Gazette published to-day, and the necessary work to prepare the area for use by aircraft will be proceeded with. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SUBMAKINE TELEPHONE TO TASMANIA</title>
                    <page.no>245</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K3L</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SAMPSON, Burford</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SAMPSON</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Is the Minister prepared to make a statement with regard to the proposed submarine telephone cable between Tasmania and Victoria ? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If so, when is it likely that Tasmania&#39;s isolation from the Commonwealth trunk line service will end? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>245</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Postmaster-General has supplied the following answers :  - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Tenders are at present under consideration, and it is hoped a contract will be entered into at an early date. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Probably about twelve months after the placing of the contract for the submarine cable. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>WIRELESS BROADCASTING</title>
                    <page.no>246</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
<para>QueenslandB Class Stations - Kelso Station, Tasmania -Political Speeches. </para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>246</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                 <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
         <para>What B class wireless stations have been licensed in Queensland? </para>
                          </item>
                                <item label="2.">
                                    <para>What are the official designationsof same ? </para>
                                </item>
                                <item label="3.">
                                    <para>By whom is each owned and controlled? </para>
                                </item>
                                <item label="4.">
                                    <para>On what date and for what period are such licences issued ? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>246</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                            </talker>
      <para>- The Postmaster-General has supplied the following statement:- </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>The information sought by the honorable senator is incorporated in the following statement: - </para>
                    <para class="block">
                        <graphic href="144332193407054_28_0.jpg" />
                    </para>
             </quote>
                    </answer>
                    <question>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>246</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K3L</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">SAMPSON, Burford</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator SAMPSON</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>asked the Minister representing the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                        </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>What is the position with regard to the broadcasting station at Kelso, Tasmania? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Have tenders been called for and accepted? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>When will the work be commenced ? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>What is the approximate date of the opening of the station? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    </question>
                        <answer>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>246</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                            </talker>
        <para>- The Postmaster-General has supplied the following answers:- </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>The manufacture of the equipment is well advanced, and it is expected the erection of the building will soon be commenced. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Yes. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>See answer to 1 . </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>- Near the end of the year. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    </answer>
                    <question>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>246</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>asked the Minister representing the Postmaster-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                        </talk.start>
                        <quote>
                            <para>What reasons are advanced by the Postmaster-General for the refusal of the Australian Broadcasting Commission to allow Mr. Bcusley, M.P., leader of the Labour party. State of New South Wales, and Major Douglas, leader of the Douglas credit movement, the right to speak in the same manner as granted to other public men in Australia? </para>
                        </quote>
                        </question>
                        <answer> 
                            <talk.start>
                                <talker>
                                    <page.no>246</page.no>
                                    <time.stamp />
                                    <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                                    <electorate />
                                    <party />
                                    <role />
                                    <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                    <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                    <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                                    <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                                </talker>
          <para>- The Postmaster-General has supplied the following answer:- </para>
                            </talk.start>
                        <quote>
                            <para>The matter is one for determination by the Australian Broadcasting Commission, &#39; and the Postmaster-General has no knowledge of any negotiations in regard to broadcasting by either of the two gentlemen named. </para>
                        </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PENSIONS DEPARTMENT</title>
                    <page.no>246</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>Salaries of Deputy Commissioners</question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>246</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Has he received the report prepared by the Commissioner of Pensions upon the matter of the salary of deputy pensions commissioners and their staffs throughout the Commonwealth, about which the Minister promised information on the 14th June, 1933? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If so, will he make the report available to honorable senators, and will he inform the Senate what action, if any, has been taken in the matter? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                  <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>246</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KQZ</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">LAWSON, Harry</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir HARRY LAWSON</name>
                            </talker>
                    <para> The Treasurer has supplied the following answers :  -
                    </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>On the 10th November, 1933, in reply to a somewhat similar question, the honorable senator was informed that the report had been received and had been referred to the Public Service Board. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>The Public Service Board has raised the classification of all  deputy  commissioners of pensions. The report is purely a departmental one, and it is not the practice to make such reports available to honorable senators. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PRICKLY PEAR</title>
                    <page.no>246</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>246</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister administering the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Has the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research at any time inquired as to the fodder value of prickly pear? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If so, what were the results arrived at from such inquiry? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>If not, will the Minister instruct the council to make such inquiry} </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>247</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answers to the honorable  senator&#39;s questions are as follows : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>No, because full inquiries have been made by the Queensland Department of Agriculture, the results of which have already been published and are available. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>In view of the action taken by the Queensland Department of Agriculture, thu activities of the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research have been restricted, in co-operation with representatives of the two States concerned, that is, New South Wales and Queensland, to an investigation of biological methods for eradication and control of the excessive growth of the pest. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>See replies to 1 and 2. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>CANBERRA</title>
                    <page.no>247</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Molonglo and Causeway Blouses</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>247</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COLLINGS</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Interior, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>What steps, if any, have been taken to remedy the housing position at Molonglo and Causeway to which Senator Collings drew the attention of the Senate on 1st December of last year? </para>
                    </quote>
                     </question>
                    <answer>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>247</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                <para> The Minister for the Interior has supplied the following answers: -
                    </para>
                    </talk.start> 
                    <quote>
                        <para>The department is developing a scheme for the erection of 143 houses, which  includes  provision for about 50 workmen&#39;s dwellings, and the construction is now proceeding. </para>
                        <para>It has not been possible so far to demolish any of thu Molonglo dwellings, as the demand for accommodation of any sort by workmen is even heavier than when this question was previously raised. </para>
                    </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PETROL PRODUCTION FROM COAL</title>
                    <page.no>247</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>247</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister administering the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice </inline > </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Has his attention been drawn to a report appearing in Sydney newspapers to the effect that &#91;lending inquiries from England and a report on the progress made there in the production of petrol from coal, the chief executive officer for the Commonwealth Council for Scientific and Industrial Research (Dr. A. C. D. Rivett) had intimated that the Hydrogenation Committee, appointed by the Prime Minister, was not likely to meet until the end of this month? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>If the statement is correct is this not a departure from the assurance that has been given both in the Senate, and by the Minister to deputations? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>Will the Minister make a clear statement as to the reasons of the Government not going on with the production of petrol from coal? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>247</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions are as follow: - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Yes. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>The statement is correct, but it docs not represent any departure from assurances that have been given. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>Pursuant to a promise made by thu Prime Minister to a deputation which waited upon him at Cessnock on 23rd March, 1934, to the effect that he was prepared to ask the Federal Cabinet to give consideration to the question as to whether it would be advisable, in co-operation with the Government of New South Wales, to ask Imperial Chemical Industries Limited to undertake the construction of a plant in Australia concurrently with construction at Billingham-on-Tees, the matter was duly considered by Cabinet, when it was decided that an expert committee be appointed tor the purpose of reporting on the matter. The personnel of the committee comprises Dr. A. C. D. Rivett, as  chairman; Mr. L. J. Rogers, the Commonwealth fuel adviser, and a representative of the defence services, as representatives of the Commonwealth; and one representative of each of those States which desired to bc represented, together with one or more representatives of Imperial Chemical Industries Limited, as the company desired. All States, with thu exception of Western Australia, which does not desire to be represented, have now nominated representatives to the committee, and Synthetic Coal Oil Products Proprietary Limited, has nominated Mr. Norman Taylor, of Imperial Chemical Industries Limited. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
    <para>The terms of reference to the committee are to report upon - </para>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>The most suitable location in Australia for a hydrogenation plant capable of using about 1,000 tons of coal per day; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Estimated costs of production; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>The estimated amount of protection and\/or subsidy which would be required in connexion with such enterprise; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="4.">
                            <para>The estimated number of men who would be directly employed in connexion with such work; this information to .be dissected showing the number of .miners and other work-people. Probable indirect employment to be shown if possible; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="5.">
                            <para>The advantages likely to accrue to Australia as the result of the installation of the plant, computing as accurately as possible items which could be set-off against the additional cost of the product ; </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="6.">
                            <para>As to when the plant should be erected ; and </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="7.">
                            <para>Any other matters considered to bc relevant to the project. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para>Some divergence of opinion exists among the States as to the proper location for a hydrogenation plant, and a good deal of additional information is required as to the merits of brown coal for production of petrol by the  hydrogenation process. It is expected that valuable information on certain points will reach Australia from England during the present month, and in these circumstances Dr. Rivett deemed it desirable to defer calling a meeting of the committee until the information arrived. In the meantime, however, members of the committee are devoting their attention to certain aspects of the matter which have been brought to their notice by Dr. Rivett.</para>
                    <para>I can give an assurance that no delay will occur, hut it is imperative that the Government should be in possession of the fullest information before giving consideration to the question of establishing an industry of  the  magnitude mentioned. </para>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PUBLIC SERVICE</title>
                    <page.no>248</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Restoration of Salaries and Wages</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>248</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Prime Minister, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Is the Government prepared to bring about the rescission of the emergency wage cuts, the stabilization of cost-of-living adjustments, and the payment of the basic wage to male employees on reaching adult age in the Federal Public Service; if not, why not? </para>
                    </quote>
                    </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>248</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- The right honorable the Prime Minister has supplied the following answer: - </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>It would be contrary to established practice to make a statement of policy in reply to a question. </para>
                    </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>WIRELESS EQUIPMENT ON COASTAL VESSELS</title>
                    <page.no>248</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>248</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Leader of the Government in the Senate, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>How far has the Government used its powers concerning safety at  Bea  in the direction of demanding that all coastal vessels of 50 tons and over trading on the Australian coast should install wireless? </para>
                    </quote>
                 </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>248</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                      <para> Commonwealth control of shipping covers only such vessels as are engaged in interstate or overseas trade. About 90 per cent. of the small craft of 50 tons and over trade within the limits of a State, and are subject to State laws. The matter of legislative control of these latter is at present the subject of negotiation with the State Governments concerned.  </para>
                      </talk.start> 
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>

            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SURPLUS MILITARY CLOTHING</title>
                    <page.no>248</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>248</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>askedthe Minister for Defence, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>Will the Minister take into account the sufferings of coal-miners and their families in </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <para class="block">New South Wales, which have been caused by the depression and lack of oversea coal orders by countries using oil fuel? </para>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>Will he order an issue to them of military clothing, flannel (bulk), and boots? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>248</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
              <para> The answers to the honorable senator&#39;s questions are as follows: -
                    </para>
                    </talk.start> 
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>The Government has taken into account the privations suffered by many sections of the community as the result of the depression and the vagaries of trade, and every endeavour has been made to give relief in the issue of military clothing when available. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>All surplus stocks of military clothing, flannel, boots, &#38;c, were distributed to those in necessitous circumstances some time ago, and the only military clothing which now becomes available is that which is returned by the troops. This clothing is issued to the State Governments from time to time for relief purposes. </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PASSPORTS</title>
                    <page.no>248</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>248</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Interior, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>How many persons received passports during the last twelve months to enable them to travel on overseas steamers not registered in Australia and sailing to Port Moresby, Papua, Saraarai, Rabaul, New Guinea, and the Solomon Islands? </para>
                    </quote>
                      </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>248</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                        <para> The Minister for the Interior has supplied the following answer: -
                    </para>
                    </talk.start> 
                    <quote>
                        <para>The question presumably refers to overseas steamers not registered in Australia which undertake short round trip cruises from Sydney to Papua, New Guinea, and Solomon Islands. Australian passengers making round trips of this kind, either by vessels which are registered or not registered in Australia, are not required to obtain passports. </para>
                    </quote>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>COMMONWEALTH BANK. EMPLOYEES</title>
                    <page.no>248</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <para>Restoration of Salaries</para>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>248</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Prime Minister, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>In view of the private trading banks of New South Wales increasing the wages of their employees by 8 per cent. of the total reductions of the 10 per cent, cut under the Premiers plan, will the Prime Minister approach the Commonwealth Bank Board with a view to the employees of the bank having restored to them the 10 per cent, which was taken from them in accordance with the Premiers plan; if not, why not? </para>
                    </quote>
                 </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>248</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
             <para> The right honorable the Prime Minister states that inquiries are being made, and  a  reply will bo furnished as soon as possible.   </para>
                 </talk.start> 
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>GREATBRITAIN&#39;SWARDEBTTO AMERICA</title>
                    <page.no>249</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>249</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Leader of the Government in the Senate, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>Is  it  a  fact  that the tenor of the note recently addressed and conveyed to the  President  of the United States of America at Washington, United States of America, by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, Mr. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., was a justification of a British default and that the interest and wellbeing of the British people must take precedence over the claims of the American bondholders ? </para>
                    </quote>
                    </question>
                    <answer> 
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>249</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0F</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">PEARCE, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Sir GEORGE PEARCE</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I would referthe honornble senator to the statement issued by the Prime Minister at Canberra on the 7th June on the subject of war debts. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TRADE AGREEMENTS</title>
                    <page.no>249</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>249</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JNM</name.id>
                            <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party>CP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">BADMAN, Albert</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator BADMAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Trade and Customs, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>How many trade agreements with foreign countries are at present in existence, if any? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>What are the names of such countries? </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>With what countries arc trade agreements at present being negotiated? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                 </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>249</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KTR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>UAP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLACHLAN, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLACHLAN</name>
                        </talker>
                    <para>The Minister for Trade and Customs has supplied the following answers: - </para>
                    </talk.start> 
                    <list type="decimal-dotted">
                        <item label="1.">
                            <para>None. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="2.">
                            <para>See answer to No. 1. </para>
                        </item>
                        <item label="3.">
                            <para>Concrete proposals for trade agreements are being discussed with Belgium, Italy, and France. Preliminary discussions have taken place with regard to Japan, Germany, United States of America, Spain, Norway, Poland, the Netherlands, and Czechoslovakia, Greece, and China? </para>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LEAVE OF ABSENCE</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>leave of absence</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sampson)</inline> agreed to- </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir Walter</inline> Kingsmill be granted one month&#39;s leave of absence on the ground of ill health. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>CUSTOMS TARIFF (EXCHANGE ADJUSTMENT) BILL 1934</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Bill read a third time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>CUSTOMS TARIFF (PRIMAGE DUTIES) 1934</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Bill received from the House of Representatives, and (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLachlan)</inline> read a first time. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>CUSTOMS BILL 1932</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>bill</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Bill returned from the House of Representatives with amendments. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>special adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir George</inline> Pearce) agreed  to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the Senate at its rising adjourn till Wednesday next at 3 p.m. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <type>adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator SirGeorge</inline> Pearce) proposed - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
            </quote>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>249</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JYB</name.id>
                        <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DUNN, James Patrick Digger</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DUNN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. -  I again enter my protest against the adjournment of the Senate for another week when there is work to be done. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <adjournment>
            <adjournmentinfo>
                <page.no>249</page.no>
                <time.stamp>18:35:00</time.stamp>
            </adjournmentinfo>
            <para>Senate adjourned at 6.35 p.m. </para>
        </adjournment>
    </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>