
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1943-09-24</date>
    <parliament.no>17</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>1</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>25</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para>ADJOURNMENT. </para>
    <para>
      <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. FORDE</inline>(Capricornia- Deputy </para>
    <para>Prime Minister) &#91;4.12&#93;. - As a mark of respect to the memory of the deceased, I
      move - </para>
    <para>That the House do now adjourn. </para>
    <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
    <para>House adjourned at 4.14 p.m. </para>
    <para class="block">Senate. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1943-09-24</day.start>
      <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon. Gordon Brown)</inline> took
        the chair at 11 a.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF EX-SENATOR ALBERT WILLIAM ROBINSON</title>
        <page.no>25</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>25</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate/>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I have received from <inline font-weight="bold">Mrs. A.W.</inline> Robinson a
            letter of thanks for the resolution of sympathy and condolence passed by the Senate on
            the occasion of the death of her husband, ex-Senator Albert William Robinson. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ASSENT TO BILLS</title>
        <page.no>26</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Assent to the following bills reported : - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>Commonwealth Electoral . (War Service) Bill 1943. </para>
        <para>Customs Tariff Validation Bill (No. 2) 1943. </para>
        <para>Customs Tariff (Exchange Adjustment) Validation Bill (No. 2) 1943. </para>
        <para>Customs Tariff (Special War Duty) Validation Bill (No. 2) 1943. </para>
        <para>Customs Tariff (New Zealand Preference) Validation Bill (No. 2)1943. </para>
        <para>Customs Tariff (Canadian Preference) Validation Bill (No. 2) 1943. </para>
        <para>Excise Tariff Validation Bill (No. 2) 1943. </para>
        <para>Income Tax (War-time Arrangements) Bill 1943. </para>
        <para>Sales Tax (Exemptions and Classifications) </para>
      </quote>
      <para class="block">Bill 1943. </para>
      <para>Invalid and Old-age Pensions (Reciprocity with New Zealand) Bill 1943. </para>
      <para>Dairying Industry Assistance Bill 1943. </para>
      <para>National Security Bill 1943. </para>
      <para>War Service Estates Bill 1943. </para>
      <para>Supplementary Appropriation Bill 1941-42. </para>
      <para>Supplementary Appropriation (Works and Buildings) Bill 1941-42. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF THE HONORABLE SIR WILLIAM HILL IRVINE</title>
        <page.no>26</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>SenatorKEANE (Victoria - Minister for Trade and Customs). - It is with regret that I
        inform honorable senators of the death on the 20th August last of the Honorable <inline
          font-weight="bold">Sir William</inline> Hill Irvine, formerly Lieutenant-Governor and
        Chief Justice of Victoria, a former Minister of the Crown and member of the House of
        Representatives and of the Legislative Assembly of Victoria. The late <inline
          font-weight="bold">Sir William</inline> Irvine had adistinguished career, both in law and
        in politics. Learned, and gifted with great mental capacity, he utilized his talents for the
        benefit of Australia and, more particularly, for the State of Victoria, where he was elected
        to the Legislative Assembly in 189-1 as member for Lowan, a seat he hold until his
        resignation in 1906, when he entered the Commonwealth sphere. During that period . he held
        several ministerial offices, being successively Attorney-General, Premier and
        Attorney-General, and Premier and Treasurer. He was elected to the House of Representatives
        as the member for Flinders at the general elections in 1906 and retained the seat until his
        appointment as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Victoria in April, 1918. During his
        term as the member for Flinders he held office as Attorney-General from </para>
      <para class="block">June, 1913, toSeptember, 1914. As a tributeto the memory of a great
        Australian I move - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the Senate expresses its sincere regret at the death of the Honorable <inline
            font-weight="bold">Sir William</inline> Hill Irvine, a former member of the House of
          Representatives for the Division of Flinders and of the Legislative Assembly for Lowan,
          Victoria, and a Minister of the Crown, also a former Lieutenant-Governor and Chief Justice
          of the State of Victoria, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public
          service, and tenders its deep sympathy to his widow and family in their bereavement.
        </para>
      </quote>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>26</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role>Loader of the Opposition</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I second the motion, and join with the Leader of the Senate <inline
              font-weight="bold">(Senator Keane)</inline> in expressing the deepest sympathy of
            members of the Opposition with the relatives of the late <inline font-weight="bold">Sir
              William</inline> Irvine in their bereavement. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>26</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KAY</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIBSON, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIBSON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I desire toassociate the members of the Australian Country party in the Senate
            with the motion before the chamber. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Sir
              William</inline> Irvine was a statesman in the truest sense of the word. His name will
            be indelibly inscribed in the history of Australia, and his life and work will provide
            an inspiration to others to endeavour to attain to the same high standard as that
            reached by him. As Lieutenant-Governor, Chief Justice and Premier of Victoria, and as
            AttorneyGeneral of the Commonwealth, he discharged his duties in a distinguished manner,
            and through his death Australia has lost one of its greatest men. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places.
        </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>26</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEATH OF THE HONORABLE DAVID JOHN O&#39;KEEFE</title>
          <page.no>26</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>26</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KE4</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEANE, Richard</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEANE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - I have also to inform the Senate of the death on the 21st July last of the
              Honorable David John O&#39;Keefe, who was a member of the first Commonwealth
              Parliament, having been elected a senator for Tasmania in 1901. Although defeated in
              1906, he successfully contested the general elections of 1910 and 1914, wasChairman of
              Committees from 1910 to 1914 and a member of the Commonwealth Parliamentary
              RecruitingCommittee from 1917 to 1918. Having been again defeated in the general
              elections in 1919, he stood for Denison, Tasmania, at the 1922 elections, and secured
              the seat which he lost in the succeeding elections in. 1925. After suffering a further
              defeat in 1931 as a Senate candidate, he won the State seat of Wilmot in 1934,
              Subsequently he was appointed Speaker of the House of Assembly in Tasmania and
              retained that high office until 1941. In that year he was awarded the distinction! of
              Companion of the Order of St. Michael and St. George. With his death passes yet
              another of the pioneers of the Labour party. His long years of public service and
              elevation to high office bear witness to the worth and to the esteemin which he was
              held by his fellow men. In recognition of his services to the Commonwealth and to the
              State of Tasmania the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. O&#39;Keefe</inline> was
              accorded a State funeral. I move - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>That the Senate expresses its sincere regret at the death of the Honorable David
              John O&#39;Keefe,a former senator for the State of Tasmania, and a member of the House
              of Representatives for the Division of Denison, and a Speaker of the House of
              Assembly, Tasmania, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public
              service, and tenders its heartfelt sympathy to his widow and family in their
              bereavement. </para>
          </quote>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>27</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KUA</name.id>
              <electorate>South Australia Leader of the Opposition</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I second the motion, and endorse the remarks of the Leader of the Senate <inline
                font-weight="bold">(Senator Keane)</inline> expressing appreciation of the
              meritorious public service rendered by the late former senator. The Opposition extends
              to the relatives of the deceased gentleman its deepest sympathy in their bereavement.
            </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>27</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KQF</name.id>
              <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LAMP, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LAMP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I wish to associate myself with this motion. I had known the late Honorable
              David John O&#39;Keefe all my life. I first remember him as editor of the <inline
                font-style="italic">Zeehan and Dundas Herald,</inline> when he adopted as his slogan
              the following lines which appear on the leader page of the <inline font-style="italic"
                >Canberra Times: -</inline></para>
          </talk.start>
          <quote>
            <para>For the cause that lacks assistance, </para>
            <para>Gainst the wrongs that need resistance, </para>
            <para>For the future in the distance, </para>
            <para>And&#39; the good that we can do. </para>
          </quote>
          <para class="block">The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. O&#39;Keefe</inline>
            faithfully observed the spirit of that slogan in its entirety. I knew him as a member of
            this Senate, as the member for Denison in the House of Representatives and as the
            representative of Wilmot in the Parliament of Tasmania. During the last State elections
            I was his campaign secretary, and he conducted himself during that campaign as one of
            nature&#39;s gentlemen. On the Monday morning after his re-election he called at my
            house with his. chequebook and desired to settle all of his accounts. I have never known
            a more noble or humane man than our late esteemed comrade. He died a poor man, which
            shows that he was not in Parliament to gain financial benefits, but to serve the
            interests of the community in general. While I was in hospital recently he visited me
            and told me that he desired to see his son in Victoria. He added, &#34; I shall be back
            wi thin a month in order to conduct your campaign, the same as you have conducted
            mine&#34;. The deceased had all the attributes of a perfect gentleman. I extend my
            heartfelt sympathy to his widow and family. </para>
          <para>
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator</inline>COOPER (Queensland).Members of the Australian
            Country party in the Senate desire to associate themselves with this motion. We express
            our appreciation of the valuable service rendered by the deceased, and offer our deepest
            sympathy to his widow and family. </para>
          <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places.
          </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF ME, ED W ARDRILEY</title>
        <page.no>27</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>27</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KE4</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>ALP</party>
            <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEANE, Richard</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEANE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I have to announce the death of another former member of the House
            ofRepresentatives, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. EdwardRiley,</inline> who died on the
            21st July last. He represented the electorate of South Sydney from 1919 to 1931. He was
            chairman of the Public Works Committee from 1914 to 1917. In 1923 he was a member of the
            select committee on the effect of the operations of the Navigation. Act on trade, and in
            1926 and 1927 he was a member of the select committee which inquired into Commonwealth
            Electoral Law and Procedure. He is another of the pioneers of the Labour movement who
            strove hard for better conditions and regulated wages for the workers, and deserves the
            affectionate remembrance of his fellow men. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate expresses its sincere regret at the death of <inline
              font-weight="bold">Mr. Edward</inline> Riley, a former member of the House of
            Representatives for the Division of South Sydney, places <inline font-style="italic"
              >on</inline> record its appreciation of his meritorious public service, and tenders
            its deep sympathy to his relatives in their bereavement. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role>Leader of the Opposition</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I second the motion, and on behalf of the Opposition pay tribute to the work of
            the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Riley.</inline> It is fitting &#39;that we
            should place on record our appreciation of his work, and extend to his family our deep
            sympathy in their bereavement. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>JQP</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">COOPER, Walter</name>
            <name role="display">Senator COOPER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- The members of the Australian Country party in the Senate desire to associate
            themselves with the motion, and to say how greatly they appreciate the work which
              <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Riley</inline> performed. He. was probably the only
            person who could say that he sat in this Parliament at the same time as his son and his
            son-in-law. -The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Riley</inline> gave the whole of
            hi3 time to the betterment of the people whom he represented, and members of the Country
            party extend to his family their sincere and deep sympathy. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places.
        </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>DEATH OF MR. JOSHUA THOMAS HOSKINS WHITSITT</title>
        <page.no>28</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KE4</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>ALP</party>
            <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEANE, Richard</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEANE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I regret to announce to honorable senators the death, on the 14th September, of
              <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Joshua</inline> Thomas Hoskins Whitsitt, a former
            member for Darwin in the House of Representatives, and of the Tasmanian House of
            Assembly. The deceased gentleman held his seat uninterruptedly in the Tasmanian
            Parliament from the time of his election in 1909 until his defeat in 1922. Later in
            1922, he successfully contested the Darwin seat in the House of Representatives, and
            retired on the expiration of the Ninth Parliament in 1925. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate expresses its sincere regret at the death of <inline
              font-weight="bold">Mr. Joshua</inline> Thomas Hoskins Whitsitt, a former member of the
            House of </para>
          <para class="block">Representatives for the Division of Darwin and of the House of
            Assembly, Tasmania, places on record its appreciation of his meritorious public service
            and tenders its deep sympathy to his widow and family in their bereavement. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role>Leader of the Opposition</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - On behalf of the Opposition, I second the motion, and join with the Leader of
            the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Keane)</inline> in expressing
            appreciation of the services rendered by the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.
              Whitsitt</inline> as a member of the Commonwealth Parliament and also of the
            Parliament of Tasmania. It is fitting that appreciation of his services should be
            incorporated in the records of the Senate. Members of the Opposition join in the
            expression of sympathy with the relatives of the deceased gentleman in their
            bereavement. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KAY</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIBSON, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIBSON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I desire to be associated with the motion. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.
              Whitsitt</inline> was a member of the Country party in its early days, when it was
            putting up a big fight on behalf of the primary producers. His decision not to stand for
            re-election was received with great regret, by members of the Country party. However, he
            transferred his sphere of activities to the Parliament of Tasmania, and there, too, I
            understand that he did remarkably good work. The necessity for frequent travelling
            between Tasmania and the mainland was the chief reason why <inline font-weight="bold"
              >Mr. Whitsitt</inline> did not remain a member of the House of Representatives. Had he
            continued to be a member of the Commonwealth Parliament I am confident that he would
            have rendered further valuable service. The deceased gentleman did not speak often in
            the House of Representatives, but when he did he spoke with no uncertain voice. He was a
            likeable man who was a force in Country party politics. I offer to his family my sincere
            sympathy in their bereavement. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>28</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KOJ</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">HAYS, Herbert</name>
            <name role="display">Senator HERBERT HAYS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I, too, should like to pay a tribute to the memory of the late <inline
              font-weight="bold">Mr. Whitsitt.</inline> It was my privilege to know him for many
            years both as a member of the House of Representatives and as a member of the Parliament
            of Tasmania. There was neve&#93;1 a more earnest man, or one more determined to uphold
            the Commonwealth Constitution. Only a few weeks aso I visited him at his home, and
            although a very sick man, he spoke cheerfully and kindly of his associations with men in
            public life. He was a great advocate of the claims of the primary producers, and he
            spoke forcefully on their behalf. He was a charming companion, and he possessed all
            those qualities which make a good Australian. I regret his passing, and support the
            motion that the sympathy of the Senate be extended to his widow and family. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places.
        </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SECOND CURTIN MINISTRY</title>
        <page.no>29</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Allotment of Portfolios - War Cabinet - Representation of Ministers - Government
        Leadership in the Senate. </para>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>29</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KE4</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>ALP</party>
            <role>Minister for Trade and Customs</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEANE, Richard</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEANE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - I desire formally to announce to
            the Senate that on the 21st September, 1943, a new Ministry was formed, constituted as
            follows : - </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Prime Minister and Minister for Defence - The Right Honorable John Curtin</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para class="block">Minister for the Army - The Honorable P. M. Forde, who willalso be
          Deputy Prime Minister. </para>
        <para class="block">Treasurer and Minister for Post-war Reconstruction - The Honorable J. B.
          Chifley. </para>
        <para>Attorney-General and Minister for External Affairs - The Right Honorable H. V. Evatt,
          LL.D., KC. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Supply and Shipping - The Honorable J. A. Beasley</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Minister for the Navy and Minister for Munitions - The Honorable N. J.O. Ma kin. </para>
        <para>Ministerfor Trade and Customs - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>
          Honorable R. V. Keane. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Labour and National Service - The Honorable E. J. Holloway</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Air and Minister for Civil Aviation - The Honorable A. S.
            Drakeford</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Commerce and Agriculture -The Honorable W. J. Scully</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Postmaster-General and Vice-President of the Executive Council - <inline
            font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline> Honorable W. P. Ashley. </para>
        <para>Minister for War Organization of Industry and Minister in Charge of the Council for
          Scientific and Industrial Research - The Honorable J. J. Dedman, </para>
        <para>Minister for the Interior - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline> Honorable
          J. S. Collings. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Transport and Minister for External Territories - The Honorable E. J.
            Ward</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Minister for Health and Minister for Social Services - <inline font-weight="bold"
            >Senator the</inline> Honorable J. M. Fraser. </para>
        <para>Minister for Repatriation and Minister in Charge of War Service Homes - The Honorable
          C. W. Frost. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Home Security - The Honorable H. P. Lazzarini</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Minister for Aircraft Production - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>
          Honorable D. Cameron. </para>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Minister for Information - The Honorable A. A. Calwell</title>
          <page.no>29</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>The members of the War Cabinet are <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Curtin, Mr. Forde,
            Mr. Chifley, Dr. Evatt, Mr. Beasley, Mr. Makin, Mr. Drakeford</inline> and <inline
            font-weight="bold">Mr. Dedman.</inline></para>
        <para>Ministers in the House of Representatives will be represented in the Senate as follows
          : - </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>Honorable R. V. Keane will represent the
          Prime Minister and Minister for Defence and the Treasurer and Minister for Post-war
          Reconstruction ; </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>Honorable W. P. Ashley will represent the
          Attorney-General and Minister for External Affairs, the Minister for the Navy and Minister
          for Munitions, the Minister for Labour and National Service, and the Minister for
          Information; </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>Honorable J. S. Collings will represent the
          Minister for Transport and Minister for External Territories, and the Minister for Home
          Security; </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the</inline>Honorable J. M. Fraser will represent the
          Minister for the Army, the Minister for Supply and Shipping, and the Minister for Commerce
          and Agriculture; and </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the&#39;</inline>Honorable D. Cameron will represent
          the Minister for Air and Minister for Civil Aviation, the Minister for War Organization of
          Industry and Minister in Charge of the Council forScientific and Industrial Research, and
          the Minister for Repatriation and Minister in Charge of War Service Homes. </para>
        <para>I have to announce also that I have been appointed Leader of the Government in the
          Senate and that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Ashley</inline> has been appointed
          Deputy Leader. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KUA</name.id>
              <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role>Leader of the Opposition</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">by leave -</inline> On behalf of the Opposition, I
              congratulate the Minister for Trade and Customs <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator
                Keane)</inline> on his appointment to the high office of the Leader of the Senate. I
              take this opportunity also to express our appreciation of the courtesies extended to
              the Opposition by the Minister for the Interior <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator
                Collings)</inline> when he was the Leader of the Government in this chamber. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>LEADER, DEPUTY LEADER AND WHIP OF THE OPPOSITION</title>
        <page.no>30</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>30</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role>Leader of the Opposition</role>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">by leave -</inline> I wish to report that . <inline
              font-weight="bold">Senator McBride</inline> has tendered his resignation as Deputy
            Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator
              Leckie</inline> has been appointed in his stead. The Opposition party has re-elected
            me Leader of the Opposition. SenatorUppill is acting Opposition Whip. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>30</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>REPATRIATION COMMISSION</title>
          <page.no>30</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>K7M</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COLLETT, Herbert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COLLETT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>Before the prorogation of tie last Parliament I placed on the notice-paper a
              question relating to the medical staff of the Repatriation Commission.. I have
              received an answer by letter, but as the question was an important one, I consider
              that the information contained in the answer should be made public. Perhaps the
              Minister representing the Minister for Repatriation would be good enough to indicate
              whether he would like me to repeat the question, so that it and the answer may be
              incorporated in the records of the Senate. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>L8E</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role>Minister for Aircraft Production</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAMERON, Donald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CAMERON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>I have no objection to the answer being made public, and will arrange for that to
              be done. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>30</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>APPLES</title>
          <page.no>30</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KR9</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LECKIE, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LECKIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Can the Minister representing the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture say
              whether it is a fact that there are vast quantities of apples still available in
              Tasmania notwithstanding that, in other portions of the Commonwealth, consumers have
              to pay exorbitant prices for apples? If so, can he say whether Tasmanian apples can be
              made available at reasonable prices to the thousands of consumers on the mainland who
              desire to obtain this fruit? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>30</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>KKR</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FRASER, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator FRASER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>Every endeavour has been made, both in Tasmania and Western Australia, to supply
              sufficient apples to markets in the eastern States, but, unfortunately, shipping
              difficulties have prevented that from being done. Commodities with a higher priority
              than apples have been given precedence in allotting the shipping space available.
            </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
        <page.no>30</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para class="block">Address-in -Reply. </para>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>30</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>K7Y</name.id>
            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">TANGNEY, Dorothy</name>
            <name role="display">Senator TANGNEY</name>
          </talker>
          <para>I move - </para>
        <para>That the following Address-in-Reply to His Excellency the Governor-General&#39;s
          Speech be agreed to:- </para>
        <quote>
          <para>May it please Your Excellency: </para> 
          <para>We, the Senate of the Commonwealth of Australia, in Parliament assembled, desire to
            express our loyalty to our Most Gracious Sovereign, and to thank Your Excellency for the
            Speech which you have been pleased to address to Parliament. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>I realize the great honour which has been done to me in affording me the opportunity
          to move this Address-in-Reply. I also realize my great honour in being the first woman to be
          elected to the Senate. But it is not as a woman that I have been elected to this chamber.
          It is as a citizen of the Commonwealth; and I take my place here with the full privileges
          and rights of all honorable senators, and, what is still more important, with the full
          responsibilities which such a high office entails. I trust that I shall carry out my
          duties in this chamber with every regard for the dignity and honour of the Senate, and
          also of the party to which I have the honour to belong. </para>
        <para>Addressing myself specifically to the motion, I express my gratitude to those who have
          rendered our nation so secure as was indicated in the Speech delivered by His Excellency.
          I pay tribute, first, to the wonderful achievements of our men and women in the fighting
          forces who in every sphere of action have so gallantly upheld the prestige of Australia.
          I also pay tribute to the remarkable achievements of our Allies to the men and women of
          China who for so many years now have fought our common enemy, to the thousands of
          Americans who left their homes and came to our assistance in our most critical hour,
          when, for the first time in the 150 years of our existence as a free nation, we were
          threatened by a foreign enemy; to our gallant Dutch allies who from our Australian
          homeland are now doing their utmost to drive back the Japanese aggressor to the confines
          of his own territory; to our gallant kinsmen in New Zealand who, for a second time, have
          shown that the word Anzac has no hollow meaning but really symbolizes the kinship of
          blood which unites us and makes the peoples of the Commonwealth and of New Zealand the
          standard-bearers of freedom in this farflung outpost of the Empire. The work which has
          been done by our Allies and the men and women of our forces has been backed up no less by
          the vast army of industrial workers, both men and women, who, in the past four years,
          have worked night and day so loyally and well to turn out the sinews of war in order that
          the best human material we have available shall with the best possible equipment bring
          closer the day of victory. </para>
        <para>Particularly, I pay tribute to the women in industry who, for the first time, have been called upon to take their places in fields
          hitherto the prerogatives of men, especially those engaged in the engineering industry
          who have turned night into day, and have pursued a way of life completely foreign to
          anything they had known before. I have seen them at work in munitions factories. I
          have seen them going on shifts at midnight with the same heroism as has marked the
          wonderful exploits of our men on the battlefields. I hope that when the day of peace
          comes what has been so willingly surrendered by our workers in industry will not be
          forgotten, and that the maximum of what they have voluntarily given up in the war
          effort will be the minimum upon which our new industrial standards will be based. I do not
          forget the men and women on the land who with very great inconvenience have toiled from
          daylight to dark in order that we and the members of our fighting forces shall be fed, and
          our food commitments to our Allies, particularly Great Britain, shall be met. They have
          done this work in spite of hardships due to unavoidable shortages of material and labour
          brought about by the war. The people of Australia owe to the people on the land a very
          great debt. </para>
        <para>I pay tribute to the Curtin Government which was called to office at a time of crisis
          unprecedented in the history of the nation. Under conditions never before paralleled in
          this country, and with a minority in both Houses, it was still able to call the nation to
          a total war effort and to co-ordinate the various forces necessary for the success of that
          effort. We know of the policy of regimentation imposed on the Australian people. Such a
          policy is absolutely foreign to our normal way of life; the imposing of it upon us must
          have been most distasteful to any government, and particularly to a Labour Government.
          However, it was necessary because the times were such as we had never before experienced;
          and all our man-power and natural resources had to be fully exploited if we were to
          survive as a free nation. Because of the measures that were taken we are now, as His
          Excellency remarked, free from danger of foreign aggression; but we are not free from the
          responsibilities which lie upon all of us to bring to the oppressed peoples of the world
          the same measure of freedom and democracy as we enjoy, and we must not rest from our
          labours until that happy state of affairs is instituted. That is why we have a
          foreshadowing of very heavy taxation because by that way of sacrifice victory will be
          achieved. Should we feel no greater impact of war than increased taxes, or the rationing
          of certain goods which we have come to regard as necessaries, but which, after all, are
          luxuries, we should indeed be thankful, because all of us know of the conditions of the
          peoples in those countries which have been overrun by the enemy. None of us likes to pay
          taxes but we must realize that the contributions required of us bring nearer the day of
          victory. We must also remember that the Government which was recently elected by the
          people of Australia has a twofold duty to perform. First and foremost is the winning of
          the war, the giving of the maximum possible assistance to our Allies so that peace may be
          won. But there is also a very heavy responsibility upon the Government to see that the
          peace shall not be lost. All of us know what happened after the last war; that it was a
          war to end wars, and would make this country fit for heroes to live in, but instead of
          Australia being made fit for heroes to live in it became a land for paupers to die in. We
          must be certain that a similar state of affairs shall not follow in the wake of this war.
          Therefore, I put it to the Senate that one of the chief functions of the Government is to
          work towards a policy to ensure that, once our national safety is assured, the fate of
          those on the home front will be safeguarded, and we shall build up a democracy on the very
          best basis that Australia can provide. The last Parliament laid down the foundation of a
          plan of social services. Social security is the right of every Australian; and I trust
          that on the foundation already laid we shall be able to build a much stronger edifice
          which, no matter how fierce the winds of reaction may blow against it, will be able to
          endure. Thus we shall make this country what it should be, a model for all other
          democracies to follow. In order to do this we must observe fully the Atlantic Charter.
          Every citizen has at least two rights - freedom from fear and freedom from want. In order
          to safeguard those rights the Commonwealth Parliament will need to take over a great deal
          of work that has hitherto been regarded as the prerogative or duty of the States. If this
          war has done nothing else it has at least made our people Australia-minded. We are no
          longer Western Australians, or Victorians, or New South Welshmen. We all are Australians,
          and we come here with a common duty to perform, not in the interests of any special
          section of the community, but in the interests of Australia as a whole. We say that
          Australia is a democracy. I hope that that is true. I believe that if any democracy is to
          succeed it must be an educated democracy, and its leaders must come from the people
          themselves. That has been proved over and over again. Therefore, in any scheme of
          reconstruction, in the new order - about which there is so much glib talk but apparently
          little knowledge - we must be certain to put first things first. In this policy of
          reconstruction we must give, first, social security to all. I understand that a portion of
          the Government&#39;s revenue from income tax has already been earmarked for that purpose.
          We shall be too late if we wait until the last gun is fired or the last shell has burst
          before we enter upon this era of reconstruction. We must begin now, and I am pleased
          to know that provision has already been made by the Government to this end. His
          Excellency&#39;s Speech also gives an indication of further provision to be made for that
          purpose by this Parliament. </para>
        <para>We must have federal control of education, and see that the various State education
          departments are freed from their present financial worries and enabled to carry out a
          policy which will give to every Australian citizen the benefits which only education can
          confer. Help has already been provided by the Commonwealth Government for university
          students, but the problem of education goes much deeper. The previous Government has done
          something for kindergartens at the one end of the scale and university students at the
          other, but the vast mass of our children in between has been left untouched. If we are to
          achieve anything as a nation, we must tackle education over its whole range, taking care
          at the same time not to make the system stereotyped. Education is just as vital a part of
          our defence system as is any portion of the armed services, and in that light it must be
          considered by this Parliament. </para>
        <para>That applies also to our other social services. We have at present a system of
          pensions which, to my mind, are very inadequate. I do not know how I or any other
          honorable senator on either side of the chamber could exist on &#163;1 6s. a week, with an odd
          6d. thrown in now and again. It is time that pensions were abolished, because we are all
          shareholders in this vast Commonwealth; there are 7,000,000 of us, and it is the duty of
          this Parliament to provide that men or women who have given a lifetime of service to the
          nation shall be given, when they reach pensionable age, not &#163;1 6s. a week as a dole,
          but their share of the national dividend which they have helped by their labour to create
          over the years. I hope, therefore, that in this new scheme of social security, adequate
          provision will be made for those who have reached the eventide of life so that they may
          enjoy in peace and security those benefits which they themselves have helped to create. </para>
        <para>The medical schemes listed under the social service proposals should also be put into
          operation, because at present only the two extremes of our people are receiving the very
          best that medical science can give. The very poor receive it as a charity or dole, and at
          the other end of the social ladder we have those who can afford to pay for it, but the
          people in between, the vast middle class, have to spend the rest of their lives paying for
          one severe illness. I do not think that the introduction of a system that would assure the
          best medical attention to all would destroy initiative, or discourage anything that the
          doctors at present do or could do. We must have a healthy community, and prevention
          is better than cure. Under present conditions many people delay going to the doctor until
          it is far too late, because they are afraid of the expense involved. I feel sure that if
          we had a national system of health this could be obviated. Quite recently I visited a
          sanatorium for tubercular patients, and was very perturbed and saddened by what I saw
          there. Many of the patients were young men and women of from 20 to 25 years of age. If we
          cast our minds back, we will find that they were some of the children who were growing up
          during the depression years, and in nine cases out of ten their present illnesses must be
          due to the circumstances which existed at that period, including malnutrition which was a
          consequence of the miserable dole upon which their parents had to exist, and unhygienic
          housing, often consisting of only shanties or huts on a river bank, that were unfit to be
          the habitations of the growing sons and daughters of Australia. That is why so many young
          people at the present moment are suffering in our sanatoriums. Had they received medical
          attention earlier, and enjoyed a proper standard of living during their growing years,
          they would be healthy citizens to-day instead of waiting for the end in institutions. </para>
        <para>I therefore hope to see during the life of this Parliament legislation enacted which
          will remove from all the fear which comes from long protracted illness, and ensure a
          decent standard of health in our community. We talk a great deal of, and pride ourselves
          upon, the standard of living which we have reached in Australia, but while our standard of
          health is what it is, we have no just cause to take pride in our standard of living. I
          therefore trust that the health measures, foreshadowed in the Speech under the heading of
          social services to be given to the community during the lifetime of the Parliament will
          take precedence in the Government&#39;s programme. </para>
        <para>That brings me to the subject of housing. Our present housing conditions are causing a
          great deal not only of discomfort but even of hardship to many members of the community.
          The Commonwealth Bank has now sufficient powers to enable it to help the workers to secure
          their own homes. By homes I do not mean flats or one-room tenements. I am thinking of
          homes with gardens to enable families to live in decency, instead of being brought up like
          rabbits. In any scheme of social service we must be certain that these reforms are
          introduced, and that our health and education systems and our housing facilities give to
          the worker, and indeed to every other member of the community, what he has a right to
          expect. I use the word &#34; worker &#34; in the broad sense. In Australia, after all, we
          are all workers. If we are not, we are drones and therefore not wanted. I speak for the
          vast majority of the people - 97 per cent of them at least - who are doing their utmost
          to build up this nation to what it should be. </para>
        <para>The rehabilitation of the men and women of the forces will be perhaps the most
          important problem which will face this Government, because if those who have offered their
          lives so valiantly do not return to an Australia which is better than the one they left,
          their sacrifice will have been in vain. I hope that in this policy of reconstruction we
          shall build on the very best of what is in the old system, and discard the rest. We must
          build up so that both men and women who have given their services so loyally during the
          last four years of bloodshed and carnage may realize, on their return, that they have not
          been let down by those of us whose walks of life lie in much pleasanter places than those
          through which they themselves have passed. </para>
        <para>I hope that, under the scheme which the Government has already enacted in the
          Australian Soldiers&#39; Repatriation Act, facilities will be given to the men and women
          of the forces to take a full share in the improved life of the whole community which we
          must make sure will follow the end of the war. I do not speak of preference to them,
          because preference to any section of the community implies a return to the old order of
          things, in which there was not sufficient for everybody, and only some people were
          privileged to work. If those conditions are allowed to return, they will be a negation of
          what we are fighting for. Under this new order there must be justice for all and not
          preference for any one section. </para>
        <para>The Speech does not in itself predict a very great deal for the future, nor does it
          make very rash and specious promises, because all of us realize that the great task which
          confronts this Parliament is the same task which confronts the people of Australia - that
          is, to bring this war to a just and honorable conclusion. To this task we must bend all
          our energies. The way will not be easy, because there is a great deal to be done before
          not only the Japanese, but also the Germans, are beaten back to the confines of their own
          lands. When this has been accomplished, we must proceed with the plans which have already
          been partly put into operation, so that we may give to every man, woman and child in this
          community the social security which is their birthright. We must also be very careful that
          those whom we select as the representatives of this nation at the peace conference shall
          be men and women of integrity - because I believe that women should play their part there
          - imbued not with a spirit of revenge but with a spirit of justice, resolved that we and
          other democracies shall receive evenhanded justice at the settlement. </para>
        <para>In this respect I should like finally to remark upon the importance of Australia,
          first as a very vital unit in the British Commonwealth of Nations, and secondly as a vast
          Pacific power. After this war, things can never be the same as they were before. We are a
          Pacific nation, and the problems of the Pacific are a special charge upon us in common with
          the peoples of New Zealand, the United States of America, Canada, China and other Pacific
          countries. We must make certain that what was done so treacherously nearly two years ago
          shall never be allowed to recur. The Government&#39;s policy in connexion with foreign
          affairs must take cognizance of the vital importance of Australia as a Pacific nation. </para>
        <para>The financial burdens which the Government of Australia will call upon the people to
          bear in the next few months will be heavy, by comparison with peace-time requirements, but
          the times are very difficult and must be faced with courage. I am certain that even when
          peace comes the present heavy burden of taxation will not be relaxed until we reach that
          happy stage in which every man and woman who is employable is in productive employment.
          But it will be ridiculous if a country which can expend &#163;1,500,000 a day for war
          cannot provide afterwards the money necessary to place its people on a decent economic
          footing for peace. I fear that for some time at least taxation will have to continue at a
          high level. The parrot-cry that money can no longer be found should not be raised, or, if
          it is, it will never again be heeded. When millions of pounds were needed to remove the
          burden of unemployment, and all its attendant evils, from the people of this community,
          the money could not be provided, yet it has now been raised for the purpose of defence.
          Its provision will be just as necessary for the defence of the rights of the people
          of this democracy when peace has been declared as it is during this time of war. I
          conclude by expressing the hope that the deliberations of this chamber during this
          session will be profitable to the Commonwealth of Australia, not only in its own right,
          but also as a unit of the British Empire. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>35</page.no>
            <time.stamp/>
            <name.id>JXE</name.id>
            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
            <party/>
            <role/>
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">NASH, Richard</name>
            <name role="display">Senator NASH</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I second the motion so ably moved by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator
              Tangney</inline> and to congratulate her upon the thoughtful speech that she has just
            delivered. I should also like to extend to her my felicitations on the historic aspect
            of her entry into this chamber. She is the first woman senator to be elected to this
            chamber. It is very- gratifying from a Western Australian viewpoint to realize that the
            people of that State are prepared to give women the same consideration in the selection
            of political representatives as has been extended to the male sex. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>It. will be recalled that the first woman ever elected to an Australian Parliament was
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mrs. Edith</inline> Cowan, who represented the electorate of
          West Perth in the Parliament of Western Australia. Subsequently Miss May Holman was
          elected to the Parliament of that State to represent the Forrest constituency.
          Unfortunately, Miss Holman was killed in a motor accident, but during her term of office
          in the Western Australian Parliament she did excellent work, always bearing in mind the
          particular problems of her sex. I am sure that, in addition to showing a keen interest in
          the welfare of women, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Tangney</inline> has the broadest
          possible outlook upon all matters affecting the people whom she has been sent here to
          represent. I endorse heartily all that she has said so ably in regard to the valiant
          service of the mcn and women of our fighting forces, and I join with the honorable senator
          also&#39; in paying tribute to the United Nations for the assistance which they have given
          to this country. I believe that had it not been for the prompt and generous help of the
          United States of America when Australia was in deadly peril of invasion, our position in
          this country to-day would not be nearly so favorable as that indicated by His Excellency
          in the Speech he delivered in opening this Parliament. It is pleasant, indeed, to note
          that despite the fact that only a short while ago this land was threatened with the
          greatest possible danger of invasion, the position in all theatres of war has improved
          vastly. That improvement reflects great credit upon the people of this country, and upon
          the Commonwealth Government which, in collaboration with the Governments of Great Britain,
          the United States of America, and other allied countries has done such good work that
          ultimate victory in this conflict is no longer in doubt. The knowledge that Australia is
          now free from the danger of invasion should be a great incentive to the people to give
          their fullest possible financial support to the Government despite the sacrifices that may
          be involved. </para>
        <para>I am pleased to note that the Government intends to carry out a comprehensive review
          of Australia&#39;s war effort with a view to rehabilitating certain classes&#39; of
          production which have been depressed unduly by the concentration upon war requirements. I
          trust that this review will mean that there will be an easing of wheat acreage
          restrictions and the limitations imposed upon the production of other staple commodities.
          The improved shipping position resulting from recent successes in the Mediterranean
          including the surrender of Italy should enable this country to adopt immediate measures to
          alleviate the food shortage in India, where we are told thousands of people are starving.
          In the light of such appalling conditions, Australia should produce the greatest quantity
          of wheat that is economically possible. I hope that the Government will give the fullest
          attention to the food front generally, and make available more rural labour so that this
          country may become one of the world&#39;s greatest granaries. In view of food shortage in
          many countries, it is essential that Australia should do its utmost to produce as much
          grain as possible, and also strive to become a predominant producer of wool and meat.
          Particularly in Western Australia, complaints are being voiced about the shortage of
          apples and pears. I believe that the Apple and Pear Board is doing excellent work,
          particularly as at present we have no export trade in those commodities, but the fact
          remains that in the orchards of Western Australia apples and pears are rotting on the
          ground, whilst many thousands of people in that State, and I presume throughout the
          Commonwealth, are unable to purchase these fruits at anything like reasonable prices, if
          at all. The Government should endeavour to improve that position by eliminating waste. </para>
        <para>I am pleased to note that the Government intends to proceed with plans for the
          rehabilitation of members of our fighting forces after the war, and also to safeguard the
          position of workers in war industries. &#39;Concrete plans for this work must he laid now.
          The men and women of our fighting forces and on the industrial front should be the
          Government&#39;s first consideration, in the post-war period. The greatest problem facing
          this Parliament will be post-war reconstruction, which cannot be handled merely by making
          speeches in this chamber. Clearly, unless adequate powers to control various aspects of
          post-war reconstruction are vested in the Commonwealth, the jurisdiction of this
          Parliament over many important activities will be limited seriously. Therefore, it is
          necessary for the people of the various States to reorientate their outlook in regard to
          granting additional powers to the Commonwealth Parliament, so that it may have all the
          authority necessary to handle post-war problems. Twelve months after the war terminates
          certain powers which at present are vested in the Commonwealth will cease to have legal
          effect, and in order to safeguard adequately the interests of members of our fighting
          forces, many of whom are being maimed or seriously wounded in the fight for democracy and
          for the safety of their country, steps must be taken at the earliest possible date to
          provide the Commonwealth Parliament with adequate authority. </para>
        <para>The magnificent victory of the Labour party at the recent general elections was due
          mainly to the fact that the policy of the Curtin Government was one of deeds and not of
          words. The policy of that Administration was an all-in war effort. It is pleasing to note
          that the Government is planning now for the development of this country when peace is
          secured. The people of Australia have indicated in no uncertain way to this Parliament
          that not only do they wish victory in this war, but also that they wish victory in the
          subsequent peace.&#39; To win the war and then to lose the peace would be disastrous. As
            <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Tangney</inline> has pointed out, it was said during
          the last war that after the cessation of hostilities Australia would be a land fit for
          heroes to live in, but we all know that such was not the case. We found instead the
          spectacle of unemployment, malnutrition and want. </para>
        <para>It is remarkable - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Tangney</inline> referred to the
          fact - that money has always been found in unlimited amounts for war purposes. Therefore,
          no adequate excuse could be found by members of this Parliament or anybody else for
          failure to make available the finance required for post-war reconstruction. I remember the
          last depression period, and have no doubt that it has not been entirely forgotten by
          honorable senators generally. At that time 29 per cent, of the people of this country were
          unemployed. That depression was caused by the manipulation of finance by private
          interests, and a recurrence of such conditions after this war should not be tolerated.
          Unemployment and undernourishment would be a national disgrace, because those evils cause
          national stagnation and seriously affect the whole community. What is worse, Australia
          would have a C3 classification. Post-war problems, being national in character, must be
          dealt with on a national basis. That is why I refer to the necessity for increased
          Commonwealth powers in the post-war period. After the war private enterprise will not be
          able to absorb the whole of the unemployed. During the last depression it was proved
          conclusively that the governments of the States were unable to deal adequately with the
          problem with which they were then faced. To make palliatives available to people who are
          starving and to children who are undernourished would be of no use. Either the States must
          agree to become more generously disposed towards the granting of adequate powers to the
          Commonwealth Parliament, or the people must be asked to determine the matter as soon as
          possible. </para>
        <para>Another important requirement for the post-war period is the right of the Commonwealth
          Bank to create national credit for national purposes. I hope that the Government will
          introduce legislation as soon as possible to restore to that bank its original charter. To
          the best of my knowledge the control of the bank has, as the result of political action,
          been placed in the hands of a board composed of private citizens. Instead of the bank
          being a people&#39;s bank, as originally intended, it is now merely a bankers&#39; bank.
          It is, in effect, a central reserve bank for ensuring the stability of private financial
          institutions. The right to create credit should be vested only in a Commonwealth
          authority, and should not be the prerogative of private financial institutions. One of the
          anomalies with regard to finance which has greatly impressed me is the fact that, before
          the war, we were told that from the point of view of orthodox finance Germany and Japan
          were bankrupt countries. Yet each of those countries evolved an internal economy which
          produced a war machine that has taxed to the utmost capacity the ingenuity of the United
          Nations and has caused the loss of the lives of thousands of Australian citizens. If
          orthodox finance results in a continuance of unemployment and starvation among the people
          of this country, I shall have none of it. Australia has been called upon to make many
          sacrifices in the prosecution of the war, and the people generally, particularly the
          working classes, have responded very well indeed to their country&#39;s call; but further
          sacrifices will be necessary on the part of every citizen. All will have to give the
          utmost possible financial assistance. I am afraid that the improved outlook which is
          indicated in the Speech of His Excellency the Governor-General may be seized upon by
          certain sections of the community as an excuse for slackening their efforts in support of
          the prosecution of the war. Therefore, I hope that the next Liberty Loan, which will be
          placed on the market shortly, will be oversubscribed. In the interests of this country and
          of allied strategy the success of the loan is essential. </para>
        <para>The recent general elections have exploded the necessity for what has been termed a
          national government. All that the people of Australia require is sound government, and I
          firmly believe that the Curtin Government will continue to make that kind of
          administration available in the interests of the country. Reference was made in the Speech
          of the GovernorGeneral to contemplated provision for certain social services. I regret
          that the </para>
        <para class="block">Speech was not more explicit in that regard. The Government is to be
          commended upon what it has already accomplished in that respect. I refer to the increase
          of the invalid and old-age pension, the increased consideration shown to blind pensioners,
          the more humane consideration of invalid pensioners, and more favorable maternity
          allowances, the recipients of which have been relieved of the means test. I hope that the
          Government will bring down legislation for unemployment benefits and for the
          nationalization of health and medical services. </para>
        <para>I congratulate the Minister for Health and Social Services <inline font-weight="bold"
            >(Senator Fraser)</inline> upon his appointment to the office which he now holds. I have
          no doubt that he will give excellent service. He has proved his ability by the way in
          which he discharged his duties in connexion with his previous portfolio, and, knowing him
          as I do, and his long association with the working classes, I am sure that his ministerial
          service will be of real value to the people. </para>
        <para>I believe that education should be considered from a national point of view. I also
          hold that ability to learn should be the governing factor in the granting of facilities
          for higher education. Many thousands of growing children are allowed the benefits of
          higher education because of the ability of their parents to meet the expense it involves.
          This brings about the cultivation of what has been called the &#34;old school tie &#34;
          spirit, but, in the interests of the Commonwealth, higher education should be available to
          all. </para>
        <para>I congratulate the Prime Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Curtin)</inline>
          upon his personal victory in the contest for representation of the Division of Fremantle
          in this Parliament. I hope that the result will have the effect of stopping at least one
          political adventurer who appeals to the people from selfish motives. The Prime Minister
          has proved himself to be one of the greatest leaders this country has ever had. It is
          strange that political opponents endeavoured during the recent election campaign to
          besmirch his good name. I saw a fairly large advertisement in the <inline
            font-style="italic">West Australian</inline> in which the Prime Minister was described
          as an opportunist. That such a man as the present Prime Minister of this country should
          be&#39; labelled an opportunist shows the lengths to which some political partisans will
          go in order to defeat an opponent. It is impossible for me to express my disgust at such
          tactics. Political propaganda of that kind is no credit to those responsible for it, and I
          suggest that the appropriate Minister should examine this matter with a view to preventing
          a repetition of such statements in the future. During the election campaign radio
          broadcasts, under the title, &#34; The Voice of Freedom &#34;, disseminated statements
          which, although extremely clever propaganda, were in the main a distortion of facts. I
          suggest that the Broadcasting Committee should call for the script of those broadcasts,
          with a view to action being taken to prevent propaganda of that kind from being broadcast
          in connexion with future elections. </para>
        <para>Until the present war began, Western Australia was, for the most part, a primary
          producing State, but as the war has proceeded numbers of secondary industries have been
          established there. Among them is the production of flax. As I believe that the flax
          industry has great possibilities in this country I suggest that proper safeguards be
          provided to ensure its continuance after the war. Another industry which has been
          established in Western Australia since the war began is that of ship-building. Whilst it
          is true that at present Western Australia is unable to construct certain classes of ships
          which are now being built in other Australian States, the artisans and workmen generally
          engaged in ship-building in the western State are equal to those elsewhere in Australia.
          Other previously unknown Western Australian industries are aircraft production and the
          canning and dehydration of fruit and vegetables. It would be desirable if those new
          industries also could be continued after the war. </para>
        <para>Western Australia, in common with the other States, suffers from a great shortage of
          houses, &#34;and I hope that, consistent with meeting military requirements, the
          Government will be able to release sufficient building materials, as well as operatives,
          to alleviate this pressing social and economic problem; it is a matter which requires
          immediate attention. Large numbers of young people are getting married, but homes are not
          available for them. The result is that there is danger of slum conditions, not only in the
          poorer residential districts but also in private houses and other places of accommodation
          in more favoured localities. The provision of homes for the people is a national
          responsibility. I suggest that homes should be made available on the basis of a weekly
          rental equal to one day&#39;s pay. Western Australia is fortunate, in having already
          established its Workers Homes Board, and I suggest that in the provision of homes that
          body should work in cooperation with the appropriate Commonwealth authority. The Social
          Security Committee has done valuable work in this connexion, and I hope that at least some
          of its recommendations will be given effect by the Government. There is ground for the
          hope that, under the present Minister for Health and Social Services, legislation which
          will be of great benefit to the people generally will be introduced. </para>
        <para>In carrying out their parliamentary duties, honorable senators and members of the
          House of Representatives representing Western Australia have to travel by the
          trans-Australian railway. On my way to Canberra for the parliamentary session I was struck
          by the type of residence provided for -railway workers along that line. These workers are
          in a somewhat different category from workers generally elsewhere in Australia in that
          they live in remote and lonely spots, in many instances in barren country where there is
          not a tree within many miles of their homes. None of the usual amenities exist, and the
          outlook is certainly uninviting. I suggest that the appropriate Minister should examine
          the accommodation provided- for these workers; to me the homes in which they have to live
          appeared to be hovels. </para>
        <para>Reference has been made to the incidence of malaria among our troops, particularly in
          New Guinea. Some time ago an Australian political leader advocated that no Australian
          soldier who had had more than two attacks of malaria should be sent back to New Guinea. In
          my opinion, that was the wrong way to deal with this problem. The proper thing to do is to
          deal with the cause of malaria. I bring this matter forward to-day because I have reason
          to believe that army officers in charge of hygiene are unable to enforce proper preventive
          measures because their rank is not sufficiently high to guarantee that their views shall
          be given effect. I understand that the position is so serious that casualties among the
          troops due to malaria exceed those resulting from combat with the enemy. I conclude by
          expressing the hope that the war will soon be brought to a victorious conclusion. </para>
        <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McLeay)</inline> adjourned.
        </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>39</page.no>
        <type>special adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Keane)</inline> agreed to- </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the Senate, at its rising, adjourn to Wednesday next, at 3 p.m. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>39</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Acquisition of Property</title>
          <page.no>39</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Keane)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
        </quote>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>39</page.no>
              <time.stamp/>
              <name.id>K2F</name.id>
              <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
              <party/>
              <role/>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BRAND, Charles</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BRAND</name>
            </talker>
            <para>.- On behalf of several property owners whose blocks of land in North Essendon,
              Victoria, are about to be acquired compulsorily by the Government, I draw attention to
              the unjust and ridiculously low prices offered. One owner paid &#163;280 for two
              blocks twenty years ago, yet after paying rates and taxes since then he was offered
              only &#163;61. Another who bought three blocks for &#163;270 has been offered
              &#163;75.Still another owner, after paying rates and taxes for 25 years on a block for
              which he paid &#163;100 has been offered &#163;15. In three other instances the owners
              are members of the Australian Imperial Force. They have not completed the purchase of
              their holdings, but the amount offered by the Government is not sufficient to cover
              the outstanding liability. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>The Constitution provides, and the High Court has ruled, that just compensation
            should be paid for property so acquired. Are these prices just compensation? Certainly
            not. The Government should set an example of fair dealing in these transactions, more
            especially when the owners are serving overseas. One is a prisoner of war in Malaya. An
            offer which is less than fair compensation is pure confiscation. It is not as though the
            local valuation of these blocks were on the decline; rather is the reverse true.
            Situated in the vicinity of the Essendon aerodrome, the owners could expect a normal
            increase of the value of their properties afterthe war when civil aviation will
            undoubtedly be further developed. I ask the appropriate Minister to look into this
            matter and to see that justice is done to these owners, who are not wealthy citizens,
            but persons who have been thrifty on small earnings. They cannot afford the expense of
            taking their case to the High Court. </para>
          <para class="block">Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PAPERS</title>
        <page.no>39</page.no>
        <type>papers</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The following papers were pre sented : - </para>
      <para>Air Force Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 198. </para>
      <para>Arbitration (Public Service) Act - Determinations by the Arbitrator, &#38;c. - </para>
      <para>No. 18 of 1943 - Amalgamated Postal Workers&#39; Union of Australia. </para>
      <para>No. 19 of 1943 - Amalgamated Postal Workers&#39; Union of Australia; Postal
        Telecommunication Technicians&#39; Association (Australia) ; and Federated Public Service
        Assistants&#39; Association of Australia. </para>
      <para>No. 20 of 1943 - Commonwealth Telegraph Traffic and Supervisory Officers&#39;
        Association. </para>
      <para>No. 21 of 1943 - Commonwealth Public Service Artisans&#39; Association. </para>
      <para>No. 22 of 1943 - Amalgamated Postal Workers&#39; Union of Australia. </para>
      <para>No. 23 of 1943 - Commonwealth Telephone Officers&#39; Association. </para>
      <para>No. 24 of 1943- Commonwealth Public Service Clerical Association and others. </para>
      <para>No. 25 of 1943 - Commonwealth Public Service Artisans&#39; Association. </para>
      <para>No. 20 of 1943 - Commonwealth Public Service Clerical Association and others. </para>
      <para>No. 27 of 1943- Blacksmiths&#39; Society of Australasia; and Electrical Trades Union of
        Australia. </para>
      <para>Beer Excise Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 228. </para>
      <para>Commonwealth Electoral (War-time) Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 175. </para>
      <para class="block">Contract Immigrants Act - Return for 1942. </para>
      <para class="block">Control of Naval Waters Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 216.
        Customs Act -Proclamations prohibiting the exportation (except under certain conditions) of
        - </para>
      <para>Macaroni; Spaghetti; Vermicelli (dated 1st September, 1943). </para>
      <para>Margarine; Neatsfoot oil (dated 27th July, 1943). </para>
      <para>Quartz crystals (dated 29th June, 1943). </para>
      <para>Ti-tree oil (dated 1st September, 1943). </para>
      <para class="block">Customs Act and Commerce (Trade Descriptions) Act - Regulations -
        Statutory Rules 1943, No. 192. </para>
      <para>Dairying Industry Assistance Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 171. </para>
      <para>Defence Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, Nos. 174, 199, 200, 218, 219, 227. </para>
      <para>Defence Act and Naval Defence Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 217. </para>
      <para class="block">Immigration Act - Return for 1942. </para>
      <para class="block">Lands Acquisition Act - </para>
      <para>Land acquired for Commonwealth purposes - </para>
      <para>Alexandria, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Amberley, Queensland. </para>
      <para>Broadmeadows, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Brooklyn, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Bullsbrook (Pearce), Western Australia. </para>
      <para>Charleville, Queensland. </para>
      <para>Cootamundra, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Crystal Brook, South Australia. </para>
      <para>Dandenong, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Dubbo, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Eagle Farm, Queensland. </para>
      <para>East Oakleigh, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Forrest, Western Australia. </para>
      <para>Gladstone, South Australia. </para>
      <para>Goulburn, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Kilburn, South Australia. </para>
      <para>Kingaroy, Queensland. </para>
      <para>Lake Boga, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Largs, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Lidcombe, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Lismore, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Lithgow, New South Wales (2). </para>
      <para>Mudgee, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Murray Bridge, South Australia. </para>
      <para>Newport, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Parafield, South Australia. </para>
      <para>Portland, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Port Melbourne, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Port Pirie, South Australia (2). </para>
      <para>Putney, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Redgate, Tasmania. </para>
      <para>Rosebud, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Salisbury, South Australia (2). </para>
      <para>Singleton, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Tamworth, New South Wales. </para>
      <para>Townsville, Queensland. </para>
      <para>Violet Town, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Warracknabeal, Victoria. </para>
      <para>Yarrawonga, Victoria. </para>
      <para class="block">Motor Vehicle Engine Bounty Act - Return for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">National Debt Sinking Fund Act - National Debt Commission - Twentieth
        Annual Report, for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para>National Security Act - </para>
      <para>National Security (Agricultural Aids) Regulations - Order - Nicotine sulphate
        (Restriction of Sale). </para>
      <para>National Security (Allied Forces) Regulations - Orders - </para>
      <para>Allied Forces (Application of the Defence (Visiting Forces) Act 1939) (No. 5). </para>
      <para>Allied Forces (Civilian Witnesses). </para>
      <para>Allied Forces (Penal Arrangements) (No. 4). </para>
      <para>Allied Forces (Relations with Civil Authorities) (No. 2). </para>
      <para>National Security (Civil Defence Workers&#39; Compensation) Regulations - Order by State
        Premier, Victoria (dated 8th July, 1943). </para>
      <para>National Security (Egg Industry) Regulations - Orders - Egg Industry (Nos. 5-7). </para>
      <para>National Security (Food Control) Regulations - Order - Cream (Restriction of use). </para>
      <para>National Security (General) Regulations - </para>
      <para>Orders - </para>
      <para>Cocoa, chocolate and confectionery. Control of - </para>
      <para>Automotive spare parts (No. 2). </para>
      <para>Building materials. </para>
      <para>Edible oils and edible oil constituents. </para>
      <para>Electric dry battery manufacture (No. 2). </para>
      <para>Electronic vibrators. </para>
      <para>Essential materials (No. 4). </para>
      <para>Grapefruit (Western Australia). </para>
      <para>Knitted goods ( No. 2 ) . </para>
      <para>Leather (No. 3). </para>
      <para>Radio service (Nos. 1-2). </para>
      <para>Trailer manufacture (No. 2). </para>
      <para>Woven woollen materials (civil needs) (No. 2). </para>
      <para>Beating and cooking appliances (control of manufacture). </para>
      <para>Heating and cooking appliances (retail sales) (No. 2). </para>
      <para>Ice industry (New South Wales). </para>
      <para>Prohibited places (2). </para>
      <para>Prohibiting work on land (2). </para>
      <para>Prohibition of non-essential production (No. 13). </para>
      <para>Returns relating to artificial silk yarn. </para>
      <para>Taking possession of land, &#38;c. (731). </para>
      <para>Telephonic communications control. Use of land (51). </para>
      <para>Vegetable seeds (No. 3). </para>
      <para>Order by Chief Warden - Victoria (dated21st June, 1943). </para>
      <para>Orders by State Premiers - Queensland (dated 30th June, 1943), Victoria (Nos. 48-50),
        Western Australia (2 - dated 5th July, 1943). </para>
      <para>National Security (General) Regulations and National Security (Supplementary)
        Regulations - Order by State Premier - New South Wales (No. 39).&#39; </para>
      <para>National Security (Industrial Property) Regulations - Orders - Inventions and Designs
        (248). </para>
      <para>National Security (Land Transport) Regulations - Order - South Australia (No. 11). </para>
      <para>National Security (Man Power) Regulations - Orders - </para>
      <para>Man Power (Local Appeal Boards). </para>
      <para>Pharmaceutical Chemists ( Supplementary Information). </para>
      <para>Protected undertakings (221) </para>
      <para>Registration of - </para>
      <para>Chemists. </para>
      <para>Dentists. </para>
      <para>Pharmaceutical Chemists. </para>
      <para>Psychologists. </para>
      <para>Regulation of engagement of em ployees - Exemptions. </para>
      <para>National Security (Maritime Industry) Regulations - Orders - Nos. 38-40. </para>
      <para>National. Security (Meat Industry Control ) Regulations- Orders - </para>
      <para>Meat- Nos.6, 8-14, 16-28. </para>
      <para>Meat (Returns) Nos. 1-6. </para>
      <para>Stock- Nos. 1-5, 7-10. </para>
      <para>National Security (Munitions) Regula tions - Order - Agricultural machinery and plant
        for processing food products. National Security (Prices) Regulations - Declarations Nos.
        117-125. </para>
      <para>Orders- -Nos. 1054-1209. </para>
      <para>National Security (Stevedoring Industry) Regulations - Orders - Nos. 15a, 20-25.
        National Security (Supplementary) Regulations - </para>
      <para>Balance-sheets of the Commonwealth Bank of Australia, Commonwealth Savings Bank of
        Australia and Note Issue Department, as at 30th June, 1943, together with
        AuditorGeneral&#39;s Reports thereon. </para>
      <para>Statement of Australian Banking Statistics for the five quarters ended 30th June, 1943. </para>
      <para>Orders by State Premiers - New South Wales Nos. 37-38, Queensland (2- dated 7th July,
        1943, and 13th August, 1943), South Australia (No. 4 of 1943). </para>
      <para>National Security (War Damage to Property ) Regulations - Orders - Public Authorities
        (3). </para>
      <para>Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, Nos. 165, 166, 107, 168, 169, 170, 172, 173, 177,
        178, 179, 180, 181, 182, 183, 184, 185, 186, 187, 188, 189, 190, 193, 194, 195, 196, 197,
        203, 204, 205, 206, 207, 208, 209, 210, 211, 212, 213, 214, 220, 221, 222, 223, 224, 225,
        226, 229, 230, 231. </para>
      <para class="block">Naval Defence Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, Nos. 201, 202. </para>
      <para class="block">Northern Territory Acceptance Act and Northern Territory (Administration)
        Act - Regulations - </para>
      <para>No. 2 of 1943- (Motor Vehicles Ordinance ) . </para>
      <para>No. 3 of 1943 - (Marine Ordinance). </para>
      <para>Northern Territory Representation Act and Commonwealth Electoral Act - Regulations -
        Statutory Rules 1943, No. 176. </para>
      <para class="block">Papua and New Guinea Bounties Act - </para>
      <para>Return for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Post and Telegraph . Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No. 215. </para>
      <para>Raw Cotton Bounty Act - Return for 1942. </para>
      <para>Sales Tax (Exemptions and Classifications) Act - Regulations - Statutory Rules 1943, No.
        191. </para>
      <para class="block">Seat of Government Acceptance Act and Seat of Government (Administration)
        Act - </para>
      <para class="block">Canberra University College Ordinance - Report of the Council of the
        Canberra University College for the year 1942. </para>
      <para class="block">Seat of Government (Administration) Act. - Statement of Receipts and
        Expenditure of the Australian Capital Territory for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Ship Bounty Act- Return for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Sulphur Bounty Acts - Return for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Supply and Development Acts- Regulations -Statutory Rules 1943, No. 164. </para>
      <para class="block">Tractor Bounty Acts - Return for year 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Wine Export Bounty Act - Return foryear 1942-43. </para>
      <para class="block">Wire Netting Bounty Act- Return for year 1942-43. </para>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>41</page.no>
        <time.stamp>12:45:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para class="block">Senate adjourned at 12.45 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>
