<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <session.header>
        <date>1950-02-23</date>
        <parliament.no>19</parliament.no>
        <session.no>1</session.no>
        <period.no>1</period.no>
        <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
        <page.no>32</page.no>
        <proof>0</proof>
    </session.header>
    <chamber.xscript>
        <para class="block">Senate. </para>
        <business.start>
            <day.start>1950-02-23</day.start>
            <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon. Gordon Brown)</inline> took the chair at 3 p.m., -and read  prayers </para>
        </business.start>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>QUESTIONS</title>
                <page.no>32</page.no>
                <type>Questions</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SHIPPING</title>
                    <page.no>32</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYA</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'BYRNE, Justin</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'BYRNE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In view of the conflicting statements that are. being circulated about a reported proposal to substitute for the four " D " class ships now plying to Tasmanian ports, " River " -class vessels of the same gross tonnage - an alteration which would be of distinct disadvantage to Tasmanian merchants and primary producers - will the Minister for Shipping and Fuel inform the Senate of the Government's policy on this matter of vital importance to Tasmania ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Government is doing everything possible to provide adequate shipping for the Tasmanian service. The report that appeared in the press was not correct. I have instructed ' my department to issue a statement setting out the facts to-day. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KVB</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MORROW, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MORROW</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister say whether it is intended to remove a number of D class vessels from the service between the mainland States and Tasmania? If so, how many ships will be removed, and what is their class? Will those vessels be replaced by ships of greater tonnage ? If so, does the Minister realize that such an arrangement will cause much inconvenience to traders and to the people of Tasmania, as the new vessels will have to wait longer periods when loading and unloading. cargoes, and, in some instances, may possibly have to sail full cargoes? In these circumstances, will the Minister review the decision with the object of leaving the D class vessels on their present routes ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- This matter has been brought to my notice. I have been informed by ' the Director of Shipping that although certain vessels have been withdrawn for repairs they have been replaced by other ships and the tonnage operating at present is greater than it was before the three ships were withdrawn for repairs. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PETROL</title>
                    <page.no>32</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0Z</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">AYLETT, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator AYLETT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Since the general election some motorists in Tasmania have at times encountered grave difficulties in obtaining petrol. The reply given to them by bowser proprietors has been, "I am sorry, but I have only enough petrol for regular customers ", or "I can let you have .only one or two gallons ". Can the Minister for Shipping and Fuel inform the Senate when the Government will fulfil its already broken election promise to provide sufficient petrol to meet the requirements of the people of Tasmania? If the Government cannot obtain sufficient petrol to enable it to fulfil that promise, will it endeavour to obtain some of the large stocks of petrol that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline> Lonegan,  M.L.C., has stated is being hoarded by farmers, and distribute it so that the needs of the public may he mct? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>32</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The Chifley Government allowed our reserve stocks of  petrol to reach a low level. Within a month of this Government taking office, it was able to increase the stocks to such a degree that they were adequate to provide a defence reserve and to meet all other requirements. If there be a slight shortage of petrol in Tasmania, it may be due to the fact that the previous Government, for some reason, placed a restriction upon the quantity of petrol that could be withdrawn from bond. That action caused some embarrassment. When I assumed the office of Minister for Shipping and Fuel, I removed that restriction. I assure the honorable senator that if petrol is not available at the bowser to which he goes, I shall see that, the matter is given immediate attention. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KKR</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FRASER, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator FRASER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister inform the Senate whether reserve stocks of petrol for defence purposes have been depleted in order to make supplies available to the public so as to enable the Government to honour the promise that its candidates made to the people at the last general election 1 </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answer is " No ". </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JQY</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COURTICE, Benjamin</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COURTICE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister say whether any ceiling is being  trained in respect of the quantity of petrol now being imported from dollar sources ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Yes. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0Z</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">AYLETT, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator AYLETT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister inform the Senate of the quantity of petrol that was allocated to Tasmania prior to the lifting of petrol rationing and the quantity of -petrol that is now being supplied to that State. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall look into the matter that the honorable senator has raised, and, if it will cheer him, I may add that I am quite willing to do so. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KKR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FRASER, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator FRASER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister say whether any petrol has been withdrawn from the defence stocks of petrol that were built up by the previous Government, and, if so, to what extent the defence stocks have been depleted ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I inform the honorable senator that we have now more stocks of petrol than the previous Government ever had, and that defence requirements are adequately provided for. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KKR</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FRASER, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator FRASER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister say what stocks of petrol are now held in this country for defence purposes? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>UAP; LP from 1944</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I understand that the previous Government set the figure at 50,000,000 gallons; I do not think that that figure has been altered. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYY</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'FLAHERTY, Sidney</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'FLAHERTY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In "view of the Minister's statement that there is now more oil fuel in Australia than formerly, will he discuss with the refining companies the possibility of providing a better grade of petrol for Australian motorists, and withdrawing from the market the fuel that is sold to-day as petrol. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection><continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall bring that matter to the notice of my technical advisers and inform the honorable senator of the result. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue></answer>
                
                
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JXC</name.id>
                            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MURRAY, Reginald</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MURRAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- As petroleum products are now available to Australia from Dutch New Guinea, I ask the Minister whether the Government will consider building in this country sufficient tankers to ensure that we shall have adequate supplies of these products for defence and developmental purposes. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>33</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I think that the cost of building tankers in this country would be prohibitive, but I shall look into the matter and let the honorable senator know what the possibilities are. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>33</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KKR</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">FRASER, James</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator FRASER</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- In view of the Minister's assurance that there. are ample supplies of oil fuel in this country, will he ensure that adequate supplies will be available for emergency electricity generating plants required in Western Australia owing to the power station breakdown. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>33</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- Nothing would give me greater pleasure than to ensure that the outlying State of Western Australia shall have an adequate supply of petrol. If the honorable senator can show me that supplies are being denied to any consumer at present, I shall give the matter my personal attention. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>33</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0W</name.id>
                            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ASHLEY, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ASHLEY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister make available to the Senate details of the quantity of petrol held in reserve stocks for defence purposes as at the 10th December last and also the quantity held in reserve as at 10th February last ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>34</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I am prepared to supply the honorable senator with the information for which he has asked, but I do not propose to make that information public at this stage. However, I assure the Senate that the quantity of petrol held in reserve for defence purposes by theprevious Government is still held in reserve for those purposes. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </speech>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE</title>
                    <page.no>34</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0N</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARNOLD, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ARNOLD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister representing the Minister for Air request his colleague to pay an early visit, to the Royal Australian Air Force aerodrome at Williamtown, in New South Wales, with a view to giving the personnel there some relief from the extraordinarily dilapidated accommodation in which they are living at present? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall bring the matter to the notice of the Minister for Air as soon as possible. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>REPATRIATION</title>
                    <page.no>34</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZ8</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FINLAY, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator FINLAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Will the Minister for Repatriation inform the Senate whether it is the intention of the Government to refer the question of exservicernen's pensions to an all-party committee for consideration and review? If that be the intention of the Government, when is the committee likely to be established? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JQP</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>CP</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COOPER, Walter</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator COOPER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is not the intention of the Government to refer the question of ex-servicemen's pensions and repatriation allowances to an all-party committee consisting of parliamentarians who are ex-servicemen. When the present Government assumed office, it established a Cabinet sub-committee, the six members of which are all ex-servicemen, to consider the important matter of the pensions and allowances that are payable under the Australian Soldiers' Repatriation Act. It is hoped that the subcommittee will arrive at decisions in sufficient time to enable appropriate- legislation to be brought before the Parliament during the present session. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>LISTENERS' GUIDE TO CANBERRA</title>
                    <page.no>34</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYY</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'FLAHERTY, Sidney</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'FLAHERTY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the Leader of the Government whether, in view of the fact that there has been a tremendous increase in the numerical strength of the Parliament, the Government will consider issuing a listeners' guide for the benefit of the general public? If the Government does not intend to do that, will he raise the matter with the publishers of the Melbourne <inline font-style="italic">Herald,</inline> who, on a previous occasion, published a listeners' guide? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZI</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'SULLIVAN, Neil</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'SULLIVAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall bepleased to discuss this matter with the honorable senator and afford him an opportunity to elaborate it in detail. If he can advance any suggestion to assist the functioning of the Parliament or thewelfare of the people of this country I shall be most happy to co-operate with him. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>COST OF LIVING</title>
                    <page.no>34</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JXE</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">NASH, Richard</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator NASH</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I preface my question to the Minister representing the Prime Minister by pointing out that theWestern Australian Government Statistician has reported that the retail pricesof food increased by more than 10 per cent, in the five main towns of that State last year. Compared with the prices obtaining in September, 1939, pricestoday are from 45.5 per cent, to 62.78 per cent, higher. As increased prices in Western Australia are indicative of the position obtaining generally throughout Australia, will the Minister inform the Senate what action the Government proposes to take to remedy this state of affairs? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZI</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'SULLIVAN, Neil</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'SULLIVAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is sadly true that during the regime of the previous Government the cost of living rosevery considerably in this country. I trust, however, that during the term of the present Government conditions will be ameliorated considerably, and that the cost of living will be reduced. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PUBLIC SERVICE</title>
                    <page.no>34</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>34</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K5X</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SHEEHAN, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SHEEHAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I preface my question to the Attorney-General by stating that prior to the dissolution of the last Parliament certain aspects of the re-employment in the Public Service of superannuated employees during the war period were under consideration. In a number of instances the amount of pension payable to them was reduced during such re-employment. Will the Minister undertake to re-constitute the committee that was appointed to examine the claims of such superannuated public servants? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K6Z</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SPICER, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SPICER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I know nothing of the matter to which the honorable senator lias referred. However, I shall cause inquiries to be made and inform him of the result in the course of a few days. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>TAXATION</title>
                    <page.no>35</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7Y</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">TANGNEY, Dorothy</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator TANGNEY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the Minister representing the Treasurer whether the Treasurer will consider the removal of sales tax from refrigerators to be used for domestic purposes in the far northern parts of Australia where they are so urgently necessary to make life bearable in the tropical conditions of those areas? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7A</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">SPOONER, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator SPOONER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall refer the' honorable senator's question to the Treasurer and shall let her have a reply as soon as possible. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>PRIMARY PRODUCTS</title>
                    <page.no>35</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0Z</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">AYLETT, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator AYLETT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture whether, in view of the high cost of shipping freights on primary products that are sent intra-state he can give the Senate any assurance that action will be taken by the Government at an early date to implement the promise given by Liberal candidates during the election campaign to introduce a system of guaranteed prices for primary products? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I shall refer that matter to the Minister for Commerce and Agriculture. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SUBSIDIES</title>
                    <page.no>35</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0C</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARMSTRONG, John Ignatius</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ARMSTRONG</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- In view of the public statements of Ministers and members of the  present  Government of their disapproval of the action of the Chifley Government in removing price subsidies following the result of the prices referendum, will the Minister for Trade and Customs give consideration to the re-introduction of subsidies as a brake on the rapidly rising cost of living? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZI</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'SULLIVAN, Neil</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'SULLIVAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The honorable senator, as a former Minister, knows as well as I do that it is not the practice to deal with matters of government policy in answers to questions. However, he and the  people  of Australia may rest assured that the Government will make every provision to prevent the cost of living from rising. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>SUGAR</title>
                    <page.no>35</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JYA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'BYRNE, Justin</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'BYRNE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Is the Minister for Trade and Customs aware that it was necessary during last month to impose severe .rationing of sugar in Tasmania, particularly in the Launceston district, because of irregular shipping services? At times from three to five weeks elapsed between shipments. Will he inform the Senate of the views of the Government as to the possibility of establishing a temporary sugar storage depot and a refinery capable of refining sufficient sugar to meet the growing needs of Tasmanian consumers and fruit preservers ? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZI</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">O'SULLIVAN, Neil</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator O'SULLIVAN</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The fact that a shortage of sugar has existed in Tasmania has not formally been brought to my notice. I assure the honorable senator that any representations he is prepared to make with a view to eliminating, or preventing, shortages of any commodity in respect of which the Government can be of assistance to the interests concerned will be given a sympathetic hearing. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>CHINA</title>
                    <page.no>35</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KBC</name.id>
                            <electorate></electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role></role>
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">WILLESEE, Don</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator WILLESEE</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister representing the Minister for External Affairs say whether the Government proposes to recognize Communist China? If so, why is an announcement being delayed? le the delay due to the criticism that was levelled at the Attlee Government when it recognized Communist China, realizing that the announcement would affect the elections in Great Britain- </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>35</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K6Z</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">SPICER, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Spicer</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I rise to order. I submit, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. President,</inline> that the honorable senator is not entitled to introduce comments into a question. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                    <interjection>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>35</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K0W</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">ASHLEY, William</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator Ashley</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- He is a new member. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </interjection>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>35</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>10000</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Honorable senators should refrain from comment when seeking information. As the Leader of the Opposition has pointed out, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Willesee</inline> is new to this chamber, and, of course, we all welcome him. However, I remind all new senators that they should be as brief as possible, and should not express opinions when asking questions. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>36</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>KBC</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party />
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">WILLESEE, Don</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator WILLESEE</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- I ask the Minister again whether the Government intends to recognize Communist China, and, if so, why the announcement has been delayed? </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                    <continue>
                        <talk.start>
                            <talker>
                                <page.no>36</page.no>
                                <time.stamp />
                                <name.id>K6Z</name.id>
                                <electorate />
                                <party>LP</party>
                                <role />
                                <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                                <name role="metadata">SPICER, John</name>
                                <name role="display">Senator SPICER</name>
                            </talker>
                            <para>- If the honorable senator will place his question on the notice-paper I shall obtain an answer for him from the Minister for External Affairs. </para>
                        </talk.start>
                    </continue>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>COAL</title>
                    <page.no>36</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>36</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0N</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ARNOLD, James</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator ARNOLD</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Can the Minister for Shipping and Fuel say what coal stocks are held in Australia at present? Has there been a substantial loss of production on the coal-fields this week? What steps does the Government propose to take to increase coal stocks in Australia? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>36</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KUA</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>LP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MCLEAY, George</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator McLEAY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I have received a comprehensive report from the Joint Coal Board. The position is not satisfactory, and consideration is being given to measures to improve stocks. Perhaps the first and most appropriate step would be to get rid of the rolling strikers. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>DISPUTED RETURNS AND QUALIFICATIONS COMMITTEE</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>36</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- Pursuant to Standing Order 38, I hereby appoint the following senators to be the Committee of Disputed Returns and Qualifications: <inline font-weight="bold">-Senator W.</inline> E. Aylett, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator D.</inline> C. Hannaford, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator J.</inline> Harris, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator W.</inline> Morrow, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator E.</inline> S. R. Piesse, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator A.</inline> R. Robertson and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator R.</inline> H. Wordsworth. </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>DAYS AND HOURS OF MEETING</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the days of meeting of the Senate, unless otherwise ordered, be Wednesday, Thursday and Friday of each week; and that the hour of meeting, unless otherwise ordered, be 3 p.m. on Wednesday and Thursday, and 10.30 a.m. on Friday. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERNMENT AND GENERAL BUSINESS</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Precedence</para>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">-Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, on all sitting days of the Senate during the present session, unless otherwise ordered, Government business shall take precedence of all other business on the notice-paper, except questions and formal motions, and except that general business take precedence of Government business on Thursdays, after 8 p.m.; and that, unless otherwise ordered, general orders of the day take precedence of general notices of motion on alternate Thursdays. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>FRIDAY ADJOURNMENT AT 3.45 P.M</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, (luring the present session, unless otherwise ordered, at 3.45 p.m., on Fridays the  President  shall put the Question - That the Senate do now adjourn, which Question shall not .be open to debate; if the Senate be in Committee at that hour, the  Chairman  shall in like manner put the Question - That he do leave the Chair and report to the Senate; and upon such report being made the  President  shall forthwith put the Question - That the Senate do now adjourn, which Question shall not be open to debate: Provided that if the Senate or the Committee be in division at the time named, the  President  or the  Chairman  shall not .put the Question referred to until the result of such division has been declared; and if the business under discussion shall not have been disposed of at such adjournment it shall appear on the business-paper for the next silting day. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SUSPENSION OF- SITTINGS</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, during the present session, unless otherwise ordered, the sittings of the Senate, or of a Committee of the Whole Senate, be suspended from 12.45 p.m. to 2.15 p.m., and from C p.m. to 8 p.m. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PUBLIC WORKS COMMITTEE</title>
                <page.no>36</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, in accordance with the provisions of the Commonwealth Public Works Committee Act 1913-1947, the following senators be appointed members of the Parliamentary Standing Committee on Public Works: - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Byrne, Senator Annabelle</inline> Rankin and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator George</inline> Rankin. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PARLIAMENTARY PROCEEDINGS BROADCASTING COMMITTEE</title>
                <page.no>37</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That, in accordance with the provisions of the Parliamentary Proceedings Broadcasting Act 1946, the following senators be appointed members of the Joint Committee on the Broadcasting of Parliamentary Proceedings: - The  President  of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Brown), Senator Maher</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Wright.</inline></para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>REGULATIONS AND ORDINANCES COMMITTEE</title>
                <page.no>37</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>37</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- I have received letters from the Leader of the Senate and from the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate nominating, in accordance with Standing Order 36a, Senators Guy, Ma her, Tate and "Wood, and Senators Arnold,Katz and Nash, respectively, as members of the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> - <inline font-style="italic">by leave</inline> - agreed to - </para>
                <quote>
                    <para>That a Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances he appointed, to consist of Senators Arnold, Guy, Katz, Maher, Nash, Tate and Wood, such Senators having been duly nominated in accordance with the provisions of Standing Order 36a. </para>
                </quote>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL'S SPEECH</title>
                <page.no>37</page.no>
                <type>motion</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Address-in-Reply. </para>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>37</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KT8</name.id>
                        <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">MCCALLUM, John</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator McCALLUM</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - I move- </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>That the following Address-in-Reply to the Speech of  His Excellency  the Governor-General he agreed to: - </para>
                </quote>
                <quote>
                    <para class="block">May it please Your Excellency: </para>
                </quote>
                <para>We, the Senate of the Commonwealth of Australia in Parliament assembled, desire to express our loyalty to our Most' Gracious Sovereign, and to thank Your  Excellency  for the Speech which you have been pleased to address to Parliament. </para>
                <para class="block">It is a great honour, of which I do not feel worthy, to be asked to move the Address-in-Reply to the Governor-General's Speech as my first speech in this chamber. "We can all agree upon one matter. Everybody was pleased to hear the Governor-General state in his Speech that Their Majesties are likely to visit Australia in . 1952. We all look forward to that visit because of the admiration that we have for the high standards that Their Majesties have always set to all citizens of the Commonwealth and because we think that there will be something symbolic in the visit. It is one of the very necessary steps that must be taken to restore the British Commonwealth of Nations to the proud position that it formerly occupied. That will be one of the main preoccupations of this Government and of all members of the Parliament. We know that the British Commonwealth has suffered the most terrible battering to which it has been subjected in the whole of its history and that great and necessary changes in its constitution have been made. They have occurred in, as it were, the hurricane season. We hope to see the end of that season shortly. We also hope once more to be able to feel that the British Commonwealth stands four square as one of the great powers of the world. There never was a time when it was more necessary that that should be so. </para>
                <para>That brings me to what is to me the most important part of  His  Excellency's Speech, that is, the brief reference in it to foreign affairs. I shall reserve anything that I have to say about foreign affairs generally, and certainly any remarks of a controversial nature, until there is a debate upon that topic. I welcome the promise that a Parliamentary Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs is to be established. I understand that it will be a joint committee upon which members of all parties will serve. The establishment of the committee will represent a new departure in Australia, but, after all, our foreign policy is new. We are feeling our way towards a definite foreign policy. I believe that we are in agreement upon fundamentals in relation to foreign affairs and that the differences of opinion that exist between parties and individuals are mainly concerned with matters of procedure, that is, the ways in which principles are to be applied. I believe that the committee to which I have referred will perform, the very useful purpose of ironing out differences and providing us with material upon which we can form what the Americans call a bi-partisan policy. Of course it must be understood at the outset that such a committee would not possess- exactly the same powers and status as the Foreign Affairs Committee in the American Senate, because a fundamental difference between our Constitution and that of the United States of America is that we have responsible government whilst that country has not. In Australia Ministers sit in both Houses of the Parliament. That is not so, however, in the United States of America, where one of the functions of the Foreign Affairs Committee is to act as a liaison between the legislature and the Executive. There is no need for us to have any agency to perform such a function because our Ministers sit on the front bench in each chamber, and they may be questioned by honorable senators and members of the House of Representatives at question time. Nevertheless there will be very important work for such a committee to perform. Necessarily it will have to be well informed on every topic relating to our external policy. I have followed the foreign history of many countries and I have found that,, frequently, mistakes have been made through sheer ignorance. Because Ministers were ill-informed, or had listened to the wrong adviser, they have taken fatal steps, causing their country to be plunged into war or into some other course which brought misery to its inhabitants. I believe that the obtaining of accurate and ample information, and the drawing of correct inferences from it, is a fundamental part of policy-mak-ing.  That is more true of foreign policy than of any other, because it is becoming almost impossible, even for a specialist, to follow the course of events in other countries. Honorable senators, and members of the House of Representatives, will need to be amply informed on particular aspects of foreign politics in order that we may frame a correct policy. Their advice, based on research and study, will have a profound effect on that .policy. When I was young we used to believe that knowledge was power. I suppose that many of the older members of this chamber have read that contention in their copy-books many times. The new theory appears to be that education does not matter, and that he travels farthest who travels lightest. I disagree with the new theory, because I believe that knowledge is the source of wisdom and that ignorance is the source of error. The great function of the proposed committee will be to dispel ignorance and to impart knowledge. I think, too - and I say this with the greatest respect to the Minister for External Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Spender),</inline> his predecessor, and the able officers who have advised them- that the Minister should have advisers other than those in his own department. Foreign affairs departments in all countries have to be divided and subdivided, in order that specialists shall be available in connexion with all kinds of matters. Usually, each specialist believes that his particular problem is the only one, and that the part of the work with which he is concerned is the most important part. Although the shoemaker used to say " there is nothing like leather " the blacksmith would never agree with him. In shaping our foreign policy we must not rely -entirely on specialists of that kind. Therefore, I contend that the informed opinion of a committee composed of honorable senators and members of the House of Representatives would be valuable and that it would help us to establish a policy that would preserve this country from disaster. </para>
                <para>I do not intend to roam, as the Old Testament and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Hughes</inline> would say, from Dan to Beersheba, but shall select one or two other portions from  His  Excellency's Speech, and comment on them briefly. Honorable senators on both sides of the chamber will doubtless agree that the development of this country is an important matter. There has been established a Ministry of Supply and Development, which will he responsible for the development of country, areas. This implies -pursuance of the policy of decentralization, the encouragement of private industry, and the using of public enterprise, wherever necessary, to supplement private industry. Coupled with that great policy of development are our immigration and defence policies. The Government intends that within a measurable time Australia shall be strong and impregnable. </para>
                <para>Although honorable senators opposite may differ in their views about the means that should be employed to bring about that result, I am convinced that their desire in this matter coincides with that of honorable senators on this side of the chamber. We live in troubled times. During the lifetime of many honorable senators now present in this chamber there have been two world wars, (Separated by a mockery of peace. We have witnessed not only the rise and fall, but also the destruction, of great nations. We have seen the old power system completely swept away and replaced by a new one, which appears to be divided between two great powers, each of them arming for what could be the most terrible conflict in history. At all costs we must preserve this new continent. To do that we must occupy it and use it and make it a home not only for our own people but also for those people that we are welcoming from other parts of the world. Our policy must be bi-partisan. There will he differences of opinion about the methods to be employed, but I am convinced that all honorable senators will approve of our intention to make Australia safe. I shall deal briefly with the controversial aspect of this matter - the means to be pursued. <inline font-style="italic">The</inline> people who elected this Government to office will demand fulfilment of the promise that adequate legal measures shall be taken to deal with subversive institutions, notably the Communist party. I trust that that matter will be debated fully in this chamber, after honorable senators have cleared their minds of cant and humbug and decided very clearly what should be done, and why it should be done. I realize, of course, that the Senate will be deluged with propaganda professing liberal principles, contending that the suppression of any institution would be an illiberal measure. I believe that we should approach this matter from the point of view of liberal principles, that is from the point of view of those people who believe that liberty is the greatest good that any government can preserve for its people. I cannot find any justification for allowing to exist a society or organization that intends to subvert by force and violence the whole of existing society. I admit, of course, that in Europe illiberal reactionary measures have been taken against such societies. I admit that there is great danger in the  suppression  of any kind cf organization. I say, however, that there can he no common ground between those who accept a liberal State, who believe in free speech, free discussion and free elections and those who are determined to overthrow such freedoms and to impose their own ideology by force and by that worst system of expression of opinion - State-directed propaganda intended not to clarify but to pervert thought. We on this side approach the matter of the Communist party as we would approach the question of any other organization that intended to establish a despotism. I do not regard communism and fascism as being opposed. I regard them as being different species of the same hateful thing. Both of them believe in tyranny. Each of them has, of course, opposed the other, just as rival bandits may oppose one another. Nevertheless, the enemy of both, and which both have tried to destroy, is the free State with representative free institutions and free speech. </para>
                <para>Honorable senators will have noticed one note running through the whole of  His  Excellency's Speech - the intention of the Government to restore free enterprise. This chamber might consider that statement carefully from the point of view of principle. Too much discussion to-day is merely on the level of catch phrase3. One person speaks of liberty, and his opponent, instead of attempting to analyse his thought, simply hurls back the accusation, " You mean liberty to exploit". That kind of talking in catch phrases has gone on during the whole of my experience, and it is futile. It issues in no clear thought on any subject whatever. At the risk of being a little tedious, may I remind honorable senators that from 1832 until the 1880's in Great Britain the dominating conception was that all controls should be thrown away, that everybody should be given almost complete liberty to do anything at all provided that he did not interfere with a few accepted things that were protected by law - life, property, and so on. That view was criticized, and justly criticized, from many angles, and from the 'eighties to the present day we have been dominated - I think that all parties have been dominated, and that political discussion everywhere also has been dominated - by the idea that the State should step in and protect the ordinary person from the too-wealthy men and the great monopolists. I fully agree, and I think that all honorable senators will agree, that, in the main, what has been done in that period has been right, and that the vast mass of regulations to provide for shorter periods of work, better working conditions, better wages, more safety in industry, and so on, and the legislation that has introduced what we call the social welfare State, has been beneficial.  But I believe that we have arrived at a point in human progress when one of those great watersheds in human history appears, and that those who go on saying that the fundamental thing to-day is to protect the ordinary man against the monopolist in business and the entrepreneur, are living in an age that is finished. I consider that the fundamental problem to-day is to protect everybody against the growing power of the State itself. We, who believe in using the State to protect the small man against the big man, should be very careful that we do not erect a Frankenstein monster that will destroy us. That statement may sound like mere rhetoric, but I do not intend it as such. 1 do not wish to minimize the evil effect that monopoly in private business oan have. I am opposed to monopoly in private business and I believe that the sentiment running through the Liberal party to-day is in favour of using the power of the State, if necessary, to assist the small man in business and to provide equality of opportunity insofar as that can be achieved by legal enactments and government administration. But to do so it is necessary to develop a great public service. As we have found out, that service can be unsympathetic and unimaginative, and can become tyrannical. One of the great problems of human nature is to prevent any person from using his position for his own advantage against the good of others, and that is as true of those who have the powers of Ministers of State and senators as much as of anybody else. We are all familiar with the oft-quoted dictum of Lord Acton - </para>
                <para>All power corrupts; absolute power corrupts absolutely. </para>
                <para class="block">The important thing to remember is that Lord Acton was a great historian and was not just uttering a mere catch-cry, wisecrack, or some remark that sounded epigrammatic and that might gain him a reputation. He was generalizing on his whole experience of history. Therefore, I wish members of the Opposition to consider, when measures come forward from this side of the chamber, whether the philosophy on which they depend is altogether inadequate to the needs of the day. T am not suggesting that it is a false philosophy and that it has not produced great and beneficial legislation. 1 consider, however, that we have reached a period when the power of the State over the individual and over groups outside the State cannot be extended without seriously endangering all our basic liberties. I believe that it is against ourselves, who govern the country, that people have to be guarded. If in any of the legislation that comes from this side of the chamber we give preference to private enterprise over .public enterprise, it is not merely that we on this side represent one section of the community rather than another, but simply that we are convinced from experience, study and reflection, that State power and State activities can go too far, and that the State has reached a position when is should seek to perform efficiently the functions that it has already taken over rather than to be continually extending its functions. </para>
                <para>I thank you, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. President,</inline> and honorable senators, for the patience with which you have heard me. I commend to the Senate the measures that were outlined in  His  Excellency's Speech, and trust that we shall approach the legislative programme, and all the problems that may arise out of it, rather as two bodies in generous emulation for the public good than as enemies. I believe that there is justification for the system of having political parties. I believe that efficient government is impossible without the existence of political parties, but I do not believe that such parties should be mere factions organized to fight one another on all matters, and to fight -ungenerously. I believe that their function is for each to strive, according to the principles it professes, for the public good. If we approach the problems of legislation in that spirit, we shall feel at the end of this session that we shall have done our duty to the people who have sent us here. </para>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>41</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KSL</name.id>
                        <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">MAHER, Edmund</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator MAHER</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - I have the privilege to second the motion for the adoption of the Address-in-Reply that has been moved in such thought-provoking, informative and highly interesting terms by my colleague, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McCallum.</inline> Almost half a century has elapsed since the Commonwealth Parliament was established, and it is gratifying evidence that Australia's expansion in respect of population, production of wealth and national income has been so substantial as to warrant increasing the number of members of both Houses of the Parliament in order to cope with the ever-increasing problems of our internal development and external relationships. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>All of us were pleased to hear from the lips of His Excellency at the official opening of the Parliament yesterday that good hopes are held out for a visit by Their Majesties the King and Queen to Australia during  1952.  A visit by the reigning sovereign would be unprecedented in the history of this country and would afford a grand opportunity to the Australian people to demonstrate their goodwill, loyalty, love and affection for the Royal Family. </para>
                <para>I wish to refer briefly to the results of the recent general election. At a free election in a free country the Australian people declared in no unmistakable manner for a change of government. I rejoice at that decision. I am certain that consequent changes in the direction of national policy will, as time proceeds, prove to be of incalculable benefit to the Australian people as a whole. I do not propose to conduct a post-mortem on the " why's " and " wherefor's " of the defeat of the Chifley Government. The people have made the decision and I believe that with faith and truth in our hearts we can agree with the Latin dictum <inline font-style="italic">Vox populi, vox Dei</inline> - The voice of the people is the voice of God. The reason for the sweeping victory that was achieved by this Government at the polls is plain to see. </para>
                <para>I refer now to the abolition of petrolrationing about which a series of questions was addressed this afternoon to the Minister for Shipping and Fuel <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator McLeay).</inline> Moving about Queensland and also New South Wales during last week, I found widespread satisfaction with the prompt and businesslike manner in which the Government had abolished petrol-rationing, which was a feature of the administration of the previous Government. I believe that when the full story is told it will indicate that the Chifley Government continued the rationing of petrol, not because a shortage of petrol existed in the sterling areas, but simply because of the socialist's love of control. When the true story is finally unfolded even honorable senators opposite will agree with the point of view of supporters of the Government. In this respect I pay a special tribute to the Treasurer <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Fadden)</inline> for his intensive study of the question of obtaining additional supplies of petrol within the sterling area and for the fine leadership that he showed on this vital issue. After he had convinced himself that the Chifley Government's policy was wrong and that petrol users were being unjustly deprived of a sufficiency of petrol for their needs he set out with characteristic determination to convince not only those associated with him in the Parliament but also the people generally that petrol rationing could, and would, be abolished. The right honorable gentleman is entitled to the fullest credit for the part that he played in bringing about the abolition of petrol rationing. </para>
                <para>Like <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McCallum,</inline> I experienced the greatest satisfaction with the decision of the Government to appoint a Parliamentary Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs. Without doubt, this will be a progressive move. We are living in a changing world and I believe that every honorable senator will agree that events of world-wide significance are moving fast. The British Commonwealth attained the zenith of its strength and prestige under <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Churchill's</inline> leadership <inline font-style="italic">pi</inline> the end of the recent war. Since that time <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Attlee's</inline> Government in Great Britain has decided to abandon valuable strategic areas in Egypt and Palestine whilst India and Burma no longer remain within the framework of the British monarchical system. I do not propose to question the wisdom or to debate the rights and wrongs of the tremendous decisions that were taken in London on those matters. However, one of the  prime factors resulting from those decisions is the emergence of the national consciousness of the Asian peoples. Australia is a near neighbour of all the Asian countries and it is well that we should keep these vast changes before our minds. As a near neighbour of all the Asian countries it devolves upon us to become good neighbours of those peoples. We should, not only through our envoys, consuls, and other direct representatives, but also in every possible way, cultivate the friendship of the peoples of those countries by extending to them the fullest measure of friendliness and goodwill which I am sure will be fully repaid. There is not only ample scope for political cordiality with them but also a unique opportunity to engage in two-way trade with them. The countries of the east require foodstuffs, clothing and manufactured goods which we produce and. we in turn . require many things that they produce. They and we can contribute to the prosperity of our respective countries. A unique opportunity is now presented to the Minister for External Affairs <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Spender)</inline> to promote good will and friendship with all the Asian countries. The Government has made a good start by its decision to reverse the fanatical, if I may use that term, and, in my view, unchristian policy that wa3 applied by the honorable member for Melbourne <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Calwell)</inline> when, he was Minister for Immigration in the cases of Sergeant Gamboa, <inline font-weight="bold">Mrs. O'Keefe, Mr. Jang,</inline> the Cingalese nurse and the Chinese seamen. The Government's decision in those matters will indicate to the leaders of the countries whose nationals are affected that the Australian people while upholding to the fullest degree the principles contained in the Immigration Act are not fanatical and unjust in the application of those principles. </para>
                <para>In view of the unsettled state of the world to-day the Government is to be commended on its proposal to intensify our preparations for the defence of this country. I have long held the opinion that room for improvement exists in our system of training army officers. I was filled with pride yesterday to see the fine young men of the Duntroon Military College forming the guard of honour for the Governor-General when he arrived for the opening of Parliament. In this country the number of young men seeking a purely military career is limited, and I consider that, to accelerate the training of army officers, provision should be made to combine military instruction on Duntroon lines with ordinary secondary education for youths of between fourteen and eighteen years of age. At the conclusion of such training these young men would be free to enter ordinary peace-time vocations. Such a system would increase greatly the flow of capable young men undertaking comprehensive courses of instruction in the arts of war and military sciences and the result would be a substantial pool of trained officers. In the past, one of our great weaknesses has been a scarcity of young men competent to assume command of our various military units when war has broken out. That has been due, as I have said, to the restricted opportunities for military training of the type given at Duntroon. As a consequence, we have had to rely upon men, who, although undoubtedly eager and brave, have lacked knowledge of military science. Some of these men, unfortunately, not because of lack of courage, but because of their inadequate preparation for war, have not enjoyed the confidence of the men that they have been called upon to lead. I believe that it is more important to increase our reserve of trained officers than to attract unlimited numbers of raw recruits into the army as privates. Admittedly, an army cannot consist of officers alone; they must have men to lead. There must, therefore, be a constant flow of army recruits, but it is even more important, I believe, that we should increase the pool of young men who, at short notice will be able to assume command of troops and impart basic military training to them. Officers having undergone the combined military-civil training to which I have referred would automatically be placed on the army reserve of officers, and, in the event of war, we should not be hampered as we have been in the past, by a lack of competent young men possessing all the qualities and training necessary for military leadership. The scheme would also be of substantial benefit to our Citizen Army. </para>
                <para class="block">Another important point would he that, having on hand a large number of officers capable of training raw recruits, we should not have to tap too deeply the industrial labour pool which is so vital to this country. I make these suggestions for the consideration of the Minister for the Army. </para>
                <para>The Government's proposal to establish a Ministry of National Development to concentrate upon major programmes of national expansion, in close and friendly co-operation with the States, and through them with local and regional authorities, is of the utmost importance and should be given the highest priority. Some States, particularly Queensland, are in dire need of improved road and rail communications. Queensland urgently requires arterial roads between such places at Charters Towers and Mount Isa, serving all the intermediate towns and districts. In Central Queensland, there is need for a main road from Rockhampton to Longreach, and, in southern Queensland, there should be highways connecting Roma and Charleville and Goondiwindi and Cunnamulla. Those roads are needed to develop the rich wool-producing provinces of southwestern, central western and north-western Queensland. This work is long overdue. Tn addition, many rail connexions are required. One, in particular, is a direct line between Callide coal-field and the port of Gladstone. The Governor-General referred yesterday to coal production and the subject was mentioned again earlier to-day. It is regrettable indeed that, due to lack of organization in the coal-mining industry in this country, the 'State of Victoria has been obliged to import costly coal, not only from poor old war-torn, battered Britain, but also from India, to meet the needs of secondary industries. It is a sad reflection on our capacity for internal development and organization that a country which is so vastly rich in coal resources should have to import this commodity. Honorable senators will agree. I am sure, that it is absurd, and even monstrous, that a land so richly endowed with supplies of coal should be unable to produce sufficient to meet its own requirements. I nope that the Minister for Shipping and Fuel <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator McLeay)</inline> despite his busy life, will be able to find time in the near future to visit Queensland to see for himself the enormous coal resources of that State. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>43</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JZ8</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">FINLAY, Alexander</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Finlay</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Is there any bituminous coal? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>43</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KSL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MAHER, Edmund</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MAHER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- There is gas coal as well as steaming coal suitable for ships and locomotives. In fact, coal of every description can be found in Queensland. It is true that in New South Wales also there are enormous reserves of high-quality coal, but it is not an exaggeration to say that in Queensland, from the southern border up as far as Cairns the country immediately east and west of the main dividing range contains large quantitiesof coal. Just how extensive those depositsare we shall not know exactly until thorough surveys have been made. Thereare, too, in Queensland vast seams of coal which can be won by open-cut methods. These deposits would be the boast of the1 people of other lands. One open-cut field is at Blair Athol, in central Queensland. I have stood on the floor of the cut and looked up at the 100-ft. cliffs of pure coal. People talk of the White Cliffs of Dover; these are the black cliffs of Blair Athol. Production of coal on this field is restricted only by poor transport facilities. The Queensland Government is endeavouring to improve its railway lines to enable them to carry faster traffic, but that is not the final solution of the problem. There is- enough coal at Blair Athol to attract the attention of overseas investors. In fact, both American and British interests have examined the field and, with sufficient encouragement, they would be prepared to spend millions of pounds on its development; but that should not be necessary. Our coal resources belong to the people of this country, and we ourselves should develop them. Queensland has enough coal to meet this country's industrial requirements for 100 years, but adequate transport facilities are lacking. Where would we be in this country to-day if railway lines had not been built into our great primary producing lands? Where would we he now if our forebears had shrunk from meeting the dost of constructing railways into the great inland regions of this continent merely because such lines would not be a paying proposition? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>Whether they pay or not is not important. The wealth of the country must be tapped. When that wealth is produced, it more than offsets any deficit that may be incurred by our railways. A recent visitor to this country, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr.</inline> Letournier,  a Canadian businessman engaged in the manufacture of bulldozers, graders and heavy machinery of all kinds, said in Brisbane, " Why are you sitting around ? You have the coal and the raw materials; get on with the job. Money is a secondary consideration. Connect the la hour with the raw material, and money will be forthcoming to produce anything that is required to develop this country ". </para>
                <para>The Ministry of Supply and Development will have ample scope to tackle the whole coal production problem. As I have said, Queensland has ample coal. New South Wales, too, has plenty. Victoria and the other States need it.  For  goodness sake let us devise ways and means of mining it and transporting it to the seaboard to be shipped to where it is required. Surely that would be much better than importing expensive coal from other countries as Victoria has had to do in the last two or three years. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KOU</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">HENDRICKSON, Albion</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Hendrickson</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Victoria will not buy Callide coal. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KSL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MAHER, Edmund</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MAHER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- Complaints have been made that Callide coal is not suitable, but I am not prepared to debate that matter with the honorable senator at present. After all, the man who pays the piper calls the tune. If Callide coal does not suit Victoria, other Queensland deposits may be able to produce coal of the desired quality. That it why I should like the Minister for Shipping and Fuel to visit Queensland. If suitable coal can be found in that State, then let us apply ourselves to its production in the quantities required to develop our industries. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <para>There are many other matters that I should like to discuss, but I shall not do so on this occasion. I conclude by saying that in this chamber the Government party is in a minority. I ask the Leader of the Opposition <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Ashley)</inline> and his supporters, as democrats in the best sense of the word, to accept in the right spirit the verdict of the people of Australia, and to assist us to pass through the Senate legislation that will be covered by the mandate that the Government has received from the people. </para>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K0W</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">ASHLEY, William</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Ashley</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I consider it to be presumptuous of the honorable senator to make that suggestion at the present stage. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KSL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MAHER, Edmund</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MAHER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is not my desire to be presumptuous. I wish to make an appeal to men who, although they differ from us fundamentally in politics, are democrats in the widest sense of the term. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
                <interjection>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>K7P</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">COLLINGS, Joseph</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator Collings</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- It is very kind of the honorable senator to say that. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </interjection>
                <continue>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>44</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KSL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">MAHER, Edmund</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator MAHER</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I could make out a case the other way, but I do not propose to do so to-day. On this occasion, I make an appeal to the Leader of the Opposition to recognize the position as it exists and to afford us his best assistance in passing through the Senate legislation that comes within the scope of the mandate that the Government has received from the Australian people. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </continue>
            </speech>
            <para>Debate (on motion by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Willesee)</inline> adjourned. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
                <page.no>44</page.no>
                <type>special adjournment</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O'Sullivan)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <quote>
                <para>That the Senate, at its rising, adjourn to Wednesday next, at 3 p.m. </para>
            </quote>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>PAPERS</title>
                <page.no>44</page.no>
                <type>papers</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>The following papers were presented : - . </para>
            <para>Australian Imperial Force Canteens Fund Act - Twenty-ninth Annual Report by the Trustees, for year 1948-49. </para>
            <para>Commonwealth Public Service Act - Appointments - Attorney-General's Department - A. S. Barnes, P. J. Clarke, A. M. Davidson, C. if. Jeffery, R. T. G. Lahey, J. R. Leslie, B. J. Letcher, H. Lindgren, R. F. Pickering, H. N. Walker. </para>
            <para>Commonwealth Public Service Act - Twentyfifth Report on the Commonwealth Public Service by  the  Public Service Board, for year 1.948-49. </para>
            <para>Ordered to be printed. </para>
            <para class="block">Lands Acquisition Act - Land acquired for </para>
            <para>Postal purposes - Tamworth, New South </para>
            <para>Wales. </para>
            <para>Scat of Government Acceptance Act .and Seat of Government (Administration) Act - Ordinance - 1950 - No. 1 - Boardinghouses (Unclaimed Goods). </para>
            <para>War Service Homes Act - Report of Director of War Service Homes for year 1948-49, together with statements and balance-sheet. </para>
        </debate>
        <adjournment>
            <adjournmentinfo>
                <page.no>44</page.no>
                <time.stamp>16:34:00</time.stamp>
            </adjournmentinfo>
            <para class="block">Senate adjourned at 4.34 p.m. </para>
        </adjournment>
    </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>