<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1970-03-03</date>
    <parliament.no>27</parliament.no>
    <session.no>2</session.no>
    <period.no>1</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>5</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para class="block">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA </para>
    <para class="block">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES </para>
    <para class="block">(HANSARD) </para>
    <para class="block">Second Session of the Twenty-seventh Parliament (First Period) </para>
    <para>SENATE </para>
    <para>The Senate and the House of Representatives, on 25 November 1969, adjourned to a date and hour to be fixed by the  President  and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Speaker</inline> respectively. By proclamation, the Parliament was prorogued by  His Excellency  the Governor-General on 23 February 1970, until 3 March 1970. The Second Session commenced on that day. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1970-03-03</day.start>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PROCLAMATION</title>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <type>proclamations</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The Senate met at 3 p.m., pursuant to the proclamation of His Excellency the Governor-General. </para>
      <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Sir Alister McMullin)</inline> took the chair. </para>
      <para>The  Clerk  read the proclamation. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>
        <inline font-weight="bold">His Excellency</inline>the Governor-General entered the chamber, and being seated, with the  President  on his right hand, commanded that a message be sent to the House of Representatives, intimating that he desired the attendance of honourable members in the Senate chamber forthwith, who, being come with their  Speaker, </para>
      <para>His Excellency was pleased to deliver the following speech: </para>
      <para>Members of the Senate and Members of the House of Representatives: </para>
      <para>You are assembled at this Second Session of the 27th Parliament to consider and decide on matters affecting the security and growth of the Australian nation, and matters concerning the welfare of the citizens who constitute that nation. </para>
      <para>This year we commemorate the discovery of Eastern Australia by Captain Cook, two hundred years in the past. </para>
      <para>Now we turn our eyes to a future which, more than ever before, is rich with the promise of achievement if we have the will to achieve. </para>
      <para>It is therefore fitting that this year  Her  Majesty The Queen, and  His  Royal Highness The Duke of Edinburgh, accompanied by their children,  His  Royal Highness The Prince of Wales and  Her  Royal Highness The Princess Anne, will visit us. They will be warmly welcome in this country. </para>
      <para>My Government will continue to support the principles of the United Nations and seek in that way the establishment of enduring peace amongst all nations. </para>
      <para>A comprehensive statement on Australia&#39;s defence policy will be made to the Parliament in the early days of this Session by the Minister for Defence. </para>
      <para>But in a world still torn by tension and by conflict we must also look to our own defences. </para>
      <para>This statement wit&#93; outline the attention being given to the long range strategic policies which will best serve Australia&#39;s security. And it will indicate the priorities to be given to the development of selfsufficient and versatile forces to support those policies. </para>
      <para>New proposals will be made for the Defence infrastructure, and for new equipment in the years ahead. </para>
      <para>Meanwhile the acquisition of the fighting equipment, which was announced in the last Budget, is proceeding. Investigation into the construction of a causeway to the naval facilities to be built in Western Australia has begun, and construction on the development of Learmonth airfield in Western Australia will shortly start. The strength of the Australian Permanent Forces, which was 83,794 at the end of 1969 is expected to increase to 86,500 by June. Legislation will be introduced to provide a uniform code of discipline for all three Services. </para>
      <para>The strength of our industrial base is of vital importance to our defence. My Government will continue its general policy of encouraging the development of new capacity in industry and has specifically allocated $3. 2m for the design of an Australian light twin engined utility aircraft, including the manufacture of two flying prototypes by the Government Aircraft Factories. </para>
      <para>In keeping with our aim to achieve enduring peace my Government believes thai aggression must be seen to be unsuccessful. Australia will therefore continue, in co-operation with the United States of America and other countries, to assist the Republic of Vietnam in its struggle to repel aggression and allow its citizens to live under a Government of their own choice. </para>
      <para>My Government will continue to give military and economic assistance to the Republic of Vietnam and will continue its Civic Action Programme. </para>
      <para>My Government is glad to note that the increasing capacity of the South Vietnamese to defend themselves has already permitted the withdrawal of some Allied Forces. Should the future situation permit a further substantial withdrawal of troops - beyond those announced by  President  Nixon on 16 December 1969  -  then in consultation with the Government of the Republic of Vietnam and the Government of the United Stales, some Australian troops will be included, at some stage, in the numbers scheduled for such withdrawal. </para>
      <para>My Government deplores the continuing threat posed by North Vietnam and strongly supports the continuing efforts which are being made to achieve a just and lasting peace through negotiation. </para>
      <para>Turning to our near North my Government, at the invitation of the Governments of Malaysia and Singapore, will continue to station forces of all three Services in those two countries after 1971. My Government believes that this continuing Australian presence will be seen as a contribution to the security of Malaysia and Singapore and to stability, progress and co-operation in South East Asia. </para>
      <para>My Government believes that our defence aid, which includes approved programmes amounting to $45m, and the gift of ten Sabre aircraft to Malaysia, is a real contribution to the defence capacity of both countries. </para>
      <para>My Government will take steps to advance Papua and New Guinea further along the road to self-government and eventual independence. </para>
      <para>My Government does not believe that an arbitrary date for independence of Papua and New Guinea should be set by it, even against the wishes of the people of the Territory and it will not do so. </para>
      <para>But my Government does believe in constant advancement towards selfgovernment. Consideration of major changes in constitutional arrangements for selfgovernment should await presentation to the Territory House of Assembly of the Report of the Select Committee on Constitutional Development, which is at present inquiring into this matter. </para>
      <para>My Government will, however, take early steps to introduce new arrangements within the scope of the present Papua and New Guinea Act. </para>
      <para>This will result in Ministerial Members accepting full day-to-day responsibility for their Departments instead of sharing that responsibility as at present with a Departmental Head. The Ministerial Member will be responsible to the Administrator&#39;s Executive Council. </para>
      <para>The scope of the responsibilities of the Administrator&#39;s Executive Council will be enlarged and additional powers will be transferred to that Council, and to Ministerial Members who form a majority of that Council. </para>
      <para>The procedures by which the Territory Budget is framed will be changed so that elected Members will have a greater voice in the actual drafting of the Budget. </para>
      <para>The Territory of Papua and New Guinea is developing economically and will in the future develop faster. </para>
      <para>But the level of local savings in Papua and New Guinea is low and finance for major development projects comes predominantly from outside the Territory. </para>
      <para>Because of this the Administration has in the past acquired - for future disposal to the people of the Territory - substantial equity holdings in certain enterprises, notably the Bougainville Copper Project and the New Britain Oil Palm Project. </para>
      <para>My Government now proposes to ask the Territory House of Assembly for legislation to establish a statutory corporation to acquire equity in major investment projects in the Territory. </para>
      <para>This new institution would have a close link with the Papua and New Guinea Development Bank and its principal functions would be to take up shares in appropriate enterprises and hold them for future disposal to the people of the Territory, to underwrite local share issues, and to establish unit trusts or investment companies. </para>
      <para>My Government will, this month, introduce  a  new scheme for practical, down to earth training of Papuans and New Guineans in Australia, in areas of training not available in the Territory. </para>
      <para>In doing this my Government will seek the co-operation of private organisations, private enterprise, and State Governments so that the scheme may be a human and economic success and, through the training provided, help Papuans and New Guineans to accept greater responsibilities in both private and government activity in their own country. </para>
      <para>Turning now to internal matters my Government believes that economic growth in Australia has continued strongly. </para>
      <para>Thus in the year to the September quarter 1969 gross national product increased by 11.7% and the indications are that this strong growth rate is continuing. </para>
      <para>Full employment has been maintained and considerable expansion has taken place. Commerce and industry - apart from some rural industries - is prosperous. Pressures on costs and prices, though strong and persistent and requiring close attention, have for the most part been kept reasonably under control. </para>
      <para>The Australian economy, moreover, has demonstrated a new resilience which has enabled it to weather problems created by droughts, and by international financial stresses. </para>
      <para>My Government will follow policies aimed at broadening the economy and further developing the Australian nation. </para>
      <para>These policies will require, among other things, an increase in labour and in skills. </para>
      <para>To this end overseas training techniques are being studied and, in co-operation with the organisations of employees and employers my Government will formulate procedures to retrain employees displaced by technological change. </para>
      <para>A training scheme for married and single women who, for domestic reasons have not previously been employed, will be set up. Special studies will be made into the problems and the rehabilitation of persons who, for a variety of reasons, have tended to be classed as unemployable. </para>
      <para>Discussions are taking place between the National Employers&#39; Organisations and the Australian Council of Trade Unions and the Government in an endeavour to develop more effective means of avoiding and settling industrial disputes within the framework of the Conciliation and Arbitration system. </para>
      <para>My Government has instituted an enquiry into Australia&#39;s future needs in postgraduate education in management and will legislate to provide the funds necessary to ensure that there are adequate facilities in Australia for post-graduate education in business management of the highest quality. </para>
      <para>Financially, last year was marked by international financial crises but it was also a year of achievement in international financial co-operation which my Government believes will provide a greatly improved financial foundation for world trade in the period ahead. </para>
      <para>In keeping with Australia&#39;s contribution in this field my Government will introduce legislation to increase Australia&#39;s quota in the Internationa&#93; Monetary Fund, and my Government will also proceed with the negotiation of new double taxation agreements and the revision of existing agreements. </para>
      <para>Legislation will be introduced to extend the authority of the Export Payments Insurance Corporation to provide export credit insurance facilities for Australian exporters to Australia&#39;s external Territories. This will improve the competitive position of Australia exporters. </para>
      <para>The Industrial Research and Development Grants Act 1967 will be reviewed during 1970-71 and the scope of complementary measures for a comprehensive and integrated programme to foster Australian industrial creativity and efficiency will be explored. So that manufacturers may plan ahead their activities in this important area, the Government&#39;s future programme of assistance will be announced well before the present legislation expires in June 1972. </para>
      <para>Many Australian investors need an immediate income from their investments. They therefore provide money for development in Australia at fixed interest. In order to provide an opportunity for such investors to participate at their choice in the equity of Australian development, my Government will introduce early legislation conditionally to restore to companies the income tax deduction for interest paid on notes which carry the option of being converted by the bolder into shares. Legislation will also be introduced to provide estate duty relief for estates of deceased primary producers. </para>
      <para>My Government will legislate to amend the Bills of Exchange Act 1909-1958 in relation to the requirements for the endorsement of cheques credited to the bank accounts of payees. It will also legislate to amalgamate the Excise Act 1901-1968, the Distillation Act 1901-1968, and the Coat Excise Act 1949-1968 into a single statute and to incorporate certain provisions of the Spirits Act 1906-1969 in that statute or in the Customs legislation. </para>
      <para>The progressive income tax scale and other aspects of the taxation system which affect particularly the lower and middle income earners are being closely studied to enable fulfilment of my Government&#39;s aim to put before Parliament specific provisions for relief in the next Budget. </para>
      <para>To enable Australian trade to fit more conveniently into the international mould, my Government will present legislation to establish a Metric Conversion Board, so that a programme for conversion to a metric system of weights and measures may, in consultation with the States and community groups, be put in hand. </para>
      <para>My Government reaffirms its belief that a tariff policy of providing adequate protection to economic and efficient Australian industries has been the basis for the sound and vigorous development of secondary industry in Australia. </para>
      <para>However there is a need to re-examine from time to time the administrative machinery under which protection is provided and an investigation will be made to see if there is scope for improving the procedures for the handling of certain types of tariff cases. </para>
      <para>After the close of this financial year new financial arrangements will need to be made between the Commonwealth and State Governments. </para>
      <para>The bases for such an agreement were put forward at the Premiers&#39; Conference held on 26th February and officers of the various Governments will shortly engage in initial discussions on them. </para>
      <para>These bases of discussion will be the proposals of the Commonwealth to assume progressively responsibility for a share of existing State Debt, to reduce the future growth of State Debt by providing each year to the States, as a non-repayable grant, some money which would now be provided as a loan, to review the present base for revenue grants, and to review the present betterment factor by which revenue grants grow annually. </para>
      <para>In adopting this course my Government is giving expression to its belief that there is a need for an increase in the financial capacity of the States. </para>
      <para>Further, at the unanimous request of the State Governments, my Government will introduce legislation which will have the effect of enabling the States to receive the revenue from receipts duty which they would otherwise lose as a result of the High Court Judgment of 19th February. </para>
      <para>As further indirect assistance to State finances, the relevant ordinance of the Australian Capital Territory will be amended to allow the recovery by the States of death duties imposed on assets held in the Australian Capital Territory by the estates of deceased persons domiciled in a State. </para>
      <para class="block">I turn now to Primary Industry: </para>
      <para class="block">My Government will continue to work actively with representative organisations to grapple with the problems facing primary producers. </para>
      <para>The Drought Bonds Scheme, which became operative last November, has provided a new line of defence against the financial burdens of drought, and financial assistance by my Government to drought affected farmers in Queensland will amount to about $15m in the current financial year. </para>
      <para>Under the provisions of the Wheat Industry Stabilisation Act 1968 arrangements were made for the Australian Wheat Board to borrow, on Commonwealth guarantee, up to $624m from the Rural Credits Department of the Reserve Bank of Australia, to enable advance payments to growers delivering wheat to the 1968-69 pool. </para>
      <para>Because of lower sales of wheat the Board will be unable fully to repay the borrowing by the due date. My Government will therefore introduce legislation in the immediately following sitting days to enable the Commonwealth to meet its guarantee by making a loan of up to $300m to the Wheat Board. </para>
      <para>My Government will also introduce legislation, in support of legislation by State Governments, in order to make fully effective the wheat delivery quota plan of the Australian Wheat Growers&#39; Federation; and to give the Australian Wheat Board discretionary powers to sell wheat in Australia, for other than human consumption, at concessional prices. </para>
      <para>In further recognition of the needs of the wheat industry my Government has decided that the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation will collaborate with the Australian Wheat Board in establishing, operating and maintaining, a laboratory to conduct research into grain storage problems. </para>
      <para>To help the wool industry my Government will introduce legislation to halve the present levy on wool growers for research and promotion and to increase its own contribution fo an average of $27m annually. This is approximately double the present contribution. </para>
      <para>In addition my Government will make arrangements to assist the marketing proposals of the Australian Wool Industry Conference for the three year period to 1972- 73. This is estimated to cost over S7m annually. </para>
      <para>My Government has striven to obtain the maximum possible share of the United States market for export of meat from Australia. As a result Australia was able, towards the end of 1969, to export an additional 14.8 million lb of meat to the United States of America, over and above the originally agreed level of 505 million lb. </para>
      <para>My Government will continue its efforts in this field, and is at present negotiating with the British Authorities to maintain Australian beef exports, and to safeguard Australia&#39;s rights and interests, in the United Kingdom market. </para>
      <para>My Government is also supporting the State Governments in a national campaign to eradicate brucellosis and tuberculosis from Australia&#39;s cattle herds. It is estimated that over the triennium to 1972 $4m will be provided for this purpose. </para>
      <para>In October 1969 my Government concluded a new domestic sugar agreement with the Queensland Government. Legislation to ratify this agreement will be introduced at the earliest opportunity. </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce legislation to ratify the agreement reached between the Commonwealth, New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia for the construction of the Dartmouth Dam. Legislation will also be introduced to establish the Snowy Mountains Engineering Corporation. </para>
      <para>My Government will over the next five years provide SI 00m for new proposals under the National Water Resources Development Programme. The new programme will cover proposals for flood prevention and flood mitigation works, and for small dams supplying particular districts and groups of farmers. </para>
      <para>My Government has already allocated $12. 8m of this $100m towards the cost of an irrigation project in the Bundaberg Region of Queensland. </para>
      <para>Legislation will also be introduced to provide funds to help finance the construction of a new power house in Central </para>
      <para class="block">Queensland at Gladstone. My Government believes that this power station will result in the construction of an aluminium smelter - possibly the biggest in the Southern hemisphere - and in other industrial development. It will be a concrete example of decentralisation and it will add to the export earnings of the nation. </para>
      <para>To assist in reducing our dependence on imports of forest products my Government will continue to give substantial support to the development of Australia&#39;s forests and forestry. Long term loans estimated at $4.8m will be provided to the States for this purpose under the Softwood Forestry Agreements Act 1967. </para>
      <para>In order to provide amenities to those engaged in work in remote areas my Government will continue its policy to extend television coverage and low powered national relay stations will be established in a further thirty-eight remote areas of the Commonwealth. </para>
      <para>During the life of the Parliament the Australian Atomic Energy Commission will begin construction of a nuclear power station in Commonwealth Territory at Jervis Bay. </para>
      <para>My Government recognises that much of the Northern Territory is heavily dependent on sea transport and that the establishment of modern port facilities will be vital to the region&#39;s further economic growth. My Government therefore proposes to undertake major new works at the Port of Darwin, including the construction of a new container and general cargo berth in the existing port area, a bulk port facility at East Arm and a new small craft facility at Frances Bay. </para>
      <para>My Government proposes to set up a Bureau of Transport Economics to analyse the economics of transport in Australia. Further, because it is clear that the costs of sea transport will greatly depend on the ability to use new and larger ships my Government proposes that a conference ot </para>
      <para class="block">Commonwealth and State Ministers meet shortly to examine and co-ordinate plans for port development </para>
      <para>My Government will continue with the standardisation of railway lines in Australia. Early legislation will be introduced to enable the construction of a standard gauge railway from Port Augusta to Whyalla and as soon as an agreement is reached between the Commonwealth and South Australian Governments, Parliament will be asked to approve the construction of the tine linking Port Pirie to Adelaide. </para>
      <para>My Government will continue to provide the climate and conditions which will encourage the maximum development of all sectors of Australian industry by private enterprise. lt believes that the development of industry on the scale and with the efficiency to compete in world markets is the cornerstone of national growth. </para>
      <para>For this aim to be achieved a strong and continuing inflow of development capital from overseas is imperative. </para>
      <para>My Government has made it clear that it prefers those who supply overseas capital for these purposes to provide the opportunity for partnership to Australian capital. This is now increasingly occurring. Australian partnership in development <inline font-style="italic">is</inline> growing. </para>
      <para>My Government proposes to take a step designed to help that growth. </para>
      <para>At present foreign firms are able to raise vast sums overseas at fixed interest for major development and expansion in Australia. </para>
      <para>Australian companies, lacking the investment appeal abroad of large international companies have been, in general, unable to tap those sources of funds for themselves, and often accept a smaller stake in development in Australia than they otherwise would. </para>
      <para>My Government will therefore ask the Parliament to legislate, during this Session to establish an Industry Development Corporation. </para>
      <para>The purpose of this Corporation will be to borrow, predominantly overseas and at fixed interest, from the sources at present tapped by foreign enterprises. </para>
      <para>My Government believes that this Corporation will help bring about greater Australian participation in the ownership of our developing nation. </para>
      <para>My Government has examined the presently unresolved legal question as to which Government is entitled to exercise sovereign control over the resources of the sea bed off the Australian coast to the outer limits of the continental shelf. </para>
      <para>At present, the various State Governments claim sovereign rights in respect of such resources from low water mark to the outer limits of the shelf. The Commonwealth believes that, except for internal waters as they existed at Federation, it has sovereign rights in this area. </para>
      <para>It is the view of my Government that it would serve Australia&#39;s national and international interests to have the legal position resolved. In order that this may happen, my Government will ask the Parliament to pass legislation to assert and establish what the Commonwealth conceives to be its legal rights. </para>
      <para>This legislation will not affect the existing agreements between the Commonwealth and the States concerning off-shore petroleum. </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce legislation forthwith to establish an Institute of Marine Science at Townsville, and to establish an Anglo-Australian Telescope Board to erect a 160-inch telescope at Siding Spring. </para>
      <para>My Government has agreed to a programme of extended wild life research by the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial </para>
      <para class="block">Research Organisation in Northern Australia and a wild life research laboratory will be established at Darwin. </para>
      <para>Legislation will be introduced to finance the Commonwealth&#39;s share of establishing a fourth school of Veterinary Science at an Australian University. </para>
      <para>A Royal Commission will be established to enquire into the question of damage which might be caused to the Barrier Reef through drilling for oil. </para>
      <para>Special grants will be made for educational research and $250,000 will be provided by my Government in 1970-71. </para>
      <para>The present programme of unmatched capital grants for construction of Teacher Training Colleges totals $24 million and will expire on 30th June this year. </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce legislation early in this Session to authorise a further similar three-year programme to the value of $30 million. </para>
      <para>My Government is at present cooperating with the States in a nation-wide survey of educational needs at the primary and secondary levels, and for teacher education including in-service training. </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce early legislation to pay pensions at standard rates to married couples who have lost the economies of living together; to authorise subsidies to organisations providing meals on wheels; and to provide capital assistance on a 2 for 1 basis to approved institutions training handicapped children. </para>
      <para>Early legislation will be introduced to improve and extend the scheme of compensation under the Commonwealth Employees&#39; Compensation Act 1930-1969. </para>
      <para>Legislation will also be brought down this Session to give effect to the scheme for the preservation of superannuation rights - the so-called portability of pensions - which was announced in the Parliament on 25th </para>
      <para class="block">September last. The arrangements will apply, after the passage of the legislation, on and from 1st January J 970. </para>
      <para>During this Session legislation will be introduced to improve the health scheme. </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce legislation to provide substantially increased medical benefits, based on the concept that medical benefits payments are to be determined by reference to the fees most commonly charged for medical services. This, and other improvements to the scheme, will require increased insurance premiums from individuals and increased subventions by the Commonwealth. </para>
      <para>My Government has also decided that the major recommendations of the Nimmo Report should be accepted and will introduce legislation to this end. Those recommendations dealing with matters for which the Commonwealth and States have joint responsibility remain to be the subject of negotiation with State Governments. </para>
      <para>The Minister for Health will make a full and detailed statement to the Parliament on these matters early in the present Session. </para>
      <para>My Government has decided that families on low incomes should be helped to meet the cost of health insurance by a graduated subsidy designed to pay the lull cost oi health insurance for families with incomes not in excess of the average minimum wage, and part of the cost of meeting health insurance for families whose incomes are little in excess of the average minimum wage. </para>
      <para>Measures will be introduced directed towards simplification of the procedures of health insurance funds, the more effective employment of their financial reserves, the maintenance of their management expenses at reasonable levels, and the improvement of their operational efficiency and economy generally. </para>
      <para>The increases in the traffic in drugs is a matter of concern to my Government. </para>
      <para class="block">Ministers of my Government have conferred with State Ministers on this problem and steps are being taken to co-ordinate the activities of Commonwealth and State law enforcement agencies. </para>
      <para>My Government proposes, after further consultation with the States, to introduce legislation to establish a National Institute of Criminology, financed by the Commonwealth, <inline font-style="italic">to</inline> carry out research and provide training for officers engaged in the prevention of crime. </para>
      <para>My Government also proposes to introduce legislation to reduce delays in the hearing of proceedings for divorce and to reduce the cost to litigants. This will be done by enabling State Courts of intermediate jurisdiction to hear certain undefended divorce cases and to simplify procedures for the enforcement of maintenance orders granted in another State or Territory, </para>
      <para>My Government will introduce legislation immediately to amend the Home Savings Grant Act 1964-67 to raise the permissible limit on the value of a house from $15,000 to $17,500, to liberalise other aspects of the Scheme and to provide that, if a Credit Union meets the conditions which will be required, savings deposited with that Credit Union will qualify for the purposes of homes savings grants. </para>
      <para>My Government will continue its policy of fostering Aboriginal initiative, will use the special capital fund which has been set up to assist in this task, and hopes that during the lifetime of the Parliament any remnants of discriminatory legislation against Aboriginals will be eliminated. </para>
      <para>International Tourism nowadays is big business. A decade ago it brought Australia approximately $16m. In 1969 it brought Australia approximately $120m. </para>
      <para>The Australian Tourist Commission, established by the Government in 1967 <inline font-style="italic">to</inline> encourage the flow of visitors to Australia. believes this can be raised to $300m per annum by 1975, if certain development programmes are adopted. </para>
      <para>The Government recognises the vital role of the States and the industry in any programme of tourism development and the Commission works closely in co-operation with them. </para>
      <para>My Government has already demonstrated its willingness to foster and develop Australia&#39;s performing arts. An Interim Council has been appointed to investigate and report on the establishment of a National Film and Television Training School. My Government will now immediately introduce legislation to establish a Statutory Corporation to promote the production and distribution of Australian-made films of high quality. An amount of $1m will be provided as initial capital for the Corporation. </para>
      <para>The policies I have outlined will necessitate a substantial programme of legislation. </para>
      <para>For some time my Government has been deeply concerned at the delays in preparing legislation because of the shortage of experienced Parliamentary Draftsmen. </para>
      <para>The prompt preparation of legislation is the basis of effective parliamentary government and so that such preparation may be expedited my Government proposes to establish by statute an Office of Parliamentary Counsel and to take administrative steps which it is hoped will lead to availability of such experienced draftsmen. </para>
      <para>And now, as we enter this new decade of opportunity for Australia, I leave you to the discharge of your high and important duties in the faith that Divine Providence will guide your deliberations and further the welfare of the people of Australia. (His Excellency the Governor-General and members of the House of Representatives retired.) </para>
      <para class="block">Sitting suspended from 3.53 to 5 p.m. </para>
      <para>The  PRESIDENT  again took the chair, and read prayers. </para>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>AUSTRALIA PARTY</title>
        <page.no>14</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>14</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K8Y</name.id>
            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
            <party>IND; AP from Aug. 1969; IND from Jan. 1970</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">TURNBULL, Reginald</name>
            <name role="display">Senator TURNBULL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- by leave - I wish to announce to the Senate that owing to a number of factors 1 resigned from the Australia Party early in January and have reverted to my status as an independent senator for Tasmania. To the many hundreds who joined the Australia Party because of my participation I wish to sincerely apologise for deserting them. To <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Gordon</inline> Barton and to the members of the national executive I owe a great deal for their support in the formation of the Australia Party and I wish them well in the future. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>COMMITTEES</title>
        <page.no>14</page.no>
        <type>committee</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motions (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Anderson)</inline> - by leave - agreed to: </para>
      <quote>
        <para>Select Committee on Off-Shore Petroleum Resources </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>That, with respect to legislation relating to the exploration for, and the exploitation of, the petroleum resources of the Continental Shelf of Australia and of certain Territories of the Commonwealth and of certain other submerged land, a select committee of the Senate be appointed to inquire into and report upon - </para>
            <list type="loweralpha">
              <item label="(a)">
                <para>whether the constitutional conception underlying the legislation is consistent with the proper constitutional responsibilities of the Commonwealth and the States; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(b)">
                <para>whether the system of administration established by the legislation is the most effective to fulfil the purpose of adequate utilisation of Australia&#39;s off-shore resources of oil and natural gas; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(c)">
                <para>whether the legislation makes adequate provision for free interstate trade in gas and oil; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(d)">
                <para>whether proper provision is made in the legislation for adequate royalties used in the national interest; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(e)">
                <para>whether the areas of permits confirmed or authorised in the legislation are excessive; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(f)">
                <para>whether proper provision is made relating to renewals to prevent stagnating oil exploration; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(g)">
                <para>whether the legislation makes adequate provision for Australian ownership and/or control or Australian participation in the ownership and/or control of Australia&#39;s off-shore resources of oil and natural gas; and </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(h)">
                <para>the provisions of the legislation generally. </para>
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>That the Committee consist of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Greenwood (Chairman) and Senators Cant, Gair, Keeffe, Laucke, O&#39;Byrne, Webster and Young.</inline></para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>That the  Chairman  of the Committee may from time to time appoint another member of the Committee to be the Deputy-Chairman ofthe Committee, and that the member so appointed act as  chairman  of the Committee at any time when the  Chairman  is not present at a meeting of the Committee. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>That, in the event of an equality of voting, the  Chairman,  or the Deputy-Chairman when acting as  chairman,  have a casting vote. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records, to move from place to place, to sit in open court or in private, and have leave to report from time to time its proceedings and the evidence taken and such interim recommendations as it may deem fit. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(6)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to meet and transact business notwithstanding any prorogation of the Parliament. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(7)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to consider the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committees on Off-shore Petroleum Resources appointed during previous sessions. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(8)">
            <para>That the Committee report to the Senate as soon as possible. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(9)">
            <para>That the foregoing provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para class="block">Select Committee on Water Pollution </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>That a select committee be appointed to inquire into and report upon water pollution and quality of water for different uses in Australia, including (a) causes and effects, (b) methods of prevention and control, and (c) matters incidental thereto. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>That the Committee consist of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Davidson (Chairman) and Senators Byrne, Mulvihill, Prowse, Rae and Ridley.</inline></para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>That the  Chairman  of the Committee may. from time to time, appoint another member of the Committee to be the Deputy-Chairman of the Committee, and that the member so appointed act as  chairman  of the Committee at any time when the  Chairman  is not present at a meeting of the Committee. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>That, in the event of an equality of voting, the  Chairman,  or the Deputy-Chairman when acting as  chairman,  have a casting vote. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>That four members of the Committee, including the  Chairman  or Deputy-Chairman, constitute a quorum of the Committee. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(6)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records, to move from place to place, to sit in open court or in private, and have leave to report from time to time its proceedings and the evidence taken and such interim recommendations as it may deem fit. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(7)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to meet and transact business notwithstanding any prorogation of the Parliament. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(8)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to consider the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committees on Water Pollution appointed during previous sessions. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(9)">
            <para>That the Committee report to the Senate on or before 30 June 1970. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(10)">
            <para>That the foregoing provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para class="block">Select Committee on Medical and Hospital Costs </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>That a select committee be appointed to inquire into medical and hospital costs in Australia and, in particular, to examine the operation and administration of the medical and hospital benefit schemes and to recommend such legislative and administrative measures by the Commonwealth as will, having regard to the constitutional division of legislative power in Australia, enable the provision of the optimum standards of medical and hospital care for all. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>That the Committee consist of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Dame</inline> Ivy Wedgwood <inline font-weight="bold">(Chairman) and Senators Bull, Dittmer, McClelland, Sim and Turnbull.</inline></para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>That the  Chairman  of the Committee may from time to time appoint another member of the Committee to be the Deputy-Chairman of the Committee, and that the member so appointed act as  chairman  of the Committee at any time when the  Chairman  is not present at a meeting of the Committee. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>That, in the event of an equality of voting, the  Chairman,  or the Deputy-Chairman when acting as  chairman,  have a casting vote. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>That four members of the Committee, including the  Chairman  or Deputy-Chairman, constitute a quorum of the Committee. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(6)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records, to move from place to place, to sit in open court or in private, and have leave to report from time to time its proceedings and the evidence taken and such interim recommendations as it may deem fit. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(7)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to meet and transact business notwithstanding any prorogation of the Parliament. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(8)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to consider the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committees on Medical and Hospital Costs appointed during previous sessions. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(9)">
            <para>That the Committee report to the Senate on or before 30 June 1970. </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(10)">
            <para>That the foregoing provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Select Committee on Drug Trafficking and Drug Abuse </para>
      </quote>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Resolution of Appointment</title>
          <page.no>15</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>That a select committee be appointed to inquire into and report upon drug trafficking and drug abuse is Australia and,in particular: </para>
            <list type="loweralpha">
              <item label="(a)">
                <para>the incidence, distribution and causes of drug abuse; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(b)">
                <para>the extent, organisation and methods of drug trafficking, including the sources of supply; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(c)">
                <para>the adequacy of existing Commonwealth and State legislation and administration; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(d)">
                <para>the adequacy of present educational programmes against drug abuse; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(e)">
                <para>the adequacy of existing international agreements affecting Australia; </para>
              </item>
              <item label="(f)">
                <para>the effectiveness of existing international law enforcement agencies and methods in regard to Australia. and to make such recommendations as it may think fit, on - </para>
                <list type="lowerroman">
                  <item label="(i)">
                    <para>legislative and administrative measures by the Commonwealth to prevent and deal with drug trafficking and drug abuse; </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(ii)">
                    <para>the desirability of further international agreements or improvements in existing international law enforcement agencies and methods so far as they affect Australia; and </para>
                  </item>
                  <item label="(iii)">
                    <para>the treatment and rehabilitation of persons dependent on drugs; </para>
                  </item>
                </list>
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item label="(2)">
            <para>That the Committee consist of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Marriott (Chairman) and Senators Branson, Buttfield, Cavanagh, Georges, McManus, Maunsell and Wheeldon;</inline></para>
          </item>
          <item label="(3)">
            <para>That the  Chairman  of the Committee may, from time to time, appoint another member of the Committee to be the Deputy-Chairman of the Committee, and that the member so appointed act as  chairman  of the Committee at any time when the  Chairman  is not present at a meeting of the Committee; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(4)">
            <para>That, in the event of an equality of voting, the  Chairman,  or the Deputy-Chairman when acting as  chairman,  have a casting vote; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(5)">
            <para>That four members of the Committee shall be necessary to constitute a meeting of the Committee for the exercise of its powers; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(6)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to meet and transact business notwithstanding any prorogation of the Parliament; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(7)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records, to move from place to place, to sit in open court or in private, and have leave to report from time to time its proceedings and the evidence taken and such interim recommendations as it may deem fit; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(8)">
            <para>That the Senate authorise the publication of all documents which may be laid before the Select Committee and of all evidence which may be given before it except such particular documents or evidence as the Committee determines should not be published; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(9)">
            <para>That the Committee shall ensure that the operational methods of law enforcement agencies be protected from disclosure where that would be against the public interest; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(10)">
            <para>That the Committee have power to consider the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committee on Drug Trafficking and Drug Abuse appointed during the previous session; </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(11)">
            <para>That the Committee report to the Senate as soon as possible; and </para>
          </item>
          <item label="(12)">
            <para>That the foregoing provisions of this Resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained In the Standing Orders. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>16</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I have to inform the Senate that I have received a copy of the Opening Speech delivered by His Excellency the Governor-General to both Houses of Parliament this day. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>VIETNAM</title>
          <page.no>16</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>1L5</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MURPHY, Lionel</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MURPHY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Leader of the Government. When is the Government going to take the Australian people into its confidence, at least to the same extent as President Nixon has taken his people into his confidence, and tell us in a plain and unambiguous way whether it wants to take Australian troops out of Vietnam and, if so, when those troops are going to be taken out? Will he tell us just what the programme is and clear up the confusion which has existed on this subject in every statement that has been made by the Government and which continues in the statement that has been made on behalf of the Government in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech today? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Supply</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have nothing to add at this time to what is to be found in  His  Excellency&#39;s Speech which was delivered in this place approximately J hour ago. 1 suggest that if the Leader of the Opposition wants to use the forms of the Senate he will have an opportunity in the succeeding days to raise the matter by way of debate. The Government&#39;s attitude has been expressed quite clearly in the message from the Governor-General this afternoon and it would be singularly inappropriate for me to attempt to add to it at this point of time. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>16</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ROADS</title>
          <page.no>16</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>16</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBY</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">YOUNG, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Senator YOUNG</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Shipping and Transport. By way of preface I point out that the volume of traffic on Highway No. 1 from South Australia to the Western Australian border has increased from 27,079 vehicles in 1967-68 to 33,861 vehicles in 1968-69 and that of the total in 1967-68 only 17.7% were registered in South Australia whereas 82.3% were from other states. I ask the Minister: Does this not clearly show that greater use of this section of the highway is now being made by interstate vehicles? If this is so should not this be regarded as a national project with the Commonwealth Government granting finance to seal the last 300 miles approximately from Eyre Peninsula to the Western Australian border, this being the only unsealed section of Highway No. 1 which extends from Cairns to some&#39; 700 miles north of Perth? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Civil Aviation</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I will submit that question to the Minister for Shipping and Transport in the other place. May I say in passing that, if my memory is correct, Western Australia has completed its section to the border and South Australia has yet to complete, either with its own resources or with some assistance from the Commonweatlh Government, about 300 miles. It seems to me to be a reasonable case. I shall certainly put it to the Minister and get an early reply for the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>17</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DAIRY FARM RECONSTRUCTION</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KRG</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LILLICO, Alexander</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LILLICO</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister representing the Minister for Primary Industry any information as to the progress made in inducing the States to adopt the Commonwealth Government&#39;s dairy farm amalgamation scheme? If he has not, will he see that this is made available to honourable senators, with particular reference to the reasons why some of the States have not adopted the scheme? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party>CP</party>
              <role>Minister for Air</role>
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I will discuss the honourable senator&#39;s request with the Minister tor Primary Industry and if I am able to do so I will make a statement later in the week. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>17</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MEDICAL BENEFITS</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZB</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FITZGERALD, Joseph</name>
              <name role="display">Senator FITZGERALD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I address a question to the Leader of the Government in the Senate, ls there any truth in the statement that the new health benefits scheme, originally estimated in the election policy speech of the Prime Minister to cost $16m, is now estimated to cost an extra $S8m? What is the cause of the increase? Will extra medical and hospital benefits be forthcoming to patients or will $33m of this sum go directly to doctors and almost entirely to specialists? Could not this election promise be regarded as a blatant political falsehood by the Liberal Party to win votes at the last election? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Naturally, I deprecate the preposterous suggestion that any statement made in the policy speech of the Government parties was calculated merely for the purpose of gaining votes. Since this is the first day of this session I will forgive the honourable senator for that implication. This afternoon in  His  Excellency&#39;s Speech there was quite a statement about proposed legislation for this session. In the fourth paragraph at page 13 of the Speech, copies of which have been circulated, the honourable senator will see quite significant forecasts of the legislation and what the Government proposes to do. I suggest that when the legislation does come before this House it will attract quite a spirited debate. I am sure that the Speech contains many points which members of the Opposition do not understand, and they cannot be expected to understand them at present. When they fully understand those points, they will be going as hard as they can to express their appreciation of the Government&#39;s proposals. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>17</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COMMONWEALTH PROPERTY</title>
          <page.no>17</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JTT</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DAVIDSON, Gordon</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DAVIDSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question, which is addressed to the Minister for Works, is related to Commonwealth buildings in Adelaide. Can the Minister furnish to the Senate details of Commonwealth building projects for the city of Adelaide? Can he also advise on projects for the Australian Broadcasting Commission and the Post Office in Adelaide? More particularly, can the Minister advise the Senate whether any further information is available regarding an urgently needed Commonwealth Centre or similar major Commonwealth complex in Adelaide? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>17</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBW</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role>Minister for Works</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIGHT, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Rather than answer the honourable senator&#39;s question in detail at the moment, I prefer to put out a statement as to the actual Commonwealth works being designed for and under construction in the city of Adelaide. However, I am sure the honourable senator will be interested to be reminded that we let the contract for the Waymouth Telephone Exchange, involving $7.1m, only within the last month, and that the preliminary design work is proceeding on the Adelaide Mail Exchange. There are other contracts for projects in Adelaide. The honourable senator referred specifically in his question to Commonwealth offices. The whole question of Commonwealth office accommodation has been the subject of a report by an interdepartmental committee. That report is under consideration at present and, of course, it specifically affects Adelaide. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>18</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LOSS OF MV&#39;NOONGAH</title>
          <page.no>18</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1Y</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BISHOP, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BISHOP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In directing my ques  tion to the Minister for Air I refer to bis recent statement which followed the finding of the Court of Marine Inquiry into the loss of the MV &#39;Noongah&#39;. In explaining the delays caused to Royal Australian Air Force aircraft the Minister said that a delay of1&#189; hours from the time of the alert to take-off by a RAAF Hercules aircraft on 25th August 1969 was not unreasonable. I ask: Pending the review by senior officers of the Minister&#39;s Department and of the Department of Shipping and Transport, to which he has referred, can he assure the Senate that stand-by crews and aircraft will be available for emergency occasions requiring them, such as the occasion of the sinking of the &#39;Noongah&#39; or a national disaster? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The present policy with regard to stand-by is that an aircraft is on 3 hours stand-by at night. In the case referred to by the honourable senator, the alert was given at 5.12 a.m. and an aircraft was airborne1&#189; hours later. It flew a distance of 250 miles and was on task at 7.26 a.m. In the statement referred to by the honourable senator I said thatI would be having discussions with officers of the Department of Shipping and Transport. The first of those discussions has already taken place and great benefits to the two departments concerned have been derived from that meeting. As to the second part of the honourable senator&#39;s question, we have already taken action to see that a stand-by crew is ready for occasions such as that referred to by the honourable senator when the second aircraft, taking off at midday, did not get off on time because of defects in the engine tachometer. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>18</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>CIVIL AVIATION</title>
          <page.no>18</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KSN</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MARRIOTT, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MARRIOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Civil Aviation whether he is aware that a printed Trans-Australia Airlines timetable of air services to and from Canberra omits any mention of air services to Tasmania, although the timetable indicates the services available to Perth via Melbourne, to Adelaide via Melbourne and to all the other States. Is the Minister also aware that the same printed timetable sets out that telephone bookings can be made by ringing numbers in the various capital cities but Hobart is not mentioned? Can the Minister find out whether the omission of details of air services to Tasmania by TAA is a premeditated snub to Tasmanians, or whether the previously scheduled services have indeed ceased and the Hobart booking office has been or is to be closed down? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">COTTON, Bob</name>
              <name role="display">Senator COTTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am grateful to the honourable senator for asking this question. I was not aware of these facts. I shall draw them to the attention of Trans-Australia Airlines and ask what is the position. 1 shall let the honourable senator know as soon as I possibly can. For my part, he may rest assured that I have no lack of regard for that beautiful island and its most hospitable and affectionate people. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>18</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NATIONAL SERVICE</title>
          <page.no>18</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K6F</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CAVANAGH, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator CAVANAGH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister representing the Prime Minister seen a report of a special United States Presidential Commission under the chairmanship of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Thomas</inline> Gates, former Secretary of Defence, which report stated that the draft system of national service in Australia is unnecessary, that Australia could have avoided the introduction of national service by raising pay and reorganising recruiting and that Australia has not made a concerted effort to attract additional recruits on a voluntary basis? Will the Prime Minister consider the findings of this important Commission to ascertain whether there is an alternative to the undesirable lottery conscript system as a method of attracting personnel to the Service? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>18</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I shall direct the honourable senator&#39;s question to the Prime Minister for reply. My understanding of the general position is that in the United States there was a very strong move to adopt the Australian method of conscription for national service. It was considered that the Australian method had much more to commend it than other methods being employed. However, it is a fair question that should be directed so that a considered reply can be obtained from the Prime </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">Minister&#39;s Department. I shall set out to obtain the information for the honourable senator. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>19</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Sir MAGNUS CORMACK</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the sudden interest of members of the Opposition in decisions and practices of the United States of America, I wish to pursue the matter by directing the following question to the Leader- of&#39; the Government in the Senate: In view of the presence in Canberra of <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Robert</inline> Thompson,  President  Nixon&#39;s adviser on counter insurgency in South East Asia, would the Leader of the Government in the Senate make arrangements for <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Robert</inline> to be made available to meet the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate so that the views of  President  Nixon&#39;s adviser on counter insurgency in South East Asia can illuminate some of the dark recesses in the minds of honourable senators opposite? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am aware that <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Robert</inline> Thompson is in Australia. I certainly shall see what can be done so that the Opposition - notably the Leader of the Opposition - and others in the hierarchy of the Australian Labour Party, can be made aware of his views. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>19</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBC</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLESEE, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILLESEE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct a question to the Minister for Air. I refer to the Minister&#39;s statement of 6th December in which he reported an injury to a passenger flying in a dual Mirage aircraft from Butterworth. As the Minister said that the accident was due to a known defect, I ask: Has it been the policy to allow defective aircraft to fly with or without passengers. If so, does the Minister intend to alter this policy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It has never been the policy of the Royal Australian Air Force to allow defective aircraft to fly either with or without passengers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>19</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>HUMAN RIGHTS</title>
          <page.no>19</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYA</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">O&#39;BYRNE, Justin</name>
              <name role="display">Senator O&#39;BYRNE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask a question of the Leader of the Government in the Senate. In view of the Governor-General&#39;s statement today that &#39;my Government will continue to support the principles of the United Nations&#39; will the Minister say whether the Government supports the </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para class="block">United Nations Declaration of Human Rights which provides that no country should exile a person or deprive him of the right to leave or return to his own country? </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>19</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JQQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">CORMACK, Magnus</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Sir Magnus Cormack</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I rise to a point of order. There is a formal procedure for discussing the GovernorGeneral&#39;s Speech. I do not think that at this juncture His Excellency&#39;s statement should be submitted to cross-examination. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>19</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>1L5</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MURPHY, Lionel</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Murphy</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- 1 suggest, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline> that you should take the view that the Governor-General&#39;^ Speech is so embracing that, if it were said that it should not be taken into consideration, that would exclude any discussion of the matters referred to in it and virtually no questions could be asked about anything at this stage. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>19</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KSN</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MARRIOTT, John</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Marriott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It is on the notice paper. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>19</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>1L5</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MURPHY, Lionel</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Murphy</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Of course it is on the notice paper, but if it were to be said that that excluded discussion then nothing could be discussed either positively or negatively, because the Speech is all embracing. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator O&#39;Byrne</inline> merely referred to the Speech as an introduction to his question. The burden of his question dealt really with what the Government is doing and how it is acting in the light of the fact that we have an obligation under the Declaration of Human Rights. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honourable senator is in order in asking a question seeking an explanation of the statement, but he must not in any circumstances proceed to anticipate what is further contained in the Speech. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>19</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JYA</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">O&#39;BYRNE, Justin</name>
                <name role="display">Senator O&#39;BYRNE</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I will reframe the question. In view of the Government&#39;s known violations of the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights in relation to Wilfred Burchett, will the Leader of the Government in the Senate prevail on his colleagues to ensure that no country, particularly Australia, exiles a person or deprives him of his right to leave or return to his country, and that no person shall be deprived of his nationality? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>19</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Government does not accept in the slightest the suggestion that there has been any violation by it of the Charter of the United Nations in the case referred to. A question has already been asked today of the Minister representing the Attorney-General in relation to one, Burchett. The Minister has chosen to have the question placed on notice. Therefore 1 will not be drawn into making any comment until that question has been answered in the normal way. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>20</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>USTASHI ACTIVITY</title>
          <page.no>20</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KVK</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MULVIHILL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MULVIHILL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask a question of the Minister representing the AttorneyGeneral. Has the Minister studied the serious allegations made by Melbourne journalist Vicki Banovic disclosing a resurgence of Ustashi activity? Will he take appropriate steps to curb such happenings particularly when attempts are being made to inject Fascism into legitimate religious exercises? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIGHT, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  I make it quite clear that . I do not accept any of the implications in the question. I inform the honourable senator that this matter is under the continuing consideration of the AttorneyGeneral and as heretofore appropriate steps are being taken. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>20</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MR WILFRED BURCHETT</title>
          <page.no>20</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8Y</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party>IND; AP from Aug. 1969; IND from Jan. 1970</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">TURNBULL, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator TURNBULL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I direct to the Leader of the Government in the Senate a question following on that asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Greenwood.</inline> I think the matter goes a bit beyond the responsibility of the Attorney-General. The question asked by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Greenwood</inline> was part of what was to have been my question. I ask: Because so many of us are completely ignorant in relation to Wilfred Burchett, is it possible for the Government to state whether allegations are being made against Wilfred Burchett or whether it is dealing with proven facts? What is the whole story? I am not the only person confused. Nobody seems to know what is the true position. I feel that the public and even the Government would benefit if a statement were made. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honourable senator admits that his question is identical in substance to a question asked earlier. The earlier question has been placed on notice. The Senate will sit tomorrow andI am sure the honourable senator will be in attendance. It may well be that an answer to his question will be given tomorrow. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>20</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LOSS OF M.V. &#39;NOONGAH</title>
          <page.no>20</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KTA</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>ALP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Air and follows an answer he gave to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Bishop</inline> regarding criticism of the Royal Australian Air Force by the Court of Marine Inquiry into the loss of the M.V. &#39;Noongah&#39;. Can the Minister satisfactorily explain why, after it bad taken the RAAF1&#189; hours to get a hercules aircraft off the ground in the first instance, as a result of a technical fault developing in it in the afternoon no aircraft was engaged in the search at a critical period? Why did the RAAF base at Richmond not get in touch with the Williamtown base, which was about 100 miles closer to the area under search, or even the Amberley base in order to get other aircraft into the air? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>20</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honourable senator has asked why it took 11 hours in this instance to get an aircraft into the air. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTA</name.id>
                <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                <party>ALP</party>
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Why did they not get in touch with Williamtown? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JXR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I am answering the question. The crew of the aircraft were asleep when the alarm was given. It was given at 5.10 a.m: the crew had to be clothed, fed and briefed. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KTA</name.id>
                <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
                <party>ALP</party>
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MCCLELLAND, Douglas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Douglas McClelland</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- While men were in the water? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JXR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Some honourable senators opposite think they are experts on Air Force matters. After that the crew had to be taken out to the aircraft where they had to go through the normal take-off procedure or drill. All this took 1&#189; hours. I do not think that anyone else could do it in less time. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KUS</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MILLINER, Bertie</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Milliner</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- They should be available. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>20</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JXR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The honourable senator says that aircraft should be available 24 hours of the day. Are the taxpayers of Australia prepared to keep aircraft such as the Hercules sitting on the ground at various points throughout Australia waiting for an accident at sea? <inline font-weight="bold">Senator McClelland</inline> also asked why it took the second aircraft so long to get to the search area. This aircraft was taxi-ing out to take off when a defect became apparent in one of the engines. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>21</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KPG</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Keeffe</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The back wheel fell off. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>21</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JXR</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
                <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- How many times has the honourable senator been informed at an airport that owing to a mechanical fault his aircraft would not be taking off for a certain time? The aircraft concerned was returned to its hard standing and the defect was corrected. It then taxied out to take off again and the same thing occurred. Eventually the aircraft took off. When it returned to base after the search the engine had to be changed. I have had discussions with senior officers in the Air Force about this incident and I am sure that the policy which will be followed in the future will overcome this trouble. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>21</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SHARES</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KSN</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MARRIOTT, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator MARRIOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Attorney-General. Will the Minister seek a ruling or an opinion from his learned colleague as to whether it would be necessary or wise for senators who become members of a Senate select committee on stock exchanges and share dealings in Australia to sell any shares held by them and to refrain from dealing in shares throughout the life of the committee? Could an opinion on this matter be given to the Senate prior to the debate on the proposed motion to set up such a Committee? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIGHT, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The question raises a very pertinent matter for consideration by those who seek to inquire into and form a judgment on the propriety of share transactions. The question brings to mind, I think, very pertinent and relevant considerations. I shall take pleasure in obtaining a considered formulation of opinion from the Attorney-General as guidance for those who sit in judgment upon people having business with the stock exchanges. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>21</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>STATES RECEIPTS TAX</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8N</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">TOOHEY, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator TOOHEY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct a question to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. In view of the decision of the High Court invalidating the States receipts tax, will the Minister inform the Senate of the position of those people who have paid the tax? I further ask: Is it a fact that those who have paid the tax under protest have a clear right of recovery? Does the Government intend to take any steps to assist in this recovery? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not want to give an answer at question time to the honourable senator&#39;s inquiry because in doing so I might cause hurt or false anticipation. I think the proper thing for me to do is have the question placed on notice and submitted to the Treasurer for a considered reply. As the honourable senator knows, there is a reference in the Governor-General&#39;s Speech to the fact that the Commonwealth intends to intercede and to act for the States in relation to the collection of the tax. The question of refinement about taxes that have already been paid, and indeed paid under protest, raises a very real and important issue which, I think, warrants a considered reply from the Treasurer. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>21</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>EXPO 70</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>CAK</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RAE, Peter</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RAE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Works a question. By way of preface I refer to the fact that the Department of Works has erected a fine and striking building at Osaka, Japan, for Expo 70 and to the fact that the building must be dismantled and removed from the site at the conclusion of Expo. Will the Minister investigate whether it is practicable to bring the structure to Australian for re-erection and use here as a striking piece of architecture of wholly Australian origin? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIGHT, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In respect of the exposition of our work at Osaka, it is a term of our participation that all structures shall be demolished at the end of the exhibition. We know from previous experience that this term has not always been enforced. The use to which this building may be put at the end of the Exposition is still being considered by the people controlling the exhibition. To offer an opinion off the cuff, I think it would be quite impracticable to bring the structure back to Australia. The hanging dish weighs some 220 tons. I will refer the. suggestion to the Department f Works for an engineering opinion and I will advise the honourable senator as to its views. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>21</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>REPATRIATION</title>
          <page.no>21</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>21</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXX</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRURY, Arnold</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRURY</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Repatriation whether crew members of Royal Australian Air Force Hercules aircraft who fly from Australia to Vietnam with supplies and equipment are entitled to full repatriation benefits, war service homes loans, rehabilitation facilities and war service land settlement loans if they are injured or wounded on these flights? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I will take up that question with the Minister for Repatriation and obtain an answer for the honourable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>22</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>RHODESIA</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>CJO</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WHEELDON, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WHEELDON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Leader of the Government in the Senate aware that a member of the Liberal Party in another place has publicly expressed approval that the illegal regime in Rhodesia has so far survived the sanctions imposed by the United Nations? Does the Government support that expression of opinion? If not, will the Government dissociate itself from that statement so that no damage may be caused to Australia&#39;s relations with its allies and fellow Commonwealth countries which have committed themselves wholeheartedly tothis United Nations action? If the Government will not do that, does it then place less value upon continuing friendship with Malaysia, the Prime Minister of which, Tunku Abdul Rahman, has been a leading advocate of the imposition of sanctions, than it does upon being identified with the unlawful, minority, racist regime in Salisbury? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honourable senator has accepted excerpts from a statement made by an honourable member in another place and has made judgments on them. I certainly would not make any comment about a statement that I read in the Press unless I had had the advantage of reading the full text of what had been said. I am sure that principle should be applied to statements that sometimes are attributed to members of the Opposition. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>22</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>COMMONWEALTH VEHICLES</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KMX</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GREENWOOD, Ivor</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GREENWOOD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Has the Minister for Supply inquired into the circumstances in which a Commonwealth car allegedly failed to arrive to convey the Premier of Victoria to a session of the Premiers Conference last Thursday? If so, what have his inquiries revealed? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Department of Supply has a huge fleet of vehicles which it provides in every State of the Commonwealth, but it does not provide vehicles in the Australian Capital Territory. Matters relating to the fleet of vehicles in the ACT come under the jurisdiction of the Minister for the Interior. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>22</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBC</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILLESEE, Don</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILLESEE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- My question is directed to the Minister for Air, In answer to a previous question he said that it was not policy to allow defective aircraft to fly. Why then did he, on 6th December 1969, announce that an accident to a passenger in a dual Mirage aircraft at Butterworth was due to a known defect? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXR</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>CP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DRAKE-BROCKMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-I made inquiries when this accident occurred. The defect bad become apparent on certain aircraft at a time when we were in the course of making alterations to the aircraft at the base. Because of this, certain instructions were issued that only the pilot was to fly in the aircraft until such time as every aircraft had been put through a test. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>22</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Anderson</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Mr President,</inline> mayI intercede to point out that for the time being we have no sessional orders? The question of when we shall lift arises. I understand that you have some announcements to make. Might I suggest that we have the co-operation of honourable senators in concluding at 6 o&#39;clock, allowing perhaps a few minutes before that time for you to make any statements you wish to make? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>22</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NATIONAL SERVICE</title>
          <page.no>22</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEEFFE, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEEFFE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister repre  senting the Attorney-General aware that conscientious objector Gordon Reisenleiter was released from Stuart gaol on 27th February 1970 as a result of the exercise of the prerogative of mercy by the GovernorGeneral? Will the Attorney-General now approach the Governor-General with a request that the same spirit of mercy be exercised in order to have all other conscientious objectors immediately released from gaol? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>22</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBW</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WRIGHT, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WRIGHT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honourable senator can be assured that all petitions for mercy will receive appropriate and prompt consideration. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>23</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>LIGHT AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY</title>
          <page.no>23</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>23</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K1F</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">POYSER, Arthur</name>
              <name role="display">Senator POYSER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the Minister for Supply a question. On 17th September last year I asked a question concerning the progress made in relation to Project N. I asked when production of this light aircraft was likely to commence. The Minister then advised me that the project was almost at the stage when an executive decision would be made in relation to it - to use his own words. Can he now advise me of the stage this project has reached and whether production will commence in the near future? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>23</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is true that a decision has been taken to proceed with Project N in relation to prototypes and that an amount of money - speaking from memory, it is $3.2 million- has been set aside for the building of the prototype Project N aircraft. I did issue a Press statement at the time- </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>23</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KOU</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">HENDRICKSON, Albion</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Hendrickson</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- You do not believe Press statements. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>23</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It was a Press statement under my name. The honourable senator is being very offensive. The statement was issued under my name; so flippancy is unwarranted in these circumstances. This is a serious matter, and I am answering a serious question. I point out to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Poyser,</inline> who has shown a particular interest in this matter, that a decision - a significant decision - has been taken, and that decision will be of vast importance to the technical and design people in the Government Aircraft Factories and the aircraft industry in Australia. It involves the building of prototype aircraft. I will see that before the evening is out a copy of the statement I made at the time is made available to the honourable senator. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>23</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NUCLEAR NON-PROLIFERATION TREATY</title>
          <page.no>23</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>23</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUD</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MCMANUS, Francis</name>
              <name role="display">Senator McMANUS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the Minister representing the Minister for External Affairs aware that during a powerful Press campaign to induce Australia to sign the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty it was freely stated in the Australian Press that certain top officials of the Department of External Affairs had decided that Australia should sign the Treaty and for a long period had pressed the Government to do so? Was this true? If it was true, was it a leakage from the Cabinet or the Department of External Affairs? If it was untrue, why was it not denied? Would the Government agree that it would be most improper for the chief officers of any department at any time to operate a Press campaign for the purpose of influencing government policy? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>23</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I agree that it would be most improper for a public servant to attempt, outside of his responsibility, to influence a decision of government. He is there clearly as an adviser to government. The honourable senator asks, in effect: If a statement is nagged in the Press, why is it not denied? He has had a long experience in political life and he would know, as would all of us in this place, that if one devoted one&#39;s time to chasing and denying or agreeing with all the statements that are made in the Press one would have very little else to do. The fact of the matter is that political writers choose to try to anticipate decisions and sometimes they attribute to people things that are not necessarily true. I would say that unless a statement is made in categorical terms and speaks of a certain person it is quite wrong to assume that a government has made a decision or is being influenced to make a decision by a public servant. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>As to the actual Treaty itself, Australia signed the Treaty on 27th February in each of the three depository capitals - London, Washington and Moscow. At the time of the signing we circulated to other governments a statement by the Australian Government setting out the matters that would have to be resolved before Australia could proceed to ratification. Indeed, a Press statement has been made and a document accompanied the Treaty. I do not think that at question time I need to elaborate on that. I think it is sufficient to say that although Australia signed the Treaty it has its reservations. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>23</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>1L5</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">MURPHY, Lionel</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Murphy</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- Could that be incorporated with the reservations? </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>23</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
                <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I shall have the reservations incorporated in Hansard. I would say that never at any stage has there been any departure from the view expressed by the Government that it did have reservations, which it still has. However, it feels that the signing of the Treaty by some other nations, notably West Germany and Japan, provides a prospect for the ultimate success of the Treaty. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>24</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>MAIL DELIVERIES</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>24</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3O</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BUTTFIELD, Nancy</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BUTTFIELD</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Does the Minister representing the Postmaster-General know that letters were posted to members of the Amalgamated Postal Workers Union of Australia by the union secretary informing them that union officials had negotiated a cessation of the recent postal delivery strike but telling members that no overtime was to be worked in order to clear accumulated mail? Is it correct that the delivery of these letters was delayed along with millions of others? ls it correct that a request was made by the APWU to the postal sorters asking them to locate these letters to see whether they could be speedily delivered? If this report is correct, will the Postmaster-General state whether similar requests by other business organisations or Individuals will be similarly dealt with and rapid delivery of mail guaranteed? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>24</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K28</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RANKIN, Annabelle</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Dame ANNABELLE RANKIN</name>
              </talker>
              <para>-The honourable senator has asked a series of questions concerning particular tetters being sent to members of a trade union, and the method which she believes was adopted so that delivery of the letters might be facilitated while other mail was delayed. I cannot give answers to the particular questions asked, but I shall certainly take the matter up with the Postmaster-General and get what information I can obtain for her. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>24</page.no>
        <type>special adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Anderson)</inline> agreed to: </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That the Senate at its rising adjourn until 3 p.m. tomorrow. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>STANDING ORDERS COMMITTEE</title>
        <page.no>24</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>24</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I present the first report of the Standing Orders Committee. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Ordered that the report be printed. </para>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Anderson)</inline> agreed to: </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That consideration of the report be made an order of the day for the next day of sitting. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>COMMITTEES</title>
        <page.no>24</page.no>
        <type>committee</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>24</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
            <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- I have received messages from the House of Representatives, dated 26th November 1969, advising of the appointment of members to joint statutory committees. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Public Works Committee</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Mr Corbett, Mr Fulton, Mr James, Mr Lei Johnson, Mr Kelly and Mr Whittorn</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Broadcasting of Parliamentary Proceedings Committee</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Mr Speaker, Mr Donald Cameron, Mr Drury, Mr Grassby, Mr Sherry and Mr Turnbull</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Public Accounts Committee</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
      </subdebate.1>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Mr Collard, Mr Cope, Mr Dobie, Mr Graham, Mr Hurford, Mr Jarman and Mr Robinson</title>
          <page.no>24</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Joint Select Committee on the Australian Capital Territory </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>24</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have received letters from the Prime Minister, the Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives, the Leader of the Government in the Senate and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate appointing members of the Joint Select Committee on The Australian Capital Territory. The Prime Minister has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Fox</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Hallett.</inline> The Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Daly</inline> and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr J.</inline> R. Fraser. The Leader of the Government in the Senate has appointed Senators Marriott, Maunsell and Withers, and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate has appointed Senators Devitt and Milliner. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>Joint Select Committee on the New and Permanent Parliament House </para>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>24</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>10000</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I have received letters from the Prime Minister, the  Deputy  Prime Minister, the Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives, the Leader of the Government in the Senate and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate appointing members of the Joint Select Committee on the New and Permanent Parliament House. The Prime Minister has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Erwin, Mr Fox,</inline></para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para class="block">
            <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Drury</inline>and <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Giles</inline> and, when the Prime Minister is unable to be present at meetings of the Committee, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Snedden.</inline> The  Deputy  Prime Minister has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Nixon</inline> to attend meetings of the Committee when he is unable to be present. The Leader of the Opposition in the House of Representatives has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Birrell, Mr Bryant, Mr Duthie, Mr Mclvor,</inline> and with the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate has appointed <inline font-weight="bold">Mr Barnard.</inline> The Leader of the Government in the Senate has appointed Senators McKellar and Dame Ivy Wedgwood and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate has appointed Senators Cavanagh and McClelland. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>SENATOR SIR MAGNUS CORMACK</title>
        <page.no>25</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Ministerial Statement</title>
          <page.no>25</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>25</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZQ</name.id>
              <electorate>Minister for Supply</electorate>
              <party>LP</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ANDERSON, Kenneth</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ANDERSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- by leave - I feel sure that all honourable senators will join with me in expressing congratulations to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir Magnus</inline> Cormack who was honoured by  Her  Majesty the Queen in the 1970 New Year Honours List. <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Magnus</inline> has had a long and distinguished career in the service of Australia in peace and in war and I am sure all will agree with me that this gracious honour from  Her  Majesty was richly deserved. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>25</page.no>
        <time.stamp>17:57:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para class="block">Senate adjourned at 5.57 p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>
