<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <session.header>
        <date>1929-11-20</date>
        <parliament.no>12</parliament.no>
        <session.no>1</session.no>
        <period.no>1</period.no>
        <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
        <page.no>5</page.no>
        <proof>0</proof>
    </session.header>
    <chamber.xscript>
        <para class="block">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA. </para>
        <para class="block">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES. </para>
        <para class="block">FirstSessionoftheTwelfthParliament. </para>
        <para>The House of Representatives in the Eleventh Parliament was by proclamation dissolved, as from the 16th September, 1929, and honorable Senators were discharged from attendance on that date. The Twelfth Parliament was convened for the despatch of business on the 20th November, 1929, and the First Session commenced on that day. </para>
        <para class="block">Senate. </para>
        <business.start>
            <day.start>1929-11-20</day.start>
        </business.start>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>OPENING OF THE PARLIAMENT</title>
                <page.no>5</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>The Senate met at 10.30 a.m., pursuant to the proclamation of His Excellency the Governor-General. </para>
            <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon. W. Kingsmill)</inline> took the chair. </para>
            <para>The  Clerk  read the Proclamation. </para>
            <para>The Deputies appointed by  His Excellency  the Governor-General for the opening of the Parliament, the Right Honorable <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Adrian</inline> Knox, P.O., K.C.M.G., Chief Justice of the High Court of Australia, and the Right Honorable <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Isaac</inline> Alfred Isaacs, P.O., K.C.M.G., a Justice of the High Court of Australia, having been announced by the Usher of the Black Rod, entered the chamber and took their seats on the dais. </para>
            <para>The Senior  Deputy  (the Right Honorable <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Adrian</inline> Knox), through the  Clerk,  directed the Usher to desire the attendance of the members of the House of Representatives, who being come, </para>
            <para>The SENIOR DEPUTY said- </para>
            <para>Gentlemen of the Senate and Gentlemen or the House of Representatives : </para>
            <para>His Excellency the Governor-General, not thinking fit to be present in person at this time, has been pleased to cause letters patent to issue under the Great Seal of the Commonwealth constituting us his Deputies to do in his name all thai is necessary to be performed in declaring this Parliament open, as will more fully appeal from the letters patent which will now be read - </para>
            <para>The letters patent having been read by the  Clerk, </para>
            <para>The SENIOR DEPUTY said- </para>
            <para>Gentlemen of the Senate and Gentlemen of the House of Representatives : </para>
            <para>We have it in command from the Governor-General to let you know that as soon as the members of the House of Representatives shall have been sworn, the causes of His Excellency calling this Parliament will be declared by him in person at this place; and it being necessary that a Speaker of the House of Representatives shall be first chosen, you, </para>
            <para class="block">Gentlemen of the House of Representatives, will retire to the place where you are to sit, and there proceed to the choice of some proper person to be your Speaker ; and thereafter you will present the person whom you shall so choose to His Excellency, at such time and place as he shall appoint. </para>
            <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Isaac</inline>
                Isaacs will attend in the House of Representatives for the purpose of administering the oath, or affirmation of allegiance to honorable members of that House.
            </para>
            <para>The Deputies and the members of the House of Representatives having retired, </para>
            <para class="italic">
                <inline font-style="italic">Sitting suspended from 10.45 a.m. to3 p.m.</inline>
            </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERNOR-GENERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
                <page.no>6</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>HIS EXCELLENCY THE GO</title>
                <page.no>6</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para class="block">VERNOR-GENERAL entered the chamber and,being seated, with the  President  on his right hand, a message was sent to the House of Representatives intimating that  His Excellency  desired the attendance of honorable members in the Senate Chamber, who, being come with their  Speaker, </para>
            <para>HIS EXCELLENCY was pleased to deliver the following speech: - </para>
            <para>Gentlemen of the Senate, and Gentlemen of the House of Representatives - </para>
            <para>You are called together to deliberate upon matters of urgent importance to the well-being of the Commonwealth. </para>
            <para>My Advisers, in the knowledge that they have received at the recent general election for the House of Representatives a mandate from the people to maintain the federal principle in industrial legislation, will submit to you early next year a measure designed to improve the working of the Federal Conciliation and Arbitration Act. </para>
            <para>Impressed with the desirability of seeking the opinion of those who have had practical experience in the working of industrial legislation, my Advisers have extended invitations to representatives of employers and employees in industry to meet in conference for the purpose of exchanging views, and of suggesting improvements whereby more cordial relations among the parties to industry may be facilitated. </para>
            <para>My Ministers have been greatly concerned over the long-drawn out dispute in the coal-mining industry on the northern field of New South Wales. Deeply conscious of the suffering that has followed on the closing of the mines over so long a period, they have devoted themselves most earnestly to the problem of bringing the parties together again in order that the hardships and distress of the miners and their dependants may be ended as soon as possible, and that the Commonwealth may no longer have to bear the economic loss consequent upon a protracted stoppage of work in one of the nation&#39;s most important industries. My Ministers, therefore, arranged for the summoning of a compulsory conference of the parties under the provisions of the Industrial Peace Act of 1920. As the conference has not met with the success that was hoped for, every avenue will be explored, and my Advisers&#39; most earnest efforts will be continued, in an endeavour to bring the trouble to a satisfactory and early solution. </para>
            <para>A communication has been forwarded to His Majesty&#39;s Government in Great Britain setting out the facts regarding the serious state of unemployment in the Commonwealth and suggesting the suspension of the assisted passage clauses of the &#163;34,000,000 migration agreement between His Majesty&#39;s Government in Great Britain and the Government of the </para>
            <para class="block">Commonwealth  of Australia. Upon receipt of a reply setting out fully the views of His Majesty&#39;s Government in Great Britain, my Ministers propose to consult with the Governments of the States on the whole question of assisted migration. </para>
            <para>The industrial conditions have impelled my Ministers to further restrict the admission of foreign immigrants to the Common wealth. </para>
            <para>My Ministers propose to co-ordinate the functions of the Development and Migration Commission, which was established in accordance with the Development and Migration Act of 1926, with those of the Commonwealth Council of Scientific and Industrial Research; and this work will be brought under the direct control of the department of the Prime Minister. </para>
            <para>My Ministers do not contemplate the creation of a Bureau of Economic Research as provided for in the Economic Research Act, to which I gave my assent on 22nd March last. In view of the present financial position, it is the desire of my Ministers to avoid, as far as possible, the creation of new departments of a semi-governmental character. By curtailing expenditure of this kind, more money will be available, for developmental work. </para>
            <para>It has been the usual practice for a newly-elected Ministry to meet Parliament and ask for an adjournment in order that its legislative programme may be prepared. On this occasion, however, my Ministers are faced with the necessity of bringing before you immediately revised Estimates for the financial year and certain urgent measures for the purpose of meeting the Commonwealth&#39;s financial obligations. A Loan Bill will be submitted to you giving authority for the raising and spending of loan moneys for the carrying out of public works. A measure to amend the rates of taxation imposed on incomes in the Commonwealth will also be placed before you at an early date. </para>
            <para>A bill to make better provision for the control of gold reserves in the Commonwealth will be submitted to you. </para>
            <para>A bill authorizing special grants to the States of South Australia and Tasmania will be submitted for your consideration. </para>
            <para>The Grafton-South Brisbane Railway Act of 1924 appropriated &#163;3,500,000 to carry out the agreement for the construction of the railway. In an amending act of 1926, this amount was increased to &#163;4,000,000. Owing to altered industrial conditions, and other unforeseen expenditure, a further sum of &#163;350,000 will be required to complete this work. A bill authorizing the . additional expenditure that is necessary will be submitted. </para>
            <para>The revised schedule of customs and excise duties, which was laid on the table of the House of Representatives on 22nd August of this year, will expire automatically on 20th December next. You will shortly be asked to consider a further revision of the tariff schedule. </para>
            <para>Owing to reduction in the price of wool, the prospects of an unfavorable wheat harvest and other causes, the Commonwealth is faced with a difficult period. These causes, important as they are in our economic life, are, however, seasonal in character. There is no reason to believe that a continuance of these conditions is likely and there should be a return to normal prosperity in the coming year. In the meantime, the public revenues of the Commonwealth are being adversely affected. </para>
            <para>In accordance with the statement of policy enunciated to the people at the recent elections, my Ministers decided to suspend compulsory military training. A general review of the present provisions for the defence of the Commonwealth has become necessary and consultations between my Ministers and officers of the Naval, Military and Air Forces, comprising the Council of Defence, have taken place. </para>
            <para>The Council of Defence unanimously agreed to the maintenance of the same army organization as has existed hitherto as a nucleus. The number of men necessary will be raised by voluntary enlistment, such a system being already provided for under the Defence Act. The question of maintaining a separate organization for the Air Force, having been brought under the notice of my Ministers by officers of the Defence Department, the Defence Committee was instructed to investigate arid report to the Council of Defence. No decision was arrived at by the council, the matter being postponed pending a comprehensive review of the position of the Air Force. My Ministers have, however, asked for a report on the possibilities of co-ordinating the work of the Air Force with that of civil aviation. </para>
            <para>My Advisers, having warmly supported previous movements to bring about limitation of armaments as a step towards international peace, welcome the invitation to be represented at the Five-power Naval Conference to be opened in London in January. They will appoint a representative to attend on behalf of Australia, in the fervent hope that the further efforts that will be made to remove some of the obstacles that now impede limitation of armaments will meet with success. </para>
            <para>My Ministers look forward to the Imperial and Economic Conferences to be held next year with the sincere hope that they will be able to co-operate with His Majesty&#39;s Government in Britain to the lasting benefit of the Commonwealth of Australia and the other members of the British Commonwealth of Nations. </para>
            <para>Shortly after the Christmas recess, which necessarily will impose a break in the work of the Parliamentary session, you will be called together again. A more detailed statement of the legislative programme of ray Advisers will then be made to you. </para>
            <para>In the earnest hope that Divine Providence may guide your deliberations and further the welfare of the people of the Commonwealth, I now leave you to the discharge of your high and important duties. </para>
            <para>His Excellency the Governor-General and the members of the House of Representatives having retired, </para>
            <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon. W. Kingsmill)</inline> took the chair and read prayers. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debate.info>
                    <title>NEW MINISTRY</title>
                    <page.no>8</page.no>
                <type> Motion </type>
                </debate.info>
                <para>Representation in the Senate. </para>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>8</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role>Vice-President of the Executive Council</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - <inline font-style="italic">(By leave)</inline> - I desire to announce to the Senate that, consequent upon the resignation of the Right Honorable S. M. Bruce, C.H., P.C., M.C., as Prime Minister,  His Excellency  the Governor-General commissioned <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. J.</inline> H. Scullin, M.P., to form a Ministry. The Ministry, which was sworn in on the 22nd October, 1929, is as follows : - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <para>Treasurer - Hon. Edward Granville Theodore, M.P</para>
                    <para>Vice-President of t.he Executive Council - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the Hon.</inline> John Joseph Daly. </para>
                    <para>Attorney-General - Hon. Frank Brennan, M.F</para>
                    <para>Postmaster-General and Minister of State for Works and Railways - Hon. Joseph Aloysius Lyons, M.P</para>
                    <para>Minister of State for Trade and Customs - Hon. James Edward Fenton, M.P</para>
                    <para>Minister of State for Home Affairs - Hon. Arthur Blakeley, M.P</para>
                    <para>Minister of Statu for Health and Min- ister of State for Repatriation - Hon. Frank Anstey, M.P. </para>
                    <para>Minister of State for Defence - Hon. Albert Ernest Green, M.P</para>
                    <para>Minister of State for Markets and Transport - Hon. Parker John Moloney, M.P</para>
                    <para>Assistant Minister - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator the Hon.</inline> John- Barnes. </para>
                    <para>Assistant Minister - Hon. Francis Michael Forde, M.P</para>
                    <para>Assistant Minister - Hon. John Albert Beasley, M.P. i have also to announce that the fol.lowing will be the arrangements with regard to the &#39; representation of Departments in the Senate : - </para>
                    <para>The Departments of the Prime Minister, Treasurer, Attorney-General, Trade and Customs and Markets and Transport will be represented by myself, and. the Departments of the Postmaster-General, Minister for Works and Railways, Home Affairs, Health, Repatriation and Defence, will be represented by the Assistant Minister for Works and Railways <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Barnes).</inline></para>
                </speech>
                <question>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>9</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>KRZ</name.id>
                            <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
                            <party />
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">LYNCH, Patrick</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator LYNCH</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- I ask the VW  President  of the Executive Council <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Daly),</inline> whether the representation of the Government in the Senate by only two Ministers, is to continue or whether that number will be increased in order to give this chamber a reasonable opportunity to handle the same volume of business that is undertaken in another place? </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>9</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate />
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role />
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>- The answer to the honorable senator&#39;s question depends upon whether or not we have a double dissolution. </para>
                    </talk.start>
                </answer>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>LEADER AND DEPUTY LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION</title>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                PEARCE (Western Australia)  &#91;3.23&#93;. -
                <inline font-style="italic">(By leave) -</inline>
                I desire to announce that I have been elected leader of the Opposition in the Senate,
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator &#39; Sir William</inline>
                Glasgow,  Deputy  Leader, and
                <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Foll,</inline>
                Opposition Whip.
            </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>DEATH OF MR. W. J. MCWILLIAMS, M.P</title>
                <page.no>9</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>9</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                        <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                        <party>ALP</party>
                        <role>Vice-President of the Executive Council</role>
                        <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>
                        <inline font-style="italic">.- (By leave)- I</inline>
                        move-
                    </para>
                </talk.start>
                <quote>
                    <para>That the Senate expresses its sincere regret at the death of William James Mcwilliams, member for the Division of Franklin, in the House of Representatives, and places on record  it8  appreciation of his meritorious public service, and tenders its &#39;profound sympathy to his widow and family - in their bereavement. </para>
                </quote>
                <para class="block">
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Lt</inline>
                    is fitting that on the occasion of the first sitting of the Senate since the lamented death of
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Mcwilliams</inline>
                    we should express our sense of the great loss which the Commonwealth has sustained by his demise, our appreciation of the eminent public service he rendered throughout a long and honorable, career both in the State Parliament of Tasmania and also in this, the national Parliament, and our own personal regret at the passing of a respected Parliamentary colleague.  His  public Life was distinguished not merely by the ability with which he performed his duties, but even more so by the unfailing courtesy and kindness of heart that he ever displayed. To hie widow and family we can but offer our respectful sympathy in the hope that the burden of their sorrow may be lightened by the knowledge that it is shared by a multitude of friends. When time shall have healed the wound they may derive consolation from the fact that
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Mcwilliams</inline>
                    by his long and devoted public .service to his fellow men deserved that it should be said of him that -
                </para>
                <list type="lowerroman-dotted">
                    <item label=".">
                        <para>. Nature might stand up </para>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <para>And say to all the world, &#34;This wau a man t &#34; </para>
                <para>
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Sir GEORGE</inline>
                    PEARCE (Western Australia)  &#91;3.27&#93;. -  I second the motion moved by the Vice-President of the Executive Council
                    <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Daly),</inline>
                    and desire to say on behalf of honorable senators sitting on this side of the chamber that we associate ourselves with the words that have fallen from his lips. In the presence of death, differences which arise in the heat of fierce party conflict are forgotten. We join with the Leader of the Government in the Senate in expressing our sympathy with the relatives of the late honorable member who passed away in such tragic circumstances.
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. McWilliams</inline>
                    was associated for a long period with the Federal Parliament and, although not a member of this Chamber, was personally knownto most honorable senators, who learned to respect and esteem him. I particularly associate myself with the sympathetic references made by the Leader of the Senate to the widow and children of the late honorable member. To them the blow will indeed be severe; but, with
                    <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Daly,</inline>
                    I trust that when the first hitter pangs of their sorrow shall have passed, this expression of sympathy from his fellow legislators may he of some comfort to them.
                </para>
            </speech>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>10</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>KUP</name.id>
                        <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">MILLEN, John</name>
                        <name role="display">Senator MILLEN</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>. - As a representative of Tasmania, I wish to associate myself with the remarks that have fallen from the lips of the honorable the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Daly).</inline> In the hurly-burly of politics many incidents occur, some of them regrettable, but the touch of death has a chastening effect and removes all rancour. The expressions of sympathy directed to the late honorable member&#39;s widow and family are tendered with the utmost sincerity. The late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. McWilliams</inline> had a wide Parliamentary experience, and his accumulated wisdom, particularly in reference to Tasmania, was frequently drawn upon by his fellow legislators. One may say that the word &#34; Tasmania &#34; was written large across his heart. He was extremely anxious that everything that could be done should be done to advance the prosperity of the island State, and his death will be a severe loss to it. </para>
                </talk.start>
                <para>Question resolved in the affirmative, honorable senators standing in their places. </para>
            </speech>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>GOVERN OR-GEN ERAL&#39;S SPEECH</title>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Address-in-reply. </para>
            <speech>
                <talk.start>
                    <talker>
                        <page.no>10</page.no>
                        <time.stamp />
                        <name.id>10000</name.id>
                        <electorate />
                        <party />
                        <role />
                        <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                        <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                        <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
                        <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
                    </talker>
                    <para>- I have to report that I have received a copy of the speech just delivered by  His Excellency  the Governor-Generalat the opening of the Parliament. For greater accuracy and the convenience of honorable senators it will be printed and copies distributed to them. </para>
                </talk.start>
            </speech>
            <subdebate.1>
                <subdebateinfo>
                    <title>Ordered -</title>
                    <page.no>10</page.no>
                </subdebateinfo>
                <quote>
                    <para>That the consideration of the Speech be an order of the day for the next day of sitting. </para>
                </quote>
            </subdebate.1>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                <title>HOUR OF MEETING</title>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <type>miscellaneous</type>
            </debateinfo>
            <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Daly)</inline> agreed to - </para>
            <para>That  the  Senate, at its rising, adjourn  till to-morrowat3p.m. </para>
        </debate>
        <debate>
            <debateinfo>
                    <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
                    <page.no>10</page.no>
                <type> Motion </type>
                </debateinfo>
                <speech>
                    <talk.start>
                        <talker>
                            <page.no>10</page.no>
                            <time.stamp />
                            <name.id>JTL</name.id>
                            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
                            <party>ALP</party>
                            <role>Vice-President of the Executive Council</role>
                            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
                            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                            <name role="metadata">DALY, John</name>
                            <name role="display">Senator DALY</name>
                        </talker>
                        <para>. - As a mark of respect to the memory of the late <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. McWilliamsI</inline> move - </para>
                    </talk.start>
                    <quote>
                        <para>That the Senate do now  adjourn. </para>
                    </quote>
                    <para>Question resolvedto the affirmative. </para>
                </speech>
        </debate>
        <adjournment>
            <adjournmentinfo>
                <page.no>10</page.no>
                <time.stamp>15:35:00</time.stamp>
            </adjournmentinfo>
            <para>Senate  adjourned at  3.35 p.m. </para>
        </adjournment>
    </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>