<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<hansard xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../hansard.xsd" version="2.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <session.header>
    <date>1921-12-01</date>
    <parliament.no>8</parliament.no>
    <session.no>1</session.no>
    <period.no>0</period.no>
    <chamber>SENATE</chamber>
    <page.no>13448</page.no>
    <proof>0</proof>
  </session.header>
  <chamber.xscript>
    <para class="block">Senate. </para>
    <business.start>
      <day.start>1921-12-01</day.start>
      <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">President (Senator the Hon.</inline> T.  Givens)  took the chair at 3 p.m., and read prayers. </para>
    </business.start>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13448</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>WASHINGTON DISARMAMENT CONFERENCE</title>
          <page.no>13448</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Transmission of Senate&#39;s Resolutions to Senator Harding</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13448</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KRZ</name.id>
              <electorate>WESTERN AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYNCH, Patrick</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LYNCH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the VicePresident of the Executive Council whether the terms of the resolution carried by the Senate on the 24th ultimo, embodying good wishes to the  President  of the United States of America in connexion with the work now being done at Washington, have been transmitted to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Harding,</inline> and, if so, whether .any reply has been received from that gentleman? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13448</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role>Vice-President of the Executive Council</role>
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I shall make inquiries, and will try to supply an answer to the honorable senator&#39;s question later in the day. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13448</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K18</name.id>
              <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BAKHAP, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BAKHAP</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I should like to ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council, in connexion with .our attitude towards the United States of America and the Disarmament Conference now being held at &#34;Washington, if, when investigating the matter of the transmission of the resolution carried on the motion of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Lynch,</inline> he will also take into consideration the comprehensive terms of the resolution carried at my instigation, and will find out whether it may be transmitted at least to <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Pearce</inline> for presentation to the  President  of the United States of America ? </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13448</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K3E</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
                <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I shall undertake the duty with pleasure. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13448</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEFENCE ESTIMATES</title>
          <page.no>13448</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13448</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JZD</name.id>
              <electorate>QUEENSLAND</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOLL, Hattil</name>
              <name role="display">Senator FOLL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of the discussion likely to take place on the Defence Estimates, I ask the Vice-President &#34; of the Executive Council whether some arrangement cannot be made to secure the presence in this Chamber of the Acting Minister for Defence to supply honorable senators with any information they may desire in connexion with the work of the Defence .Department ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13449</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>OBLIGATIONS TO RETURNED SOLDIERS</title>
          <page.no>13449</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Alleged Repudiation by the Government. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate>SOUTH AUSTRALIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the VicePresident of the Executive Council if he is aware of any circumstance which would justify a Minister of the Crown in making a statement that the Commonwealth Government evidently intended to a large extent to repudiate their obligations to returned soldiers? Is there any justification for such a statement? Is the Minister aware of any reasons arising from the relations between the Government of South Australia and the Commonwealth Government to justify a Minister of the Crown in making such a sweeping assertion? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not believe that there is any justification for the statement, but I should like the honorable senator to give notice of his question, in order that it might be more fully replied to. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13449</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>NEW GUINEA TERRITORY</title>
          <page.no>13449</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Prospecting at Rabaul. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYG</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ELLIOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Arising out of a question I asked last week, I ask the Vice-President of the Executive Council whether his attention has been directed to a paragraph which appeared in yesterday&#39;s <inline font-style="italic">Age,</inline> in which it was announced that a certain company had, through its representatives, pegged out certain mining claims at Rabaul, although the Minister assured us that until the policy of the Government in connexion with prospecting in New Guinea was announced no one would be permitted to carry out prospecting operations there. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am as deeply interested in the subject of his question as is <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> himself. I feel sure that no one has received a permit from the Department to carry out prospecting work in New Guinea. I hope that the Territory will be open to prospecting by all Britishers within a very short time. I have sent for the newspaper, in order to acquaint myself with the terms of the paragraph referred to, and I shall follow itup by ascertaining what has been done in the matter. It will take a few days to find out whether such a company as is referred to is in existence, and is working in New Guinea, as it will be necessary to send a wireless message to the Administrator. The settlement of the matter will not be delayed a moment longer than can be avoided. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13449</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>SETTLEMENT OF RETURNED SOLDIERS: QUEENSLAND</title>
          <page.no>13449</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>SenatorFOLL. - I ask the VicePresident of the Executive Council whether he is aware of the fact that a number of returned soldier settlers in Queensland have recently had to abandon their farms; or are talking of doing so, because they are unaible to make a living on them? Does the honorable senator know that the Queensland Minister of Lands has made an announcement that no further applications for land will be received from returned soldiers ? Is this in accordance&#39; with the agreement entered into between the Commonwealth Government and the Government of Queensland ? Will the Commonwealth Government endeavour, by some means or other, before making money available to the State Governments, to see that lands allotted to returned soldiers are more suitable for soldier settlement than some of the land thrown open to them in the past? </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I believe that at the recent Premiers&#39; Conference some modifications of the original agreement with the State Governments were made, but I am not in a position to say what they were. If the honorable senator will give notice of his question, I will see whether it is possible to supply an official statement showing what are the terms of the present contract between the Commonwealth and State Governments in connexion with the land settlement of returned soldiers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13449</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>WAR SERVICE HOMES&#39; COMMISSION</title>
          <page.no>13449</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Charges by Messrs. Ashworth and Caldwell. </para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13449</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Senator ELLIOTT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the VicePresident of the Executive Council, in view of the controversy which is being carried on in the press between <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Ashworth</inline> and the War Service&#39; Homes Commission relating to the Caldwell case, would it be possible to have the whole of the file placed on the  table of the Senate, so that honorable senators may have an opportunity of looting into it for themselves? I understand that some inquiry was made by the Public Accounts Committee, but <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Caldwell</inline> claims that he was not allowed to crossexamine witnesses. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <para>The <inline font-weight="bold">PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. T. Givens)</inline> .  - Order ! The honorable senator should not make a statement of that kind in asking a. question. </para>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13450</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JYG</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Harold</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I wished to explain the reason for my request. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">PRESIDENT, The</name>
              <name role="display">The PRESIDENT</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator offered more than an explanation. He repeated a statement by <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Caldwell.</inline> The honorable senator should know that he is not entitled to make a statement in asking a question, and, that being so, it is quite clear that an outsider like <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Caldwell</inline> should not be allowed to make a statement through the honorable senator. </para>
          </talk.start>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13450</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>JYG</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Harold</name>
                <name role="display">Senator ELLIOTT</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- It will serve my purpose if the Minister will undertake to lay on the table of the Senate the file dealing with the matter, including the correspondence between <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Caldwell</inline> and the Minister for Repatriation. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask the honorable senator to give notice of his question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13450</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>DEFENCE DEPARTMENT</title>
          <page.no>13450</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Dismissal of Returned Soldiers</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2C</name.id>
              <electorate>VICTORIA</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BOLTON, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator BOLTON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Minister for Defence, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Is it a fact that, owing to retrenchment insisted on by the House of Representatives, the Government are dismissing a considerable number of employees in the Defence Department; if so, will not such action seriously impair the efficiency pf that Department? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>Do the proppsed dismissals affect returned men; if so, will the Government arrange that all returned men so dismissed be employed in other Departments where the House of Representatives has authorized expenditure? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answers are - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Action had been taken to dispense with a certain number of temporary employees, but such action has now been suspended in accordance with the statement made by the right honorable the Prime Minister yesterday in reply to a question by the honorable member for Wentworth (Mr.Marks) in the House of Representatives. The efficiency of the Department in the prosecution of the present policy would be affected adversely by a proportion of such dismissals. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>The dismissals would affect returned men. The second part of the question of the honorable senatoT will be brought to the notice of the Prime Minister. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <para>SenatorFOLL asked the Minister representing the Minister for Defence, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Has he seen a statement appearing in the Brisbane press that forty returned soldiers have been dismissed, and, as a consequence, a large amount of very valuable stores has been left unguarded? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>Is this in accordance with fact? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="3.">
              <para>If forty lower-paid returned soldiers have been dismissed from Victoria Barracks, Brisbane, and less supervision will be necessary, is it the intention of the Government to likewise retrench higher-paid officers? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13450</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K3E</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
                <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- The answers are - 1 and 2. Action had been taken to dispense with a certain number of temporary employees, but such action has now been suspended in accordance with the statement made by the right honorable the Prime Minister yesterday in reply to a question by the honorable member for Wentworth <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. Marks)</inline> in the House of Representatives. As a result of such dismissals, the Department would be in some difficulty to provide adequate protection for their stores. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="3.">
              <para>The dismissal of these men would npt necessitate the retrenchment of higher-paid permanently-employed <inline font-style="italic">personnel,</inline> the services of whom are still required. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>QUESTION</title>
        <page.no>13450</page.no>
        <type>Questions</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>PUBLIC ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE</title>
          <page.no>13450</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Powers of Inquiry</para>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KRZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYNCH, Patrick</name>
              <name role="display">Senator LYNCH</name>
            </talker>
            <para>asked the Minister representing the Attorney-General, <inline font-style="italic">upon notice -</inline></para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Whether the Public Accounts Committee have adequate powers for full and complete inquiry into the charges appearing in the press concerning the administration of the War Service Homes Sub-department? </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>If the Public Accounts Committee have not adequate powers, in what respect are their powers deficient? </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </speech>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13450</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>1</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The answers are - </para>
          </talk.start>
          <list type="decimal-dotted">
            <item label="1.">
              <para>Yes ; so far as any such charges are relevant to any inquiry before the Committee. </para>
            </item>
            <item label="2.">
              <para>See answer to No. 1. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PUBLIC SERVICE BILL</title>
        <page.no>13450</page.no>
        <type>bill</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>
        <inline font-style="italic">In Committee</inline>(Consideration resumed from 11th November, <inline font-style="italic">vide</inline> page 12694) : </para>
      <para>Postponed clause 38 - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>Any person not more than fifty years of age, who has served in the Permanent Naval Forces of the Commonwealth for the full period for which he enlisted or engaged, and has a satisfactory record, shall be eligible for appointment by the Board, without examination, to any office in the Fourth Division in the Department of Trade and Customs. </para>
      </quote>
      <para class="block">Upon which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Thomas</inline> had moved, by way of amendment - </para>
      <quote>
        <para>That all the words after the word &#34;Division&#34; be left out. </para>
      </quote>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13451</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  Honorable senators will remember that this clause was postponed because there was some doubt as to whether  it  made it quite clear that preference was to be given to naval men who had seen active service, and not to men who bad served only in the naval depots and had never left Australia. That is the intention, and I have an amendment to submit which will extend the operation of the clause to the Health Department. I believe that this will be in accordance with the desire of honorable senators. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13451</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K8L</name.id>
            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
            <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  The purpose of my amendment is to enable persons who have been in the Permanent Naval Forces in the Commonwealth, and are not more than fifty years of age, to become eligible for appointment in any Division of the Public Service. The clause limits their eligibility for appointment by the Board without examination to any office in. the Fourth Division of the Department of Trade and Customs. Why should appointments be limited to that Division? Why should not such persons be eligible for appointment to any Division of the Public Service? </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13451</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  The persons referred to are eligible for appointment to any position they may be capable of filling. The purpose of my amendment is to give them special privileges in Departments that are related. In sub-clause 2 of clause 79 there is provision that in making any appointment under clause 39 preference shall, subject to competency, be given to returned soldiers. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8L</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  But the clause we are discussing does not deal with returned soldiers at &#39;all. It relates to members of the Permanent Naval Forces of the Commonwealth&#39;. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Sailors and nurses come under the definition of returned soldiers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8L</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  If clause 79 covers clause 38, plus something more, where is the necessity for clause 38 at all? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Foster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Suppose two men, one from the Permanent Naval Forces and the other a returned soldier, apply for a position. Under clause 38 the returned soldier would get the preference. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- A man who has seen active service in the Navy will get preference over men of the Permanent Naval Forces serving in Australian depots. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Foster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Clause 38 deals with the eligibility of persons who have not been, to the war.. Clause 79 is a preference clause. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13451</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K8L</name.id>
            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
            <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I am afraid I cannot see any light. As I understand it, clause 38 simply means that certain persons who have served in the Permanent Naval Forces for a stated period will be eligible for appointment without examination  to  any office in the Fourth Division of the Department of Trade and Customs. Why this limitation? In the Post Office, for instance, sailors who are sail makers may be employed on the mail bags. They may have served their full time in the Navy, &#39;and whilst they would be eligible for appointment without examination  to  the Fourth Division of the Department of Trade and Customs under this clause, they would not be eligible without examination for appointment to the Fourth Division of the Post and Telegraph Department. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  They would be eligible for any position they are capable of filling in the Service. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8L</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Not under clause 38, because they may not have gone to the war. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The men who went to the war will get preference. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13451</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8L</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am afraid I cannot understand the position; but I suppose I shall have to be satisfied with the Minister&#39;s statement. I ask leave to withdraw my amendment. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn. </para>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> agreed to - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the following words be added to the clause : - &#34; or in the Department of Health.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Clause, as amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>Postponed clause 39 - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>Where the Board reports to the GovernorGeneral that it is not desirable that the examination system shall be applied in relation to an appointment to a specified position, or in relation to appointments to a specified class of positions, in the Fourth Division, the Board may appoint &#39;a person without examination to that position, or to a position in that class, under such conditions as are prescribed. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the words &#34;under such conditions as are prescribed &#34; be left out, with a view to insert in lieu thereof the words &#34; and if the Board so orders, that person shall be exempt from compliance with the life assurance provisions of this Act.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13452</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>.- The deletion of the words suggested by the Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Russell)</inline> may result in certain members of the Public Service being unfairly treated by appointments being made to the Fourth Division without examination. I may mention the case of an officer in the Fifth Division who was temporarily appointed to the Fourth Division, and then transferred into the Third Division over the heads of other officers who had served a longer period. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Was he a capable officer ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- His capacity would be tested by examination. If the clause is amended in the manner suggested it will give the Board power to promote officers to higher positions without examination, and to overlook officers in a lower grade. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLU</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GLASGOW, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Sir Thomas Glasgow</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- If promotions are made according to merit, are they not justified ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Favoritism is sometimes shown. It can operate in another way. A public servant may prove his capabilities by passing an examination, but if appointments are made without his knowledge he has no opportunity ot applying. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There must be an initial qualification. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Quite so; but an officer may be compelled to remain in a position until he persuades some one to recommend his promotion. It is only bv examination that the capabilities of officers can be ascertained. An engineer connected with the Post and Telegraph Department may possess considerable practical experience, and if tested by examination could prove his worth, whilst another man who has had little experience might be placed over his head-. Should there not be an examination to test the capabilities of such officers? If the clause is amended in the manner suggested it will enable preference to be shown, and, although in this instance I shall be acting contrary to my usual practice, I intend to vote for the retention of the words. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13452</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KKH</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
            <name role="display">Senator FOSTER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - This clause deals with the appointment of officers&#34; without examination, and the retention of the words. &#34; under such conditions as are prescribed&#34; would lead to unnecessary inconvenience. It mav be necessary to appoint an officer to a certain Division, but unless one possessed the knowledge of a prophet it would be impossible to prescribe the conditions for an examination. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13452</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Senior</inline> seems to have misunderstood the position. The object of the preceding clause is to give absolute preference to members of the Naval Forces who have seen active service during the war, and is limited to the Fourth Division. It refers solely to new appointments, and has nothing whatever to do with promotions. It would be unreasonable to suggest that a man of fortyeight or forty-nine years of age should sit for an. examination before being appointed as a warder, or a watchman in the Quarantine Department. A man may have lost his fingers when on active service, and, although unsuited for certain classes of work, would be quite capable of acting as a watchman. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Senior</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- But the clause is not limited to such cases. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Those employed in the Fourth Division are generally mechanics, warders, carpenters, labourers, or watchmen, and it is unnecessary for them to pass an examination before being appointed. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Senior</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There are others, apart from those mentioned by the Minister, employed in the Fourth Division. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13452</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Men who have seen active service in the Naval Forces would be peculiarly suited for service in the Quarantine Department. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Senior</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  It will also affect engineers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Foster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  An engineer has a certificate which is a sufficient guarantee of his capabilities. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is  so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13453</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I do not wish to see this clause amended in such a way that appointments can be made on any other basis than that of ability. If the different classes of work were specified in the clause I would withdraw my objection to the amendment; but the provision is so wide that there is a possibility of promotions being made on other than merit. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13453</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - A similar provision has been in the Commonwealth Public Service Act for seventeen or eighteen years, and now, when an effort is being made to give preference to those who have been on active service with the Naval Forces, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Senior</inline> raises an objection. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Senior</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  It is unfair of the Minister to say that I am showing any opposition to their appointment. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator wishes to compel men fifty years of age to pass an examination whereas that has never been the practice in connexion with appointments to the Fourth Division. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2C</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BOLTON, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Bolton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Does the Fourth Division consist entirely of ex-service men ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No; it comprises these following such occupations as those I have mentioned. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2C</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">BOLTON, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Bolton</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Under the Minister&#39;s proposal they could be appointed without examination. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K2L</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">REID, Matthew</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Reid</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  They are all to be taken on their merits, in the Fourth Division. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Yes, they are mostly tradesmen. We say that a mau. who has served in the Navy would be particularly handy for work, say, a.t a quarantine station. Any soldier, sailor, or nurse, with the necessary qualifications, is to be eligible for any position in the (Civil Service.  </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Foster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  There is no mention in the clause of returned soldiers or sailors. The clause deals with anybody. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Clause 79, which has to be read in conjunction with clause 39, provides for preference to returned soldiers, and &#39; &#39; returned soldier &#39; &#39; is defined as including nurses and sailors who have been on active service. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13453</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  Turning to clause 2-2, we find that the Fourth Division includes all officers who are not included in the First, Second, or Third Divisions. It embraces nearly all the postal sorters, a large number of officers in the Customs Department, and men who in status are just below the clerical stait. Able men may be in the Service for forty years, and still be in the Fourth Division. Clause 39 makes no mention of naval men or returned soldiers, but says that any person may be appointed to the Fourth. Division without examination. I object to the door to the Civil Service being opened so wide that anybody may be appointed to it, irrespective of his suitability, whereas in ordinary cases an examination has to be passed. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13453</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council&#34;</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  Under the present law, there is power to make appointments without examination. Clause 34 D (1) of the Commonwealth Public Service Act states&#39; - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>Where the Commissioner reports to the GovernorGeneral that it is desirable Hint the system of examination should be applied in relation to an appointment to a specified position, or appointments to a specified class of positions, in the General Division, there may be appointed to that position, or to a position in that class, a person who has not passed the prescribed examination. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">The object of the present provision is to give pos-tiona to the men who most serve them. Men who are already in the Service cannot be applicants for new appointments. They cannot occupy two positions at the same time. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JYG</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ELLIOTT, Harold</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Elliott</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  If positions were open without examination, it would be possible for the Board to give -preference to their friends. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13453</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Soldiers have not previously had to pass examinations for appointment in the Fourth Division. Has that provision done any harm to Australia? <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Senior,</inline> seems to be suspicious that the door will be opened too wide. The object is to give preference to those who have served their country <inline font-style="italic">well.</inline> and I ask the honorable senator to have confidence in the Administration. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator SENIOR</inline>(South Australia) have confidence in him, but I would point out that he is unable to give a promise as to what policy may be adopted by any of his successors in office. The clause does not limit the choice to returned soldiers, sailors and nurses, but it says that the Fourth Division can be filled anyhow and from anywhere. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13454</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Absolutely no. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13454</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K2C</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">BOLTON, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator BOLTON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>.- How will this provision agree with clause 33, which distinctly says that there shall be an examination for appointment to the Fourth Division, although the educational examination shall be of an elementary character? If we accept the amendment, it means that, notwithstanding clause 33, the Board may appoint persona to the Fourth Division, whether they are returned soldiers or not. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13454</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  All applicants have had to pass an examination, so we have had to make special provision for soldiers. Some soldiers have been gassed, and the insurance companies charge an extra 10 per cent.on account of their physical condition. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13454</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKH</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">FOSTER, George</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Foster</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Soldiers and sailors have nothing to do with this clause. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13454</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- If they have war injuries, and cannot obtain insurance at ordinary rates, we wish to exempt them from examination. Are we going to compel them to pay 10 per cent. or 15 per cent, extra? Surely an effort to do a good turn to ease the position of these men, whether sailors or soldiers, ought to be appreciated. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Amendment agreed to. </para>
        <para>Clause, as amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>Postponed clause 40 agreed to. </para>
        <para>Postponed new clause 46a - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>If an officer of the Royal Australian Naval Radio Service be appointed to the Commonwealth Service, either before or after the commencement of this Act, his service in the Royal Australian Naval Radio Service shall, for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be service in the Commonwealth Service. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13454</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -When  the war broke out the aerial service was transferred to the Navy Department. The employees who were transferred with it from the Postal Department were permanent men, and they retained their permanency. When the Navy took over the business they were enlisted under the  Navy  Act. The proposal provides that their service with the Navy Department shall count as part of their period of Commonwealth service. I think that is fair, because a man could not be better employed than as a wireless operator during the war. These men will probably all pass back to the Postal service now that that Department has taken over the aerialservices. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Clause agreed to. </para>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> agreed to- </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the following new clause be inserted: - &#34;46b. For the purposes of this Act, temporary service in the Commonwealth Service, if continuous with permanent service, shall, in the case of persons appointed without examination, be reckoned as service in the Commonwealth Service.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Postponed clause 69 (Leave for military or naval purposes). </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13454</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I regret that there was a misunderstanding in reference to this clause. Some members who raised an objection . have since changed their minds. Some of the men engaged in the Defence Department during the war dug themselves into snug positions as permanent hands, sometimes at an increased rate of pay. The proposal is that the longest period of local leave that can be granted to them shall be twelve months. They are not to transfer from one Department to another for the purpose of getting an increase in salary. This does not affect members of the Australian Imperial Force. They get leave for war service, but the home service men can only get leave from the Department when an acting man has been called in for a period of twelve months. Exceptions may be made by the Board. A man like the Secretary of the Defence Department, who may be an ex-military man liable to be called up, may be exempted and given an extension. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Drake-Brockman</inline> wanted to know why the leave was restricted to twelve months. He was under a wrong impression as to the way in which the clause would affect officers of an Expeditionary Force serving overseas. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para class="block">He has since admitted that, and has assented to the proposal. </para>
        <para class="block">Clause agreed to. </para>
        <para>Postponed clause 78 (Temporary employment of returned soldiers). </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13455</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  In connexion with this clause, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Elliott</inline> desired to stipulate that temporary employees should not he dismissed merely for the purpose of providing permanent positions for boys who had been in the Telegraph Department. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para class="block">That the following new sub-clause be added: - &#34; (4) The employment of a returned soldier shall not be terminated for the purpose only of creating an office to be filled by the promotion of a telegraph messenger.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendment agreed to. </para>
        <para>Clause, as amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>Schedules agreed to. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13455</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I desire to move for the insertion of a Fifth Schedule. Originally it was proposed in the Bill to appoint a civil servant as  chairman  of the Appeal Board. There was a little confusion in the minds of honorable senators, and a feeling that he might be subject to the control of the head of a Department. The civil servants appealed to the Senate to appoint an outsider as  chairman.  The determination of the Appeal Board is final, and, therefore, it is not under the control of anybody. In order to leave no possibility of doubt on this point, the insertion of a Fifth Schedule is proposed in order to require an oath from members of the Board that they will give their decision free of bias. This will protect them from interference by heads of Departments. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the following new schedule be inserted: - </para>
          <para>FIFTH SCHEDULE. </para>
          <para>Oath. </para>
          <para>I, A.B., do swear that I will well and truly servo our Sovereign Lord the King as a member of the Appeal Board constituted under the Commonwealth Public Service Act 1921,. for the purpose of the appeal made by (here insert name of appellant) &#91;or, in case of the  Chairman,  or elected representative of the Division to which the appellant belongs, as a member of any Appeal Board constituted under the Commonwealth Public Sen-ice Act 1921 of which I may be a member&#93;, and that I will perform the duties and exercise the powers imposed or conferred upon me as such member without fear or favour, affection, or ill-will. So help me God. </para>
          <para>Affirmation. </para>
          <para>I, A.B, do solemnly and sincerely affirm and declare that I will well and truly serve our Sovereign Lord the King as a member of the Appeal Board constituted under the Commonwealth Public Service Act 1921, for the purpose of the appeal made by (here insert name of appellant) &#91;or, in the case of the  Chairman  or elected representative of the Division to which the appellant belongs, as a member of any Appeal Board constituted under the Commonwealth Public Service Act 1921 of which I may be a member&#93;, and that I will perform the duties and exercise the powers imposed or conferred upon me as such member without fear or favour, affection, or ill-will. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>If the head of a Department tries to interfere with a Board acting under such an oath or affirmation, it will be bad for that head of a Department. </para>
        <para>Proposed new schedule agreed to. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13455</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I should like to know whether, before the Bill is finally passed, honorable senators will have a fair copy of it, as amended, placed in their hands. I have tried this afternoon to follow the alterations made,but have been unable to do so owing to the multitude of amendments proposed. I should like to see a fair print of the Bill as amended before it is read a third time. Perhaps the  Minister will say whether honorable senators will be supplied with it. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13455</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Yes. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <para>Title agreed to. </para>
        <para>Bill reported with amendments. </para>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator E.</inline> D. Millen) proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That so much of the Standing and Sessional Orders be suspended as would prevent the Bill being passed through its remaining stages without delay. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13455</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  If the Standing Orders are suspended, and the Bill is passed through its remaining stages, we shall not have a clear copy of it, as amended, placed before us, and will not be in a position to correct any obvious mistakes which we may have made. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13455</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  It is my intention to recommit several clauses. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13455</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K8L</name.id>
            <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
            <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  The Minister for Repatriation <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator E. D. Millen)</inline> is asking that the Standing and Sessional Orders shall  be suspended, to enable the remaining stages of the Bill to be passed without delay. 1 should like to know the object of submitting that motion. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUL</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>FT; ANTI-SOC from 1910; LP from 1913; NAT from 1917</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator E D MILLEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It i9 necessary to carry such a motion to enable us to proceed to-day with the recommittal of the Bill. &#34;We should otherwise have to give notice of its recommittal for tomorrow. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K8L</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>NAT</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">THOMAS, Josiah</name>
              <name role="display">Senator THOMAS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think that no honorable senator will object to the recommittal of the Bill; but if the motion is agreed to the Government will be able to go further with the measure if they so desire. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KUL</name.id>
              <electorate>NEW SOUTH WALES</electorate>
              <party>FT; ANTI-SOC from 1910; LP from 1913; NAT from 1917</party>
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">MILLEN, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator E D MILLEN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- They will be able to do so; but they will not do so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator E.</inline> D. Millen) proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the report be now adopted. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Bill be recommitted for the purpose of reconsidering clauses 5, C, 7, proposed new clause 7a, clauses 14, 22, 23, 51. 53,62, 65, 71, 77, and 96, and the second schedule and the third schedule. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendment of the amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Payne)</inline> agreed to - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That after the figures &#34;23&#34; the figures &#34;48&#34; be inserted. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendment, as amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>
          <inline font-style="italic">In Committee</inline>(Recommittal) : </para>
        <para>Clause 5 - </para>
        <list type="decimal">
          <item label="(1)">
            <para>The officers and employees appointed permanently or temporarily under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this Act, and holding office at the commencement of this Act, shall remain in office as if this Act had been in force at the time they were appointed, and they had been appointed hereunder, and this Act shall apply to them accordingly. </para>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the words &#34; and employees appointed permanently or temporarily &#34; be left out, with a view to insert the word &#34; appointed &#34;. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13456</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K5R</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
            <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I am inclined to accept this amendment very greedily. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The intention is to continue temporary men in the Service. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There is something in it for which I have been fighting all along. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KRZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYNCH, Patrick</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Lynch</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The thin end of the wedge. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is more than that. The amendment will cover persons appointed, whether permanently or temporarily, under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this measure. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- They will remain. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K5R</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">SENIOR, William</name>
              <name role="display">Senator SENIOR</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In view of decisions given recently, I do not wish anything better than what the Minister proposes by his amendment. It represents a very big opening. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13456</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KPE</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I should like to know the object the Minister has in proposing the leaving out of the words &#34; and employees appointed permanently or temporarily&#34;. The effect of the amendment will be that permanent officers and also temporary officers employed under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this measure will remain in office as if it had been in force at the time they were appointed. The idea is to give permanancy to temporary officers. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No ; but to continue them in their present positions when they come under the provisions of this Bill. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- But that is in the clause as it stands. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand it is merely a drafting amendment. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is all very well to say that.What is the effect of the amendment? That is the question. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The effect is to secure them under this Bill in their employment as temporary employees. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- But that is what the clause specifically provides at present. It says that officers and employees appointed permanently or temporarily under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this Act and holding office at the commencement of this Act shall remainin office as if the Act had been in force at the time of their appointment. How can the Minister by striking out the words continue that right? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13456</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is believed that my amendment more adequately expresses the intention of the Bill. It specifically states that any persons temporarily employed under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this Bill shall remain in such employment subject to the provisions of the Bill. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13457</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- -I do not understand why this &#34; riddle-me-re &#34; system should have been adopted if the effect is as the Minister indicates. Once this Parliament had a reputation for turning out Statutes that could be read by the people affected, and understood by them, but it seems that the longer we continue the worse our Statutes become. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13457</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - The object of the amendment is to make it perfectly clear that temporary employees will not be transferred as permanent employees under the provisions of this Bill. I am advised that there is some ambiguity in the drafting of the existing clause, hence the need for this amendment. There is no alteration in the principle of the measure, I understand. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>Amendment agreed to. </para>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> agreed to - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the following new sub-clause be inserted - &#34; (1a) Any persons who, at the commencement of this Act, are temporarily employed under or by virtue of any Act repealed by this Act, shall remain in such employment subject to the provisions of this Act which shall apply to them accordingly.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Clause, as further amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>Clause 6 - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>In this Act unless the contrary intention appears - &#34;Returned soldier&#34; means any person who (whether before or after the commencement of this Act) has served with satisfactory record in any Expeditionary Force raised under the provisions of the Defence Act 1903-1918, and includes- </para>
          <list type="loweralpha">
            <item label="(a)">
              <para>a member of the Army Medical Corps Nursing Service who is accepted or appointed by the Director-General of Medical Services for service outside Australia; </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(b)">
              <para>any member of the Naval Forces who has been on active service outside Australia or on a ship of war; </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(c)">
              <para>any person who, during any war, has been employed in the transport service in connexion with any such Expeditionary Force, and who, while so employed, served in the zone of war; and </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(d)">
              <para>any person who was born in Aus tralia, or resident in Australia within six months prior to enlistment, and who, at any time during any war, served with satisfactory record in an Expeditionary Force raised in the United Kingdom or in any British Dominion. </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13457</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>VictoriaVicePresident of the Executive Council</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role />
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I have a number of amendments, the purpose of which is to make clear that in the definition of &#34; returned soldier &#39; &#39; any of the references will mean the late great war and not any wars preceding it, and that preference under this Act will mean preference to those who took part in the war in any of its theatres of operations. I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That in the definition of &#34; Returned soldier &#34; the word &#34; has &#34; (first occurring) be left out with a view to insert in lieu thereof the words, &#34;enlisted prior to&#39; the 11th day of November, 1918, and.&#34; </para>
          <para>That after the word &#34; served &#34; (first occurring) the words, &#34; in the war &#34; be inserted . </para>
          <para>That the word &#34;is,&#34; paragraph (a), be left out with a view to insert in lieu thereof the word &#34;was&#34;; </para>
          <para>That after the word &#34;Australia,&#34; paragraph (a), the words, &#34;during the war&#34; be inserted; </para>
          <para>That after the word &#34; Naval Forces,&#34; paragraph (b), the words, &#34;of the Commonwealth &#34; be inserted. </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Amendments agreed to. </para>
        <para>Amendment (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That after the word &#34;has,&#34; in paragraph (b), the words &#34; during the war &#34; be inserted. </para>
        </quote>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13457</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KPE</name.id>
            <electorate>Tasmania</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
            <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - It is exceedingly difficult to follow the amendments being moved by the Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Russell),</inline> because they are not amendments to the Bill, but to amendments previously made. Many amendments were circulated by the Minister when the measure was previously before the Committee, and it appears that we are now further amending them. What is the purpose of this amendment? Is &#34; the war &#34; defined in the Bill ? <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell.</inline> -Yes ; and the intention of these amendments is to make it perfectly clear that all references to &#34; the war&#34; are to the war which commenced on 4th August, 1914. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13457</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KPE</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">KEATING, John</name>
              <name role="display">Senator KEATING</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is &#34;the war&#34; to be defined ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13457</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Yes; it is defined in a later amendment. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <para>Amendment agreed to. </para>
        <para>Amendments (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> agreed to - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the word &#34;any&#34; (second occurring) in paragraph (c) he left out with a view to insert in lieu thereof the word &#34;the&#34;. </para>
          <para>That the word &#34; any &#34; (third occurring) in paragraph (d) be left out with a view to insert in lieu thereof the word &#34; the &#34;. </para>
          <para>That the word &#34;an&#34; in paragraph(d) be left out with a view to insert in lieu thereof the words &#34;a naval or military&#34;. </para>
          <para>That the following definition be added at the end of the clause: - &#34; &#39; The war &#39; means the war which commenced on the fourth day of August, One thousand nine hundred and fourteen.&#34; </para>
        </quote>
        <para>Clause, as further amended, agreed to. </para>
        <para>Clause 7 (Act not to apply to certain officers). </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13458</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the words &#34; a Chairman of an Appeal Board&#34; be left out. </para>
        </quote>
        <para class="block">When the measure was previously before the Committee, it was decided to include a  chairman  of an Appeal Board in the list of persons to whom the Act would not apply. It is now proposed to strike out the words indicated, and thus exclude the  chairman  of an Appeal Board. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13458</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Those words are not in the clause. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13458</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K18</name.id>
            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">BAKHAP, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN (Senator Bakhap</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- For the information of the Committee, I may explain that those words were inserted when the clause was previously before the Committee, and the effect of the present amendment is to rescind a previous one. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13458</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Unless we specially provide, this measure will apply to a chairman of an Appeal Board. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13458</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is the desire of a majority of public servants that this Bill shall apply to the  chairman  of an Appeal Board. It is unlikely that there will be more than, say, twenty appeals during a year, and,- under the clause as previously amended, it would have been impossible to appoint officers from the Attorney-General&#39;s Department, such as <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Knowles</inline> or <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Bonniwell,</inline> who have a thorough knowledge of the Service, to the position of  chairman  of an Appeal Board. When the representatives of the Public Service were informed that such officers could not be appointed, they were anxious that an amendment in this direction should be made. They expressed their willingness for the clause to be amended, so that <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Knowles</inline> could be appointed, because he is an officer in  whom they have every confidence. An officer in the Attorney-General&#39;s Department could, without difficulty, obtain the necessary leave to act as  chairman  of an Appeal Board. I think he would be a more suitable man, because he would have qualifications equal or superior to those of a police magistrate. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13458</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Is it desirable that this Bill should apply to the  Chairman  of the Appeal Board, and, if so, why ? If that is not desirable, I also ask why? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13458</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- We desire to appoint a civil- servant. The  Chairman  would lose his privileges under the Act if he were exempted. We wish him to retain his rights in the Service. If consideration of the clause is postponed, I shall have it re-drafted. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Clause postponed. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13458</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KLS</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I move - </para>
        </talk.start>
        <quote>
          <para>That the following new clause be inserted :  - &#34;7a. (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act - </para>
          <list type="loweralpha">
            <item label="(a)">
              <para>all appointments or promotions of officers of the Senate shall be made by the Governor-General on the recommendation of the  President  of the Senate; </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(b)">
              <para>all appointments or promotions of officers of the House of Representatives shall be made by the GovernorGeneral on the recommendation of the Speaker; </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(c)">
              <para>all appointments or promotions of officers of both Houses of Parliament shall be made by the GovernorGeneral on the joint recommendation of the  President  and the Speaker; and </para>
            </item>
            <item label="(d)">
              <para>the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker,  as the case may be, may from time to time fix the periods of recreation leave which may be granted to officers of the Parliament. &#34; (2) Subject to this section, unless inconsistent with the context, any action or approval required by this Act or the regulations thereunder to be taken or given by the Board may, so far as officers of the Parliament are concerned, be taken or given by the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker  (as the case may be) in substitution for the Board, and any action required or authorized by this Act or the regulations thereunder to be taken by a  permanent head or chief officer shall or may be taken by the  Clerk  of the Senate so far as relates to officers of the Senate, and by the  Clerk  of the House of Representatives so far as relates to officers of that House, and by the- Parliamentary Librarian so far as relates to officers of the Parliamentary Library, and by the Principal v Parliamentary Reporter so far as relates to officers of the Parliamentary Reporting Staff, and by- the Secretary of the Joint House Department so far as relates to officers of that Department. &#34; (3) Any reference in this Act or the regulations thereunder to the Minister shall, so far as the Departments of the Senate, the House of Representatives, the Parliamentary Library, the Parliamentary Reporting Staff, and the Joint House Department are concerned, be read as a reference to the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker  (as the case may be). </para>
            </item>
          </list>
        </quote>
        <para>* (4) The officers of the Senate; the officers of the House of Representatives, the officers of the Parliamentary Library, the officers of the Parliamentary Reporting Staff, and the officers of the Joint House Department shall bc deemed to constitute separate Departments under this Act. , / &#34; (5) The classification of officers of the Parliament shall bo made by the  President  or the  Speaker  or by the  President  and the  Speaker,  as the case may be: &#34; Provided that if the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker  (as the case may be), by writing addressed to the <inline font-weight="bold">Chairman</inline> of the Board, requests the Board to classify any officers of the Parliament, the Board shall classify those officers in the manner provided in this Act. &#34; (6) The Governor-General may, on the recommendation of the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker  (as the case may be), make, in relation to officers of the Parliament, regulations prescribing all matters in relation to which the Board is, by this Act, authorized to make regulations. &#34; (7) Any regulation made under this Act  by the Board shall apply to officers of the Parliament, unless and until - </para>
        <list type="loweralpha">
          <item label="(a)">
            <para>a regulation is made under the last preceding &#39; sub-section inconsistent with, or prescribing matters dealt with in, that first-mentioned regulation ; or </para>
            <list type="decimal">
              <item label="(6)">
                <para>the Governor-General, upon the recommendation of the  President  or the  Speaker  or the  President  and the  Speaker (as the case may be), by order declares that such regulation shall not apply to officers of the Parliament.&#34; </para>
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <para>My object in moving the insertion of this new clause is to meet what I believe to be the almost unanimous desire of the Senate, and of Parliament generally, that Parliament should have control of its own officers. It is my belief that that is a correct and proper thing. I have consulted with <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker</inline> in the matter, and the clause has been prepared by the Parliamentary Draftsman for the pur pose of giving effect to what is believed to be the express wish of Parliament. Of course it is for Parliament to say whether the clause meets with its approval or not. It largely follows the provisions of the old Act, except as to one or two matters where experience has shown that some alterations are necessary, but these alterations are of a very minor character. As the clause is a very long one, and somewhat complicated, I suggest that discussion would be facilitated, and the Committee would be enabled to arrive at a more accurate decision, if the various parts of it were put separately. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13459</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K18</name.id>
            <electorate>TASMANIA</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">BAKHAP, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN&#34; (Senator Bakhap</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- As the clause is somewhat complicated I shall put each sub-clause separately, as suggested. </para>
        </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13459</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JU7</name.id>
            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
            <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I desire to give notice of an, amendment ta this clause. At present the officers of Parliament are controlled by the  President  of the Senate, so far as Senate officers are concerned, by the  Speaker  of the House of Representatives, so far as officers in that branch of the Legislature are concerned, and in some cases officers are under the joint control of the  President  and the  Speaker.  I propose to include with the  President  and the  Speaker  the members of the House Committee, so far as that Committee controls officers, and also the Library Committee, so far as it exercises similar powers. I think my reasons for this action are fairly well known to honorable senators, because the matter has been discussed before. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> has just informed the Committee that it is his opinion that Parliament should have authority over its own officers. There can scarcely be two opinions on that point. All Parliaments retain control over their own officers, for obvious reasons. There should be no power higher than the Parliament. If we allowed our officers to be under an outside authority, we should practically lose the control of Parliament. If the House and Library Committees are brought in to work in, conjunction with the  President  and the  Speaker,  we shall be reverting to the position which existed when the Commonwealth was established. Very many honorable senators who have sat on the House Committee have wondered why it is in existence. It is practically without authority. When a meeting is called - and that only happens at very wide intervals - there is really no -work to do. Anything of consequence that the House Committee controlled in former years has been taken away from it. If the Committee had some power and authority, honorable senators would be proud to be members of it; but what satisfaction is there in being a member of a Committee that has no power? </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13460</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3B</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">ROWELL, James</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Rowell</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- &#34;We corrected a few abuses that existed in Sydney. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13460</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am glad to hear that; but as far as the officers of the Senate are concerned, I hold that the House Committee has no power whatever. There is a Public Service Act which places the control of public servants generally in the hands of several Boards. If breaches of the regulations are committed, or if officers desire to appeal against injustices, the Boards come into operation. &#34;We have safeguarded the interests of the public servants outside Parliament - in the Post Office, the Customs Department, and other Departments. Public servants have many ways in. which they may ventilate their grievances and get their case heard, but officers of the Senate have no means of being heard. They have no Appeal Board, or Board of Inquiry. Members of Parliament know very little of what goes on in connexion with the control of officers. No report is published, such as is issued in relation to the Post Office and the Customs Department. Still, honorable senators keep representing that Parliament ought to control its own officers. Parliament does not control its officers, and it is in order to give some control into the hands of the Committee that I move my amendment. I hope honorable senators will see the reason and necessity for it. Unless the amendment is carried officers of the Senate can have no protection, and Parliament can have no effective control over them. It is an absolute necessity that the House Committee should be given that power. I move - </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>That at the end of paragraph <inline font-style="italic">(a)</inline> of subclause 1 the words, &#34; and House Committee &#34; be inserted. </para>
        <para class="block">If the amendment is carried, subsequent alterations will have to be made throughout the clause. The Library Committee and the Joint House Committee will have to be included in the proposal. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13460</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KLS</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -The sub-clause with which the Committee is now dealing is on all-fours with the provisions of the present Act. Practically no alteration is proposed in the law as is stands at present. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie proposes to make a very drastic alteration, and I submit that the reasons he has put forward in support of his proposal are entirely inadequate. He says it has been demonstrated in the past that Parliament has had no control of its officers, and he asserts that it will have no control in the future unless the Joint House Committee act with the  Speaker  or  President,  as the case may be. I want to point out that if the amendment is carried Parliament will not have any more control over its officers than it -has now. It has absolute control of the  President  and the Speaker; both are responsible to Parliament, and can be removed by a simple vote of either House. Parliament would not have any more control if it brought in a Committee, because the Committee would be no more responsible to Parliament than is the <inline font-weight="bold">President. Senator de</inline> Largie contended that this thing was not done until recently. It never has been done by this Parliament, or by any Presiding Officer of it. It would be utterly impracticable to do it, because Parliament does not usually sit for more than five months in the year. For the remaining seven months of the year the Committee could not be got together, and there would be no one available capable of dealing with any matter that might arise. I think it is generally conceded, and it has been embodied in all the Public Service Acts, that officers of the Public Service should not have recourse to political influence or be subjected to political control. I venture to say that if we had a  Committee acting in conjunction with the  President  there would be nothing but political wire-pulling from end to end of the Service in the Senate. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13460</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Would not that statement apply equally to the  President  personally as to the Committee? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13460</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Certainly ; but the evil would be multiplied a hundredfold if there were a dozen individuals concerned instead of one. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The chances of influencing the individual would be greater than the chances of influencing the Committee. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not think so. My experience is quite the opposite. I know, of my own knowledge, at least twenty members of Parliament, including some Ministers, who have tried to influence me. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the honorable senator in order in making that statement? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am in order. The statement is not only in order, but it is a fact. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator has either said too much, or too little. Having made that statement, he ought to give the names of the members concerned. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The Committee ought to be informed of the names. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie was one of them. I have been spoken to by various members. In addition to the difficulty that would arise owing to the Committee not being available for twothirds of the year, there is the further difficulty that there is no Committee constituted to deal with the Senate, and no Committee constituted to deal with the House of Representatives. There is a Joint House Committee, which was created to deal with matters that do not come under the separate jurisdiction, of either House. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie says that the House Committee is of no importance. I say that many important things come before that Committee, and many important decisions are registered by the Committee. As far as I am concerned, every opportunity has been given to the Committee to deal with all the matters that properly come before it, and, as far as I have been able to ascertain, it has exercised as much influence during the last few years as ever it did. Even if the amendment is incorporated in the clause, there will still be a Department which will be outside the control of the Committee, namely, <inline font-style="italic">Hansard.</inline> The position will then be anomalous. Personally, I think any President would like to be relieved of the duty, and of the abuse that is poured upon him when he acts independently in carrying out his duties. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Is the honorable senator not taking up a peculiar position when he says that any  President  would be glad to get rid of the duty, while he still advocates, that the  President  should retain it? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is a responsibility that properly belongs to the  President&#39;s  position. I say that emphatically. No  President  would have any control over a staff if members of the staff could go to a Committee .which had power to override his decisions. If it is desired to maintain discipline and good order, thelaw, which has acted so well in the past, should be continued in the future. It is a question whether we should have one head of a Department or a dozen. Good service is not likely to be obtained if there are a dozen bosses on the same job. As for <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie&#39;s contention that members of the staff have no means of appealing against the President&#39;s decisions, honorable senators will remember that in this session very much has been heard of the grievances of servants of the Senate. Officers always have a right <inline font-style="italic">i</inline> appeal through senators, who can shoulder the responsibility upon one man. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- If the  President  deals with the staff asdrasticallly as he has dealt with me,  I pity them. The&#62; Standing Orders give me the right to  make a statement, and he refused me that right. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13461</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator, I think, is introducing a matter which, does not belong properly to this discussion. I ask honorable senators to judge this amendment, not from my stand-point or that of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker</inline> or any other individual, but from the standpoint of the good of the Service generally. I may pass away to-morrow ; another  President  may be here. Probably there will be another  President  in a very short time, and then <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Gardiner</inline> may be more satisfied. I ask honorable senators to come to a decision entirely irrespective of any individual, and with regard only to what is best for the Service. Unless the responsibility is placed upon one person, good service will not be obtained, and discipline will be destroyed. I ask the Committee to reject the amendment, and to pass the clause as it stands. The sub-clause is an exact copy of the law which has proved satisfactory in the past, and has, I maintain, fulfilled every requirement of the Service to the full satisfaction of Parliament and its officers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13462</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>JU7</name.id>
            <electorate>Western Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
            <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  I am sorry that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> should have introduced the personal note. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The honorable senator should set him a good example by leaving it out. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I left it out, but I shall not do so any&#39; longer. When I am singled out for attack&#34; in the way I have been, I should be but a poor type of man if I did not at least take my own part. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The honorable senator might offer the other cheek. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I have not been brought up to practice that Christian precept. We have been told that political influence has been used. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> has said that it was used by twenty members of this Parliament and by some Ministers. I got that statement from the honorable senator in evidence given before the Select Committee of which. I was  Chairman.  The honorable senator evidently expected that it would be given greater publicity than it can receive from the publication of the minutes of evidence taken before the Select Committee, and consequently he desired today to get it out first. When I asked the honorable senator whether I was one of the twenty members of Parliament to whom he referred he said I was not. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-Not  at that particular time. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I said that we should have the names of the twenty members of Parliament referred to, and <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> now says that I am one of them. That is a contradiction of the statement he made before the Select Committee, when he said that I was not one of the twenty. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Not at that particular time. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I had to drag information out of the honorable senator when he appeared as a witness before the Select Committee. He told the Committee that twenty members had come to him and had tried to use political influence to have a fourth class clerk appointed. When I asked him if I was one of them he said, &#34;No.&#34; So that I am perfectly right in what I said, and what </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para class="block">
          <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline>said in reply to me waa wrong. I had to go on questioning the honorable senator. I had to ask nine questions to drag out of him what he was privately circulating about me amongst members of this Parliament. I had to &#34; fossick it &#34; out by asking question after question. If I had been ashamed of anything I had done, I should not have tried to drag out of the honorable senator what I knew he was privately circulating about me. This is the manly person who is able to withstand political influence. When, it came to a question of how long ago the matter to which the honorable senator referred had occurred, he said it was six or seven years ago. This will show honorable senators how long <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> can carry a grudge, and also that he can make use of private conversations when it suits him. It should be a warning to honorable senators who go to his private room, as to how guarded and careful they should be in their attitude towards a man of that kind. So far as political influence is concerned, we have it in the words of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> himself, that that influence is being used now. In order that an end might be put to it, <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> sometime ago proposed that the control of the officers or Parliament should be taken out of the. hands of Parliament. Why did he do such a thing if he believes; in the amendments he has proposed to this Bill ? </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  I never proposed anything of the kind. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Some time ago the honorable senator, without consulting Parliament, sent a memorandum to the Government in which he suggested the handing over of the servants of this House into the hands of the Public Service Commissioner. In other words, he proposed stultifying the power of Parliament over its own officers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13462</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  On a point of order, which I raise merely to avoid unnecessary debate, I direct your attention, sir, to the fact that the matter to which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie is now referring can come on properly for discussion later. If you will look at sub-clause 5 of the proposed new clause, you will find that I am submitting a definite proposal upon which the matter which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie is now raising can be properly discussed. My point of order is that the honorable senator is  anticipating the discussion of a matter which may be more appropriately discussed on sub-clause 5. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K18</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN (Senator Bakhap</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- What is before the Committee is really one clause; and, whilst for convenience sake we are taking the discussion of the sub-clauses separately, I can hardly assume the responsibility, under the Standing Orders, of ruling <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie out of order. I may appeal to the honorable senator&#39;s good sense to confine his discussion, for convenience sake, to the different sub-clauses as we come to them. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am surprised at the trivial nature of the point of order which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> has raised. I should have thought that a gentleman who had studied the Standing Orders and professed to be conversant with them would not have raised a point of order with so little in it. I was referring to a memorandum concerning the officers of Parliament; and, if this matter is to be intelligently discussed, that memorandum should not be left out of our consideration. We are now dealing with the control of officers of the Parliament, and the memorandum to which I have referred embodies a proposition which <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> made without consulting Parliament, without consulting the House Committee, and apparently without consulting any one but <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker,</inline> and I question if he even consulted <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker.</inline> He certainly did not consult Parliament, as he should have -done, because this is not a Government matter. Why should the honorable senator have sent his memorandum to the Government? The Government have no right to control the officers of Parliament. It is Parliament that should have been consulted. By all its legislation, and by the precedents laid down by practice, Parliament has always asserted its right to control its own officers. Why should <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> go behind the back of Parliament to give away a right which Parliament has in its own hands, and without even consulting it? There was a bit of funny work connected with that action which ought to be revealed, and I hope that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> will be sufficiently candid to let us know what was behind it all. The honorable senator swallowed that proposition, and he now comes along with an other. He now proposes that Parliament should exercise control, whereas before he contended that it should not. He gives as one of his reasons that political influence is exercised. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Did not <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Thomas</inline> make a most convincing speech, which may have shown- <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> that he was wrong? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- He may have done so. I suppose that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Thomas,</inline> like myself, occasionally makes convincing speeches. <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> has contended that Parliament would be given no greater control of its officers by the adoption of my amendment. I hold that if the House Committee were included as I propose, consisting as it does of a number of members of this Parliament, it would provide, a wider control over the officers of Parliament than the one-man control that we have at the present time. This has broken down in the hands of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens.</inline> I am sure that any one who examines impartially cases that were recently before Parliament will admit that there should be a change, and that the control of the officers of Parliament should be vested in more than one man. I hold that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> is not a man who can be left coldly in control of any one else. He has not the necessary temperament. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K18</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN&#34; (Senator Bakhap</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think the honorable senator had better not discuss the matter so particularly from the personal point of view. The Committee is dealing with paragraph <inline font-style="italic">a</inline> of sub -clause 1 of the proposed new clause and the amendment, which the honorable senator has moved, is to add to it the words &#34; and House Committee.&#34; The Presidency of the Senate is, as every honorable senator knows, a dignified position, and should, I think, be discussed impersonally. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13463</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- We have to remember that there may be many changes in 4he occupancy of the position of President of the Senate. Future Presidents may go wrong, and act in the same way as the present President has done, and then the Senate will be in the same unhappy position that we find ourselves in to-day. Under the Bill we have given the right to members of the Public Service to appeal to a Board, and I say that officers of Parliament should have <inline font-style="italic">same</inline> Committee to whom they may ap peal. I am, suggesting that the House Committee should take the place of the Appeal Board or Board of Inquiry provided for public servants generally. I hold that the House Committee is the proper body to take up this work. Sena- 1 tor Givens has said that the House Committee has never done the work I propose to hand over to it. The honorable senator is speaking of things concerning which he has had no opportunity to obtain, an inside knowledge. I was a member of the first Library Committee of this Parliament. There are members still in the House of Representatives who were on that Committee. There is a member in this chamber at the present time who was on that Committee. I was a member of the second House Committee appointed, and I oan speak with authority of the work which was done by those two Committees. I can say that during the first and second Parliaments those Committees were consulted in every instance by the  President  or the  Speaker,  as the case might be, when amy staff matter came forward. I quite well remember <inline font-weight="bold">Sir Richard</inline> Baker, the first  President  of the Senate, making a statement to the House Committee after the first Public Service Act was passed. He said that now that the Act was passed it was necessary to recognise it in some way or another. He said that he saw very great difficulty in the way of administering his Department and. at the same time applying the provisions of the Public Service Act. He further said that, consequently, he intended to exercise control through the House Committee. He said, &#34; This House Committee will take the place of the Appeal Board, <inline font-style="italic">or</inline> the Board of Inquiry, as the case may be, and we shall go on in the future as we have done in the past.&#34; These are things on. which I can. speak from personal knowledge. I can say, further, that only very recently, when the matter was brought up in the Library, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. McDonald,</inline> a member of another place, practically substantiated what I am saying here to-day. Now, as to the statement that officers may bring any grievances they have before the Senate, let me say that that may be a very unpleasant task. Honorable senators will not desire to challenge the Presiding Officer in that way when they could have things put right before a Com- mittee. Time and again I have gone to tha  President  in connexion with staff  matters of which I was informed to have grievances put right. Sometimes I succeeded, and sometimes I did not. I say that honorable senators should not have to do that sort of thing. The House Committee should be the body to deal with staff grievances. I do not think it right that an honorable&#39; senator should have to appeal to the  President  to do something out of compliment to him, for this or that officer. These things must be taken in hand by some one. If they are ignored the result will be that what ia every one&#39;s business will become nobody&#39;s business. Looked at from every point of view, it will he seen that there will be an advantage in giving the House Committee the &#39;power I propose. I am surprised that politicians should repeat the dirty insinuations of the press with regard to the exercise of political influence&#39;. I am surprised that a gentleman holding the dignified office of  President  of the Senate should be a party to passing on such wretched, untruthful suggestions about political influence. . </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13464</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>10000</name.id>
            <electorate />
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
            <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
          </talker>
          <para>- Order ! I think &#39; the honorable senator will see that it  is  necessary for me to protect the dignity of the Presiding Officer of this Chamber. Therefore I must ask him to desist from making any further statements of that nature. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13464</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  I object, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chair.man.</inline> to any consideration being shown to me in Committee by virtue of my position as  President,  and which may not be given to any other honorable gentleman of this Chamber. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13464</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Certain duties are &#34;confided to me by virtue of my position as the second officer of this Chamber, and my conception, of the matter is that the occupant of the presidential chair is the custodian of the dignity and power of this Chamber, and should be protected. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13464</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  He is not President now. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13464</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The  President  at all times is  President.  Such is my view of the position; and, notwithstanding what the  President  himself has said, I feel it my duty to protect the occupant of that office from any imputation which I think is improper. Therefore I must ask <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie not to make use of such expressions as &#34; untruthful &#34; in regard to statements that may emanate  from the  President.  Honorable senators will see that, in regard to this matter, I am in the first place considering the dignity of this Chamber and not the individual occupant of the presidential chair. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator DE LARGIE</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chairman,</inline> you misunderstood my use of the word. I was applying it to those accusations which are made by all and sundry, and I said I waa surprised that the  President  should be a party to passing on statements of that kind, which were untrue. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13465</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KLS</name.id>
            <electorate>Queensland</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I have no desire, by reason of my official position, to deprive any honorable senator of his right in a discussion in Committee. The statement made by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie is not in accordance with facts. He said that I went behind the back of Parliament to make this recommendation with regard to the officers pf Parliament, and that I went behind the  Speaker  also. Either that is true or it is not true. The facts may be simply stated: It was within the knowledge of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker</inline> and myself that after a very full inquiry into the Public Service, the late Public Service Commissioner <inline font-weight="bold">(Mr. McLachlan)</inline> recommended to the Government certain lines upon which the Public Service should be organized, and expressed the view that there was no reason why officers of the Parliament should be treated as distinct and separate from, other members of the Public Service. That came within the knowledge of <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Speaker</inline> and myself. We had a consultation about the matter, and deemed it our duty to report to the Government that the classification of officers in both Houses, of all parliamentary officers in fact, should be made by the Public Service Commissioner or the Board, and that the appropriate salaries belonging to their classification should be determined thus, but that Parliament should, as hitherto, retain the sole control over its employees. That is what I am now proposing. I am prepared to defend my action anywhere. Instead of going behind the back of Parliament we took Parliament into our confidence. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Yes, months later, and after I had moved for the appointment of a Select Committee. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not think that is so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am sure of it. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- So far from trying to take away the control from Parliament, we protested against the Government bringing in the Bill in its present form, making the officers of Parliament subservient to the Public Service Commissioner or the Board. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Why was not your memorandum addressed to the Parliament rather than to the Government? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Because the Government, and not Parliament, was drafting the Bill, and in our memorandum to the Government we made representations as to what the Bill should contain. The Government ignored our representations, with the result that the Bill which this Committee has passed through its hands takes control of the parliamentary officers away from Parliament and places them under the Board. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- -You  are ignoring Parliament in your present proposition. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GIVENS</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- On the contrary, my amendment is intended to rectify what I consider is a mistake. All this discussion has arisen simply because I am trying to improve the Bill in the direction I have indicated, and restore to Parliament that control over its parliamentary officers which the Government propose to take away from Parliament. I may say that after our representations had been made, the Government consented to my moving these amendments in Committee. I have no desire to labour the question. I have nut the facts before the Committee, and I am content to leave the matter in honorable senators&#39; hands. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13465</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
            <electorate>South Australia</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
            <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - I think the strongest argument for <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie&#39;s amendment has been supplied by the  President  himself. He has stated that he has been called Upon to withstand political influence on twenty different occasions. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Where are those twenty politicians that he speaks of? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13465</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- It is, I think, undignified that the debate should proceed on the lines it has taken. The  President  has intimated that he felt obliged to submit these amendments to the Bill. In my view, the House Committee should have greater powers of control. The  President,  of course, should, <inline font-style="italic">ex officio,</inline> be Chairman of the Committee ; and, although he may be charged with the obligation of performing certain duties, he should report in detail to the Committee at regular intervals. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- But if we provide that certain matters must be done by the House Committee, we shall exclude the  President  altogether. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No President would take the responsibility under such conditions. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The  chairman  of the Australian Mutual Provident Society discharges all the functions of the Board and reports to that body. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JXP</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DRAKE-BROCKMAN, Edmund</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Drake-Brockman</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is because the regulations governing the society provide that he may do so. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Well, that is the kind of administration we want in regard to our parliamentary officers. At present there is too, much duplication altogether. It cannot be said that there is contentment throughout&#39; this building, because there is not. That, at all events, is my experience. The  President  of to-morrow may be a man who would not treat men exactly as they should be treated and I contend that the House Committee should have authority and be held responsible. I can give honorable senators a case in point. I have had two or three letters, and several officers of the Parliament have seen me, asking why the House Committee fail to do certain things. So far as I am concerned, there was no political influence about that. The House Committee, in my opinion, is wrongly named. Its powers are too circumscribed, and should be extended. The  President  will admit that practically little interest is taken in the work submitted to the meetings of the House Committee. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator has taken a great deal of interest in it on several occasions. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- There may have been two or three occasions on which the business before the Committee was of interest to me. The  President  should be <inline font-style="italic">ex-officio</inline> Chairman of the House Committee, and that Committee should have greater powers in dealing with the officers of Parliament. If such a suggestion were adopted, what would be the result? Trivial matters, such as those which have been discussed in the Senate during the last few months, would not have arisen and the dignity of the Senate would not have been lowered. If the </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>House Committee had power to deal with the grievances of those employed in the parliamentary buildings, many of the difficulties which now prevail would be removed. If the Committee decide to give the  President  full authority we shall have to stand behind him.. </para>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KRZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">LYNCH, Patrick</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Lynch</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- What is done in other Parliaments? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- This is the first Parliament of which I have been a mem ber. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>SenatorFoster. - In some States the officers of Parliament are under the control of the Chief Secretary. </para>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is so. I am merely endeavouring to show what I think the duties of such Committees should be. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The most important Committee appointed by the Senate has never had anything to do. The Committee of Disputed Returns and Qualifications must be appointed, but it is only in exceptional circumstances that it is called upon to act. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13466</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator WILSON</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- That is merely a </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para class="block">Bafety valve, and the services of such a Committee may be required at any time. I have suggested the direction in which I think an alteration could be made to advantage, but if the amendment is adopted I shall be prepared to bow to the will of the Committee. We must, however, remember that Presidents come and go, and I am not prepared to hand over such powers while we have a House Committee which should carry out the work. </para>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13466</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>K3E</name.id>
            <electorate>Victoria</electorate>
            <party>NAT</party>
            <role>VicePresident of the Executive Council</role>
            <in.gov>1</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
            <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. - The amendment appears to be somewhat irrelevant to the Bill. It is the duty of Parliament to control its officers; but it must be remembered that parliamentary authority is quite distinct from Government authority. In this instance the power is in the hands of Parliament and not of the Government. Interference on the part of the Government in matters which should be controlled absolutely by Parliament would never be tolerated. I have endeavoured to ascertain the wishes of honorable senators in regard to the provisions of this measure, which apply to the officers of Parliament, and I am determined not to assist in handing over to the Government, or to any other authority, the powers and privileges which should be in the hands of Parliament. This House  has a right to control its own business. Some honorable senators have said that they do not know the functions of the different Committees, and have suggested extended powers, but I do not think it is the duty of honorable senators to become members of an appeal board to consider the grievances of parliamentary employees. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Why not? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not think it desirable. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  They have not any other authority to whom to appeal. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Is the Minister providing anything else? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The real trouble seems to be that the members of the Committees do not know what their duties are. There are five Committees, excluding the two joint Committees, appointed by the Senate, and if the Government were to introduce a measure defining the powers of the Committees there would be justifiable opposition because that is the duty of the Parliament. I have no power as a Minister, apart from my right as a senator, to suggest alterations in the method of conducting the Library, but I naturally wish to exercise my rights as a senator in common with other honorable senators when the occasion arises. I do not think the amendment submitted is relevant to the Bill, and I am, therefore, not prepared to accept it. One of the last duties I would desire to perform would be that of fixing wages and hours. I am in favour of arbitration for the settlement of disputes but if a Minister were called upon to settlethem, his task would be an unenviable one. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  The Minister is not asked to do it. Such matters should be brought before the House Committee. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Does not the Minister&#39;s argument concerning the inability of a Minister to deal with such matters apply with equal force to the  President  ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. It might bo said that the  President  has despotic powers. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Gardiner</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  And he uses them despotically. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The  President  is elected by a majority of the Senate, and if his actions at any time do not meet with the approval of honorable senators he can be removed from office. The business of Parliament is not entirely in the hands of Ministers. We are elected by the people to do what we consider right according to our intelligence and judgment. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- You  often do things and advise Parliament afterwards. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No. All  the  proceedings of Cabinet are reported  to  Parliament. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K18</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN (Senator Bakhap</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I direct the Minister&#39;s attention  to the  fact that there is not the slightest suggestion in the amendment of authority being exercised by the Government or by  a  Minister. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K3E</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
              <name role="display">Senator RUSSELL</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Members  of Parliament  should not be members of  a Committee  controlling parliamentary  employees. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
      </speech>
      <speech>
        <talk.start>
          <talker>
            <page.no>13467</page.no>
            <time.stamp />
            <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
            <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
            <party />
            <role />
            <in.gov>0</in.gov>
            <first.speech>0</first.speech>
            <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
            <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
          </talker>
          <para>. -  In the early stages  of the  debate on this amendment, I endeavoured to secure the call, and, after unsuccessful attempts, I was assured by one honorable senator that this was not any business  of  mine, as it concerned only <inline font-weight="bold">Senator de</inline> Largie and the  President.  When <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> said that at least twenty honorable senators had endeavoured to influence him, I interjected that that ought not  to  have been said, because the manner  in  which the statement was uttered would lead to the belief that Ministers or honorable senators had been endeavouring  to  use undue influence. I do not think  that  could be said of any honorable senator. I can quite understand that <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> is unaccustomed to speaking  on  the floor of the Senate and may have said more than he intended, or unintentionally conveyed a wrong impression. But the point is clear, and, in my mind, no honorable senator has the right to make charges by imputation or innuendo. If an endeavour has been made to use undue influence, let the names be mentioned, and those responsible answer for themselves. At present, the charge rests upon every one, because we cannot divorce the utterances of <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> from those of the  President. </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KBJ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">WILSON, Reginald</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Wilson</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Has the honorable senator &#34;put a word in&#34; for any one? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13467</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- No; but if  I  did I would be merely doing my duty as a citizen and as a representative of the people. If I knew of a good man, who could render satisfactory service as an officer of Parliament, I should have the right to inform the  President  that he was an excellent man for a certain position. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KLS</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GIVENS, Thomas</name>
              <name role="display">Senator Givens</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  At various times I have received written recommendationsconcerning applicants for employment. There is nothing improper about that, but when, in addition, an honorable senator endeavours to induce me to give undue consideration to an applicant for a position, it is highly improper. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <interjection>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>JU7</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">DE LARGIE, Hugh</name>
              <name role="display">Senator de Largie</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-  Who were the twenty ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </interjection>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Let us get away from that aspect of the question. When <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Givens</inline> considers the position, and &#39;reads his utterances in cold type, he will .find that his remarks have left a nasty impression in the minds of honorable senators. I am quite satisfied that I am putting the case fairly in saying that honorable senators will never go to the extent of endeavouring to use undue influence. One of my interjections was to this effect, &#34; I pitied the officers of this House under the despotic dictatorship cf the  President,  judging by my own experience.&#34; I feel, however, .that in pursuing this course I am joining in the scandal which&#39; has been the means of lowering the dignity of the Senate. I also said that despotic powers had been used despotically by the  President.  If the  President  carried out his duties&#39; in the way his conscience dictates, he is guilty; but that is for others to judge. My conscience is clear on everything I have done. I shall give a few illustrations to show that 1 have been treated in a drastically despotic manner1. I have been subjected to indignities to which I would not ask anybody to submit. On one occasion I was called upon to withdraw a statement. Our Standing Orders provide that, before an honorable senator is removed, he should be given an opportunity to make a statement or to offer an apology. I rose a dozen times to make a statement, and I was ordered by the  President  to sit down. If I live to be a hundred years old, the indignity to which I was submitted by this gentleman will never be forgotten. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>K18</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN (Senator Bakhap</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I do not think the honorable senator should introduce that matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think I am perfectly in order in showing the type of man to whom it is proposed to give these powers. i The  CHAIRMAN.  - I am very loath at any time to impose any restriction upon debate, but the honorable senator is referring to something which took place in this chamber, and, he is criticising a decision of the Senate in connexion wilh its ordinary legislative proceedings. I can see no relation whatever between that matter and the question now under consideration. If the honorable senator will pardon me, may I delicately suggest that he abandon that argument for the time being, and reserve it for some other occasion ? </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- Delicate suggestions are of no use at all. I am within my rights in referring to this matter. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- The honorable senator is not within his rights. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I think the  Chairman  will see that we are discussing the question of whether this  President  shall have, and shall continue to exercise, certain powers over certain persons, and I am merely trying to show how this same  President  has exercised his powers in the past. If I can demonstrate that he is absolutely a tyrant in the exercise of his powers, I am presenting a good argument-- </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I understand that the matter to which the honorable senator refers was ratified by the Senate, and, therefore, he is out of order in introducing a discussion of that matter in considering the present Bill. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am sorry I have not been permitted to carry my remarks sufficiently far to enable the  Chairman  to appreciate my argument. The  President  was supported, on the occasion to which I have referred, by the whole of the Senate, but my contention is that a moderate-minded gentleman in such circumstances would never have placed the Senate in the position of supporting him in doing an injustice. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- -That is a reflection! on the Senate. &#176; </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13468</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>-If that is your ruling, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chairman,</inline> I shall leave that point, and pass on to another reason why the proposed powers should not be conferred on the  President.  On another occasion! I was speaking on the Electoral Bill. Nothing could be more important than the legislation under which members of Parliament are .returned. The </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Bill in question was introduced after ten o&#39;clock at night. I began to speak. The supper hour passed, and from a quarter to one until twenty minutes to eleven o&#39;clock the next morning I was refused an opportunity of procuring necessary refreshment. </para>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I allowed the honorable senator to proceed sufficiently far to enable me clearly to determine what matter it was to which he was alluding. Beyond all doubt he is referring to a proceeding in this Senate, and to actions of the  President  in his presidential capacity, and he has introduced an ordinary parliamentary matter, which is foreign to the present Bill. I rule that any action taken by the  President,  or taken by the Senate in indorsement of any action, of the  President,  ia quite irrelevant to the subject-matter of the Bill before the Committee. I now ask the honorable senator to refrain from continuing along those lines. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I ask you, <inline font-weight="bold">Mr. Chairman,</inline> in justice to yourself, to hear the conclusion I am going to draw, lest by cutting me off in the middle of my remarks you may &#39;be giving a wrong ruling. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- In connexion with this Bill the honorable senator must nob refer to a proceeding in the Senate, to which no objection was taken by the Senate at the time. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- I am not discussing the Bill, but a proposed new clause dealing with the question of whether this Senate, or the  President,  shall have certain powers. As soon as I have finished my reference to what the  President  has done, I shall try to show that the House Committeeis the most incompetent that has ever sat here. After standing for more than ten hours at a stretch at the table of the Senate, and after being subjected to the inhuman treatment which I received from the gentleman to whom it is proposed to give these powers- </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <continue>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>10000</name.id>
              <electorate />
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">CHAIRMAN, The</name>
              <name role="display">The CHAIRMAN</name>
            </talker>
            <para>- If the honorable senator persists in his remarks along those lines I shall have to take other steps. I rule thathe is out of order in now referring to those proceedings, which arc well within the cognisance of many honorable senators. </para>
          </talk.start>
        </continue>
        <para>Progress reported. </para>
      </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>PAPER</title>
        <page.no>13469</page.no>
        <type>miscellaneous</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <para>The  following paper was presented:- </para>
      <quote>
        <para>Public Service Act-Regulations amended- Statutory Rules 1921,Nos.214 and 215. </para>
      </quote>
    </debate>
    <debate>
      <debateinfo>
        <title>ADJOURNMENT</title>
        <page.no>13469</page.no>
        <type>adjournment</type>
      </debateinfo>
      <subdebate.1>
        <subdebateinfo>
          <title>Private Members&#39; Business - Days of Sitting</title>
          <page.no>13469</page.no>
        </subdebateinfo>
        <para>Motion (by <inline font-weight="bold">Senator Russell)</inline> proposed - </para>
        <quote>
          <para>That the Senate do now adjourn. </para>
        </quote>
        <speech>
          <talk.start>
            <talker>
              <page.no>13469</page.no>
              <time.stamp />
              <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
              <electorate>New South Wales</electorate>
              <party />
              <role />
              <in.gov>0</in.gov>
              <first.speech>0</first.speech>
              <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
              <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
            </talker>
            <para>.- Will the Minister <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator Russell)</inline> be good enough to allow me to submit the motion standing in my name for the appointment of a Select Committee f </para>
          </talk.start>
          <interjection>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13469</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>K3E</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">RUSSELL, Edward</name>
                <name role="display">Senator Russell</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I desire first to confer with the Leader of the Senate <inline font-weight="bold">(Senator E. D. Millen),</inline> who has been busily engaged elsewhere throughout the day. I shall see him this evening, and ascertain if the honorable senator&#39;s motion can be put through to-morrow. T understand that there is no objection to it. . </para>
            </talk.start>
          </interjection>
          <continue>
            <talk.start>
              <talker>
                <page.no>13469</page.no>
                <time.stamp />
                <name.id>KKZ</name.id>
                <electorate />
                <party />
                <role />
                <in.gov>0</in.gov>
                <first.speech>0</first.speech>
                <name role="metadata">GARDINER, Albert</name>
                <name role="display">Senator GARDINER</name>
              </talker>
              <para>- I am very anxious to have the Committee appointed. I hope tha Government will realize the advantage of meeting on Monday morning in order to give us a chance to complete our business next week. </para>
            </talk.start>
          </continue>
          <para>Question resolved in the affirmative. </para>
        </speech>
      </subdebate.1>
    </debate>
    <adjournment>
      <adjournmentinfo>
        <page.no>13469</page.no>
        <time.stamp>18:27:00</time.stamp>
      </adjournmentinfo>
      <para>Senate adjourned  at 6.27  p.m. </para>
    </adjournment>
  </chamber.xscript>
</hansard>
