<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" []>
<HANSARD DATE="04/03/1981" PROOF="No" PAGE="303" CHAMBER = "Senate" PARLIAMENT.NO = "32" SESSION.NO = "1" PERIOD.NO = "2" > 
<CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><BUSINESS.START>
<DAY.START DATE="04/03/1981">Wednesday, 4 March 1981</DAY.START>
<PROCTEXT><PARA></PARA>
<PARA> The DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator C. R. Maunsell) took the chair at 2.15 p.m., and read prayers.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</BUSINESS.START><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="303"><TITLE>DEATH OF SENATOR JOHN WILLIAM KNIGHT</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="303" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Government in the Senate)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr Deputy President, all honourable senators will have been greatly saddened to learn of the death in the early hours of this morning of our colleague Senator John William Knight. All of us were shocked to learn last Saturday of the massive heart attack which he had sustained that afternoon in Jindabyne. Our anxieties increased as the daily medical reports showed no improvement in his condition and no signs of restoration of consciousness, and yesterday, at the request of his medical advisers and his family, I informed the Senate that he was dangerously ill and that the prognosis was poor. Unhappily that report proved all too true.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> John Knight's death at the early age of 37 years is a great personal tragedy to his family. To his fine wife, Karla, to her two young sons, to his mother and to his sister we extend our heartfelt sympathy. Theirs is the harshness and the bewilderment of a grief caused by the sudden loss of a dearly loved one, the loss of a vital family member. It must seem inconceivable to them, as it does to us, that he was not permitted to journey through the fullness of his years within the development and progress of his family. But that was not to be. We have been given a salutary reminder that death is no respecter of age or person. </PARA>
<PARA> John Knight was born in Armidale on 20 November 1943. He held the degree of Bachelor of Arts with honours from New England University and a Master of Arts degree from the East-West Center in Hawaii. He was a Fulbright Scholar. Subsequently he became a visiting fellow at the Australian National University in 1975. John Knight joined the Department of Foreign Affairs in 1965 and served as a career diplomat in India, Fiji and Saudi Arabia. In 1966 he was appointed third secretary in the Australian High Commission in New Delhi. He was, for a time, private secretary to the Rt Hon. Sir Billy Snedden, K.C.M.G., Q.C. </PARA>
<PARA> John was elected to the Senate for the Australian Capital Territory on three occasions-in 1975, in 1977 and in 1980. Within the Senate he served on a number of committees. He was a member of the Library Committee from 17 August 1978 and of the Standing Orders Committee from 26 November 1980. He maintained a keen and perceptive interest in foreign affairs and defence and served on the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence from 24 March 1976. He was dedicated to the welfare of the Australian Capital Territory and served on the Joint Committee on the Australian Capital Territory from 25 March 1976, for most of that time as its chairman. </PARA>
<PARA> John was appointed Government Deputy Whip in the Senate from 1 March 1978 and became Government Whip from 25 November 1980. In these capacities he served with distinction and with a sensitive understanding of the parliamentary institution. It is an enduring tribute to him that his qualities as a man-his innate sense of decency, his warm humanity and his tolerance and goodwill-were widely recognised and acknowledged and that his wide circle of friends cut right across party lines. His professional career was a promising one. He was very well equipped, both intellectually and by temperament, for public life. His sense of service and his dedication have built an enduring memory in the minds and hearts of many Australians. </PARA>
<PARA> But in the end, it is not the public figure but the private person whom we mourn. It is the loss of the devoted son and brother, the loving husband and the father that is the central focus of grief. In acknowledging, as we do, the death of a very valued colleague, may we extend our warmest sympathy to his mother, his sister, his wife Karla and his two sons. I am reminded that Shakespeare wrote:</PARA>
<PARA> Thou know'st, 't is common; all that lives must die, Passing through nature to eternity. </PARA>
<PARA>It is doubly sad when such proof of our frailty and our mortality is provided by the young, the talented and the family man. We will miss him. I therefore move:</PARA>
<PARA> That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death this day of Senator John William Knight, a senator for the Australian Capital Territory from 1975 and Government Whip in the Senate from 1980, places on record its appreciation of his long and meritorious public service, and tenders its profound sympathy to his widow and the members of his family in their bereavement. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="303" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Opposition)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of the Opposition I second the motion of condolence for our former colleague, John Knight. As a senator and as Government Whip, John Knight enjoyed the respect and liking of members of the Senate on this side of the chamber. In his electorate of the Australian Capital Territory he was a hard-working and popular parliamentarian. As Government Whip, he was a courteous and trusted man. In debates in the Senate, he was a lucid, reasoned and informed contributor, prepared to conduct arguments in a generous manner, without rancour or personal malice and, as such, he was one of those younger senators who had the capacity to raise the standards of the Senate out of the mire of bitterness engendered in 1974 and 1975.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> John Knight, throughout his adult life, followed a highly successful career academically, in foreign affairs and in politics. I have no intention of dwelling on the details of that career. The tragedy, the inexplicable thing, is that it was cut short at the prime of his life when he had so much to offer his family, the Parliament and his country. Mostly, when we speak to condolence motions for former parliamentarians, memories and regrets are qualified by the knowledge that the person whom we remember has had, as is said, a good innings and a fair share of life's chances and opportunities. But unhappily, in the case of John Knight, those qualifications do not apply. He will be sadly missed and affectionately remembered. The sadness which we feel, however, is of small consequence compared with the tragic loss suffered by his wife and family. To them, on behalf of the Opposition, I extend our sincere sympathy and deep regrets. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="304" SPEAKER="Scott Sen The Hon D.B." NAMEID="MQ7" PARTY="NCP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="MQ7">Senator SCOTT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the National Country Party of Australia)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I offer the very deep sympathy of the National Country Party on the tragic loss of Senator John Knight. It is indeed a loss to the Senate, to the Parliament and to the community in which he lived and which he served. I had the good fortune to have a relatively close association with John Knight during the years he was in this Parliament and I recall him in the chamber as a fine debater and one who gave good service to the Government and to the Parliament as Deputy Whip and later as Government Whip in this chamber. I was also closely associated with John Knight on the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence, and his contribution to that Committee will never be forgotten. Outside the chamber and the Parliament I was for some years a constant squash partner of John Knight, and I learned very well what a talented and fine sportsman he was.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> As has been mentioned here this afternoon, John had a very fine mind. He was an effective and sincere representative of the Australian Capital Territory and one of its finest promoters. He had in his make-up a real measure of humanity. He was a man of great and contagious enthusiasm, and I hope that we will all be the better for his example. Finally, I offer again the very sincere sympathy of the National Country Party to John Knight's wife, Karla, their children and the rest of John Knight's family on this tragic occasion. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="304" SPEAKER="Chipp Sen The Hon D.L." NAMEID="3V4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="3V4">Senator CHIPP</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Australian Democrats)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of the Australian Democrats I too pay tribute to my close mate John Knight-a mate of nine years. John Knight was a good man, an honest man, a kind and tolerant man. He was loved and he loved. In my assessment of people I can find no other words to pay a high tribute to a human being than to call him or her good, honest, kind and tolerant, but above all-the highest accolade-to say that he loved and was loved. Whilst we are shocked at the premature death of such a young man we can be thankful for the blessed relief that death finally brought him and his loved ones once his body and his brain had been struck such massive blows. I will grieve for his memory but not for him because John Knight is now where neither pain nor anguish can hurt him. Hate or bitterness will no longer visit him; only peace he will know. It will be to his beautiful and wonderful wife, Karla, and his other loved ones to whom my sympathy, love and prayers will be directed.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="304" SPEAKER="Martin Sen K.J." NAMEID="3E4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="3E4">Senator MARTIN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;As senators we each of us today mourn the loss of a colleague and many of us mourn the loss of a very dear friend. I knew John Knight well and I am proud and happy to call him friend. I knew him through his activities in the Senate. I got to know him very well also when we were both on a delegation to Japan and China in early 1977, just over 12 months after he became a member of the Senate. I knew his motivation to enter politics. I knew a lot about his circumstances in life-as a child, as a young man and as a maturing man. John was not born to any sort of privilege. He came from very much an average Australian background. However, he had a number of great advantages over the average person. He had great intelligence and an enormous zest for life. He used that zest, together with his intelligence, as his motivator.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> He wasted none of his talents. He was an ambitious young man but it was not an amibition that sought to express itself in self-aggrandisement. He sought through his ambition and talents to serve his country and the people who live in it. He really cared about Australia and he cared about his fellow Australians. </PARA>
<PARA> He initially sought to serve Australia through service with the Department of Foreign Affairs and in the foreign service. Subsequently he sought to enter parliament to further his work for his country and those in it. He believed in a free, equal Australia. He chose a particular philosophy as the way that he saw best to work for it. But as has been said earlier, he bore no political rancour or malice to any opponent. </PARA>
<PARA> He worked as he saw best he could. He cared about and worked in two main areas that I can recall. One was in foreign affairs, and tribute has been paid to the great contribution he made with his experience and talents in that area. But he also worked very hard, as all of us on this side of the chamber will be aware, for those who are disadvantaged socially either through economic circumstances or through physical circumstances. He believed that the benefits of being an Australian should be available to all Australians and he dedicated himself to that belief. </PARA>
<PARA> He was blessed with a beautiful loving wife, Karla, and two very lovable little boys, Joshua and Jason. I know through my friendship with him that those three people were the joy of his life. Our thoughts go to them today as they have been with them over the past four days. </PARA>
<PARA> I add my personal condolences to those already expressed and to be expressed. Of course, one must also express sympathy for the enormous grief that his mother and his sister, Jenny, have today in the great personal tragedy that they have to bear. John Knight was a good senator in the fullest possible meaning of that term. His death is a loss to the Senate and to our country. It is a great personal loss to all of us in this place but particularly and most tragically, to his family to whom we seek to offer our sympathy and support. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="305" SPEAKER="Grimes Sen D.J." NAMEID="9V4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9V4">Senator GRIMES</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I wish to add briefly to the motion of condolence my words of sympathy to John Knight's family. He was a good, kindly and talented senator, as has been said. I was particularly associated with him in his consistent interest since he was elected to this Parliament in the affairs and the problems of the disabled in this community. Only recently he was organising a conference on this very important subject. One could also admire his non-dogmatic approach to foreign affairs. His sensible and reasoned contributions to debates on this matter impressed us all, I believe.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I think it is ironical that the last conversation I had with John Knight in this chamber was on a third interest of his, and that is the reform of the procedures of this Parliament. Perhaps his unfortunate death may make us all think seriously about reforming the sorts of procedures we use in this place which can contribute, I believe, to people's illnesses and ill health. To his wife, his children and the rest of his family I add my condolences. I am deeply grieved at the death of such a good and young man who had a great future ahead of him. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="305" SPEAKER="Sim Sen J.P." NAMEID="9R7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9R7">Senator SIM</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Western Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I join my colleagues in the Senate in expressing my very deep grief at the death of John Knight. Senator Scott made a comment about John Knight's contribution to the deliberations of the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. His great knowledge and his great integrity made a lasting contribution to the work of that Committee. Perhaps on a lighter side, my colleagues on the Committee will recall his insistence on correct punctuation. Commas and semicolons had to be always in the right place. Perhaps that is indicative of the man himself and the correctness of his life.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> With Senator Fred Chaney, I was at the hospital last night until the early hours of this morning and left not long before John died. I am sure that our lasting memories are of the fortitude of his wife, Karla. She is a most wonderful woman who bore the strains and stresses over the last days with tremendous courage. As we left the hospital in the early hours of this morning our hearts were with the woman we were leaving behind. I join my colleagues in expressing my deep grief and extend to Karla, the children, his mother and his sister, who have borne two tragedies in two days, our deepest sympathy. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="305" SPEAKER="Sibraa Sen K.W." NAMEID="EJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="EJ4">Senator SIBRAA</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I wish to be associated with the motion of condolence. I do so for a number of reasons but mainly because I feel that I knew John Knight probably as well as or better than any other honourable senator on this side of the chamber. When I was elected to the Senate in 1975 the first committee I served on was the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. Senator Knight and I continued to serve on that Committee over the last five years. When one spends that much time working with someone he gets to know him reasonably well.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> But the real friendship I developed with John Knight began when we both attended a series of seminars and conferences on the Pacific and South East Asia at the East West Center at the University of Hawaii and later in Washington. It was essential that we work closely together in presenting Australia's point of view as well as our own different parties' points of view. After these meetings John and I spent some time privately in the United States of America, sometimes staying with his friends and sometimes staying with mine. In 1979 he and I were part of a month long delegation to Africa. Again we shared accommodation when it was necessary. I will always remember with some humour-I am sure Senator Georges will remember too-one night in Kampala when we took turns in sleeping in the bath after our hotel room had been hit by shrapnel during the disturbances that followed the change of the presidency in Uganda. </PARA>
<PARA> Although Senator Knight and I often had strong differences of opinion on matters of foreign policy we were always able to discuss our differences over a few beers or after tennis and on many occasions reach a bipartisan position. Southern Africa, the Middle East and the South Pacific come readily to mind. In fact, in his speech in this place last Thursday evening he referred to the fact that he was strongly supporting a number of my suggestions on the report on the Association of South East Asian Nations presented by the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. Comments that he also made that night on Indonesia were discussed with me, Senator Primmer and some of our other colleagues beforehand. It was also important that that sense of co-operation existed between the Whips. Senator Robertson and I certainly had no complaints on that score. For these reasons I feel I had a close friendship with John Knight. Not only has the Government lost a good colleague but also the Senate has lost a good colleague. I have lost a good friend and colleague. To his wife and family I extend my sincere sympathy. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="306" SPEAKER="Hamer Sen D.J." NAMEID="4H4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4H4">Senator HAMER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There were many facets to the life of John Knight. I will dwell on one of them which was very important though not usually visible to the public. I refer to his contribution to parliamentary party committees. We are all aware of the influence these committees can have on national policy, albeit behind the scenes. I served with John Knight on two such government committees-the foreign affairs and defence committee and the committee on the arts. As chairman of those two committees and on behalf of the members I extend deepest sympathy to his wife Karla and his two children. As a member of the Government foreign affairs and defence committee, John made a distinguished contribution, particularly in the field of foreign affairs in which he had a special expertise. He always showed clarity of vision, concern for Australia's interests and sympathy for the reasonable rights of others. On the arts committee, he was the Australian Capital Territory representative. He worked hard and, where necessary, he fought hard for the cultural development of the national capital. In all his work on these committees he approached each problem, not in any rigid doctrinaire basis, but in an attempt to find out what was best and what was fairest. That is the way I shall remember him. He always fought for what was best and fairest.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="306" SPEAKER="Ryan Sen S.M." NAMEID="GD5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GD5">Senator RYAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I wish to add my support to the condolence motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate, Senator Carrick. Like John Knight, I was elected by the citizens of the Australian Capital Territory to represent them in this place for the last five years. John Knight was the first senator elected by the people of the Capital Territory. He and I were elected in 1975, but John got the highest primary vote. I believe that he was very proud of being the first senator for the Territory. Certainly he had good reason to be. The people of the Australian Capital Territory were very proud of John Knight, their first senator. They had good reason to be. We spent a lot of time together. Although we were elected as candidates for different political parties, and with distinct political philosophies, we shared many things. We shared the excitement and the honour of being the first representatives of the Australian Capital Territory in this place. We shared aspirations for the development of the Territory as a community where people live and not just as the national capital. I think, too, because we each had young families, that we shared some concerns and misgivings about how we would combine our parliamentary and community obligations with our family responsibilities. Despite our political differences we had a great deal in common.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Over the last five years we often worked together in a way that John always sought to make very co-operative. In fact, for that five years the Australian Capital Territory had two Australian Labor Party representatives and John Haslem and John Knight as Government representatives. We were a group often commented upon by people in the Australian Capital Territory for being together and working co-operatively. Many of the issues we were concerned with were not issues that needed to be discussed in ideological terms but rather in terms of how we could serve the community. I believed and continue to believe that our electors like to see their elected representatives working in a co-operative and harmonious way. Political life in this country is not often admired by the general public. There is much criticism of the way we comport ourselves on various occasions. It was really very fine that in the Australian Capital Territory we were perhaps able to demonstrate some of the more co-operative and human aspects of our work as elected representatives. </PARA>
<PARA> John's work in the Senate, his work on foreign affairs committees and so forth are very well known to all honourable senators. I pay tribute to the marvellous work he did over the last 5 1/2 years in the community as a very caring, very concerned and very involved local representative. In that work he was most ably and admirably supported by his wife, Karla, a woman of whom we are all extremely fond and for whom we feel most deeply at this time. Although his life ended tragically soon, he achieved an enormous amount. The citizens of the Australian Capital Territory have been very well served by their first senator. I know that they will always remember him for his service. Australians too, I think, have been honoured to have such a fine man as John Knight serving them in the national Parliament. I can only hope that the knowledge and the recognition of what an outstanding, compassionate, successful person John was in his public life, as well as his private life, will be at least some consolation to Karla, Joshua and Jason in the dreadful loss that they have experienced. On behalf of John's electors and my electors, I add my words of support to the motion of condolence. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="307" SPEAKER="Teague Sen B.C." NAMEID="PJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="PJ4">Senator TEAGUE</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I share the Senate's expression of enormous loss in the tragedy of our close friend. John Knight was a splendid person and an outstanding Australian. He brought energy, skill, an intelligent and fearless attitude to inquiry and an Australian kind of compassion to his successive careers of service to the Australian community. He was a diplomat for 10 years and a senator for five. His service was not limited to the Australian Capital Territory which he represented in the Senate and for which he acted day by day so tirelessly, professionally and well. His service was to the national interest of all ordinary Australians and, very explicitly, reached out to all the world.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> John and I often talked together about political and personal matters. We were the same age, we both had deep roots in Australia and we were Liberals with similar approaches and interests. Having undertaken tertiary studies and gained honours degrees in history, we both valued Australian politics. My wife Kathy and I over several years have felt very close to John and his wife Karla. They welcomed us when I first became a member of the Senate and often, since then, when our children too were together here in Canberra. It cuts deeply now to think that later this month we had planned so joyfully to go to Lake Ginninderra with our families. </PARA>
<PARA> John loved to be with his family, to be vigorous at sports, to hit the fresh air and to laugh a lot. Only last Wednesday we went out together into the sunshine of the Parliament's courts, he to play squash and I to play tennis. Last Easter John and I had an active one week visit to Taiwan. We went largely with regional foreign policy assessments in our minds. It was an occasion I will always remember, not least for the complete dedication John had for honestly and rationally serving Australia's best interests, but also for the clear intensity of his perceptions of the issues of foreign relations. Last Thursday I was reminded again of the kind of dedication John Knight had to these matters. That evening he had roundly participated in the Senate debate on relations between Australia and member countries of the Association of South East Asian Nations. After the Senate adjourned and towards midnight we met as we were preparing to leave Parliament House. We talked again of ASEAN, of a solution for the problem of Kampuchea, of nationalist movements in the Soviet Union and of the new implications of the politics of Islam. </PARA>
<PARA> When we think of John we think of his dear wife Karla, so marvellous and always so alive, and we think of his two strong little boys, Jason and Joshua, so much like John. For Karla and for all of us, the boys, as they grow up throughout their lives, will recall to us their father; they will remind us of John. We extend to Karla and the boys, John's mother and sister and all the Knight family, our true sympathy and our prayers. John was a good friend, a good senator. We will miss him greatly. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="307" SPEAKER="Puplick Sen C.J.G." NAMEID="TI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TI4">Senator PUPLICK</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Those of us in this place who revel, perhaps excessively, in our relative youth are rendered humble by tragedies such as the death of John Knight at the age of 37 years. Sic transit gloria mundi. As has been said, John was a fine representative of the Australian Capital Territory. The respect in which he was held, not only by his electors but also by the members of the Liberal Party in the Capital Territory, is perhaps evidenced by the fact that he is the only person I know of who has won Liberal Party preselection in absentia. He was, in fact, overseas serving in our Embassy in Saudi Arabia at the time of the preselection, but the preselection committee of the Liberal Party in the Capital Territory had sufficient knowledge of and faith in John Knight that despite his absence he won endorsement.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> John and I were friends for some years long before my entry into this Parliament. We had a couple of additional things in common apart from our philosophies and our views of the world. We were both very proud of our association with the Young Liberal Movement. We were both particularly interested in the affairs of the Indian sub-continent. He had served there as a diplomat and my father was born and brought up there. He spoke very fluent Hindi and I spoke a little-enough to enjoy the odd special joke that some knowledge of that language and its odd words allows one to indulge in. One is reminded of the view of the classical Greek poet to the effect that no man should be called happy until he has passed through his life full of sorrows and of woes. I simply want to add my personal expressions of sympathy to Karla and John's children on my own behalf and on behalf of my wife, Francesca, who is also a friend of theirs. I extend particularly my sympathy to John's mother, who tragically has lost both a husband and a son in the same week. I wish to say in conclusion: 'Farewell, my friend. The bell has tolled; it has indeed tolled for all of us'. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="308" SPEAKER="Colston Sen M.A." NAMEID="PF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="PF4">Senator COLSTON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In the time that I have been in this chamber I have never entered into a debate on a condolence motion, but this afternoon I feel compelled to do so. John Knight and I entered the Senate at the same time-after the 1975 election. Those of us who came here after 1975 tended to identify with one another, whether we were on this side of the chamber or the other. In this way I got to know John Knight very well. However, I came to know him even better when I served with him for some time on the Joint Committee on the Australian Capital Territory. I learned then what an enthusiastic representative he was for his electors in the Australian Capital Territory. I worked very happily under his chairmanship of the Committee. I learned then, too, how well respected he was not only on his side of the chamber but also on this side and outside in the community. I was reminded last year, when in Suva, of how well respected he was even beyond the shores of Australia. When I visited the office of the Australian High Commission in Suva many of his former colleagues in the Department of Foreign Affairs asked about him. From their comments I became well aware that the respect extended far beyond this place.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> When I learned at the weekend that John Knight had become seriously ill I was astounded. If I had been asked to look at all senators in this chamber and identify one person who might be placed in that position, John Knight probably would have been the last person I would have chosen. When I learned this morning of John's untimely death I felt it almost unbelievable, as I am sure many of us do now, that he has left us. John Knight's death is a tragic loss to the Senate, it is a tragic loss to the Australian Capital Territory and it represents a tragic loss to all of Australia. That loss, however, must be deeply overshadowed by the extreme and devastating loss that it is to his family. To them I extend my personal sympathy. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="308" SPEAKER="Walters Sen M.S." NAMEID="UJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UJ4">Senator WALTERS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I join with my colleagues in speaking to the motion of condolence. As all of my colleagues have stated, John's overriding attributes were his tolerance and kindness. He and Karla showed kindness to us when we first came to Canberra. He acted as host to so many of us and looked after us so well. He gave us advice on local matters when it was needed. His short period in the position of Government Whip has proved, I believe, that both sides of the House can get together in a way that the community can respect. I have never heard anyone complain of John's handling of his job as Whip. I have heard only praise. As has been said today, many of us have worked on committees with him. I have worked with him on two committees. He would attend other committees of which he was not a regular member whenever matters concerning his constituents were involved. He was an extremely hard worker. There is very little that I can add to what has already been said. Our own sadness and loss in this chamber are overshadowed only by the sympathy that we have for Karla, Jason and Joshua. I extend to them my personal sympathy along with that of my colleagues.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="308" SPEAKER="Young Sen H.W." NAMEID="HV7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="HV7">Senator YOUNG</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Today is a very sad day for the Senate because of the tragic death of John Knight. Above that it is a very sad day for his wife Karla, their two boys, and John's family. It is a sad day for this country also because of one so young being struck down in the prime of his life, particularly in view of the type of person that John Knight was. John, in his all too short span of life, achieved a great deal in the diplomatic world and then in the Senate chamber of this Federal Parliament. He dedicated himself to his task and never walked away from any responsibility; rather, he accepted a challenge with greater enthusiasm.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> During all the time he has been in the Parliament, with his application, dedication and above all his rare ability, he won respect and friendship and finally rose to become Government Whip. As Whip he continued to hold the respect of each and every one of us in this chamber. This has been exemplified today by those who have responded to this condolence motion. I join with those who have spoken in expressing to his wife, Karla, his two boys, his mother and his sister deepest sympathy in their tragic loss. It is a tragedy that has occurred all too soon, for he was a young man. John Knight will be missed in this chamber and in this country because he had so much more that he could have contributed in this world. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Harradine Sen B." NAMEID="6H4" PARTY="IND" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6H4">Senator HARRADINE</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I too should like to associate myself with the condolence motion. I am the only independent member of the Parliament and I know that it is not easy for the Government Whip or the Opposition Whip to control the only independent member of this Parliament. I was the recipient of the courteous, efficient service of John Knight in his position as Government Whip. I place on record my grateful appreciation for that. Obviously, from what has been said about the life of John Knight, his wife and children can be very proud of him. I should like to associate myself with the expressions of sympathy for his wife, his two children, his mother and his sister, who through the darkness of the coming days and months, by not forgetting what they have learned in the light, will come to a realisation of the ultimate reason for what now appears such a tragedy.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I invite honourable senators to signify their assent to the motion by standing in silence in their places.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative, honourable senators standing in their places. </PARA>
</INTERJECT>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Adjournment" PAGE="309"><TITLE>ADJOURNMENT</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Government in the Senate)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That, as a mark of respect to the memory of the late Senator John William Knight, the Senate do now adjourn till tomorrow at 10.30 a.m. </PARA>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
<PARA>Senate adjourned at 2.57 p.m. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE></CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS PAGE="309">
<TITLE>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA> The following answers to questions were circulated:</PARA></PROCTEXT>
<ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="309"><TITLE>Radon Gas: Mary Kathleen Mine</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="164">(Question No. 164)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Keeffe Sen J.B." NAMEID="SG7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SG7">Senator Keeffe</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister for National Development and Energy, upon notice, on 2 December 1980:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1) What is the volume of radon gas coming from the tailings in the Mary Kathleen mine area.</PARA>
<PARA> (2) Are such gases blown west of the tailings area; if not, in which direction do prevailing winds usually blow the gas.</PARA>
<PARA> (3) What proportion of the background particulate radiation exposure in Mount Isa results from Mary Kathleen.</PARA>
<PARA> (4) What are the seepage rates of contaminated waters from the tailings dam at Mary Kathleen.</PARA>
<PARA> (5) Does the Mary Kathleen mining company have any plans for the stabilisation of the tailings after mining ceases; if so, what are the costing estimates.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator Carrick</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1), (2), (3), (4) and (5) Responsibility for regulation of all mining operations within Queensland rests with the State Government from whom specific information on the Mary Kathleen operation should be sought.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="309"><TITLE>Distillate and Petrol Prices</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="210">(Question No. 210)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Thomas Sen A.M." NAMEID="TS7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TS7">Senator Thomas</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister for National Development and Energy the following question, upon notice, on 4 December 1980:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1) Have certain fuel companies, in the current Prices Justification Tribunal Inquiry, requested price increases of 2 cents per litre for distillate and only 0.9 cents per litre for petrol.</PARA>
<PARA> (2) What are the reasons for and the effects of the comparatively larger increase in distillate prices as against petrol.</PARA>
<PARA> (3) Is this disparity in the prices requested a result of (a) petrol price discounting; (b) the fact that people have been able to conserve petrol, but not distillate; (c) the fact that the productive industries which use distillate are locked into its use; or (d) the inability of the present refineries to vary their product mix or other reasons.</PARA>
<PARA> (4) Is it the Government's intention to take action to maintain the historic price relativity between petrol and distillate in view of the effect of distillate prices on the productive industries such as mining, farming and transport.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="309" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator Carrick</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1) Amoco has requested price increases of 2 cents per litre for distillate and 0.9 cents per litre for petrol. Examples of increases requested by other companies for higher operating costs, overheads and the effects of increased levels of capital expenditures, are shown in the table below:</PARA>
<PARA>Automotive Premium</PARA>
<PARA>distillate motor spirit</PARA>
<PARA>(cents per (cents per</PARA>
<PARA>litre) litre)</PARA>
<PARA>BP  1.20 1.10 Esso  1.79 1.79 Shell  2.23 2.00 Sleigh  0.96 0.96</PARA>
<PARA> The Prices Justification Tribunal has not yet concluded this inquiry.</PARA>
<PARA> Further applications were made to the Prices Justification Tribunal in respect of recent crude oil and product cost increases. Interim increases in the maximum justified wholesale price were approved as a result of increases in the following costs:</PARA>
<PARA> the price of imported crude oil rose as a result of the December meeting in Bali of the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC);</PARA>
<PARA> following the increase in the price of the marker crude Saudi Arabian Light, the import parity price of indigenous crude oil was raised on 1 January 1981;</PARA>
<PARA> increases in the proportion of imported crude to local crude used by refineries;</PARA>
<PARA> increases in the costs of imported products; and</PARA>
<PARA> increases in the costs of working capital.</PARA>
<PARA> The increases for the abovementioned companies were:</PARA>
<PARA>Automotive Premium</PARA>
<PARA>distillate motor spirit</PARA>
<PARA>(cents per (cents per</PARA>
<PARA>litre) litre)</PARA>
<PARA>Amoco  2.06 2.06 BP  1.90 1.90 Esso  1.57 1.57 Shell  2.11 2.22 Sleigh  1.35 1.43</PARA>
<PARA> In this instance some of the price increases for motor spirit exceed the price increases for automotive distillate.</PARA>
<PARA> (2) and (3) Both in Australia and overseas, the impact of higher petrol prices has led to a contraction in the demand for petrol relative to the demand for distillates. The opportunities for conserving diesel are rather less than the opportunities for saving petrol. Several key growth industries such as transport, agriculture and the mining industry are significant users of distillates.</PARA>
<PARA> Middle distillates (kerosene, jet fuel, heating oil and automotive distillate) have grown from 28.6 per cent of consumption of major petroleum products in 1978-79 to 30.1 per cent in 1979-80 and 31.4 per cent in the six months to 31 December 1980. By contrast petrol consumption has declined from 48.2 per cent of 1978-79 consumption of major petroleum products to 44.4 per cent in 1979-80, but increased to 45.5 per cent in the six months to 31 December 1980. As a percentage of consumption for major petroleum products, the 2.7 per cent reduction in petrol consumption over these 30 months correspnds closely with the 2.8 per cent increase in demand for middle distillates.</PARA>
<PARA> Australian refineries to date have been designed to maximise their production of petrol. With a shift in the pattern of demand for petroleum products, refiners have several investment options to increase their proportion of middle distillates. Whether or not these investments are made will depend on the companies' assessment of viability which in part, will depend on their perception of price movements.</PARA>
<PARA> The applications to the Prices Justification Tribunal for price increases were in some cases greater for automotive distillate than for petrol. This may be attributed to the operation of market forces already described. Larger price increases have generally been sought where demand is relatively strong.</PARA>
<PARA> The recent incidence of petrol discounting appears to have been caused by refiner/marketers wishing to maintain their market shares in a contracting market. However the demand for diesel fuel has been relatively more buoyant and, perhaps as a consequence, there was little evidence of discounting.</PARA>
<PARA> (4) The Government recognises the importance of distillate prices to the economy as a whole and to particular industries, such as mining, farming and transport. However, there is a need to ensure a continuation of the investment programs required to meet the continuing growth in distillate demands. A fixed price relationship between petrol and distillate could affect the incentives to the refining companies to undertake this investment. Maintenance of our present level of supply security implies that it is important to ensure that the future growth in distillate demand can continue to be met from Australian refineries.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON></ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS></HANSARD>

