<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" []>
<HANSARD DATE="30/04/1981" PROOF="No" PAGE="1541" CHAMBER = "Senate" PARLIAMENT.NO = "32" SESSION.NO = "1" PERIOD.NO = "2" > 
<CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><BUSINESS.START>
<DAY.START DATE="30/04/1981">Thursday, 30 April 1981</DAY.START>
<PROCTEXT><PARA></PARA>
<PARA> The DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator C. R. Maunsell) took the chair at 10.30 a.m., and read prayers.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</BUSINESS.START><PETITION.GRP PAGE="1541">
<TITLE>PETITIONS</TITLE>
<PETITION PAGE="1541" PRESENTERS="GIETZELT" NAMEIDS="RG4">
<TITLE>Education Funding</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="GIETZELT" NAMEID="RG4" PARTY="unknown" ELECTORATE="unknown">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RG4">Senator GIETZELT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I present the following petition from 81 citizens of Australia:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. A petition of the undersigned citizens, residents within the Federal electorate of Dundas, respectfully showeth:</PARA>
<PARA> Our dismay at the reductions in the total expenditure implemented in 1980 and proposed for 1981 and in particular on government schools and colleges.</PARA>
<PARA> Our concern at the immediate and long-term effects such reductions are having, and will have, upon the educational needs and welfare of the children and students within public schools, Technical and Further Education Colleges, Colleges of Advanced Education and Universities.</PARA>
<PARA> Our further concern that education, which is a major element in the public sector of the Australian economy, has been consistently down-graded from a position of importance in the development of the National economy as a whole.</PARA>
<PARA> Our affirmation that Australia's own development depends upon the development of its most important natural resource, our children, and that education must be restored to a position of major priority for this task by this and all future Federal Governments.</PARA>
<PARA> We call upon the Federal Government to immediately restore and increase substantially its allocation of resources to education in government schools and colleges in order to achieve these ends.</PARA>
<PARA> And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.</PARA>
</SPEECH></PETITION>
<PETITION PAGE="1541" PRESENTERS="MELZER" NAMEIDS="OL7">
<TITLE>Defence Service Home Loans</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="MELZER" NAMEID="OL7" PARTY="unknown" ELECTORATE="unknown">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OL7">Senator MELZER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I present the following petition from 48 citizens of Australia:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:</PARA>
<PARA> That the members of the Women's Services of the 1939-45 War not at present considered eligible for Defence Service Home Loans should qualify as 'Australian Soldiers' under the Defence Service Homes Act. They volunteered for service with the Naval, Military and Air Forces, serving wherever they were sent in whatever capacity they were required and yet are refused Defence Service Home Loans.</PARA>
<PARA> They took the oath to resist His Majesty's enemies which meant to fight His Majesty's enemies, and although not used in actual combat in war zones, they were available for that use and had sufficiently grave need arisen would have been used, to serve with distinction as have women of other lands.</PARA>
<PARA> In accordance with the Acts and Regulations of the period, the women of the Military Forces had enlisted for service anywhere, some of the Naval women to sail in any waters, others with service on warships optional, while the women of the Air Force could have been sent to Papua New Guinea or other territories under the control or care of Australia.</PARA>
<PARA> Ex-servicemen of the Royal Australian Navy, the Australian Imperial Force and the Royal Australian Air Force who volunteered in the 1939-45 War but were not sent to War Zones are granted home loans. Not to grant eligibility to all ex-servicewomen of 1939-45 War is unjust and unfair.</PARA>
<PARA> Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that you favourably consider amending the Defence Service Homes Act by repealing sub-section 4 (2A) (b) (c) (d) of the Principal Act as amended by No. 137 of 1978, and grant eligibility to all members of the Women's Royal Australian Naval Service, the Australian Women's Army Service, the Women's Auxiliary Australian Air Force, the Australian Army Medical Women's Service, and the Voluntary Aid Detachment of 1939-45 War.</PARA>
<PARA> And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.</PARA>
</SPEECH></PETITION>
<PARA>Petitions received.</PARA></PETITION.GRP><QWN PAGE="1541">
<TITLE>QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</TITLE>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1541">
<TITLE>HEALTH CARE FOR DISADVANTAGED PERSONS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Social Security. I refer him to the statement relating to health which was brought down last night. I ask: Is the Department of Social Security to be responsible for classifying the disadvantaged groups defined in the Government's health statement? How does the Department propose to assess the eligibility of people who are in and out of the work force for short periods, doing casual and part time work and so on? How often does it expect to have to assess people as disadvantaged? Will it reissue cards each time it makes an assessment? Given that the Government expects to pay for a million disadvantaged people a year, how many cards does the Department expect to issue for temporary purposes?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M." NAMEID="EF4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="SOCIAL SECURITY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="EF4">Senator CHANEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Department of Social Security will have the administrative responsibility for this, although other departments will also be involved. For example, the Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs will be responsible for identifying migrants and refugees who, under the arrangements, will have six months' qualification for disadvantaged status.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Button" NAMEID="4F4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator Button</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;They are easy, aren't they?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="EF4">Senator CHANEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;They, of course, are easy. In addition, there are categories of persons who are identified by their status as social security beneficiaries. They too are easy. The categories of beneficiaries who give rise to potential difficulty are those classified according to income. An important element of protecting their interests will be that prior classification will not be required for them to attract benefit. In other words, it will be possible for them to seek and obtain medical assistance and subsequently to seek from my Department classification as disadvantaged which will permit them to receive benefits. All of the administrative details have not been worked out. I will examine in detail the series of questions asked by the honourable senator and give him a more detailed reply. Some form of card will be issued to people who identify themselves and who fit within the income limits which have been defined. That will entitle them to the benefits of disadvantaged status which will cover them for their health costs.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I wish to ask a supplementary question. Do I take it that it is implicit in the answer the Minister has given that low income earners who are not recipients of pensions or benefits will have to front up, as it were, to the Department of Social Security to collect their disadvantaged cards? Will that be a consequence?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1541" SPEAKER="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M." NAMEID="EF4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="SOCIAL SECURITY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="EF4">Senator CHANEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There will be a requirement for people who wish to have prior cover to go to the Department of Social Security to obtain the necessary identification. That will involve, obviously, their indicating their income position and the number of children they have because the income level varies according to the number of children. There is a $20 adjustment for each child of the family. An important point which I mentioned in the original answer is that it will not be necessary for a person to have done that prior to seeking medical attention.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1542">
<TITLE>PROPOSED TAX CUTS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Teague Sen B.C." NAMEID="PJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="PJ4">Senator TEAGUE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Treasurer and relates to the Government's announcement yesterday of substantial tax cuts of approximately $500m which will operate from July. Will the details of these tax cuts be available before the Parliament rises or will they be contained in the Budget statements? Will the pay-as-you-earn deductions taking account of these tax cuts be available from the beginning of July?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Guilfoyle Sen The Hon Dame M.G.C." NAMEID="6D7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FINANCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6D7">Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Treasurer made a statement on taxation matters yesterday. He mentioned that legislation providing for the half-tax indexation adjustment will be introduced later this session. He said that he will be providing at a later date details of the half-indexation factor to apply in respect of the 1981-82 year and details of the impact of half-indexation on taxation scales in that year. I think we will need to wait for further information from the Treasurer before I am able to provide any more information to the honourable senator. I also would need to await the Treasurer's response to the details of the policy change concerning the concessional rebate for health insurance that was announced yesterday.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1542">
<TITLE>EXPORTS OF KANGAROO PRODUCTS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Mulvihill Sen J.A." NAMEID="GM7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GM7">Senator MULVIHILL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Home Affairs and Environment. In view of the action of the United States Government in lifting its long term ban on the importation of Australian kangaroo products, what action is contemplated to ensure that the decision does not unleash what I would call unbridled fauna carnage? Will the existing plan, concerning adequate culling, quotas, tags and all the rest of it, be rigidly adhered to? When will these quotas end? In particular I ask, and I am not indicting the vast number of Australian land owners but am referring to the larrikin element that abounds among the commercial kangaroo product exporters of Australia, what efforts will be made to ensure rigidly that if there is genuine culling in some areas-I do not deny that there should be-the rarer species of kangaroo will not be caught under the guise of adequate culling?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am aware that the United States of America has lifted the bans on the importation of kangaroo products into that country. The honourable senator asked about the regulations that will apply here to the culling of kangaroos. The Commonwealth plays a significant role in the establishment and maintenance of the States' kangaroo harvesting quotas. The then Minister for Home Affairs and Environment, Mr MacKellar, agreed to the present quotas as recently as 6 March this year. The Minister for Home Affairs and Environment has advised that the lifting of the importation bans by the United States will have no effect whatsoever on Australian quotas. The quotas will not be affected by the new arrangements. I will have to seek for the honourable senator information as to the date on which the present quotas will end. I undertake to get that information. I will also pass on the honourable senator's concern that the rarer species of macropods should be protected in any culling program that takes place.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Mulvihill Sen J.A." NAMEID="GM7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GM7">Senator MULVIHILL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr Deputy President, I wish to ask a supplementary question. Can we ascertain whether the ministerial council responsible for wildlife conservation, which is usually chaired by the Federal Minister responsible for the environment, proposes to have an early summit meeting? Without being too suspicious, I feel that one or two States will be under a lot of pressure to fudge the quotas that have been agreed to. Could that matter be looked into?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1542" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I could have added, in answering the original question, that Senator Mulvihill may well know that quite a bit of work has gone into reintroducing some rare species of wallabies and kangaroos into this country. I remind the honourable senator of the parma wallaby which my friend Mr Peter Piggott has bred on his property in the Blue Mountains. I do not know whether such a summit meeting is intended, but I undertake to obtain that information too from the Minister.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1543">
<TITLE>APPEALS TO THE PRIVY COUNCIL</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1543" SPEAKER="Puplick Sen C.J.G." NAMEID="TI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TI4">Senator PUPLICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask the Attorney-General: In the event of the State of New South Wales requesting the Federal Government to assist it in abolishing all appeals from New South Wales courts to the Privy Council, would the Federal Government be prepared to do all within its powers, especially those available in placitum (xxxviii) of section 51 of the Constitution, to facilitate this long overdue and widely supported legal reform? Would the Federal Government be prepared to assist New South Wales even if other States did not wish to be associated with such changes? Would not a refusal by the Federal Government to assist in such an endeavour be interpreted both as a reflection on the competence, authority and status of the High Court of Australia and as an unwillingness to give real meaning to the term 'co-operative federalism'?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1543" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Some time ago the New South Wales Parliament requested the Commonwealth Government to exercise the constitutional powers that are available to it to abolish appeals to the Privy Council from New South Wales. The Commonwealth Government has also had requests from the Victorian Parliament and the Tasmanian Parliament to exercise similar powers in relation to other matters where those States are still suffering under constitutional constraints-what we call residual links with the United Kingdom. At a Premiers Conference nearly two years ago this whole subject was discussed and the Standing Committee of Attorneys-General was asked to look at the whole question of residual constitutional links with the United Kingdom, other than links with the Crown. The Standing Committee has been doing that and at its meeting on 10 April last it finalised a report for the Premiers Conference which will take place at the end of June.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The view that the Commonwealth Government has taken all along in relation to this matter is that it wishes to see a resolution of all these problems affecting all the States and it wishes to do so in the one exercise. The Commonwealth Government's policy is quite clear. We wish to see the abolition of appeals to the Privy Council and we make no bones about that. In fact, I reiterated that as recently as on the occasion of the retirement of the Chief Justice of the High Court of Australia. The reason we have not been prepared to act on the request of one State is that we believe this matter relates very fundamentally to constitutional structure. There is also some doubt as to how far we can act on one State's request if other States say it affects them, although that is a legal argument under the Constitution. From the point of view of policy, we have felt that it was desirable to see whether we could get a resolution of these problems affecting all the States and to do it all in the one exercise.</PARA>
<PARA> As I have said, the Premiers Conference two years ago took the same view and referred this question to the Standing Committee. When the Premiers Conference gets this report-not at the meeting to be held in a few days time but at the normal Conference held at the end of June-it will, of course, have to be decided by the Premiers whether it is possible to resolve this matter in one package or whether other more limited steps are necessary. As to some of the questions Senator Puplick has asked, such as whether the Commonwealth Government will act on the request of New South Wales alone and so on, we have reserved our consideration until we see whether this exercise we have embarked upon can be successful. I do not think there is any doubt whatever-as I said, it has been confirmed by the Premiers-that the attitude the Commonwealth Government has adopted is the preferable course. We hope that it will be successful.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1544">
<TITLE>REPATRIATION BENEFITS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Tate Sen M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator TATE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question, which is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Defence, concerns the callous refusal of the Government to permit sailors who served on HMAS Sydney and its destroyer escorts during the Vietnam war to share in the benefits of our repatriation system. Is it a fact that the coastal waters off Vietnam through which those vessels moved were declared a war zone? Is it a fact that the port in which the vessels were anchored was defoliated in order to clear the area of Vietcong snipers? Is it a fact that on occasions when they were at anchor the sailors were closed up at war stations because of the dangers of their situation? Is it a fact that diving teams were constantly sent down to ensure that the hull and anchor cables were not in jeopardy because of mines? Why does the Government, led by a Prime Minister who was a Minister for Defence during that Vietnam war, continue callously to refuse to recognise the fact that these sailors were, indeed, exposed to danger and ought to receive the benefits of our repatriation system?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I think that is the sort of question that ought to be placed on the Notice Paper. As Senator Tate has asked me the question, I will refer it to the Minister for Defence and ask him to provide a detailed answer to the honourable senator.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1544">
<TITLE>AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY: TRAFFIC LAWS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Mason Sen C.V.J." NAMEID="YJ7" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YJ7">Senator MASON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to Senator Durack as Attorney-General and as Minister representing the Minister for the Capital Territory. Is it a fact that faults in the Canberra traffic laws mean that for more than a year now persons parking illegally in areas reserved for disabled persons, doctors, diplomats and members of parliament cannot be penalised in the courts? When will this absurd, anomalous and notorious situation be rectified?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The administration of the ordinance is in the hands of the Minister for the Capital Territory. I do not represent him, but I will refer the question to him and ask him to reply.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1544">
<TITLE>AUSTRALIAN LAW REFORM COMMISSION TRIBAL LAW INQUIRY</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Ryan Sen S.M." NAMEID="GD5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GD5">Senator RYAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs aware of strong criticisms by the National Aboriginal Conference delegates attending the World Council of Indigenous Peoples of the Government's handling of the Australian Law Reform Commission inquiry into tribal law? Is the Minister aware of a reply to me from the Attorney-General to question No. 291 in which he states that no funds have been provided to the Australian Law Reform Commission specifically to provide for proper mechanisms for consultation with Aboriginal communities on the tribal law issue and that no funds have been provided by the Department of Aboriginal Affairs for translation and transport expenses that will be incurred if proper consultation, as desired by the NAC, is to take place? What assurances can the Minister give that funds will be made available to ensure that the tribal law inquiry will be a genuine exercise in consultation with Aboriginal communities and not merely a tokenistic and pointless charade?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am aware of papers which were prepared by officers assisting the Australian delegation at the World Council of Indigenous Peoples. I am not certain how many of the recommendations put forward have been accepted as the view of the conference. I have no reason to doubt that the content is as Senator Ryan has stated it. I must say that I am not aware of the answer she received from the Attorney-General to Question on Notice No. 291. I think what is important is that the Australian Law Reform Commissioners, particularly Mr Debelle, have been moving very extensively through Aboriginal communities. They have been consulting very extensively. They have been seeking the views of involved people in a very extensive way. In fact, I was asked today about a meeting soon to take place in Lismore in New South Wales. I have read the reports of meetings which have taken place in many outback centres as they have sought Aboriginal views. The question the honourable senator asked, however, is really one which I need to discuss with my colleague the Attorney-General. At the moment I cannot give her the kind of assurances that she seeks.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Ryan Sen S.M." NAMEID="GD5" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GD5">Senator RYAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask a supplementary question. Will the Minister assure us that he will look at the specific problem of providing funds for such purposes as the translation into Aboriginal languages of the Law Reform Commission's draft paper-such funds have not yet been made available and such translations have not yet been made; therefore, consultation cannot take place with people who are not speakers of English-and for the costs of transportation of Aboriginals living in remote communities to centres the Law Reform Commission is visiting? The Minister will be aware that the Law Reform Commission is not visiting all the remote areas. If there is no translation of the Law Reform Commission's proposals into tribal languages and if people living in remote areas are unable to get to the places the Law Reform Commission is visiting, then there will be no consultation. So it is funds for those specific purposes that I am now asking the Minister to look at.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1544" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will certainly examine both those matters.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1545">
<TITLE>ROYAL HOBART HOSPITAL</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Walters Sen M.S." NAMEID="UJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UJ4">Senator WALTERS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is the Minister representing the Minister for Health aware that 400 staff members at the Royal Hobart Hospital last night called for the resignation of the Tasmanian Minister for Health following the rundown of staffing levels at that hospital which has caused the closing of wards and necessitated telegrams being sent to 69 expectant mothers, who were told that they could not have their babies at the hospital that month but would have to seek accommodation elsewhere? Could the Tasmanian Minister for Health apply to the Commonwealth to increase bed charges for insured patients within that hospital? If he did so, would permission be granted immediately by the Commonwealth?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In the statement which I read yesterday in this place on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Health, I identified as one arm of the Government's strategy the hope that the States would raise increased revenues for both in-patient and out-patient services. In that statement I said:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>. . . particularly if the States raise the bed day charge in public hospitals from $50 for a shared room and $75 for a private room to a level which more closely approximates the actual daily bed cost involved.</PARA>
<PARA>Of course, the daily bed costs of Australian hospitals, particularly hospitals of the size and complexity of the Royal Hobart Hospital, are far in excess of those amounts. The daily bed costs of some hospitals exceed $200. I was not aware that 400 staff members of the Royal Hobart Hospital had made the call for the resignation of the Tasmanian Minister for Health, as indicated by Senator Walters. If the Tasmanian Minister for Health did make application to the Federal Government to increase bed charges in the public hospitals, it would be consistent with our announcement yesterday for permission to be forthcoming. I am advised that approval would in fact be forthcoming and that such charges could then be introduced at as early a date as the Tasmanian Government wished to introduce them.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1545">
<TITLE>AIDS FOR THE DEAF</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Hearn Sen J.M." NAMEID="FE7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="FE7">Senator HEARN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is the Minister representing the Minister for Communications aware that an aid known as Porta Printer II, designed to assist the deaf with communication, is available only at the cost of $800 a unit-$1,600 for two people to communicate-plus the cost of installation? As most deaf people cannot aspire to highly paid jobs because of their communication difficulty, they would be unable to afford to buy this unit. Could this equipment be provided at a reasonable rental for those in need of this facility?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am interested in the honourable senator's reference to an apparatus which she called the Porta Printer II and her indication that it costs $800 a unit, which means that it would cost $1,600 for two people to communicate. I will have to refer this matter to the Minister for Communications. I will do so and obtain an early answer for her.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1545">
<TITLE>AIR FARE INCREASES</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Watson Sen J.O.W." NAMEID="VJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VJ4">Senator WATSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Can the Minister representing the Minister for Transport assure the Senate that when the next air fare increase is approved no recognition will be allowed for the costs incurred by strike action? Further, does the Minister not agree that the past practice of passing on such strike costs in the form of higher approved air fares places the airline industry in an unfair position compared with other industries in relation to union negotiations?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1545" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will refer the substance of the question to my colleague in another place. I understand that there is an intention to establish an air fares tribunal for the future. I am not aware of the terms of reference or the functions of that tribunal, but I will draw attention to Senator Watson's suggestion regarding the costs of strike action. It is true that these actions and rising costs put the airlines in a particularly invidious position. They inevitably cause not only the inconvenience of the days when the strike is on but also considerably higher fares spread over a period. So, as I said yesterday, we have a situation in which a small minority seeking its own self-interest punishes the total community for a very long period. Australia will have to realise that it cannot have a continuous outbreak of such instances which are in themselves a form of civil war and which are both counter-productive in the long run for those who bring on the strikes and very punitive upon the community as a whole. I will refer the question to the Minister.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1546">
<TITLE>SUPPORTING PARENT'S BENEFIT</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1546" SPEAKER="Melzer Sen J.I." NAMEID="OL7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OL7">Senator MELZER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I address a question to the Minister for Social Security. Is it a fact that the Family Law Act recognises, for the purposes of divorce, that a marriage might have irretrievably broken down, even though the two parties remain living under the same roof, and that in the past the Department of Social Security has recognised this by paying supporting parent benefit to eligible people, usually women, in these circumstances? Is the Minister aware that in recent weeks a directive has been issued from Canberra curtailing the payment of this benefit? Does the Minister realise that the effect of this directive will be that the supporting parent, usually the mother, and the child will have no option but to turn themselves out on to the street in order to be eligible for benefits? Is the Minister aware that many women's refuges are threatened with closure due to the reduction in funding and that they will not be able to cope with any increased demand on their services? Is the Government, through the Social Services Act, attempting to apportion blame, contrary to the intention of the Family Law Act? What steps will the Minister take to have this directive repealed and so restore dignity, which was intended by the Family Law Act?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1546" SPEAKER="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M." NAMEID="EF4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="SOCIAL SECURITY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="EF4">Senator CHANEY</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;As far as I can recollect, my attention has not been drawn to any directive of the nature mentioned by the honourable senator. I think it is the sort of thing that I would remember had it been drawn to my attention. I will make inquiries to see whether there is any truth in the matter which obviously has been raised with her. Without making those inquiries I cannot deal adequately with a number of the parts of the question. As I say, I will make those inquiries as soon as possible. I am not aware of any reduction in the funding of women's refuges. Only a small portion of the funding for women's refuges is actually made through my Department. I think the honourable senator will be aware that the child care component of funding comes from the Department of Social Security. The major funding comes through the Department of Health, usually through a State department. I am not aware of any reduction in funding. I suspect the position is, as is so often the case when a reduction of funding is alleged, that there simply have not been as many increases as have been requested by the organisations which are involved in providing those shelters.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> With respect to the apportionment of blame in the situation of marriage breakdown, elements of the income security system remain which require the officers of the Department of Social Security to make decisions about whether desertion has occurred. It is true that that has ceased to be a relevant matter within matrimonial law, but it does remain a relevant factor in the consideration of certain benefits paid by my Department. That gives rise to some difficulties and it is a matter to which my attention has been drawn and which I have under consideration. I think that one of the most difficult tasks the Department has is in dealing with situations where it is called upon to make decisions relevant to the living relationships of couples. That applies in the circumstances raised by the honourable senator in her question and in the assessment of whether a de facto relationship exists in the case of unmarried couples. I think that this places a very heavy burden on officers. I have given some consideration to whether some more objective criteria, such as the sharing of expenses, might not provide a better test and one which would be less difficult both for the individuals concerned and for the officers who are called upon to administer the benefits.</PARA>
<PARA> I will take up the matters raised by the honourable senator and let her have a more detailed reply. The point that the honourable senator has raised is but one of a series of difficulties which, probably, can never be totally removed but which we might be able to ameliorate.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1546">
<TITLE>OIL EXPLORATION IN NORTHERN TERRITORY</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1546" SPEAKER="Kilgariff Sen B.F." NAMEID="8H7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8H7">Senator KILGARIFF</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is the Minister for National Development and Energy able to confirm that at present some 18 on-shore petroleum permit applications in the Northern Territory await Government consideration and that the majority of these applications have been held in obeyance for some time as they are subject to Aboriginal land claims? Can the Minister also confirm that the applications cover a proposed minimum expenditure commitment of some $65m and the drilling of 52 exploration wells? Having in mind the very real need to assess future oil reserves on and off the Australian mainland, can action be taken to expedite the granting of permits for oil exploration in the Northern Territory?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1546" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Of course, Senator Kilgariff will realise that on-shore exploration for petroleum in the Northern Territory is the responsibility of the Northern Territory Minister for Mines and Energy, Mr Tuxworth. Therefore, I cannot readily confirm the figures mentioned by the honourable senator, but I understand that generally the position is as he has outlined it. I completely agree that it is most desirable to expedite further exploration for petroleum reserves, both on-shore and off-shore, in Australia. I will suggest to Mr Tuxworth that, if he will provide me with the relevant details of the applications that are being held up, I will take up the matter with my colleague, the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, with a view to expediting decisions in respect of Aboriginal land claims.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1547">
<TITLE>MENTALLY HANDICAPPED OFFENDERS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="Coleman Sen R.N." NAMEID="5V4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5V4">Senator COLEMAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Attorney-General. I draw his attention to a report that appeared in the Daily News on 17 March 1981 under the headline 'Two Options for Retarded: Judge'. The report was of Justice Brinsden's finding in a case in which a mentally retarded person, reported to have a mental age of 8 to 10 years, was found guilty of the rape of a 63-year-old woman. Justice Brinsden said the lack of a suitable institution in Western Australia meant prison and probation were the only available choices. Does the Minister agree that in such a case neither prison nor probation may be suitable? If so, does the Federal Government, in the International Year of Disabled Persons, intend to look at this area with a view to finding a more productive setting in which offenders could serve their sentences and at the same time receive such assistance as is necessary to adjust to living within society?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The matter raised by Senator Coleman, as far as the legal aspects are concerned, seems to me certainly to refer to State law and the responsibilities of the State Government. As to what arrangements in regard to mentally retarded people may be contemplated between the Commonwealth and a State, that would be a matter for the Minister for Social Security. If his attention was not focused on Senator Coleman's question, I will make sure it is.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1547">
<TITLE>HOBART AIRPORT: EMERGENCY RESCUE SERVICES</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="Archer Sen B.R." NAMEID="IE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="IE4">Senator ARCHER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask a question of the Minister representing the Minister for Transport. In view of the fact that the recent crash of an aircraft carrying six people en route from Victoria occurred in water within the approaches to the Hobart airport and as all three commercial aircraft which have crashed approaching or leaving Hobart airport have crashed into water, will the Minister urgently reconsider the decision made some two years ago to remove the emergency rescue boat from the Hobart airport?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have some advice on this matter of the search and rescue arrangements at Hobart airport. My advice is that the search and rescue launch previously operated by rescue and firefighting services at Hobart airport was withdrawn, for a series of cogent reasons, in favour of a helicopter operation. First of all, delays were involved in getting the launch to the crash site in Frederick Henry Bay-for example, up to one hour or more-because of road transport from the airport to the launch site followed by the time taken for the launch to negotiate the distance to the crash site. Senator Archer would appreciate that that is a very real disability. Secondly, it was extremely difficult to get the launch into the water in heavy seas, as well as highly dangerous for the fire crew engaged in the rescue operation. Thirdly, in heavy seas, provided the launch could be put into the water, visibility for search purposes was very limited. Further, a launch search at night would be extremely ineffective compared with the current use of a helicopter which is able to hover at will and also to use a very effective search light, as was done during the rescue operation in Frederick Henry Bay on Monday, 27 April, during the very successful search for the crashed Aero Commander. I am advised by my colleague, the Minister for Transport, that, for the reasons I have stated, he does not intend to alter the existing search and rescue arrangements at Hobart airport.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1547">
<TITLE>BUDGET LEAKS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="McAuliffe Sen R.E." NAMEID="9K7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="9K7">Senator McAULIFFE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. Has he seen a report by the journalist Maximilian Walsh that alleges that the leak of the contents of the Budget last year to Mr Laurie Oakes came from a member of the Government? Is the Minister aware that Mr Walsh alleges that the leak was designed to play down coverage in the media of the announcement that the Government was going to sell to private interests 15 per cent of quotas controlling the import of textiles, clothing and footwear? Finally, I ask the Minister: Should not a public inquiry be held into the Budget leak so that suspicions about the matter can be either dispelled or confirmed?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1547" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Budget leaks are very serious matters. I think Senator McAuliffe would acknowledge that fact and the Government certainly would. Therefore, anybody who is in possession of information which would confirm that a particular person was responsible for the leak has one public duty and one public duty only-to come forward and disclose that information. If Mr Walsh has that information he should not simply assert it, which is not good enough, because the ethics of this matter apply to journalists as they do to any member of the public or to the Parliament. If he has that information he should bring it forward and it will be readily examined. I have not seen his assertion. I confirm that Budget leaks are profoundly serious matters, and I invite him to bring his information forward.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1548">
<TITLE>EXPORT OF GRAIN TO SOVIET UNION</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Jessop Sen D.S." NAMEID="2G7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2G7">Senator JESSOP</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs and refer to the recent decision by the Government to lift restrictions on the sale of grain to the Soviet Union. Was the Government aware of the decision made by President Reagan before he announced the United States attitude to this subject? Can the Minister provide me with further details concerning the decision recently made by the Australian Government?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Guilfoyle Sen The Hon Dame M.G.C." NAMEID="6D7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FINANCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6D7">Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; I understand that the Government was kept informed of the United States policy on this matter and that consultations and discussions were held between the two governments. The Foreign Minister recently announced our attitude on this matter, and that statement setting out the Government's position was made this week, I think.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coleman" NAMEID="5V4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5V4">Senator Coleman</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It did not say that trade had increased by 400 per cent while the sanctions applied, though.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6D7">Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; If there are particular aspects that Senator Jessop wishes to have discussed with the Foreign Minister, I could see that any details, including the matter raised by Senator Coleman, are provided to Senator Jessop for his information.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1548">
<TITLE>TEXTILE, CLOTHING AND FOOTWEAR QUOTAS</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Finance and I ask: Is the Government planning later this year to sell 15 per cent of the quotas controlling the import into Australia of textiles, clothing and footwear? Will the sale of 15 per cent of the quotas give a few importers, not- ably the larger retail chains, the chance to tie up quotas? Will it also enable these importers to determine the real tariff level that the market will bear and to mark up their imported goods to that level at a potential profit of millions of dollars?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Guilfoyle Sen The Hon Dame M.G.C." NAMEID="6D7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FINANCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6D7">Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; I think the matter of the sale of quotas ought properly to be referred to the Minister representing the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs. There are provisions for the sale of quotas, and I think it is known that retail chains have been purchasing quotas from those who have them available for sale. I am not aware of the precise detail requested by Senator Button, but I will refer the question to the relevant Minister and see what information can be provided as soon as possible.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1548">
<TITLE>TELEPHONE SUBSCRIBERS: INVASION OF PRIVACY</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Colston Sen M.A." NAMEID="PF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="PF4">Senator COLSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question to the Minister representing the Minister for Communications is prompted by the increasing number of complaints I have received from telephone subscribers who are being harassed by sales men and women making unsolicited telephone calls to sell their wares. These telephone subscribers object to the privacy of their homes being invaded in this way. Can the Minister advise whether such invasions of privacy can be prevented and, if they cannot be prevented, will the Minister investigate whether some measures can be introduced to stamp out this practice?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I must say that I also am aware of expressions of concern from numbers of my acquaintances and some of my constituents about unsolicited telephone calls from canvassers for particular causes or from people trying to sell services or other matters. I have been approached in this way and I have found it most distasteful. I do not know what can be done specifically to deal with what I think is a very legitimate request from the honourable senator. I will undertake to obtain this information for him.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1548">
<TITLE>GOVERNMENT INFORMATION UNIT</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Gietzelt Sen A.T." NAMEID="RG4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RG4">Senator GIETZELT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask the Leader of the Government in the Senate whether, since the recent disclosures in the Senate and before a Senate Estimates committee of the activities of the Government Information Unit-perhaps one could call it the Government's propaganda unit-he has had any discussions with Mr Laurie Power, the officer of the Unit who operates out of the Minister's Sydney office. Has he asked Mr Power to cease party political activities either on the Minister' behalf or on behalf of the Liberal Party?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1548" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have not sought to talk to Mr Power because Mr Power understands quite clearly that his role is not to pursue party political activities on my behalf or on behalf of others.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Chipp" NAMEID="3V4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="3V4">Senator Chipp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;How does he know that?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;He, of course, knows that because I conveyed that message to him quite some months ago. I will bring the question to the attention of the Minister in charge of the Government Information Unit to see whether there is any need for rules to be laid down. It may well be that that is so. If it is, the Minister can examine the matter.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1549">
<TITLE>MILITARY-STYLE WEAPONS: IMPORTATION</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Elstob Sen R.C." NAMEID="O97" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="O97">Senator ELSTOB</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Trade and Resources. At a meeting in Adelaide some weeks ago the Police Federation voiced its concern that, because of a change in the interpretation of a customs regulation, military-style weapons were imported into Australia. I ask the Minister whether he will review the relevant regulation to prevent such dangerous weapons from being readily available to the general public.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I believe that the matter is within the portfolio of the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs. I will direct the substance of the question to the Minister and ask him to give it consideration.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1549">
<TITLE>REDCLIFF PROJECT</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Jessop Sen D.S." NAMEID="2G7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2G7">Senator JESSOP</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask the Minister for National Development and Energy whether Dow Chemical (Australia) Ltd is this year spending between $1m and $2m to update its environmental impact study on the Redcliff project? Is it also a fact that, because of the international economic climate, the world demand for PVC is now greater than it was 18 months ago and that the project is by no means a dead issue? Can the Minister provide any further information concerning the progress that is being made in these studies?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Senate will be aware that over a considerable period there were discussions between the South Australian Government and Dow Chemical with a view to a significant chemical industry being established at Redcliff for the manufacture of PVC and chemicals. For a time there was apparently a setback, due either to Dow Chemical's projected commitments in other countries or to the recessive tendencies in the world caused by the oil pricing situation.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I am not aware of the actual expenditure by Dow in updating the consideration, but, if I recollect correctly, in a discussion that I had with the South Australian Minister, Mr Goldsworthy, a week or two ago in Adelaide, he gave me to understand that the prospect of Dow in Redcliff was certainly not dead and that there was a degree of activity in the consideration. As to the specifics of the money, I do not know. I will find out and let Senator Jessop know.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1549">
<TITLE>RUNDLE SHALE OIL PROJECT</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Walsh Sen P.A." NAMEID="TJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TJ4">Senator WALSH</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask the Minister for National Development and Energy whether he remembers saying at his 2 February Press conference in reply to a question about disparities between the National Energy Advisory Council report and his accompanying Press release concerning the viability of the Rundle project:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> What we do know is that the Rundle developers say that they will and they are the people who, that is, the partners and Exxon, say that they will produce 18 to 20,000 barrels a day by 1984 and that they hope to produce 240,000 barrels a day by 1988 so that eight to 10 years on our calculations is a reasonable one.</PARA>
<PARA>Can the Minister refer us to the statement in which the partners and Exxon said they will produce 18,000 to 20,000 barrels a day by 1984? If they did not make such a statement and the Minister was not trying to talk up the prospect and the price of the partners' shares on 2 February, why did he invent such an unequivocal statement?</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I recollect making a statement in substance similar to that indicated by Senator Walsh. It was no invention. It was my understanding, certainly from what the partners had indicated to me as their intention and, I think, from the substance of other reports. But certainly from the information conveyed by them to me and to other members of the Government it was no invention. It was a statement of fact. I would have thought that after the disclosure yesterday of the movement of shares and the fact that the share movement had been very largely a movement in the six months before I visited Rundle, any mention of talking up shares would have disappeared.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Regarding the question of talking up shares, the fact is that, if one looked at a statement, I think in the Australian newspaper of 19 September last year, one would find that the Esso partner in Rundle had expressed very considerable doubt about costs and had virtually indicated there in a statement which was reported as having been made before the Securities and Exchange Commission the fact that the costs of the first part of the project might treble. So there was a statement, and an authoritative statement, showing the elements that were released in March or April to have been stated by a partner then. So there was no question of talking up. The tendency was otherwise.</PARA>
<PARA> I again remind the Senate that Senate Hansard shows that I had indicated the magnitude and difficulties and that, indeed, the Press had reported me as being one who was taking a pessimistic view on Rundle. If the financial Press report of my taking a pessimistic view is talking up shares there is no meaning in the English language.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Walsh Sen P.A." NAMEID="TJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TJ4">Senator WALSH</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr Deputy President, I wish to ask a supplementary question. Can Senator Carrick refer us to the source upon which his statement that the partners and Exxon say they will produce 18,000 to 20,000 barrels of oil a day by 1984 is based?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1549" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have made it clear that the primary source was statements by the partners--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Walsh" NAMEID="TJ4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TJ4">Senator Walsh</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;What statements?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;By the partners to me and to other Ministers. The partners know that that is so, and so do the Ministers who received that statement of intention. I will seek to find out whether that was committed in writing elsewhere.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1550">
<TITLE>AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT ASSISTANCE TO REFUGEES IN AFRICA</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1550" SPEAKER="Lajovic Sen M.E." NAMEID="NH7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NH7">Senator LAJOVIC</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Has the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs noted an item in the Backgrounder reporting on the International Conference on Assistance to Refugees in Africa-ICARA-held in Geneva where donor countries pledged some $US560m as assistance to African refugees? As Australia has contributed $US11.6m and is the ninth largest contributor, can the Minister inform the Senate which other countries contributed and the amounts they contributed?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1550" SPEAKER="Guilfoyle Sen The Hon Dame M.G.C." NAMEID="6D7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FINANCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6D7">Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; I do not have the detail requested by Senator Lajovic. I will seek it from the Minister for Foreign Affairs.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1550">
<TITLE>RUNDLE SHALE OIL PROJECT</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1550" SPEAKER="McLaren Sen G.T." NAMEID="4L7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4L7">Senator McLAREN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I remind the Leader of the Government in the Senate that on 26 March this year I asked him a question concerning the Rundle shale oil project. The pertinent part of my question was:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Has there been a revision of his announced target date for commencement of production at Rundle? If so, what is the reason for the revision and what is the new target date?</PARA>
<PARA>Senator Carrick, in part of his reply, said:</PARA>
<PARA> My understanding is that at the moment there are discussions between the partners regarding any necessity to revise their estimates as to the volume of product output and the time of such production. Such an announcement has not yet been made.</PARA>
<PARA>Yesterday Senator Carrick incorporated in Hansard a table of the share transactions and in answer to a question earlier this morning he cited some of the large transactions which took place. When I looked at the table which he incorporated in Hansard yesterday I noted that from 20 February to 3 April there was a turnover in excess of five million shares and that the largest single day's trading took place just one week after he gave me that answer. On that day 1,831,220 Southern Pacific Petroleum NL shares and 137,500 Central Pacific Minerals NL shares were traded. How could the Minister have given me that answer when we now see that, after his visit, the largest single day's trading took place on 3 April, just a week after he gave the answer? Why did he not advise the Senate at that time of the information which he was given on 15 February and which he has told the Senate on many occasions in answers to questions, and why could he not have given it to me on 29 April when I asked the question? Why did he withhold that information?</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1550" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Rather than withholding the information that I was able to give, I gave all that was available to me. I said that there was, as I understood it, a significant revision of costs and of the program but that that was not yet complete. As to further details, Senator McLaren will understand that the Government sought from the Solicitor-General legal advice as to how far a government could go in making available to the public information about a project when the Government itself was not able to give specific or accurate details of the mining project or what the costs would be and when the only job we could possibly do was to insist, as we did, upon the partners reaching agreement on detail and cost as quickly as possible. That we did and that we disclosed. As Senator McLaren has asked me about that, I suggest that he take note of what happened in an interview on AM on Friday, 10 April when the Chairman of the Sydney Stock Exchange, Mr Frank Mullens, was asked questions about the share movement on the Exchange. He was asked this question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> What does it suggest to you when an unusually large turnover of shares takes place two days after the Federal Government was told of the problems with the project?</PARA>
<PARA>The Chairman of the Stock Exchange, who would be authoritative in this matter and who had undertaken to make an investigation, said:</PARA>
<PARA> Well, funnily enough I don't know that it proves anything. In fact, I would be certain it doesn't prove anything, and particularly in the shares of those two companies which do tend to go from very low turnover if any on some days to quite high turnover on others. So I don't think people want to jump to the conclusion there is necessarily any form of insider trading . . .</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Georges" NAMEID="7V4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7V4">Senator Georges</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is rubbish. We heard that sort of thing for week after week on a committee.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Anyone can reflect in this chamber with impunity, if his ethical conscience allows him to do so, upon the integrity of people outside parliament. The Chairman of the Stock Exchange is a highly respected person and he would have to stand by proof or otherwise--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Georges" NAMEID="7V4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7V4">Senator Georges</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;He is a stockbroker and he has a vested interest in that sort of operation.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The honourable senator might think that being a stockbroker is a sin. He went on to say:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>. . . nevertheless we are certainly prepared to look just to see if there is any initial evidence that there might have been some misuse of information.</PARA>
<PARA>The fact is that the table incorporated in Hansard yesterday showed these things. In answer to Senator McLaren I repeat that it showed that Central Pacific shares which were $11 on 31 October were $5.80 or half the value by 13 February. In that period of some five months they had halved. That was before my Rundle visit. On the following day shown on the table, on 20 February, with the knowledge of my Rundle visit, the shares fell 70c, as distinct from having fallen some $5 or more over the previous period. Southern Pacific shares, which had been $4.20 on 31 October, fell to $2.15-that is, they more than halved-over the period prior to that. They fell by some 7c to $2.08 afterwards. I remind the Senate that I pointed out that on 20 February 704,700 shares were traded. On 5 December 859,400 shares were traded. On 12 December 1,045,000 shares were traded. In early January 806,000 shares were traded. Clearly there was an enormous movement beforehand. Of course, everybody would have known and would have taken note of the statement as reported in the Australian newspaper on 19 September by Mr Jim Kirk. It is reported that he said in a speech made to the Securities Institute of Australia that there were some real problems concerning the fuel, concerning the retorts, and concerning the feedstock. He is reported as saying that the latest cost estimate he had seen on stage one of Rundle was $1.1 billion in 1979 dollars so that spent cost will be $1.5 billion and $1.7 billion.</PARA>
<PARA> That was a perceptive statement considering what emerged in the April statement. Frankly, the knowledge to the securities industry of the cost and the difficulties had been gained from the Esso Chairman earlier. I have no doubt that that caused the movement of the shares. We acted within the advice given to us by the senior law officer.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1551">
<TITLE>SKILLED TRADESMEN: SHORTAGES</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1551" SPEAKER="Lewis Sen A.W.R." NAMEID="NG4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NG4">Senator LEWIS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Attorney-General in his own capacity and as Minister representing the Ministers for Employment and Youth Affairs, Business and Consumer Affairs and Industrial Relations. I refer to the continued reported shortages in skilled tradesmen, particularly in the metal and engineering industries, and the effect on business of inter-union disputation and wildcat strikes. I ask: Is it not a fact that one of the consequences of such strikes has been to bankrupt many small businesses? Is it not a fact that in the case of the Newcastle State Dockyard, Evans Deakin dockyard, Brisbane, and Walkers dockyard, Maryborough, such disputation was responsible for the closure of those yards and the loss of thousands of jobs at the yards and in supporting industries? Can the Minister say whether the militancy and disputation of certain unions has been a cause in the failure of employers to attract sufficient numbers of apprentices to make successful tradesmen? Can he tell the Senate whether it is a fact that the armed forces have no difficulty in attracting applicants of the required calibre for the same trades?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1551" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Lewis's question ranges over a number of different ministries, including that of the Minister for Defence, I noticed. I am not in a position to provide the detailed answer that such a serious question demands. I certainly am aware of, and the Government is deeply concerned about, the shortage of skilled tradesmen and the effect that wildcat strikes, or indeed any strikes, have on business, and particularly on small businesses. I will refer the question to the appropriate Ministers and ask them to provide a detailed answer to Senator Lewis.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1551">
<TITLE>HEALTH INSURANCE</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1551" SPEAKER="Evans Sen G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister representing the Treasurer, unless he would prefer the Minister representing the Minister for Health to answer it. It concerns yesterday's health and tax statements. Can the Minister advise the Senate why it is that contributions to health insurance funds are to qualify as additional concessional tax deductions but not actual expenditure incurred on health care? Does this have any justification in principle or is the Government's only motivation the desire to force people to fill the coffers of the private funds?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1551" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I take it that the Government has been anxious to extend to as many people as possible the tax relief they will be able to get from the contributions they make to medical and hospital insurance, our desire being to get as many people in as we can. I remind the Senate that there will be a tax rebate separate from the existing concessions, of 32c in the dollar, which will have effect from 1 July. Only about 8 per cent of the taxpaying community in fact claims deductions over and above the $1,590 block. The part of the honourable senator's question which gives me some concern and which I will have to check asked what the position is as regards additional net expenditure.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Evans" NAMEID="VD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator Evans</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Or, in some people's cases if they don't insure themselves, actual expenditure.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will come back as quickly as I can on that matter of detail and give him that piece of information. I think the people of Australia welcome the decision to provide this extra taxation rebate in terms of contributions to basic hospital and medical insurance. There is no difficulty at all in answering that part of the honourable senator's question. As I have said, I will seek extra information on the other matter he has raised.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1552">
<TITLE>HEALTH FACILITIES: PAPUNYA</TITLE>
<ANSWER PAGE="1552" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator PETER BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In replying to a question without notice yesterday from Senator Kilgariff, I inadvertently gave some inaccurate detail which I would now like to correct. Senator Kilgariff asked me about the condition of health services for Aboriginal people at Papunya and whether an official committee reviewing facilities at Papunya had referred any decision to the Government. I replied that a senior official of my Department had recently gone to the Northern Territory. That is correct. The official I named was the official who had gone there. I advised the Senate that he had gone to Papunya. That is correct. I also advised the Senate that he was carrying out investigative work for the Department. That is correct. In fact, the official did not visit Papunya for the purpose of examining the health service. He went there for another purpose.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Senator Kilgariff will be aware that, since the Central Australian Homeland Aboriginal Medical Services were established continuously there, they have been reviewed by a team of experts headed by Professor Tony Radford, Professor of Community Medicine at Flinders University. I am informed that the evaluation team last made an on-site visit to Papunya in November 1980. The team found at that time that the health service there-that is, the Lyappa Health Service-had experienced administrative and service difficulties but that it was acceptable to the Papunya community. The final report of Professor Radford's team-that is the point of Senator Kilgariff's question yesterday-will be made available to the relevant State and Northern Territory Ministers when finalised. The Commonwealth Government will also give close attention to the report. I am informed that the current expectation is that this final report will be available during the first half of 1982.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1552">
<TITLE>NORTHERN IRELAND</TITLE>
<ANSWER PAGE="1552" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In the Senate on 28 April and again yesterday Senator Keeffe asked me as Minister representing the Prime Minister questions concerning a hunger strike being undertaken in Northern Ireland by Bobby Sands, a member of the illegal Irish Republican Army. He asked me to expedite an answer. I now have the following information for Senator Keeffe: Bobby Sands is serving a 14-year sentence in Belfast's prison for possession of firearms and ammunition with intent. He embarked upon a hunger strike in an attempt to gain political status for himself and certain other prisoners in Northern Ireland found guilty of criminal charges. Sands won a by-election on 9 April for a Northern Ireland seat, which has clearly been interpreted as a considerable success by those supporting the campaign for political status for prisoners. The British Government has stated:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> There can be no question of political status for someone who is serving a sentence for crime . . . It is not political. To give concessions on political status would put many people in jeopardy.</PARA>
<PARA>It would be a matter of great regret if current events in Northern Ireland led to a further increase in violence. The situation there is both complex and tragic. The problems of Northern Ireland are, however, a matter for resolution between the local people and the British Government.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1553">
<TITLE>NORTHERN IRELAND</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1553" SPEAKER="Georges Sen G." NAMEID="7V4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7V4">Senator GEORGES</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(11.42)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; by leave-I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the Senate take note of the answer. </PARA>
<PARA>I should have thought that, in responding to Senator Keeffe's question, the Government would have shown the same concern as it shows in matters relating to human rights. In the Senate from time to time motions concerning the rights of people in the Soviet Union and other places are moved by Government senators. I should have thought that the rights of people in Northern Ireland would be very much the concern of this Government and this Parliament. I should have thought also that the Government would exercise some humanity and seek to make some representations to the British Government concerning Bobby Sands. </PARA>
<PARA> In answer to the question, the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Carrick) stated that it was a matter of criminal intent on the part of Bobby Sands which resulted in his receiving a sentence of some 14 years. That matter is under disputation in Northern Ireland. Bobby Sands and those who support him say that it was a matter of some political consequence, that they did what they did for political reasons, and that for that reason they should be given political status. That is a matter of debate. That is the reason for the campaign by Bobby Sands. Nevertheless, whether he is right or wrong, he is taking a course which may lead-it seems that it will lead-to his death. I would ask the Government to reconsider the position which it has taken, to make representations to the British Government about showing some compassion and to ask the British Government to accept that the consequences of Bobby Sands's death would be further violence and death in Northern Ireland. Already further deaths have occurred but it seems to me that the violence will escalate. </PARA>
<PARA> For too long we have ignored the problem in Northern Ireland and in other areas. We seem to concentrate on positions on ideological levels against the Soviet Union and socialist countries. But we have shown very little concern about Lebanon and El Salvador. Surely we should show great concern about Northern Ireland, which is part of the Commonwealth of Nations. I think that it is very much our responsibility to show some concern. We cannot write it off and put it to one side by suggesting that it is a matter for the people of Northern Ireland and the British Government. It is very much a matter for us here. Therefore, I ask the Government to reconsider the answer that it has given to Senator Keeffe and to show some compassion and concern. If an interest were shown by parliaments such as this Parliament and some sympathy and concern were expressed about the problem of Northern Ireland, perhaps the Irish people would be in a better position-when they considered the fact that an interest was being shown elsewhere-to resolve their differences. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Chipp" NAMEID="3V4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="3V4">Senator Chipp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;And the British Government also.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7V4">Senator GEORGES</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Yes, of course, and the British Government also. For that reason I have put the matter on the Notice Paper. I trust that if the Government is not prepared to respond immediately, it will bring the matter to the top of the Notice Paper so that we can debate it and so that many people in this place can express the concern that I have expressed. I seek leave to continue my remarks later.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Leave granted; debate adjourned. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</QUESTION.BLOCK>
</QWN><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1553"><TITLE>PRESENTATION OF PAPERS</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1553" SPEAKER="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L." NAMEID="2U4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2U4">Senator CARRICK</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Government in the Senate)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Papers are tabled in accordance with the list circulated to honourable senators. I ask that the list be incorporated in Hansard.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Leave granted. </PARA>
<PARA> The document read as follows-</PARA>
<PARA> 1. Milk Authority of the Australian Capital Territory-Annual Report 1979-80-Pursuant to Section 21H of the Milk Authority Ordinance 1971. </PARA>
<PARA> 2. Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation-Annual Report 1979-80-Pursuant to Section 57 of the Science and Industry Research Act 1949. </PARA>
<PARA> 3. Trans-Tasman travel arrangement-Text of a statement by the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs. </PARA>
<PARA> 4. Agreement with Mexico on co-operation in science and technology-Text of a statement by the Minister representing the Minister for Foreign Affairs on Science and Technology Co-operation with Mexico. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1553"><TITLE>COMMONWEALTH SCIENTIFIC AND INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH ORGANISATION</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1553">
<TITLE>Annual Report 1979-80</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1553" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Leader of the Opposition)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(11.48)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the Senate take note of the paper. </PARA>
<PARA>I want to make some comments which arise from the annual report of CSIRO for the year 1979-80 because it is a very important organisation and, in the view of the Opposition, it should perhaps have a more expanded importance in certain areas, particularly that of manufacturing industry. The Senate will recall that several years ago an inquiry was established into CSIRO. The Independent Inquiry into the CSIRO, the so-called Birch committee-it was presided over by Professor Birch-in bringing down its report made a number of suggestions about structural changes which should be made to CSIRO. One of the committee's important recommendations, in our view, was that the Organisation should involve itself more strongly in the manufacturing industry sector. In our view a stronger manufacturing industry sector in Australia is necessary for employment and continuing wealth creation. It is essential that the revenue from resources development be used to build up and stimulate new areas of manufacturing industry. </PARA>
<PARA> The Jackson Committee to Advise on Policies for Manufacturing Industry and the Crawford report on structural adjustment have been in the hands of this Parliament for four or five years and make similar recommendations to those in the comments which I have made. Therefore we commend, in the context of this report, the establishment of the Division of Manufacturing Technology. Let me refer to the passage in the report which deals with the establishment of that division. Under the heading 'Initiatives for Manufacturing Industry' the report states:</PARA>
<PARA> A preliminary analysis by the Manufacturing Industry Committee indicated the need for CSIRO to increase its research on metal-products manufacturing a sector that accounts for some 45 per cent of Australia's manufacturing industry. The Committee recommended that a CSIRO Division of Manufacturing Technology be established to work closely with firms engaged in the metal-processing industries. The Executive accepted this recommendation and the new Division, which has been developed from the existing production technology group of the Division of Materials Science, came into existence in April 1980. </PARA>
<PARA>The report goes on to say that the new division has been established in Melbourne and has a branch in Adelaide. A Sydney branch will be established in due course. The division head is to be Professor R. H. Brown, who was formerly of the University of Western Australia. That is an encouraging indication of CSIRO's implementing an important recommendation of the Birch Committee. Although some concern can be derived from the report in that it is essential that the results of any activity of this new division should flow through to industry and that industry should obtain the benefits of these results in as quick and efficient a manner as possible, it is somewhat disappointing to note on page 44 of the report that the possibility of a CSIRO extension service to translate, as it were, the results of CSIRO research directly into industry has been ruled out. The reason is described as costs. I hope the Government will consider quickly and seriously making funds available for this purpose. I now refer the Senate to the section of the report which provides:</PARA>
<PARA>. . . The Executive commissioned a report on CSIRO's present and future programs for transferring scientific and technical information to manufacturing industry. </PARA>
<PARA> The Report, prepared by the Director of the Bureau of Scientific Services, examined the idea of an extension service to manufacturing industry analogous to that operating in the rural sector but concluded that cost factors alone made this impractical. </PARA>
<PARA>I say to you, Mr Deputy President, and Senator Neal, as members of the National Country Party, that one of the great successes of government in Australia in my view has been the co-operation which has developed over many years between organisations such as CSIRO and farm organisastions. The fact is that CSIRO transferred the benefits of its technology and research discoveries very quickly to the rural sector-in a sense this has been one of the few triumphs of Australian governments, and I refer to government in the broad sense. We know the efficiency with which that process operated and the results which have been obtained in terms of pretty efficient rural industries in Australia. The same process in the 1980s should, in our view, be applied to manufacturing industry. </PARA>
<PARA> Manufacturing industry in Australia is not in a very healthy situation. Its health could be much improved by advanced technology and the benefit of research in organisations such as CSIRO being transferred to it on an efficient and sensible basis as has been done in the past with rural industries. I strongly commend to the Government the view that the money which the CSIRO report says is not available should be made available for this purpose. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Jessop" NAMEID="2G7">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2G7">Senator Jessop</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Senate standing committee report on industrial research and development in Australia made that point. We are anxiously awaiting the Government's response to that. So I would like to think that you will lend your support to that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Of course I will. I am not averse to somebody putting in an advertisement for anything. I am very glad that your committee did make that point. Perhaps we can wait anxiously together. I think it is necessary for a little more discussion to take place in this Parliament on our general policies on technology transfer, particularly the transfer of technologies from multinational corporations operating in Australia. We should look very hard, I think, at the experience in Korea. I do not mean that we should look at the social experience in Korea. I do not think we should look too hard at that experience at all and seek to transfer it to this country. I mean that we should look at the way in which Korea has handled overseas technology and technology transfer because in Korea the emphasis has been on applying overseas technology very rapidly to the Korean economy. The emphasis has been not so much on basic research but on the method of application of overseas technologies in Korea. It has been a success story in terms of the Korean economy.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> If I have to keep on citing this example for years to come I will do so because, like Senator Jessop, I am anxious that these words should not fall entirely on deaf ears. The fact of the matter is that this Government is totally supine in relation to the conditions it imposes on foreign capital invested in Australia. It is the most cowardly government in the world in terms of the conditions which it imposes on foreign capital coming here. One of the most important conditions which it ought to impose, particularly in the mining industry, is in relation to the question of the technology of infrastructure development. I again cite the Norwegian example. In Norway 12 or 14 years ago, when masses of foreign capital were coming into that country for the development of the oil industry, the Norwegian Government made a decision that the engineering work for that development would be done by Norwegian companies. As I have said, 12 or 14 years later, as a result of that policy which was applied in Norway right from the beginning, it has become a net exporter of engineering equipment for the oil industry. That is something we ought to be doing here. We do not lack the technical capacity to do it. What we lack is the guts in terms of the Government's capacity to say to those who wish to invest in this country: 'Sure, you can bring your money here but the technology in particular aspects of the industry will be developed under Australian management and Australian control'. </PARA>
<PARA> One other aspect of this report that I want to deal with is the question of salinity and land use loss. This is dealt with at page 123 of the report, where it is recorded that the salt problem largely resulting from irrigation has now moved into non-irrigated areas. The land loss from salination in Australia is enormous and at every election in this country the political parties trot out a few bribes for the farmers because they think it is the way to handle, as it were, the rural vote. That is not the way to deal with major problems of concern to non-metropolitan communities in Australia looking at the long term. Australia has to face up to two enormous problems: One is the salinity of soil and land loss as a result, and the other is deforestation of this country. A fortnight ago I heard a Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation scientist say at a seminar that by the year 2000 Australia could be a completely treeless landscape as a result of the rapid spread of dieback and diseases of that kind which are associated in part with soil quality. The cherubic Senator Jessop was about to interrupt me again--</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Jessop" NAMEID="2G7">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2G7">Senator Jessop</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I was going to educate you a bit, but carry on.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The point I am making, whether or not one agrees with it, is that it is necessary for us to have a national land use policy. It is all very well to have a resources boom which might last 50 years, if we are lucky, but Australia cannot neglect its greatest resource, which is land. It will be there, I hope, long after wealth has been generated by a resources boom, and on a permanent basis.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> These matters are adverted to in this important report by the CSIRO, an important organisation in the national life of this country. It has a fine record as a national institution. I summarise my concerns by saying that in a number of areas we need policy action on behalf of the Government in relation to the functions of the CSIRO and in relation to the development of national strategies on these matters. The areas which I have specifically identified, arising from this report, are the areas of land use, technology transfer, and the building of the manufacturing industry base in this country. The Government has an onus to give attention to those matters. I seek leave to continue my remarks later. </PARA>
<PARA> Leave granted; debate adjourned. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Ministerial Statement" PAGE="1555"><TITLE>TRANS-TASMAN TRAVEL ARRANGEMENT</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1555">
<TITLE>Ministerial Statement</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1555" SPEAKER="Mason Sen C.V.J." NAMEID="YJ7" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YJ7">Senator MASON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.3)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> -by leave-I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the Senate take note of the paper. </PARA>
<PARA>Like hundreds of thousands of people in this country, I am an ex-New Zealander with close contacts with that country, and I am impelled to comment briefly on the iniquitous and absurd proposal to introduce passports for persons who wish to come from New Zealand to Australia, thereby destroying the unique relationship between those two countries which has existed for over half a century. There are probably no two countries in the world with closer independent family ties than those between Australia and New Zealand. Many families such as my own have tended to alternate between Australia and New Zealand, generation by generation. I hope-I think others in this country share that hope-eventually for closer ties between Australia and New Zealand, as provided for in the Australian Constitution. </PARA>
<PARA> I think the excuse that has been put forward-controlling crime-as a reason for reintroducing passports between Australia and New Zealand is not a good reason. It is a naive expectation, at best, that it will have any control at all over a criminal with any expertise, background or knowledge. Passports can be forged, people can conceal their criminal motivations in all but the crudest of examples. I think all we will catch by this arrangement is a few very small fish, and the large ones will just laugh at us. It will do a great deal of damage, however. Initially it will damage the tourist trade. People will not bother to go backwards and forwards between the two countries if the necessity to have a passport is imposed on them. One of the things about travel to and from New Zealand was that one did not have to have a passport. </PARA>
<PARA> It is an absurd situation which will involve Australians who are going to New Zealand on holiday having to go through the laborious and time-consuming process of getting a passport so that they can get back into their own country. It makes nonsense of what we are to hear later in the day about the razor gang because this will add greatly to the work of public officials in Australia. A number of complaints have come to me recently from constituents about very tedious and enormous delays in the issuing of passports. Apparently, people have to stand in queues not only once but several times to go through what should be the very ordinary and routine procedure of getting a passport. There will now be further delays because of the great extent of travel to New Zealand, and thus will add to that burden. </PARA>
<PARA> I do not propose to speak for long on this matter because of the time exigencies of the Senate. I will just say in conclusion that this would seem to be another indication of the regrettable tendency of this Goverment not so much to do useful things but to add to the general vexatious mess of red tape with which people must cope even when going on holiday. I urge the Government to take another look at this new policy which, I warn it now, will be one of great and extensive unpopularity. I seek leave to continue my remarks later. </PARA>
<PARA> Leave granted; debate adjourned. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1556"><TITLE>JOINT COMMITTEE ON THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1556" SPEAKER="Neal Sen L.W." NAMEID="NM7" PARTY="NCP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NM7">Senator NEAL</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of the Joint Committee on the Australian Capital Territory, I present a report on the proposals for variations to the plan of layout of the city of Canberra and its environs, the seventy-first and seventy-second series, together with extracts from the minutes of proceedings of the Committee.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Ordered that the report be printed. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1556" SPEAKER="Neal Sen L.W." NAMEID="NM7" PARTY="NCP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NM7">Senator NEAL</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-This report covers two variations to the city plan. The first deals with a car park in Deakin while the other concerns the extension of William Hovell Drive from Coulter Drive to Kingsford Smith Drive. The Committee has approved the Deakin variation, which is for the gazettal of a car park to enable the construction of medical offices on the site. The Committee has, however, expressed concern about car parking in the area and asked for a report on the question of car parking to be submitted to the Committee in a year's time.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The proposed extension of William Hovell Drive has been given detailed consideration by the Committee. The Committee held a public hearing on the proposal on 13 March 1981, and a sub-committee of members inspected the proposed extension later that day. The Committee considered the evidence given at the public hearing at a later meeting and then decided to hold a further public hearing on the proposal. This hearing was held on Tuesday, 28 April. Prior to this hearing the Committee conducted a further inspection. </PARA>
<PARA> Alternative alignments for the proposed road were considered by the Committee, but the Committee was not convinced that any of them justified a departure from the preferred alignment of the National Capital Development Commission. According to the National Capital Development Commission, the road will cost $2.9m at 1980 prices. The first alternative proposal would involve moving the road nine metres west. It would involve reconstruction of part of the intersection and would cost in the vicinity of $30,000. Mr Dobie, one member of the Committee, has submitted a dissent but has indicated his support for this proposal. The second proposal increases the length of the road by 270 metres and costs an estimated $120,000. The third alternative is to increase the length of the road by 600 metres. This would cost an estimated $350,000. </PARA>
<PARA> The Committee acknowledges that the road may reduce the amenity of some residents near the road but also acknowledges the need for the construction of the road as an integral part of the road network for Belconnen and the additional cost to the community if alternative proposals were accepted. Accordingly, the Committee has approved the variation with the recommendation that the acoustic earth mound be raised by approximately half a metre. </PARA>
<PARA> In conclusion, I would compliment all those involved in the inquiry. The Committee cannot satisfy all those involved, but we have made a decision in the general interest of the residents of Canberra. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1557"><TITLE>STANDING COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE AND THE ENVIRONMENT</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1557">
<TITLE>Pollution of the River Murray</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1557" SPEAKER="Jessop Sen D.S." NAMEID="2G7" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2G7">Senator JESSOP</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-The Senate would be aware that the Standing Committee on Science and the Environment, under its reference about the continuing scrutiny of pollution, has been examining pollution in the River Murray system and tabled reports on the matter in June 1979 and September 1980. The Committee is very concerned at the situation which has developed at the mouth of the River Murray at Goolwa in South Australia. It appears that the river is no longer flowing into the sea and, in fact, the sea is encroaching upon the lower reaches of the river. It is claimed that this could aggravate the salinity problem in the river for as far as 100 miles upstream. The Committee has decided, as a matter of extreme urgency, to inspect the mouth of the River Murray on Friday, 15 May. It is proposed to invite representatives of the River Murray Commission and the appropriate South Australian Government departments to join the Committee in this inspection. It has also been decided to hold a public hearing on the matter in Adelaide as soon as possible with the intention of reporting back to the Senate during the Budget session.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1557"><TITLE>STANDING COMMITTEE ON REGULATIONS AND ORDINANCES</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1557">
<TITLE>Australian Capital Territory Traffic (Amendment) Ordinance 1981</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1557" SPEAKER="Lewis Sen A.W.R." NAMEID="NG4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NG4">Senator LEWIS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Vic)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-On behalf of the Regulations and Ordinances Committee, I am taking the unusual step of reporting to the Senate on the Committee's deliberations concerning the Australian Capital Territory Traffic (Amendment) Ordinance 1981. It is clear to the Committee, as a result of the debate in the Senate last Tuesday evening and media reports, that public interest in this matter is at a very high level. As was indicated during that debate, a member of the Committee requested that the legal adviser to the Committee be asked to provide, as expeditiously as possible, a report on the ordinance. That report, and a public submission, were considered by the Committee at a meeting this morning. Following the Committee's preliminary investigations this morning and in accordance with its usual practice, the Minister for the Capital Territory (Mr Hodgman) will be asked to respond urgently to certain matters which are to be put to him by the Committee today. The Committee will report further to the Senate as soon as possible.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Adjournment" PAGE="1557"><TITLE>SPECIAL ADJOURNMENT</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA></PARA>
<PARA> Motion (by Senator Durack) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA> That the Senate, at its rising, adjourn till Tuesday, 5 May 1981, at 3 p.m. or such later time as the President may take the chair.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Adjournment" PAGE="1557"><TITLE>ADJOURNMENT</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1557">
<TITLE>Australian Capital Territory: Magistrate-Presentation to Senator</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1557" SPEAKER="Durack Sen The Hon P.D." NAMEID="8G4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="ATTORNEY GENERAL" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="8G4">Senator DURACK</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Western Australia-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Attorney General)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(12.14)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In order that the Estimates committees may meet for the remainder of the day, I now move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the Senate do now adjourn. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1557" SPEAKER="Mulvihill Sen J.A." NAMEID="GM7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="GM7">Senator MULVIHILL</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.15)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I rise simply to make a correction to remarks that I made last night in expressing some concern about the workings of justice in the Australian Capital Territory. Briefly I referred to a certain magistrate in the Territory by name but since have learnt that there are two magistrates with similar names. The result is that, as is recorded on page 1494 of yesterday's Senate Hansard, I inadvertently erred in referring to Magistrate Nichols, instead of Magistrate Nicholl. That is the distinction. My remarks, which I stand by, should have been directed to Magistrate Nicholl. Apparently there is a slight variation as between the names of the two magistrates. Accordingly, I make that correction.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1557" SPEAKER="McLaren Sen G.T." NAMEID="4L7" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4L7">Senator McLAREN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.16)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> -I wish to take a few moments of the Senate's time to make a little presentation to my parliamentary colleague, Senator Walters. Everyone in the Senate knows that at times I am very concerned about Senator Walters. In view of some of the remarks that she has made in the Senate this week, and again today by way of an interjection in respect to socialism, I have been especially concerned about her health. The Senate will know that over the years Senator Walters has expressed a great concern about superphosphate. I believe that at one time I told her that she reminded me of years ago when my father used to take Kruschen salts every morning before breakfast-just enough to cover a sixpence-because he reckoned that it was a great thing for the health and I said that I thought that Senator Walters was taking a little drop of superphosphate on a sixpence every morning before breakfast.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> My concern is that since the decision of the so-called razor gang is now to be handed down, she might not be feeling too well at the end of the day because the superphosphate bounty might be removed. Therefore, I have taken the opportunity of having a little present prepared for the honourable senator. It is made up in a little plastic bag. It is a superphosphate tablet which is suitably inscribed with my compliments and the words: 'A phosphate tablet implanted with socialism seeds taken regularly will work wonders for the liver'. I hope that when Senator Walters takes this tablet, and finds that she likes it, she will come to me and allow me to provide her with more. The source is plentiful and I can recommend the effectiveness of the tablet. I am sure that she will soon be feeling much better. I now have much pleasure in presenting her with this superphosphate tablet. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1558" SPEAKER="Walters Sen M.S." NAMEID="UJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UJ4">Senator WALTERS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.18)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It gives me great pleasure to accept the tablet presented by Senator McLaren. The more he gives me the less he will have to give to others. The question that I would like to ask, as Senator Puplick has remarked, is: What would Senator McLaren have been like before he started to take these tablets regularly? The honourable senator tells me that the tablet contains numerous socialist seeds. I am sure that he has consumed many over the years. I can only surmise that had we got to Senator McLaren first we would not have to put up with so many quorums being called or so many irrational or illogical statements being made in this place. I assure Senator McLaren that I will not be consuming any of these seeds; I will keep the tablet for posterity.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME><NAME NAMEID="7V4">(Senator Georges)</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Senate stands adjourned until Tuesday next at 3 p.m. or such later time as the President may take the chair. Estimates Committee D will meet in the Senate chamber. Estimates Committee E will meet in Senate committee rooms 1 and 2 and Estimates Committee F in Senate committee room 6. The bells will be ring for three minutes prior to the sittings of the committees. Honourable senators are reminded that Estimates committees G and H are scheduled to meet on Monday, 4 May at 10.30 a.m. Honourable senators are also reminded of the Joint Sitting of members of the Senate and of the House or Representatives which is to be held in the Senate chamber at 2.15 p.m. on Tuesday, 5 May, prior to the sitting of the Senate.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>Senate adjourned at 12.20 p.m. </PARA>
</INTERJECT>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Papers" PAGE="1558"><TITLE>PAPER</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA></PARA>
<PARA> The following paper was presented, pursuant to statute:</PARA>
<PARA> Parliament Act-Proposed Works in the Parliamentary Zone-Car parks behind the provisional Parliament House-Bitumen seal a presently gravelled car park; provide an additional bitumen sealed car park; and provide security lighting for each car park, together with locality plans (2).</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE></CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS PAGE="1558">
<TITLE>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA> The following answers to questions were circulated:</PARA></PROCTEXT>
<ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1558"><TITLE>Public Television</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="338">(Question No. 338)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1558" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator Button</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Communications, upon notice, on 25 February 1981:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1) What actions have been initiated or taken by the Government or any of its instrumentalities to introduce public television in Australia as promised in the statement by the then Minister for Post and Telecommunications, in October 1980.</PARA>
<PARA> (2) What financial support will be provided by Government to public television.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1558" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator Peter Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Minister for Communications has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> (1) On 1 October 1980 the office of the Prime Minister wrote to the Chairman of the Public Broadcasting Association of Australia (PBAA), stating that it was expected that applications for some public television licences would be invited in the first quarter of 1981. The Department of Communications is currently finalising draft policy guidelines for the introduction of public television services, following consultation with relevant government departments and authorities, the PBAA and potential user groups.</PARA>
<PARA> (2) The Government is currently examining the question of Government funding of public television.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1558"><TITLE>Public Television</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="343">(Question No. 343)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1558" SPEAKER="Button Sen J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator Button</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Communications, upon notice, on 25 February 1981:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Did the Prime Minister's Office write a letter quoted in the Age, dated 13 October 1980 which said that it was ''planned that applications for licences to conduct (Public Television) services be invited for the first quarter of 1981; if so:</PARA>
<PARA> (a) what arrangements have so far been made to carry this undertaking into effect;</PARA>
<PARA> (b) how many licences for new public television stations have been or are planned to be, granted from 1 January until 31 March 1981;</PARA>
<PARA> (c) how many such licences have been planned for to date and what are the names of the station, or planned stations, the name of the licensee, and the frequency allocated, where possible;</PARA>
<PARA> (d) how many licences arrangements have been issued/entered into before 31 March 1981;</PARA>
<PARA> (e) how many station sharing arrangements have been planned for to date;</PARA>
<PARA> (f) what is the projected cost of such arrangements; and</PARA>
<PARA> (g) what technical facilities and other assistance will be provided for the establishment of new stations, or for the facilitation of station sharing agreements in regard to each new station, or sharing agreement planned.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1558" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator Peter Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Minister for Communications has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Yes, the Prime Minister's Office did write such a letter to the Public Broadcasting Association of Australia (PBAA).</PARA>
<PARA> (a) Draft Policy Guidelines for the introduction of public television are now being finalised by the Department of Communications, following consultation with relevant Government Departments and Authorities, the PBAA and potential user groups.</PARA>
<PARA> (b) to (g) Once the Policy Guidelines have been approved and published, planning proposals for licensed public television services will be considered by my Department. This should lead to the invitation of applications for the grant of public television licences for special purposes, such as educational and community services.</PARA>
<PARA> At the same time, channel sharing arrangements between public television groups and existing stations (ABC, SBS and commercial) may develop. Since public television and channel sharing arrangements are still in the preliminary stages of development, the precise details of possible arrangements are unknown at this stage. However, my Department is continuing to monitor these developments, and more detailed information of the kind requested by Senator Button, will be provided when available.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1559"><TITLE>Public Broadcasting and Television</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="364">(Question No. 364)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1559" SPEAKER="Chipp Sen The Hon D.L." NAMEID="3V4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="3V4">Senator Chipp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Communications, upon notice, on 26 February 1981:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> What steps does the Government intend to take to legislate for the support and encouragement of public broadcasting and public television, in fulfilment of the Prime Minister's undertaking by letter of 1 October 1980 to the Public Broadcasting Association of Australia.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1559" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator Peter Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Minister for Communications has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> On 1 October 1980 the office of the Prime Minister wrote to the Public Broadcasting Association of Australia (PBAA), stating that it was expected that applications for some public television licences would be invited in the first quarter of 1981. My Department is currently finalising draft policy guidelines for the introduction of public television services, following consultation with relevant Government Departments and Authorities, the PBAA and potential user groups.</PARA>
<PARA> The question of support and encouragement of public broadcasting and public television is currently being reviewed by Government. The need for legislation to implement such support and encouragement is also being examined.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1559"><TITLE>Government Centre: Tokyo</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="560">(Question No. 560)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1559" SPEAKER="Mason Sen C.V.J." NAMEID="YJ7" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YJ7">Senator Mason</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 31 March 1981:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Has the Government adopted a proposal to build a 12 to 15 storey Government centre in the Toronomon district of Tokyo, Japan; if so, what is the estimated cost of such a proposal.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1559" SPEAKER="Baume Sen The Hon P.E." NAMEID="ME4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="ME4">Senator Peter Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Minister for Administrative Services has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The Government is considering the desirability and practicability of a property consolidation in Tokyo, but no decisions have been taken.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON></ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS></HANSARD>

