<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" []>
<HANSARD DATE="11/09/1991" PROOF="No" PAGE="1373" CHAMBER = "Senate" PARLIAMENT.NO = "36" SESSION.NO = "1" PERIOD.NO = "4" > 
<CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><BUSINESS.START>
<DAY.START DATE="11/09/1991">Wednesday, 11 September 1991</DAY.START>
<PROCTEXT><PARA> The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Kerry Sibraa) took the chair at 10 a.m., and read prayers.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</BUSINESS.START><QWN PAGE="1373">
<TITLE>QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE</TITLE>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1373">
<TITLE>Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Hill Sen R.M." NAMEID="BH4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator HILL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to Senator Button, the Leader of the Government in the Senate and Minister representing the Prime Minister. I refer him to the statement of Mrs Kelly that the tape of her meeting with environmental leaders will not be produced by today's deadline in accordance with the order of the Senate. I ask: does this mean that it is Mrs Kelly who decides whether or not orders of the Senate directed to the Government are complied with?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;As I understand it, this is a matter of constitutional practice concerning the powers and privileges of the Senate and the House of Representatives. It is ultimately a matter to be resolved between the two Houses, if necessary. In so far as Mrs Kelly's claim is concerned, I think that she is entitled to make that position clear. In so far as the Senate is concerned, it is all very well for Senator Hill to describe it as an order of the Senate, but it is a resolution of the Senate, and that can be resolved only between the two Houses.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Hill Sen R.M." NAMEID="BH4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator HILL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I ask a supplementary question. Is the Minister saying that this is a decision for Mrs Kelly and not a decision for the Government, notwithstanding that the resolution or order-whichever word one chooses to use-is directed to the Government and not Mrs Kelly?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do not think that I can add anything to what the Prime Minister said yesterday about that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1373">
<TITLE>Farm Accidents and Injuries</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="West Sen S." NAMEID="1X4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="1X4">Senator WEST</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash; Does the Minister for Industrial Relations have information on the rate of accidents and injuries on Australian farms? What action has been taken to remedy the record of fatalities on farms?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Government is acutely aware of the alarming rate of injuries in rural Australia. In 1989, Worksafe Australia reported on workplace fatalities and stated that the farming sector had the third highest number of deaths at work after the mining and transport industries. In fact, the average annual fatality in farming Australia is at the ratio of 19.4 per 100,000 compared to the all industry average in Australia of 8.1 per 100,000. Over the two years of the Worksafe study, 257 farm related fatalities, including 34 involving children under the age of 15, were identified. The major cause of death was mobile mechanical equipment, which accounted for 70 per cent of the deaths. About 40 per cent of all farm related deaths were caused by tractors or equipment attached to tractors.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> To help farming communities improve rural occupational health and safety, Worksafe Australia has developed, in association with farming organisations, a safety kit called the State farm safety kit. I have one of those kits here, and I will just show it to the Senate and make it available for honourable senators who wish to have access to it.</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Short" NAMEID="DJ4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator Short</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Hold it up a bit.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will hold up the farm safety kit. It is a substantial piece of work by Worksafe Australia. There are now 25 different rural communities which have formed farm safety committees in their region and which use this kit and there are some five others that are being established. This is a major improvement in lifting the standard of safety in rural Australia, and I commend Worksafe for the work it is doing on it.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1373">
<TITLE>Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Reid Sen M.E." NAMEID="VI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VI4">Senator REID</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Can the Minister representing the Prime Minister indicate whether the Prime Minister or any of his Ministers have listened to and heard the tape that records the meeting between the Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories and the leading conservationists?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I said earlier, as the Prime Minister told the House of Representatives yesterday, he informed the Leader of the Opposition that a member of his staff did not ask for the tape but saw a copy of the relevant part of the transcript, read the relevant part of the transcript and informed the Prime Minister that the transcript totally endorsed and confirmed what the Minister had told him. I have nothing to add to that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Reid Sen M.E." NAMEID="VI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="ACT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VI4">Senator REID</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. In the circumstances, does the Minister not find it quite extraordinary that no Minister has taken the trouble to listen to that tape so as to be able to comment upon it? The matter has become one of major public importance.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1373" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do not find it extraordinary at all.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1374">
<TITLE>Higher Education</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1374" SPEAKER="Bell Sen R.J." NAMEID="7U4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7U4">Senator BELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Does the Minister representing the Minister for Higher Education and Employment Services share the concern of students about the severity of the crisis in higher education regarding overcrowding and underfunding, including the open flouting of health and safety regulations with students crammed into aisles, sitting on the floor, on rubbish tins or on milk crates and standing at the back of lecture theatres? Does the Minister endorse the practice of the issuing of tickets to lectures, students being locked out of lectures, more lectures being held after hours and in off-campus venues, and tutorials which are almost as large as lectures? Is the Minister aware of severe shortages of library books, computer terminals and other resources, modifications to curriculum and assessment processes, and the abolition of many tutorials? Will the Minister make a commitment to restore funding to at least 1983 levels per full time student and provide additional funding for a 3.5 per cent annual growth in the number of higher education places in the next 10 years, as requested by the Higher Education Round Table which nationally represents students, postgraduates and academics?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1374" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There is one thing, amongst others, that I have learnt in answering questions from Senator Bell.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Senator Collins interjecting-</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Not only one, but one amongst a number. One of the main things is that I do not take at face value the assertions that Senator Bell makes. I have had a number of instances in other areas of education policy where assertions have been made and they have not withstood scrutiny. In not responding to some of the specific assertions made by Senator Bell, I will address the issue of overcrowding or over-enrolments-because there is a difference-and I will also go to the impact of the most recent Budget on higher education.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Why don't you just answer the question he asked?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;If Senator Macdonald was listening-and it probably is a bit early for him-he would realise that the underlying premise of Senator Bell's questions goes to over-enrolments and overcrowding and what the Government is doing. I will not go to the specific instances of libraries and whatever but I will go to the core issue, and that is answering the question.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> On the question of over-enrolments, we recognise and we are addressing this problem. We recognise that a number of factors have contributed to over-enrolment. But the Government's view is that over-enrolment appears to be occurring principally because of increased retention rates of students and increased acceptance of offers by applicants for new places. Both of these have exceeded the projections of institutions based on previous experience.</PARA>
<PARA> A number of reasons have contributed to the change in retention acceptance rates, including the current economic recession and increased school retention rates. While it is difficult to control the retention rates of continuing students, institutions do have more control on the number of new students. The number of offers made to new students must be more closely monitored and adjusted to particular circumstances.</PARA>
<PARA> It is worth noting that a recent report by the Victorian Post-Secondary Education Commission suggested that almost half of the over-enrolment problems in Victoria are due to existing students staying on at universities in that context. Mr Baldwin's Department and the Australian Vice-Chancellors Committee are undertaking a joint analysis of the statistics and profile returns of institutions with a view to coming to agreement on a broad system-wide approach to the problem. Following these discussions, and prior to the forthcoming profile discussions with higher education institutions, Mr Baldwin will be making a statement on an agreed strategic approach to this problem.</PARA>
<PARA> To the extent that the Government recognises the problem and also reflecting our continued commitment to the expansion of higher education opportunities, Senator Bell should recognise that in this financial year we have provided an extra $76m, and $42m for 1993. The bulk of this will be used to help alleviate the pressure of over-enrolments and overcrowding. That is an important part of the Budget and one which should be recognised for the important measure it is, in terms of combating the over-enrolment problem.</PARA>
<PARA> Enrolment growth assistance will total $70m over the next four years. This will be built into the base operating grants for institutions. That is an important contribution. In 1992, $9m will also be provided for assistance with enrolment growth and $53m for new buildings and refurbishment. The extra $53m for refurbishments and acceleration of new building projects brings total capital funding for 1992 to $266m, which compares with $213m this financial year. On a rough calculation that is at least 20 per cent extra over this financial year.</PARA>
<PARA> In addition, if Senator Bell were to be even-handed about this, he would take into account that the Government has taken steps towards increasing the contribution by industries to higher education and at the same time providing extra growth. Up to 600 new places in 1992, and 700 in both 1993 and 1994, will be funded on a cost-sharing basis with employers. Senator Bell has raised a number of assertions, probably all with an eye to grabbing the odd headline here or there.</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Boswell" NAMEID="YE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YE4">Senator Boswell</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is ungracious-absolutely ungracious.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Boswell knows that it is also true. Basically, the Government has recognised a need for action in this area. We have responded not only by way of assistance in terms of catering for enrolment growth-the extra $70m over the next four years is important there-but also by recognising the need for capital expenditure in institutions as well.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1374" SPEAKER="Bell Sen R.J." NAMEID="7U4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="7U4">Senator BELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I do not know whether the Minister was trying to deny the existence of the symptoms of overcrowding that I described or whether he is just expressing his insensitivity for what the National Union of Students has observed. I ask the Minister: are these promises for the future in recognition of the success of the Government's strategy and policies in higher education? If they are, why was the success of these policies not predicted so that we would not be in this mess now because it would have been catered for already?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1374" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That is a petty, carping supplementary question. To make the assertion that the Government does not recognise or I am insensitive to the problems in this sector has no substance in fact. Senator Bell refers to promises into the future. The Budget is before this Parliament. It is being assessed by this Parliament. In that Budget one finds that allocation of moneys. If that is the best Senator Bell can do he is letting his constituency down enormously. The money is in the Budget and it will be spent. That is the best form of commitment any party in this place can give. It is very easy for him to sit over there making all sorts of offers in terms of his constituency but he must acknowledge that the money is in the Budget. It is not a promise for the future; it is happening now.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1376">
<TITLE>Credit Information Records</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Aulich Sen T.G." NAMEID="JE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="JE4">Senator AULICH</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs and regards privacy protection for all Australians. What further steps has the Government recently taken to ensure that Australians have access to credit information records held about them?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Tate Sen The Hon M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" MINISTERIAL="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator TATE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am pleased to be able to inform the Senate that from 24 September Australians will be able to have access to their credit records: information held in relation to those transactions between credit providers and borrowers which is so much a part of the ordinary life of every Australian, as we do live in a debt-ridden society.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Any Australian who is a borrower will be able to have access, free of charge, to any credit information held on that person by a credit reporting agency. Basically this would be the Credit Reference Association of Australia Ltd or the Tasmanian Collection Service. People will be able to get hold of this credit record, free of charge, every six months. I believe that is a very important access entitlement of borrowers to credit records which are held about them. Not only that, but they will be able to check on those records as to their accuracy and the timeliness of the information held. If they are found to be inaccurate, the Credit Reference Association or the Tasmanian Collection Service will have to inform all those who have been notified of the inaccurate information recorded during the previous three months.</PARA>
<PARA> This is being done under an arrangement worked out by Kevin O'Connor, the Privacy Commissioner, in consultation with the Credit Reference Association. I believe this is a very useful exercise of his powers to hold consultations and to devise a code of conduct in relation to privacy which will well serve the interests of all Australians. I certainly urge all those who are borrowers in our community to take advantage of these rights, as I say, from 24 September.</PARA>
<PARA> In relation to the some other elements of the privacy legislation, it is necessary to postpone their coming into effect until 25 February next year to enable financial institutions and credit reporting agencies to put into place necessary computer systems and other technology. Those regulations will also come into place and that will be an important completion of the regime of privacy that will be put in place in relation to the credit reports which are held on, I guess, almost every Australian in our society.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1376">
<TITLE>Australian Dollar: Interest Rates</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Short Sen J.R." NAMEID="DJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator SHORT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is to the Minister representing the Treasurer. I refer the Minister to the recent strength of the Australian dollar, both before and since last week's interest rate cut. Does the Minister agree with the reports from financial markets that this strength is due to the fact that real interest rates in Australia are amongst the highest in the world? Particularly in light of expectations of a fall in official US interest rates which will make Australia's real interest rates relatively even more attractive to overseas investors and thereby put further upward pressure on the Australian dollar, I ask the Minister: what action do the Government and the Reserve Bank of Australia propose to take to prevent the Australian dollar rising to a level that adversely affects Australian exporters even more?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Short ought to know better than what he said in the second part of the question. If the Government proposed-and indeed it does not-to take any action about a dollar which is floating--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Crichton-Browne" NAMEID="XF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XF4">Senator Crichton-Browne</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Floating! You have had a massive intervention in the past 24 hours.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Crichton-Browne knows what I mean. If the Government proposed any action, one certainly would not announce it during Question Time in the Senate. Senator Short ought to know better than to ask a question such as that.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I do not want to speculate about the behaviour of the Australian dollar. It has been an issue which has confounded economists and commentators, particularly at the time of the Gulf war, for example. It is probably still doing so. I do not want to offer speculative views about the way in which the dollar is behaving or is likely to behave.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Short Sen J.R." NAMEID="DJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator SHORT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask the Minister, who is being unduly sensitive on that issue, a supplementary question. I know he has had some problems in recent days. It does not absolve him in this instance, though. Does the Minister not agree that a more responsible approach by the Government to fiscal and associated policies would have prevented this unwelcome upward pressure on the Australian dollar occurring in the first place?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1376" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I do not understand Senator Short's definition of more responsible fiscal policy.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Kemp" NAMEID="WW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="WW4">Senator Kemp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Of course you don't.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;No, I do not.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;But your policies have thrown one million people out of work.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Perhaps the Leader of the Opposition could be quiet for a minute. He is talking about people being thrown out of work. He ought to understand that the suggested fiscal policy announced by Senator Short in the Senate prior to the Budget and by his Leader subsequent to the Budget would have had the Budget in balance, something the Opposition never did in its entire time in government. It would have had thousands more people out of work as a result of that fiscal policy. If that is what Senator Short wants, he should go out there in the stumps and say it. He comes in here talking about more responsible fiscal policy, which is an entirely subjective view. I do not regard his view of the matter as responsible and I do not attempt to define what that means.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1377">
<TITLE>Iraq</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1377" SPEAKER="Vallentine Sen J." NAMEID="IG4" PARTY="IND" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="IG4">Senator VALLENTINE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I refer the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to a number of reports from NGO workers and United Nations agency staff currently involved with humanitarian relief work in Iraq. On the basis that all these reports point to widespread human suffering amongst civilians in Iraq-with a breakdown in health care, power supplies, food production and distribution, water supplies and quality, and the prediction of substantially greater famine and far greater pressure on a deteriorating health system by the end of the year-I ask the Minister whether the Australian Government is now prepared to argue at the United Nations that Iraq be allowed to purchase food and medicine out of its oil revenue before paying reparations, given that the country's minimum requirement this year for outside food and medicine is $3.5 billion and that the UN agencies, the Red Cross and NGOs can raise only about $200m. I accept that such distribution will need to be strictly controlled to prevent supplies going to the military, but I ask this question knowing that if the UN Security Council does not change its position an appalling tragedy will affect the people of Iraq within the next few months.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1377" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Government obviously shares Senator Vallentine's concerns for the welfare of the people of Iraq, whatever our view may continue to be about the quality and character of its Government. We are aware of reports by UN officials and non-government organisations that warn of the possibility of a major human tragedy if humanitarian needs in Iraq are not addressed swiftly.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The 28 August report of Prince Sadruvdin Aga Khan, the Secretary-General's delegate on humanitarian needs in Iraq, estimates the cost of imports required to maintain normal food consumption levels to be $US1.32 billion for a six-month period. Security Council resolution No. 706 of 15 August permits the sale by Iraq of up to $US1.6 billion worth of oil over a six-month period, subject to the payment by Iraq of 30 per cent of this amount into the compensation fund and lesser amounts to pay for ongoing UN activities in Iraq. Iraq will have $US933m available for its own purchasing after meeting these obligations.</PARA>
<PARA> In addition, there is already an ongoing UN and NGO humanitarian program in Iraq, which is providing food, medicine and health care to Iraqi civilians. Funding for this operation was provided by the international community through contributions to the UN humanitarian fund for civilians in the area. The UN is well aware of the need for early preparations for the harsh winter and, I am advised, is attempting to make appropriate arrangements.</PARA>
<PARA> As to the latter part of Senator Vallentine's question, the UN sanctions committee is empowered to review the level of sanctions applied to Iraq every 60 days in the light of the policies and practices of the Government of Iraq and may reduce or lift sanctions as it sees fit. Clearly, the behaviour of the Iraqi Government, in attempting to hide details of its nuclear and biological weapons programs, works against the possibility of sanctions being lifted entirely. Iraq does, however, retain the right to make purchases of food and other essential items from its own resources. Australia's sale of wheat to Iraq in June, for example, was paid for from Iraqi assets held in a Swiss bank account. The Government is generally mindful of the concerns that have been raised by Senator Vallentine and will certainly be continuing to watch the situation very closely.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1378">
<TITLE>Unionism at Robe River</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1378" SPEAKER="Crane Sen W." NAMEID="UW4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UW4">Senator CRANE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is to the Minister for Industrial Relations. Last Thursday with regard to Robe River, and in particular Cape Lambert Services and Westug, the Minister said that `it goes into voluntary liquidation and another company is contrived to take its place'. Then on Monday the Minister described Westug as a new company sponsored by Robe River. Is it not the fact that there is no relationship between Westug and Robe River? Did not Robe River decide to put its tug services out to tender, a tender which was won by an unrelated company Westug? If that is so, why did the Minister contrive a situation to damage one of Australia's most successful enterprises? Is the Minister simply a puppet of the Seamen's Union of Australia, or is there another explanation for the Minister's misleading the Senate in this way?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1378" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You did not check the veracity of the information, did you? You just accepted the brief.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Short" NAMEID="DJ4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator Short</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You didn't do your homework.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Ignore the interjections.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Thank you, Mr President. I will ignore them. It seems that Senator Crane has a brief from Robe River to pursue this question in some detail. Yesterday Senator Crane accused me of misleading the Parliament.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Short" NAMEID="DJ4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="DJ4">Senator Short</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You did.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Panizza" NAMEID="JI4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="JI4">Senator Panizza</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is in the record.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I did not mislead the Parliament. I resent that remark and ask for it to be withdrawn. I think that it is a reprehensible reflection on a member of this chamber. I resent it deeply. I did not mislead this chamber. For members opposite to throw an accusation around like that willy-nilly reflects very badly on them. In fact, Senator Crane misled this chamber yesterday when he accused me in an answer of misleading it and when he produced so-called statistics that the eight appeals that I had referred to had not been appeals by Robe River. Yesterday Senator Crane said, `I emphasise eight appeals by Robe River to the Industrial Relations Commission and two appeals to the High Court'. He went on to argue that that was not true.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I have the details of the eight appeals here. They start from 13 June 1989-an appeal by Robe River against a Commission decision, dismissed. There was another on 6 September, dismissed; another on 5 October, dismissed; another on 8= October, dismissed; another again on 8= October 1990, dismissed; another on 19= June 1991, substantially dismissed and part of it referred for another hearing; another on 19 June, and the same result for that; and another on 22 July. If anyone has misled this chamber, it has not been me; it has been Senator Crane in the case of this question. So far as Westug is concerned, I believe that a contrived arrangement has been arrived at by Robe River.</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Kemp" NAMEID="WW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="WW4">Senator Kemp</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Where is the evidence?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I believe that on the basis that the wholly-owned subsidiary of Robe River, Cape Lambert Services, underwent a dispute with the Seamen's Union. In this context I should qualify the definition of `dispute'. This was not a strike or a stoppage but a paper dispute conducted through the Commission and exhausted through the Commission with appeals to the High Court.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> After that matter came to a conclusion, this company went into voluntary liquidation-and lo and behold, out of the blue comes this company, which I understand a former captain of one of the tugs of Robe River formed. In those circumstances, I believe that this was a contrived arrangement. I think those opposite would be naive to pretend that in a robust industrial situation like this it was not. If they were, they would be arguing the cause of an employer wanting to avoid its legal requirements. I do not alter, I do not resile and I will not back down from any of the statements that I have made in this House.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1378" SPEAKER="Crane Sen W." NAMEID="UW4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="WA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UW4">Senator CRANE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I ask the Minister for Industrial Relations to also name the two cases he referred to in which the union appealed against Robe River.</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1378" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I said last week that there were eight appeals by Robe River to the Full Bench of the Commission and substantially the union was upheld in every single one of them. That is a matter of fact.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The High Court matters have not been finished.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;If I were Senator Hill, I would not make that gesture in this chamber; it is a very offensive gesture.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The High Court matters have not yet been finished.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There were two other appeals by the union, that is true, but it does not deviate from the point: so what?</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1379">
<TITLE>Firearms Control</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1379" SPEAKER="Beahan Sen M.E." NAMEID="NE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NE4">Senator BEAHAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs. Has the Minister's attention been drawn to media reports that the ACTU congress has called for tighter gun controls? How will this expression of support from a major national institution assist in the desirable movement towards a nationwide approach to the possession of firearms in Australia?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1379" SPEAKER="Tate Sen The Hon M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS" MINISTERIAL="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator TATE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have heard calls from the ACTU congress meeting yesterday on Federal and State governments to demand registration of all firearms, tighten eligibility rules governing the issue of shooters licences, and ban semi-automatic weapons. I am quite confident that in that resolution the congress is reflecting the views of its very wide membership in the Australian community and, of course, a much wider group of Australians, such as are reflected in the one million signatures gathered by the Sydney Telegraph Mirror in its petition calling for stricter gun control laws in New South Wales.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I agree with ACTU President, Martin Ferguson, when he said that workers and their families were often the unnecessary victims of lousy gun control legislation. I believe that once again he is well reflecting the concern of unions such as the police associations around Australia which have taken a very strong stance in this regard and have been joined by their New Zealand colleagues only this week at a meeting of the various associations in New Zealand. He is also reflecting the concern of the bank employees representatives, many of whom have had members killed, certainly injured and definitely threatened, intimidated and traumatised by the experience of being confronted by a bank robber wielding a weapon.</PARA>
<PARA> In so far as the congress called on Federal and State governments to once and for all resolve this issue decisively, we will take up that challenge at the Police Ministers Council meeting and then at the Premiers Conference. That focus will be not only in regard to gun control legislation, which must not be frustrated by the demarcations relating to old colonial boundaries-we must have a nationwide approach-but also it must be wedded to a much larger change in our society to do away with the culture of violence which underpins and underlies the occasional eruption into the type of massacre we saw at Strathfield Plaza and on other occasions.</PARA>
<PARA> The ACTU congress has added its voice to many other voices in the community, both of individuals and of organisations, which demand change by politicians in this regard. We will respond to that request from the community and I believe that, by the end of this year, we will have very fruitful social change Australia-wide in this particular matter.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1380">
<TITLE>Trade Quotas</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1380" SPEAKER="Boswell Sen R.L.D." NAMEID="YE4" PARTY="NP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YE4">Senator BOSWELL</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Prime Minister. It refers to the announcement of quotas imposed on Australian beef entering America. Does the Minister agree that a quota is the ultimate form of tariff and is completely contrary to the principles of GATT? The EC and the United States have increased their export subsidies while Australia has done everything to promote world trade by reducing tariffs, deregulating the wheat industry, lowering our quarantine standards, accepting a lower Codex import standard of food, and lifting the embargo on the sugar industry. As Senator Button was one of the prime architects of internationalising our trade, would he accept that the Australian trade position is so serious that it has reached a state of emergency? Would he use his position, as the third highest person in the Government, to urge the Prime Minister to lead a trade delegation, at a head of state level, directly to Mr Bush and other world leaders to represent Australia's position in this trade debate?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1380" SPEAKER="Button Sen The Hon J.N." NAMEID="4F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator BUTTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I heard this morning that Mr Austen, the Chairman of the Meat and Livestock Corporation, is going to the United States I think today to carry out negotiations with the United States industry. I also heard a representative of the US beef growers being very sanguine, as it were, about the likely success of Mr Austen's mission.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Senator Boswell has asked me to agree to a number of propositions which are of a general kind; for example, whether I regard quotas as a most pernicious form of trade protection. The answer to that is probably yes, although maybe some countries have devised a worse form of trade protection than that, but I am not aware of one.</PARA>
<PARA> As I understand it, the request of the United States Government is that our beef exporters would enter into voluntary restraint agreements. They were obliged to do that in 1982, 1983, 1987 and 1988. The so-called voluntary restraints are an art form developed particularly by the United States in its trading relationships with Japan. Whether they are accurately described as quotas, I do not know.</PARA>
<PARA> The point about Senator Boswell's question is that one does regard this form of trade negotiation as inconsistent with the United States general position in the Uruguay Round. It is certainly inconsistent with the interests of Australia. In that context, I am not sure what can be done apart from the action which the Government and the Meat and Livestock Corporation have taken.</PARA>
<PARA> It is not easy to ask the Prime Minister to go to the United States in respect of one particular industry, important as it is, on a mission which may or may not be successful. I very much doubt whether it would be successful. I do not think that is a matter which the Prime Minister has considered at this time.</PARA>
<PARA> The Government is doing all it can to obtain higher access, for our beef producers in various countries, to ensure that we are equitably treated as the major meat exporter with approximately 60 per cent of the market. Again, it serves to highlight the importance which has to be attached to a satisfactory outcome of the Uruguay Round. I cannot give Senator Boswell a more specific answer than that at this time. I just urge the support of the National Party in endeavours which the Government does make.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1381">
<TITLE>Shipping</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1381" SPEAKER="Reynolds Sen The Hon M." NAMEID="XI4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XI4">Senator REYNOLDS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support. What action is being taken to detect substandard ships trading in Australian waters? In particular what action is being taken against owners of the merchant ship recently reported in Townsville as being in a dangerous state of disrepair? Will the owners also be investigated for an alleged oil spill which is currently polluting local beaches?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1381" SPEAKER="Collins Sen The Hon R.L." NAMEID="OF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NT" MINISTERIAL="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="OF4">Senator COLLINS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On 30 August, a foreign flag vessel, the Moksong, was detected in Townsville by the master of a tug as having some serious structural damage above its waterline. The Moksong had gone to Townsville to load sugar. As a result of the report by the tug master to safety authorities, a marine inspector from the register of the ship, that is, the Korean register, inspected the ship and found that the damage was of such a nature that the ship would be endangered if it had been loaded with sugar. The ship was cleared to sail under light conditions and therefore was ordered to return to its home port for repairs without having been able to load its cargo.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The situation currently is that we carry out inspections of about 25 per cent of the vessels that enter Australian ports under our port inspection program in accordance with the international conventions that we are party to. This is a very high percentage in comparison with world practice. Regrettably, in the last year, 60 per cent of the ships that have been inspected have had to be detained because of serious structural problems or, unfortunately in the case of half of those vessels, serious deficiencies in the life saving equipment on board the ships. Under those circumstances, the ships are required to have repairs carried out in Australia before they are allowed to leave port. Following the Kirki incident, the Australian Maritime Safety Authority is currently investigating practical means of upgrading, within the conventions that we are party to, the level of inspections on board these ships to make them more stringent and perhaps have a two stage system which involves being able to physically inspect certain designated areas of the ship as well as carrying out a paper inspection, which is the normal practice at this point in time.</PARA>
<PARA> There have been some oil spills in Queensland. It is not known at this stage whether this vessel was responsible. The spills occurred under our national plan in the area designated for Queensland jurisdiction. An investigation is currently being carried out by Queensland State authorities into spills which appear to be of ship bunker fuel, that is, fuel oil.</PARA>
<PARA> I know that samples have been taken and that at this point in time the investigation has ruled out two ships. The investigation is continuing. I am assured that, if the Queensland State authorities actually manage by chemical analysis to identify the ship from which the oil has come, prosecutions will be launched.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1381">
<TITLE>Fire Protection Maintenance Services</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1381" SPEAKER="Calvert Sen P.H." NAMEID="5F4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator CALVERT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Administrative Services. Why has the Department of Administrative Services failed to allow all fire protection maintenance service contractors who have been recognised by the Standards Association of Australia to tender for the provision of fire protection maintenance services to Commonwealth owned buildings in the ACT? Is the Minister aware that, of the five companies selectively chosen by him to provide these services, four are subsidiaries of the one major company? Is the Minister also aware that this closed shop tendering process is likely to cost the Australian taxpayers an estimated $5m over the life of the contract? Why is the Minister prepared to deny market forces the opportunity to determine the successful tenderer for the provision of fire maintenance services in Canberra?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1381" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Calvert raises a question about which I will get more detail. What I will say at this time is that things have not been what they should have been and are not what they always seem to be. A number of his colleagues have come in here making all sorts of assertions. The only advice I give Senator Calvert at this stage is: do not make their mistake by putting out press statements alleging all sorts of rorts and other misadventures and misdeeds when the truth may in fact be totally different from what he is asserting, as has been the experience of his colleagues.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1382">
<TITLE>Illegal Narcotics Trade</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Bourne Sen V." NAMEID="TW4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TW4">Senator BOURNE</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Is the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade aware of the extent of the drug trade across the Burmese borders, particularly with China and Thailand? What is the estimated amount of heroin originating in Burma and any other Burmese narcotics which end up in the illegal drug trade in Australia? What steps is Australia taking to eliminate the trade in illegal narcotics between Australia and Burma?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Evans Sen The Hon G.J." NAMEID="VD4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC" MINISTERIAL="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VD4">Senator GARETH EVANS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Given the illegal and clandestine nature of opium and heroin production, it is obviously not possible to quantify precisely the extent of drug trafficking across Burmese borders. Opium and heroin produced in Burma are trafficked principally via Thailand, China and India. Thailand remains the primary trafficking route for narcotics produced in Burma. However, China's southern provinces of Yunnan, Guizhou and Guangxi have recently become major trafficking routes for heroin produced in Burma. By November 1990, Chinese authorities had intercepted over 1,000 kilograms of heroin.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Estimates for the 1990 production of opium in Burma vary considerably but can reasonably be placed in the range of 2,000 tonnes to 2,500 tonnes, with estimates for 1991 production in the same range. The best estimate is that there are 900 tonnes to 1,000 tonnes of opium available in Burma for processing to morphine and heroin, with almost all of this refined product being exported. The amounts that we are talking about-even though we cannot estimate them precisely-are horrifyingly large.</PARA>
<PARA> It is estimated that 70 per cent to 75 per cent of the heroin entering Australia is produced in the Golden Triangle, with the majority originating from Burma. Burma is not regarded as a source of illicit drugs other than opium and its derivatives. To control the illicit traffic in narcotics from the Golden Triangle, Australia is active in several areas. Narcotics related assistance is provided to South East Asia; the Australian Federal Police has liaison officers in Bangkok, Chiang Mai, Kuala Lumpur, Singapore, Manila and Hong Kong; and the Australian Customs Service again has extensive control operations at the customs barrier.</PARA>
<PARA> Recently, agreement has been reached on projects under the United Nations international drug control program subregional strategy for South East Asia. The first will be a joint drug abuse control project on the China-Burma border. Similarly, there is agreement, in principle, for a joint UNDCP-Burma-Thailand project. Australia supports UNDCP through a core budget contribution of approximately $700,000 and support for its regional activities in South East Asia. We may give consideration in the future to support for the UNDCP's joint projects with Burma.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1382">
<TITLE>Superannuation Tax</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is directed to the Minister for Industrial Relations. I refer to Budget figures which show that the gross operating surplus for companies after tax and interest is now at its lowest level in 25 years and, further, that labour productivity has been virtually stagnant over the last five years. In view of these very depressing statistics, does the Minister agree that the Government's proposed 2 per cent increase in superannuation tax will add another $3 billion to $4 billion to the national wages bill and that the ultimate effect will inevitably be increased unemployment and inflation, as predicted by Mr Chris Murphy of the ANU, unless employees are required to contribute by way of wages forgone. Is it also a fact that, under the proposed new arrangements, an employer could satisfy its statutory obligation by contributing to any complying fund and yet still be in breach of award obligations requiring payment to be made to a prescribed industry fund? If this is so, does it not make a mockery of the principle of choice?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I welcome this question on superannuation. The question does not contain a recognition that the 3 per cent award based superannuation that now applies in Australia arose out of wages forgone at the time it was introduced.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Alston" NAMEID="LD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Not so at all; you have not read the national wage case.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Let the Minister answer the question.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;As a result of the national wage case, wages were forgone and the amount was taken as superannuation, thus establishing in Australia an award entitlement for blue-collar workers who hitherto had not had a superannuation entitlement. It at least extended the right of superannuation more equitably than it was before.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Previously, managerial elites and white- collar workers were the recipients of superannuation. Now, as a consequence of the accord, blue-collar workers are too. The equity principle is being more extensively met. Senator Alston's question is about legislative superannuation that was announced in the Budget and how this Government intends to meet the criteria of equity to guarantee that all employees in this country have a superannuation entitlement.</PARA>
<PARA> There is an economic and social imperative that a form of national income retirement scheme be established now. We are all aware that the ageing of the Australian population is increasing and that by the end of the century there will be more people on the age pension per ratio of people in the work force than there are now. There will be fewer taxpayers supporting a higher pension pay-out. This requires a government to face those circumstances and make a decision about a national retirement scheme.</PARA>
<PARA> This Government has the courage to do that-it made such an announcement in the Budget. While this need is not recognised on the Opposition side, nonetheless it is recognised widely in the community.</PARA>
<PARA> Senator Alston asked whether or not the increase in superannuation entitlements will be an unfair impost on companies. The Treasurer announced that the superannuation legislation should apply from 1 July next year. So during the early phases of the economic recovery in the course of the next 12 months, there will be no additional superannuation impost.</PARA>
<PARA> The second point is that the superannuation impost has a line drawn under it. For those companies with a payroll of half a million dollars or less-typically companies in this country that employ about 24 people-there will be no increase in superannuation above the current award level of 3 per cent. So only medium and larger companies will meet the impost.</PARA>
<PARA> The third point, which I think answers Senator Alston's question-and I think I noted all aspects of it-is that the Government has worked out with the ACTU an arrangement that the level of superannuation contribution is to be regarded, in terms of future wage movements, as a way of ensuring that there is no wage break-out and is to be taken into consideration in terms of future aggregate wage outcomes. In short, that is to say that wages and superannuation are to be seen as a total cost and that the benefit can be taken in wages or superannuation in later systems.</PARA>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I find that a bitterly disappointing answer on behalf of all those people who asked me to get some clarification on these matters.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Richardson" NAMEID="4E4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator Richardson</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Who would ask you?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Well, they cannot get the answer from the Government, and it is quite clear why.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Government senators interjecting-</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Just pay the money back and we will talk later.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Senator Alston will ask his supplementary question.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There are two propositions.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Richardson" NAMEID="4E4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator Richardson</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You can wait for that. You will get your serve.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Righto. First, what are the employment and inflationary consequences--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Cook" NAMEID="RF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator Cook</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Are you asking a question or making a speech?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator ALSTON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;That was my first question. I am asking Senator Cook again in simple terms so that, hopefully, I can get an answer this time. The first part of my question was: what are the employment and inflationary consequences? The second part was: what happens if a company contributes to any complying scheme that is not an industry fund? Is it still in breach of the award obligations?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1382" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I am asked a question about the employment and inflationary implications. As I have said, the implementation of this legislative arrangement will not commence until 1 July next year. One can project the employment and inflationary figures beyond this current term. It is also the case that funds can accumulate at a considerable rate. It is estimated by non-Treasury sources that, by the end of this century, those funds will contain between $300 billion and $600 billion. That massive pool of potential investment in Australian industry will also have an impact on the level of employment and the ability of Australian companies to compete. Thus, it will also have an impact on inflation. When one puts that alongside of the other policies to manage the economy, it can be said that while there may be some employment and inflationary impact--</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Alston" NAMEID="LD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;There will.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Well, there may be. In all of these circumstances, particularly in relation to the obligation on the Government to put forward a retirement package, they are appropriate measures for the Government to introduce.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The second question asked what type of funds will be recognised for the purpose of superannuation contributions. The Treasurer has spoken on this matter and has indicated that later this month it is his intention to have consultations to finalise the terms of the legislation.</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Alston" NAMEID="LD4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Award breaches are your responsibility.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I point out that it is not my responsibility; it is the Treasurer's. He is going to undertake community consultation with all interested groups in order that the Government may come to a conclusion about the appropriate way of introducing this scheme.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1384">
<TITLE>International Labour Organisation</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1384" SPEAKER="Burns Sen B.R" NAMEID="2F4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="2F4">Senator BURNS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Has the Minister for Industrial Relations seen reports of sillier than usual comments by his counterpart in New South Wales to the effect that conventions of the United Nations International Labour Organisation are designed mainly for Third World countries? If these reports are accurate, can the Minister advise the Senate whether our national Government shares these views and attitudes? Can the Minister further advise the Senate on the appropriateness or otherwise of those ILO conventions for Australia as a developed economy?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1384" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Convention 87 is the convention on freedom of association. That convention recognises exemptions in the case of the right to strike where essential services are involved. Therefore, the ILO is concerned to see that where essential services legislation applies it is legislation which genuinely covers real essential services and not legislation that is stretched to cover non-essential services, thus depriving particular workers in the non-essential area if covered by such legislation of their rights under the ILO convention.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The ILO committee of experts has made a direct request to Australia and referred to the New South Wales Government's essential services legislation. It has raised a number of questions about that legislation which go to its belief that the legislation covers non-essential areas and is not in conformity with the ILO freedom of association convention.</PARA>
<PARA> When I received that report from the ILO, I passed it onto the New South Wales Government, which has endorsed the particular convention and freely embraced its ratification. I was disappointed to see in the Sydney Morning Herald of 3 September a comment by the New South Wales Minister for Industrial Relations and Employment, Mr Fahey, that he did not accept the ILO's criticisms of the State legislation.</PARA>
<PARA> The ILO asked him to examine why that legislation is not in conformity with a convention that has been accepted by the New South Wales Government. He said that he does not accept the criticisms but that he has not yet conducted examinations, and I believe that he is obliged to do so.</PARA>
<PARA> According to this report, he also said, `The ILO is only for Third World countries'. That seems to suggest that, if we are regarded as a first world country, we are exempt from observing international minimum labour standards. That is, of course, not true. The remarks by Mr Fahey are those of a two-bit dictator-the sort of remarks expected from a country with an authoritarian regime that flouts international standards and regards the observance of reasonable--</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On a point of order, Mr President, I object to the use of the words, `two-bit dictator'.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Richardson" NAMEID="4E4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator Richardson</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;All right, he is a one-bit.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Mr Fahey is a member of State Parliament and that comment should be withdrawn.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I withdraw that comment, if that is what you are requesting me to do, Mr President. Mr Fahey is behaving like a petty despot in an authoritarian regime that flouts international standards. It does not reflect well on Australia's credibility in the world when standards embraced voluntarily by States and governments can be so described. It reflects very badly on Mr Fahey that he should behave in this way towards an international standard that his State has embraced and that he is required to observe.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1385">
<TITLE>Political Advertising</TITLE>
<QUESTION PAGE="1385" SPEAKER="Bishop Sen B.K." NAMEID="SE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator BISHOP</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;My question is addressed to the Minister for Administrative Services. In Estimates Committee F hearings yesterday, the Chairman of the Australian Broadcasting Tribunal, Mr Peter Westerway, stated that he had been consulted by Minister Bolkus on the Political Broadcasts and Political Disclosures Bill and that he had made a report to the Minister. Will the Minister make that report available to the Senate Select Committee on the Political Broadcasts and Political Disclosures Bill so that the Committee may consider that report and, indeed, consider whether it is proper for the Minister to seek advice on draft legislation from the person and/or the Tribunal which will ultimately be called upon to adjudicate upon the issues arising from such legislation?</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Honourable senators interjecting-</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Hill" NAMEID="BH4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="BH4">Senator Hill</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, on a point of order: can the honourable senator be allowed to give the question in a form we can all hear?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Senator Hill, there have been constant interjections, particularly from my left, all through Question Time. There are too many interjections from all sides of the chamber at Question Time.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1385" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Despite the fact that Senator Bishop may have been mumbling, I was able to pick up the question. The answer is no; I will take advice as the Government Minister from whatever quarters I want to. That advice will be given to the Senate as in the normal practice when I or any other Minister decides to do so.</PARA></TALK.START>
</ANSWER><QUESTION PAGE="1385" SPEAKER="Bishop Sen B.K." NAMEID="SE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="SE4">Senator BISHOP</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Will Minister Bolkus, the Minister for mumbles, advise the Senate whether he will make that report available to the Committee? Will he answer the second part of the question as to whether he considers it proper and whether the Committee may consider it proper that the Minister seeks advice from the Tribunal which will ultimately be required to adjudicate upon matters arising from the legislation?</PARA></TALK.START>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1385" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA" MINISTERIAL="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator BOLKUS</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The only difference between the first question and the supplementary question was the manner in which Senator Bishop asked it. I have already answered the question.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Button" NAMEID="4F4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4F4">Senator Button</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Mr President, I ask that further questions be placed on the Notice Paper.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
<QUESTION.BLOCK PAGE="1386">
<TITLE>Rice</TITLE>
<ANSWER PAGE="1386" SPEAKER="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S." NAMEID="RF4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="WA" MINISTERIAL="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="RF4">Senator COOK</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Earlier this week Senator Bjelke-Petersen asked me a question concerning rice and trade with Thailand. I have now been supplied with an answer to that question for those parts of it that I did not answer. Rather than read it, I wonder whether I could have leave of the Opposition to have this answer incorporated in Hansard.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Leave granted.</PARA>
<PARA> The answer read as follows-</PARA>
<PARA> 1. I can confirm that the Thai Government does impose a ban on the import of rice.</PARA>
<PARA> 2. As part of the Uruguay Round Agriculture Negotiations outcome, Australia is seeking the conversion of all existing non-tariff barriers on agricultural products to tariffs. The Cairns group, of which both Thailand and Australia are members, believes that this fundamental reinstrumentation of existing barriers to more transparent forms of border protection, with subsequent reductions in these tariffs, will be an important element of a liberalising agriculture reform package. If the Cairns group's objectives in the negotiations are met, non-tariff barriers of this kind will be removed.</PARA>
<PARA> 3. While our understanding from industry representatives is that Thailand is not an identified target for the export of Australian rice, one company has raised with us a specific aspect of Thailand's ban on the import of rice as it affects their product. We have been pursuing this case through our embassy in Bangkok and it will be taken up at the annual joint trade committee meeting which is due to be held in Melbourne from 17 to 18 September.</PARA>
<PARA> 4. As part of widespread consultations on market access issues, we have just completed discussions in Bangkok with the Thai authorities aimed at reinforcing coordination on international trade negotiations and obtaining improvements in Thailand's tariff regime.</PARA>
<PARA> 5. No useful purpose would be served by introducing Australian tariffs on imported rice. Our aim is to achieve with Thailand a balanced package of concessions that address each country's specific areas of trade interest.</PARA>
</ANSWER></QUESTION.BLOCK>
</QWN><DEBATE TYPE="Personal Explanation" PAGE="1386"><TITLE>PERSONAL EXPLANATION</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1386" SPEAKER="Spindler Sen S." NAMEID="0X4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="0X4">Senator SPINDLER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-Yesterday in the second reading debate on Loan Bill (No. 2) 1991, Senator Kemp stated that my alternative Budget had a $2.4 billion discrepancy. I refer the Senate to Hansard of Thursday, 22 August 1991, page 984, where I made it quite clear that Senator Lees had put it on public record that it was a typographical error because the term `weekly' should have been `fortnightly' and that the figures in fact had been correctly computed. I commend the reading of Hansard to Senator Kemp as an admirable source of information.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><PETITION.GRP PAGE="1386">
<TITLE>PETITIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The Clerk" NAMEID="10001">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10001">The Clerk</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
</PROCTEXT><PETITION PAGE="1386" PRESENTERS="KERNOT; VALLENTINE" NAMEIDS="XW4; IG4">
<TITLE>Aidex Exhibition</TITLE>
<PARA>To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled:</PARA>
<PARA> A humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:</PARA>
<PARA> Attention is drawn to Australia's increasing role in the militarisation of the Pacific region and in particular to the current Government-led arms export drive.</PARA>
<PARA> The arms trade is not only detrimental to Australians affected by the diversion of public money away from socially beneficial areas-for example, health, education and social welfare-but is an integral factor in the oppression and poverty of the people of the Third World.</PARA>
<PARA> Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that the Australian Parliament will:</PARA>
<PARA> Cease all military aid and training to governments engaged in repression of their own people.</PARA>
<PARA> Direct all Federal and State Government Departments and instrumentalities to withdraw from participation in and support for AIDEX and similar arms fairs in Australia and overseas.</PARA>
<PARA> Close down AIDEX 1991.</PARA>
<PARA> Establish a register of all applications for arms transfers and offset agreements which would be subject to public scrutiny.</PARA>
<PARA> Redirect all monies currently being used to promote the arms industry to socially useful research, development and production.</PARA>
<PARA> And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="XW4">Senator Kernot</NAME><FROM> (from 22 citizens) and </FROM></PRESENTER><PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="IG4">  Senator Vallentine</NAME><FROM> (from 39 citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PETITION PAGE="1387" PRESENTERS="VALLENTINE" NAMEIDS="IG4">
<TITLE>AIDEX Exhibition</TITLE>
<PARA>To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:</PARA>
<PARA> We the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully call on the Government to withdraw its endorsement from the arms bazaar, AIDEX `91, scheduled to be held in Canberra, 26-28 November, 1991, and to ensure that no government department or company takes part in the aforementioned event.</PARA>
<PARA> And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="IG4">Senator Vallentine</NAME><FROM> (from 153 citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PETITION PAGE="1387" PRESENTERS="REID" NAMEIDS="VI4">
<TITLE>Ukrainian Sovereignty</TITLE>
<PARA>To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament.</PARA>
<PARA>The Petition of the undersigned shows:</PARA>
<PARA> That we the undersigned, deplore the Soviet Union and Russia's continuing attempts to deny Ukraine its rightful sovereignty, independence and nationhood.</PARA>
<PARA> Your Petitioners pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled should support Ukrainian/Australians in pursuit of Sovereignty, independence and nationhood for Ukraine as proclaimed in Kiev on Saturday August 24, 1991.</PARA>
<PARA> And your Petitioners, as in duty bound will ever pray:</PARA>
<PARA>May your kindness, O Lord, be upon us who have put hope in you; may the Lord give strength to His people; may the Lord bless His people with peace, save your people, O Lord, and bless your inheritance. Amen.</PARA>
<PRESENTER.BLOCK>by <PRESENTER><NAME NAMEID="VI4">Senator Reid</NAME><FROM> (from 150 citizens).</FROM></PRESENTER></PRESENTER.BLOCK>
</PETITION>
<PARA>Petitions received.</PARA></PETITION.GRP><DEBATE TYPE="Notice of Motion" PAGE="1387"><TITLE>NOTICES OF MOTION</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1387">
<TITLE>Electoral and Referendum Amendment Bill 1991</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1387" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of Senator Bolkus, I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, he shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the following bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918 and the Referendum (Machinery Provisions) Act 1984, and for related purposes.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1387">
<TITLE>Federal Court of Australia Amendment Bill 1991</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1387" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of Senator Tate, I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, he shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the following bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1387">
<TITLE>Australian Taxation Office: Media Release</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1387" SPEAKER="Watson Sen J.O.W." NAMEID="VJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VJ4">Senator WATSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That, while deploring some taxpayers' misuse of tax file numbers, and endorsing the enforcement of the law by the Australian Tax Office (ATO), the Senate-</PARA>
<PARA> (a) regrets that the media release by the ATO, No. 91 of 30 April 1991, was misleading; and</PARA>
<PARA> (b) requests its withdrawal and replacement with a statement that more accurately reflects the findings of the court.</PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1387"><TITLE>HOURS OF MEETING AND ORDER OF BUSINESS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA> Motion (by Senator McMullan)-by leave-agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA> That the order of the Senate of 15 August 1991 be varied to provide that the hours of meeting of the Senate on Thursday 12 September 1991 be 10.00 a.m. to 3.00 p.m. and the routine of business be:</PARA>
<PARA>(a) Petitions</PARA>
<PARA>(b) Notices of motion</PARA>
<PARA>(c) Postponement and re-arrangement of business</PARA>
<PARA>(d) Tabling of Government documents</PARA>
<PARA>(e) Any proposal to debate a matter of public importance or of urgency</PARA>
<PARA>(f) Discovery of formal business</PARA>
<PARA>(g) Government business</PARA>
<PARA>(h) At 12.45 p.m., matters of Public Interest</PARA>
<PARA>(i) At 2.00 p.m., questions</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Miscellaneous" PAGE="1387"><TITLE>TABLING OF DOCUMENTS</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1387" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Manager of Government Business in the Senate)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Documents are tabled in accordance with the list circulated to honourable senators. With the concurrence of the Senate, I ask that the list be incorporated in Hansard.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Leave granted. </PARA>
<PARA> The list read as follows-</PARA>
<PARA> 1. ADVANCE TO THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE-AUGUST 1991. </PARA>
<PARA> 2. SUPPORTING APPLICATIONS OF ISSUES FROM THE ADVANCE TO THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE-AUGUST 1991. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! As the Senate will be adjourning early today to enable Estimates committees to meet, there will not be an opportunity to consider the Government documents just tabled. Documents will, therefore, be listed on the Notice Paper and honourable senators will have the opportunity to consider them during General Business on Thursday, 10 October 1991.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Matter of Urgency" PAGE="1388"><TITLE>MATTER OF URGENCY</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1388">
<TITLE>Protection of Environment</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I have received the following letter from the Acting Leader of the Australian Democrats, Senator Coulter:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Dear Mr President,</PARA>
<PARA> Pursuant to standing order 75, I give notice that today I propose to move that:</PARA>
<PARA>`In the opinion of the Senate, the following is a matter of urgency.</PARA>
<PARA> The need for the Federal Government to more widely exercise its constitutional powers so as to more effectively and comprehensively protect the Australian environment.'</PARA>
<PARA>Yours sincerely,</PARA>
<PARA>(JOHN R. COULTER)</PARA>
<PARA>Senator for the State of</PARA>
<PARA>South Australia</PARA>
<PARA>Is the proposal supported?</PARA>
<PARA> More than the number of senators required by the Standing Orders having risen in their places-</PARA>
</INTERJECT>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I understand that informal arrangements have been made to limit the debate to 45 minutes with speaking times as follows: Senator Coulter, 15 minutes; Senator Michael Baume, 5 minutes; Senator Calvert, 5 minutes; Senator Macdonald, 5 minutes; and the Minister, 15 minutes. With the concurrence of the Senate, I shall ask the Clerks to set the clock accordingly.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
</PROCTEXT>
<SPEECH PAGE="1388" SPEAKER="Coulter Sen J.R." NAMEID="TF4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator COULTER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Deputy Leader of the Australian Democrats)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(11.08 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That, in the opinion of the Senate, the following is a matter of urgency:</PARA>
<PARA> The need for the Federal Government to more widely exercise its constitutional powers so as to more effectively and comprehensively protect the Australian environment. </PARA>
<PARA>Mr President, I had earlier accepted that arrangement in relation to time. As everybody knows, this issue has arisen in recent days as a consequence of meetings between the Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories, Mrs Kelly, and representatives of various peak conservation groups around this country. I think that it is worth stressing and putting on the record the very wide constitutional powers which the Federal Government does possess in protecting the environment. On several occasions, we have seen both the Opposition, when it was in government, and the present Hawke Government exercise those powers. </PARA>
<PARA> What is of concern now is that there are substantial indications from media reports, from meetings between Minister Kelly and peak environment groups and from some of the documentation in relation to negotiations now proceeding between the Federal Government and the States that the Federal Government is seeking to apply those powers which it possesses much less assiduously than it has applied them in the past and very much to the detriment of the Australian environment. That is at a time when quite clearly many national issues are evident which can only be addressed at the national level, which therefore must necessarily involve the application of these constitutional powers and at a time when the Australian public, by all the polls which have been conducted, is indicating that it wants the Federal Government to exercise those powers because it recognises that, in many respects, the Australian environment is very much under threat. </PARA>
<PARA> The Federal Government has constitutional powers under section 51 of the Constitution. I remind the Senate that under section 51(i) the Federal Government can make laws for the good government of the Commonwealth with respect to trade and commerce with other countries and among the States-these are very wide powers indeed. Under section 51(xx) it can control the operations of foreign corporations and trading and financial corporations formed within the limits of the Commonwealth. Of course, the external affairs powers have been more widely used than those powers. </PARA>
<PARA> I think most people who dwell upon the meaning of those words would recognise that most, but not all, of the environmental damage occurring in Australia would relate to the operation of trading companies and corporations. Some damage would occur as a result of individual actions but most of it could be controlled by the Commonwealth using those powers. As I have indicated, we recognise that there are a number of areas where the States alone are incapable of properly exercising environmental management. National issues must be controlled at the national level. I will just mention a few of those areas. </PARA>
<PARA> In relation to national energy policy, the Federal Government has notionally-and I stress `notionally'-committed itself to the Toronto targets, which include reducing carbon dioxide emissions by 20 per cent by the year 2005. Yet we have seen nothing at all from the Federal Government on exactly how it will make those targets stick. The State parliaments of Queensland, Western Australia, Tasmania and Victoria are entertaining schemes for the further development of power stations between now and the year 2005. We have seen nothing at all in relation to a national transport policy despite the fact that transport is one of the major users of fossil fuels and therefore a major emitter of greenhouse gases. We have seen nothing from the Federal Government which, at the national level, seriously addresses those problems. </PARA>
<PARA> It is clear that we need national standards on the quality of air and water. Just the other evening during a meeting of Estimates Committee A, officers and the Minister for Social Security (Senator Richardson), who is at the table, spoke about the establishment of an EPA and the need to ensure that the standards which are likely to be set will take into account the lowest common denominator standards which can be agreed between the States. </PARA>
<PARA> Quite clearly, we need national standards in respect of the handling and disposal of toxic waste. Quite clearly, we need national legislation and national standards in respect of coastal management and tourism, environmental impact statements and the assessment of environmental impacts. If we do not have those things in relation to coastal management, EISs and the like, we will see a continuation of the practice of large companies, very often multinational companies, picking off one State against another for the lowest standards of environmental protection they can get. Quite clearly, the States are at a serious disadvantage when it comes to protecting the environment properly. </PARA>
<PARA> On a Four Corners program the other evening Minister Kelly agreed that it was quite ridiculous that the long-footed potoroo-that was the one example she used-was protected in Victoria but was not protected if it hopped across the border into New South Wales. Of course, the issue of endangered species goes well beyond that: it goes to properly protecting the ecological systems in this country so that the full range of species-animals, plants and, indeed, all other parts of the ecology which support those more obvious species-can also be protected. </PARA>
<PARA> That can be done only at the national level through national inventories and national protective laws. It is clear that the full exercise of those Federal powers is capable of controlling well over 90 per cent of those activities that damage those very important elements of our environment. </PARA>
<PARA> In the past we have seen coalition governments and the present Hawke Government use those powers. The Fraser Government used its external affairs powers to prevent sand mining on Fraser Island and, through the operation of that power, effectively stopped a damaging operation on an environmentally sensitive island until such time as, more recently, the present Government saw fit to move towards World Heritage status for the island. It is fair to comment that it seems most unlikely, given what we have heard from the Federal Opposition, that in 1991 it would move down the same road and use those powers in the way in which Prime Minister Fraser was prepared to use them. </PARA>
<PARA> In the case of the Hawke Government we have seen protection of the south- western region of Tasmania, the Franklin River area. It is interesting to note and to put on record that that was done not only under the exercise of the external affairs powers but also involved the use of section 51(xx) of the corporations' powers under the Constitution. That decision, which was challenged in the High Court and upheld, rested on the use of both powers. </PARA>
<PARA> I notice that Minister Richardson is in the chamber and will be speaking shortly on this matter. He will know that section 5 of his own ozone protection legislation drew specifically on the use of the corporations' powers. So far as I am aware, not only has there been no challenge to that provision, but also there has not even been a suggestion that the law may be challenged. We have seen the use of those powers by governments of both major political parties. </PARA>
<PARA> What do we have now? We now have every indication of a very considerable backdown by the Federal Government and a deferral to the States of many of those powers. I have with me a copy of discussion draft 4 of the Intergovernmental Agreement on the Environment. I understand that this is the document to which the Federal Government and the States are now working. We find in paragraph 3.1.2 (iii) under `Commonwealth responsibilities' that the Commonwealth is specifically agreeing to:</PARA>
<PARA>consult with and . . . secure the agreement of the States and Territories at First Minister level prior to entering into any international commitments which impose costs or obligations on the States or Territories. </PARA>
<PARA>In parenthesis in that paragraph, preceding the phrase about securing agreement, we see the words `use its best endeavours to'. It indicates in my mind that the Federal Government is prepared to not enter into any of those international agreements if a State or Territory does not agree. The words in parenthesis beg the question. What happens if the `best endeavours' fail to secure an agreement? The implication from the rest of the document is fairly clear that in those circumstances the agreement would not be entered into. I draw attention to paragraph 3.1.4 which says:</PARA>
<PARA>When ratifying any international agreement on environmental matters, the Commonwealth will include in the instrument of ratification a statement on the manner in which the obligations incurred shall be implemented in Australia. This statement will be consistent with the roles and responsibilities established pursuant to this agreement and may only be made following consultation with the States and Territories at First Minister level . . . </PARA>
<PARA>In other words, this is an overriding condition written into this draft agreement between the Commonwealth and the States. Further on, under the heading `Commonwealth Interests: Vertical Cooperation', paragraph 3.3.2 states:</PARA>
<PARA>The interests of the Commonwealth in environmental matters are constituted by-</PARA>
<PARA>this set of definitions defines what shall be the Commonwealth interest in environmental matters-</PARA>
<PARA>(iv) matters where the relevant States or Territories agree that there is a national interest . . .</PARA>
<PARA>In other words, if the States and Territories do not agree that a matter is in the national interest, then, by definition under this section, it is not a matter for Commonwealth interest. It continues:</PARA>
<PARA>(v) matters which the Commonwealth and a majority of the States agree are matters of national interest . . . </PARA>
<PARA>Quite clearly, that states that, if a majority of the States do not agree, the Commonwealth essentially has its hands tied by the intergovernmental agreement on the environment which is under discussion. </PARA>
<PARA> The Democrats are vitally concerned that, at a time when there is need for an even more positive, more deliberate and more far-reaching exercise of Commonwealth powers to protect the environment in all those areas I have mentioned, at a time when the Australian public is more environmentally aware than it has been at any time in the history of this country, at a time when the majority of Australians want the Federal Government to move more forcefully and more deliberately in this area-precisely at this time-it seems that the Federal Government is walking away from its responsibilities. </PARA>
<PARA> It seems that the Government is prepared to accept the lowest standards from the States in terms of environmental protection and to pass onto the States very considerable costs in relation to the protection of the environment when a State wants to pick up those issues. We call on the Federal Government to reverse its stand and to move strongly to exercise those constitutional powers, which undoubtedly it possesses. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1391" SPEAKER="Baume Sen M.E." NAMEID="LE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator MICHAEL BAUME</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(11.23 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Pursuant to contingent notice and on behalf of the Opposition, I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent me moving an amendment to the urgency motion moved by the Acting Leader of the Australian Democrats. </PARA>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative.</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator MICHAEL BAUME</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Omit all words after ``Federal Government to'', substitute ``understand the critical need in Australia for sustainable development subject to appropriate Commonwealth and State environmental safeguards.''. </PARA>
<PARA>I have moved that amendment because there is a need for reality in the environmental debate. Regrettably, the Australian Democrats have yet to acknowledge this. This puts at risk Australia's capacity to undertake the sort of environmental protection which can come only from a society with the financial ability to sustain the very real costs of environmental protection. </PARA>
<PARA> The best ally of environmental degradation is poverty-just look at Ethiopia. A society which is sufficiently vibrant, healthy and strong has the best prospects of environmental protection; it is able to afford the costs of conservation. Land degradation is the greatest individual cause of environmental breakdown in Australia. Australian farmers are less likely to protect, and less capable of protecting, the land when they are going broke, as they are now, than when they are economically viable. It is a simplistic nonsense to say that there is an inevitable and total conflict between developing and protecting the environment. </PARA>
<PARA> Mr Kerin, the Treasurer, put his finger on it very well. I hope that the Government will recognise that my amendment is worthy of its support because Mr Kerin certainly supports this view. When speaking with people who call for negative economic growth as the only path to ecological survival, such as the Australian Democrats, Mr Kerin said:</PARA>
<PARA>That is acceptable if you happen to be fabulously wealthy, landed and indifferent to the fate and future of those who are not. </PARA>
<PARA> It is not acceptable if you happen to be a subsistence peasant in the Third World, a bonded labourer without access to clean drinking water or fuel, wood or proper housing or health care or clothing, or an unemployed factory hand in the suburbs of Melbourne or Sydney. </PARA>
<PARA>And we have quite a few of them at the moment-thanks to the Government's engineered recession. The fact is that there is no inevitable conflict between a growing and healthy economy and preservation of the environment. This nation should be looking at the whole concept of sustainable development. </PARA>
<PARA> We wish to amend this urgency motion so that the Federal Government understands the critical need for sustainable development subject to appropriate State and Commonwealth environmental safeguards. There is no doubt that some Government members understand that need. I have just quoted one of them-Mr Kerin. </PARA>
<PARA> I admit that we are at some loss to understand the Government's total policy. In the last two days Mrs Kelly, the Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories, has been actively seeking to undermine the Government's policy as outlined by the Prime Minister (Mr Hawke) of cooperation with the States. What is the Government's policy? Is it, as Mrs Kelly says, crass politics? Will it be sustainable? Is it likely to be changed if Mr Keating becomes the leader? Of course, Mr Keating is being run out of the stable by Senator Richardson. Will Mr Keating be the Green alternative? Is he wearing the Green colours on this track?</PARA>
<PARA> It is vital that the Australian people know exactly what the Government's policy will be. Is it the one being undermined by Mrs Kelly or is it the Prime Minister's? Will we see this cooperative, positive development-which certainly the Opposition supports-of relationships between the States and the Commonwealth so that ground rules can be established, and so that we can have sustainable development and an honest, coherent and understandable approach to development which protects the environment? We must have appropriate environmental safeguards-and the only way we can get them is through cooperation with the States. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1392" SPEAKER="Calvert Sen P.H." NAMEID="5F4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator CALVERT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(11.28 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I support my colleague Senator Michael Baume. I am pleased to see that we have moved this amendment to put some commonsense back into the urgency motion moved by the Australian Democrats. Senator Baume summed it up when he talked about the reality, which is that there are currently over one million people out of work in Australia; that we have balance of payments problems approaching $10m to $20m; and that we have an international debt of $140 billion-and that continues to rise. The Government has been dithering with this sustainable development and its resource legislation. It seems to have lost its leadership and it is certainly not doing the country any good.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I remember very well before the last election the then Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories, Senator Richardson, running around the country touting himself as the only option in terms of environmental management. I think that he sucked in the Australian Conservation Foundation. But where are we today? We are still arguing and the country is still divided over these types of issues. Today, we have the Australian Democrats coming out and saying that they want the Federal Government to more widely exercise its constitutional powers. </PARA>
<PARA> Madam Acting Deputy President, as a Tasmanian I can tell you of the effect of those powers and their effectiveness in Tasmania. We are virtually a bankrupt State, and have been ever since Senator Gareth Evans sent spy flights to check out what was going on. As a result of the stopping of sensible development in Tasmania, we have a State that is divided. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Forestry Commission owes $400m.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator Calvert</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Yes. I am talking about Senator Coulter, who is a conservationist, and his ideas about clean air and all the rest of it. The result of those spy flights and kowtowing to the Green movement in Tasmania is that we have had a fossil fuel burning generator puffing out all the emissions about which Senator Coulter complains every day. It is costing Tasmanian taxpayers and consumers heaps of money, all because we have closed down some of the projects that the Hydro Electric Commission wanted to go ahead with.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I am sure that most people would know that, because of the dithering that has been going on and all the uncertainty, we have lost a very good opportunity in the Wesley Vale mill, which Senator Button was supporting so strongly. That issue has been going on and on; it is like Blue Hills. We have ended up with a position now where any developer that wanted to support APPM in that project would have second thoughts. In fact, Noranda has already made that point quite clear. </PARA>
<PARA> When a State or country is falling upon hard times, as Australia and Tasmania are-Tasmania has the highest unemployment rate in the country and our youth unemployment figures are standing at 40 per cent-we have to take a good hard look at our States and the economy and go back to doing the things that we do best. Tasmania has always done best in agriculture, forestry, mining and tourism. Forestry and mining have absolutely had the stuffing kicked out of them because of the uncertainty. They are not just my words. One only has to talk to representatives of the industry. If we look at the mining industry in Tasmania, we can see that Tasmania's mineral production exceeded $1 billion last year for the first time. The industry employs about 20,000 Tasmanians. The Tasmanian Chamber of Mines report states:</PARA>
<PARA>Mixed and often negative signals have been sent to industry by this Government on issues such as land use, energy pricing, development rules and environmental regulation. These have combined to make investors feel at best, uncertain or at worst, unwelcome.</PARA>
<PARA>The report also states:</PARA>
<PARA>Exploration activity has continued its long term decline. This decline in exploration effort will impact directly on the industry's long term ability to sustain itself.</PARA>
<PARA>My own State of Tasmania is in such a mess at the moment because of the sorts of Federal controls we have had in the past and the uncertainties that have been caused by the Federal Government choosing to exercise its constitutional powers, for example, when an election is coming up and it needs to support the Green movement. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1393" SPEAKER="Macdonald Sen I.D." NAMEID="YW4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator MACDONALD</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Queensland)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(11.34 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The refusal to log forests, the failure to approve pulp mill guidelines, the inability to mine rare earths and other pressing controversies will add to the overall bill for environmental consciousness. The Australian Democrats seem to be incapable of learning that we cannot completely protect or preserve everything.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> There is no doubt, and no-one would argue, about protecting the environment. Certainly, the Democrats do not have any monopoly on the wish and the desire to protect the environment; we all do. Even the ALP does. It makes a vote winning election gimmick out of it but I suspect that deep down a few of its members genuinely want to protect the environment. </PARA>
<PARA> The proposal by the Democrats in this motion is not what is needed. We do not need the Commonwealth to more widely exercise its constitutional powers to protect the environment. We need the Government more responsibly to exercise those powers so that we do not have the sorts of decisions that are made in relation to Coronation Hill, where the environment was really a very minor part of the consideration. It was a decision that could have meant so much to Australia's economy, so much to the one million people who are unemployed. There will be more people unemployed because of the irresponsible use by this Government-this Federal Government, this central Government-of its environmental and other powers. </PARA>
<PARA> I am amused at some of the things that Senator Coulter talked about. As I understand what he said in his speech, he was criticising the Queensland Government, the Western Australian Government and the Tasmanian Government for looking at coal-fired power stations. Is that what Senator Coulter was doing? I hope I did not get him wrong on that?</PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;And Queensland with Tully Millstream.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator MACDONALD</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;And Queensland with the coal-fired power station. I tell Senator Coulter that he is about to become the victim of a very clever trap. There are a lot of people who are now against the Tully Millstream. Does Senator Coulter know why? Because there are enormous amounts of coal in Queensland and they want to use the coal. They do not want to go to Tully Millstream for power because they want to burn all that coal and fix up the ozone layer and whatever else it does. Senator Coulter is a pawn in that. He is being trapped into supporting that by opposing Tully Millstream.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Tully Millstream is what this country needs to get its power from resources there cheaply, economically and in an environmentally sound manner. The Queensland Electricity Commission has spent millions of dollars doing an environmental impact survey into that. The conservationists are against it. Have any of those conservationists from CAFNEC or the groups in the north Queensland areas ever gone through, ever accepted QEC's offer to look at the scheme, to find out what it is about, to look at the environmental reports and to see that there is no problem with that proposal environmentally?</PARA>
<PARA> As far as World Heritage listing goes, there will be more areas given by the QEC into the wet tropics World Heritage area. It is going to increase the area in that particular region. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You don't understand.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator MACDONALD</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Senator Coulter can say that we do not understand. He will come back to me, as will Senator Kernot, with the questions: what about wind power? What about solar power? If Senator Coulter can convince me that those projects are economically sustainable, I will be all for them. I agree with wind power; I agree with solar power. But we have to be able to do it economically. Hydro power is as pure and as good to the environment as water is, but it just does not add up.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I ask Senator Coulter to get Senator Kernot to support me in this. When the Standing Committee on Transport, Communications and Infrastructure finishes its current inquiry into satellite broadcasting, I will propose-Senator Coulter can ask Senator Kernot to assist me-that the Committee look into wind, solar, gas, methane and coal power. We will have an inquiry to see whether they are economically sustainable. If they are, I am with Senator Coulter. But they are not. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You are prejudging it now, are you?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator MACDONALD</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Let us have the inquiry. We cannot just dismiss the one million people who are unemployed as a result of this Government's policies. It is also a result of the fact that people like Senator Coulter refuse to have proper development in this country. They refuse it and throw more and more people on the scrap heap for fairytale ideas that come from the bottom of the garden. They do not understand what it does. That is the reason why we must support the amendment. (Time expired)</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1394" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="SOCIAL SECURITY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Minister for Social Security)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(11.39 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;The Government will be opposing both the urgency motion moved by Senator Coulter and the amendment moved by Senator Baume. In doing so, I would like to congratulate Senator Coulter for at least putting the debate over the last few days into proper perspective. The debate ought to be about the substance of the issue. It certainly has not been.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The urgency motion talks about the Federal Government using its powers more widely so as to more effectively and comprehensively protect the Australian environment. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It should be more wisely, not more widely.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I think that, in terms of the breadth of division of the last few years and in its substance, the national Government has used its powers very widely and, I would like to say, very wisely. It may be good enough for Senator Macdonald to allege that no-one in the Labor Party might care and that it was all done as some sort of stunt but, whatever else the Labor Party has or has not done in the course of the last few years, I shall look back with great pride at a number of environmental decisions, particularly in relation to the wet tropics and Tasmania. Those decisions were taken by the Commonwealth despite the objection of the States.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Where will you find the wet tropics in Tasmania?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I said `the wet tropics and Tasmania'. Senator Macdonald did not hear me properly. While I was still the relevant Minister and there was no Federal-State process, on a number of occasions in the Senate I made it clear-and I am sure that Senator Coulter will recall this-that in the future the Commonwealth would much prefer, for example in World Heritage nominations, to have the agreement of the States. That made simply good sense. In December 1988, I attended in Brazil a meeting of the World Heritage Committee and witnessed the spectacle of State Ministers running through delegates, putting a different view to the Commonwealth and, in fact, attempting to gravely distort the debate. While that could be overcome in terms of a decision being taken, it was certainly over time going to bring Australia's position into some disrepute.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> In my view, that was not sustainable-to use a word that has arisen quite a few times during this debate. I made it clear then that from now on this Government would attempt to get the agreement of the States. For the next nomination that was then proposed, which related to Shark Bay in Western Australia, that process began while I was the relevant Minister and continued until the position was reached where the Government could finally get the Western Australian Government to agree. The point is that what is happening now in this process with the States is no real change from what I said before. It does not mean that the Commonwealth will walk away from the exercise of its power when that is necessary, even if that is to override a State. </PARA>
<PARA> I shall go through a number of points. Firstly, Senator Coulter is relying on a document that was prepared in April largely by State officials. That fourth draft was prepared on the basis that the States and the Commonwealth would go away to discuss it, which is what occurred, and that they would reconvene in August to go over that draft. In the interim, the Commonwealth very substantially redrafted that fourth draft and did not accept much of what it contained because in far too big a way it represented a diminution of the Commonwealth's role, responsibility and power. Therefore, the Commonwealth changed the whole structure of that document. I think that honourable senators will find that the States have pretty well accepted the contents of that redraft. I do not believe that they will find too much to concern themselves about in the final draft when it appears. Obviously, today I cannot say what the final draft will contain, because it is still a matter for negotiation. </PARA>
<PARA> Inherent in Mrs Kelly's approach to these negotiations with the States has been the view that we had to have proper national standards. Senator Coulter used the phrase, `lowest common denominator', suggesting that in some way any one State with an unacceptable view of the environment would be able to exercise some sort of veto power. Even though I do not think he expressed it in those words, I do not think that is an unreasonable interpretation of what he said. </PARA>
<PARA> If that is to suggest that a State with a particularly poor environmental record such as New South Wales would be able to veto a Commonwealth decision, that is simply not right. Mrs Kelly has been at pains to point out that the Commonwealth will be looking towards majority decisions and not allowing one or two States to say, `We won't cop this; therefore, the process is not on'. There has to be a real agreement and it will not be, cannot be, a lowest common denominator driven agreement. </PARA>
<PARA> On how those things are to be addressed, in all of these intergovernmental negotiations the Commonwealth is going through a very wide range of issues in looking for those national standards. I can quote air quality, water quality, noise, contaminated sites, hazardous wastes, motor vehicle emissions-to use a point which Senator Coulter stressed during his contribution-and waste minimisation; and the ecologically sustainable development groups are looking at the greenhouse issues to which Senator Coulter referred. </PARA>
<PARA> I note, of course, that in the amendment moved by Senator Michael Baume there is no reference to ecologically sustainable development, just sustainable development. All honourable senators know what that means when it comes from the Opposition. When the Opposition talks about sustainable development, it talks merely about the capacity of either the timber industry or the mining industry to have unfettered access to any area it likes. That has always been the Opposition's position and will remain so. It is not the Government's position, nor is the Government moving towards it during these negotiations. </PARA>
<PARA> Both the Prime Minister and the Minister have made it clear that the Government is prepared to use its constitutional powers to protect the environment, and that will not stop. We will not resile from that position in the course of these negotiations with the States. In relation to resource security, which has obviously been a real point of contention with the environment movement, no approval will be given until the Commonwealth is satisfied with environmental standards. We will also continue to use our powers up-front where necessary. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Michael Baume" NAMEID="LE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator Michael Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;We will accept your addendum to our motion to make it `ecologically' if you like. Would you like that?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I would like the Opposition to start using the term `ecologically sustainable development'. I would be happy to grant Senator Baume leave to change his amendment to that effect, because that would be a sign that the Opposition is beginning to understand. But I will get to the reasons why I oppose the amendment in any event in a moment.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Michael Baume" NAMEID="LE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator Michael Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I see. That was just a debating point.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;No, it is not a debating point; it is a very substantive point. However, there is another substantive point which overrides it.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Michael Baume" NAMEID="LE4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator Michael Baume</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;In that case, if it would encourage you to support the amendment, we will add it in happily.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I would like the Opposition to add it in because, as I said, the Opposition has never talked about `ecologically sustainable development'. The Opposition's amendment uses the word `understand'-the need for the Government to understand the importance of it. It is the Labor Party which brought up the need for that sort of development in this country, which put it on the agenda for political debate and which began all of those groups discussing it. We are the ones who kicked off a debate on that sort of development in Australia.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> So we do not need to understand it; we always did. If the Opposition were to amend its motion to read `the need for the Opposition to understand it' we would be very happy to support it, as would the Democrats. It would go through here unanimously and we would be delighted. I can give the Opposition the further undertaking that it will get leave to do that if it seeks to do it. However, I suspect it will be a long and unhappy wait for most of us if we seek to wait for the Opposition to wake up on any of those points. </PARA>
<PARA> It was in some of the speeches of Opposition senators that the game, to some extent, was given away. We had Senator Macdonald's obsession with Tully-Millstream. That was quite an issue way back even in 1988, but certainly by 1989 it was a big issue in Queensland. </PARA>
<PARA> As the Minister, I did go up to inspect the Queensland Electricity Commission's plans for the protection of two species. I do not recall their names. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;But you support the project, don't you?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Just hang on, Senator Macdonald. I said that the Commonwealth would support the project's going ahead but with a very big proviso that the need for the power was demonstrated. There has been an examination of this. But I do not believe that the Commonwealth is yet in possession of anything like the information that would be required for it to come to the conclusion that there had been a demonstration of the need for this power.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Macdonald" NAMEID="YW4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;So there are no environmental problems with it?</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It is ridiculous to say that there are no environmental problems with a very big hydro-electric dam which must inundate a World Heritage area. That makes it a big problem. But if there is a demonstrated need for power, the World Heritage Convention itself allows for acts of that kind.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> So there is an environmental problem which does not go away. As someone who has been there and looked at what the Queensland Electricity Commission has been intent upon doing, I would have to say that it has made a very real attempt in respect of those two species and I commend it for its efforts. Having commended the Commission, it does not mean, however, that we support the project. So far as the Commonwealth is concerned, that will depend entirely on a proper examination of the need for the power. </PARA>
<PARA> We must all remember that the need for extra power will diminish in Australia over the course of the next decade. There will be in place in this country a number of savings in the area of energy which will transform the way in which we, as a nation, think about energy issues. </PARA>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It would save a lot of money and provide employment too.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It will provide a lot of employment and the prospects for savings are massive. That is why that Tasman Institute report of a week or two ago is so much nonsense. That is something else that we have to debate in the chamber at another time. I was particularly annoyed by it.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Coulter" NAMEID="TF4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;You are on.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Good. I hope we can. In the last couple of moments left to me, I turn to some of the points raised by the Opposition. First, Senator Michael Baume said to us that there was a need for reality in the environment debate. If there was, we would not be looking to Senator Baume or the Opposition to give us any of it. Over the last four or five years the Opposition has demonstrated that it has a complete inability ever to come to grips with what the environmental debate is about. I think Senator Calvert gave us a very good demonstration of that when he referred to Wesley Vale. Access Economics has taught the Liberal Party to raise at every opportunity the subject of Wesley Vale, as if, in some way, this was a great failing by the Commonwealth in terms of environmental policy.</PARA></TALK.START>
<INTERJECT CHAIR="0" SPEAKER="Senator Watson" NAMEID="VJ4">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VJ4">Senator Watson</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It was.</PARA></TALK.START>
</INTERJECT>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;It just was not. It was a great failing in the first instance by the then Premier, Robin Gray, to come up with a decent set of environmental standards; a huge failure which we were able to overcome in a flash. But we had to deal with a company which was facing an inquiry in Canada. Although Noranda could not afford to agree with the standards that we announced, it could agree later on once much higher standards had been imposed upon it by the Canadian Government.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The Opposition talks about the reasons for the mess in Tasmania. I hope that by now all Tasmanians understand that the reason for the mess in Tasmania was the complete inability by the then Premier, Robin Gray, to come to grips with fiscal policy. He attempted to spend, spend and spend to hide the inadequacies of his Government. Unfortunately, that has caught up with every Tasmanian and every Tasmanian has to bear the burden of those years of profligate waste. Profligate waste is typical of Opposition efforts in this regard. </PARA>
<PARA> All we had from Senator Macdonald was again an obsession with one project-we were told about a refusal to log forests, an inability to mine rare earths, et cetera. What that really amounts to is a statement of where the Opposition stands in this debate. Sustainable development to the Opposition means unfettered access to any extractive industry to any part of Australia and that is something we will not wear. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1397" SPEAKER="Baume Sen M.E." NAMEID="LE4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="NSW">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LE4">Senator MICHAEL BAUME</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-I move:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That my amendment be amended to read as follows:</PARA>
<PARA> Omit all words after ``Federal Government to'', substitute ``confirm the critical need in Australia for ecologically sustainable development subject to appropriate Commonwealth and State environmental safeguards.''. </PARA>
<PARA>By way of a very brief explanation, I take the point of the Minister for Social Security (Senator Richardson) that it would be difficult for the Government to support an amendment outlining the need for the Government to understand, the inference being that it does not at present understand. Whether that is so is a matter that we could debate. </PARA>
<PARA> My interest in this matter is seeing the position confirmed that there is a critical need in Australia for sustainable development, subject to appropriate Commonwealth and State environmental safeguards, which I understand to be the formal position of the Prime Minister (Mr Hawke) and the Government, and a position which I also understand is being undermined by Mrs Kelly in her private meeting with environmentalists, which is now a matter of public concern. Having met the Government's objections, I now ask that the Government support our amendment, as amended. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1398" SPEAKER="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F." NAMEID="4E4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" MINISTERIAL="SOCIAL SECURITY" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="4E4">Senator RICHARDSON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Minister for Social Security)</ROLE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;by leave-On behalf of the Government, I have no difficulty in saying that we can support an amendment that confirms the critical need in Australia for ecologically sustainable development subject to appropriate environmental safeguards. That is fine. The trouble is that in this place we will never agree with the definition of `appropriate'. That is not up for debate. Appropriateness is in the mind of the beholder. As far as the Government is concerned, we can agree with that.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1398" SPEAKER="Coulter Sen J.R." NAMEID="TF4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator COULTER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(South Australia-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Acting Leader of the Australian Democrats)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(11.58 a.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;in reply-We would oppose this because, quite clearly, the wording indicates that the Opposition still does not understand that ecologically sustainable development does not need to be subject to anything. That will underpin the whole economy from now until indefinitely into the future. It should not be made subject to something; environmental safeguards are, in fact, intrinsic to ecological sustainability so the motion really is a tautology. It shows lack of understanding on the part of the Opposition and we would have to oppose both amendments and stay with the original urgency motion.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
<PARA> Amendment, as amended, agreed to. </PARA>
<PARA> Motion, as amended, agreed to. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Committee" PAGE="1398"><TITLE>COMMITTEES</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1398">
<TITLE>Scrutiny of Bills Committee</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1398">
<TITLE>Report</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1398" SPEAKER="Faulkner Sen J.P." NAMEID="5K4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NSW" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME><ELECTORATE>(New South Wales)</ELECTORATE></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On behalf of Senator Cooney, I present the fourteenth report of 1991 of the Standing Committee for the Scrutiny of Bills.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Ordered that the report be printed. </PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5K4">Senator FAULKNER</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I also lay on the table Scrutiny of Bills Alert Digest No. 15 dated 11 September 1991.</PARA></TALK.START>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1398">
<TITLE>Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs</TITLE>
<DEBATE.SUB2 PAGE="1398">
<TITLE>Extension of Time to Report</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA> Motion (by Senator Faulkner, for Senator Cooney) agreed to:</PARA>
<PARA> That the time for the presentation of the report of the Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs on mergers, monopolies and acquisitions under the Trade Practices Act be extended to 1 December 1991.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE.SUB2></DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Adjournment" PAGE="1398"><TITLE>ADJOURNMENT</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><INTERJECT CHAIR="1" SPEAKER="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT" NAMEID="10000">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="10000">The DEPUTY PRESIDENT</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;Order! Before I put the question for the adjournment, I advise honourable senators that Estimates Committee A will meet in Committee Room 2S1, Estimates Committee B will meet in the Main Committee Room, and Estimates Committee C will meet in 2S3 commencing at 1.30 p.m. Estimates Committee A will be televised on channel 2 and Estimates Committee B will be televised on channel 22. It being 12 noon, I put the question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> That the Senate do now adjourn.</PARA>
</INTERJECT>
</PROCTEXT>
<DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1398">
<TITLE>Taxation</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1398" SPEAKER="Watson Sen J.O.W." NAMEID="VJ4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VJ4">Senator WATSON</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12 noon)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;On 25 June this year, the Commissioner of Taxation stated that the modern Australian Taxation Office, under self-assessment, aimed to become `an organisation of people equipped, trained and committed to helping taxpayers and their clients carry out their responsibilities under the law'. He went on to state that by becoming such an organisation the Office hoped to maximise voluntary compliance amongst taxpayers. These are notions which I fully support.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> In order to help the Australian Taxation Office become an organisation committed to helping taxpayers to carry out their responsibilities under the law, the Treasury, through its administration of the Office, has as one of its income tax subprograms a taxpayer assistance group. Two of the objectives of this group are to `conduct effective publicity campaigns to educate taxpayers and other clients by communicating changes to tax law and administration to improve the level of voluntary compliance' and to `publish in a timely manner, technical advice and non-technical information to educate taxpayers.' Again, these are concepts and objectives which we all fully endorse. </PARA>
<PARA> Today I wish to bring to the attention of the Senate particular aspects of the ATO's publicity campaign. A campaign of fear and certain misinformation is being promoted which is not in line with the stated aims and objectives of the Australian Taxation Office's client assistance group. In fact, it is not in line with everyday normal business practice. </PARA>
<PARA> There are a number of aspects which I wish to raise. To begin, I wish to highlight the ATO's handling of the case of the illegal immigrant portrayed in media release No. 20 of 30 April 1991. The release was headed `Heavy Penalties Follow Misuse of Tax File Numbers'. I seek leave to have this press release incorporated in Hansard. </PARA>
<PARA> Leave granted. </PARA>
<PARA> The release read as follows-</PARA>
<PARA> The Commissioner of Taxation, Mr Trevor Boucher, said that today's decision in a Sydney court indicates that mechanisms are in place to ensure tax file numbers retain their high integrity. </PARA>
<PARA> The case involved an illegal immigrant who lodged two tax returns. He used his own name and tax file number on one return but omitted the income he earned in the name of a friend. He also included income he earned on a return lodged in this friend's name. </PARA>
<PARA> This meant he understated his income and took advantage of the tax free threshold twice, despite the fact that the threshold is not available to non-residents. </PARA>
<PARA> The magistrate found the defendant guilty of 9 charges, including using another person's tax file number, using a false identity in the course of his employment and making a false and misleading statement in a tax return. He was sentenced to 6 months imprisonment and fines totalling $9186. These fines included an order to pay the Commissioner 200% of the tax avoided in addition to the tax payable due to the understated income. </PARA>
<PARA> `The heavy penalties handed down in this case show that it is simply not worth trying to misuse tax file numbers for personal gain', said Mr Boucher. </PARA>
<PARA> `The new tax file number arrangements were introduced to fight tax evasion. Any anti-evasion procedures will inevitably challenge some people to try and beat the system. </PARA>
<PARA> In designing our systems and work practices we have looked at the potential for tax file numbers to be used for improper purposes and have guarded against possible fraud. </PARA>
<PARA> We trust our staff who administer the system. Our organisation relies on our people to safeguard the interests of all Australians. To further protect the integrity of the tax file number system, we have built in strict safeguards such as reconciliations, computer access control and quality assurance procedures', added Mr Boucher. </PARA>
<PARA> `The introduction of proof of identity measures, strict privacy guidelines and severe penalties for improperly using tax file numbers further secures the system', concluded Mr Boucher. </PARA>
<PARA>Canberra</PARA>
<PARA>30 April 1991</PARA>
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="VJ4">Senator WATSON</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I thank the Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer (Senator McMullan). The Senate may be thinking, `Why bring up a media release from 30 April?'. It is because the media release is still being used as the basis of articles being written about this matter. In the last three weeks a regular article written by a well-known tax expert in Australia has been published in two popular dailies-the Examiner and the Mercury. This particular expert also writes for other mainland papers. However, the press release of 30 April gives, unfortunately, the wrong information. The ATO knows this but has done nothing to correct what has happened.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> The ATO has preferred to have incorrect punitive aspects of not complying with the Income Tax Assessment Act published and disseminated. Consequently, an incorrect aura of fear of what could happen to everyday taxpayers has developed. This press release of 30 April gives the impression that the misuse of the tax file number will result in heavy penalties. There are penalties for the misuse of the tax file number, as there should be, but they are not in accordance with those given in that press release. </PARA>
<PARA> Briefly the facts, as per the Tax Office release-I emphasise that they are facts `as per the Tax Office release'-involve an illegal immigrant who lodged two returns. According to the release, he used his own name and tax file number on one return, but omitted the income he earned in the name of a friend. He also included income he earned on a return lodged in his friend's name. This meant that he understated his income and took advantage of the tax-free threshold twice, despite the fact that the threshold is not available to non-residents, which illegal immigrants are. </PARA>
<PARA> The release then went on to state that the magistrate found the defendant guilty of nine charges, including using another person's tax file number, using a false identity in the course of his employment and making a false and misleading statement in a tax return. He was sentenced to six months imprisonment and ordered to pay fines totalling $9,186. These fines included an order to pay the Commissioner of Taxation 200 per cent of the tax avoided in addition to the tax payable due to the understated income. </PARA>
<PARA> The same press release records Mr Boucher, representing the Australian Taxation Office, saying:</PARA>
<PARA>The heavy penalties handed down in this case show that it is simply not worth trying to misuse the tax file numbers for personal gain. </PARA>
<PARA>Mr Peter Roach in a recent article, `A Taxing Interpretation', in the August edition of the Charter magazine, expressed amazement that an offence against a relatively new taxation legislation provision could be thought to warrant so great a penalty as imprisonment for a term of six months. </PARA>
<PARA> Consequently, the matter was further investigated by Mr Peter Roach who, by the way, is a former senior member of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal. He contacted the Australian Taxation Office, which directed him to the officer responsible for the case. According to Mr Peter Roach's article, the information thus obtained should give us all cause for concern. </PARA>
<PARA> The sentence for imprisonment referred to in the media release of 30 April 1991 had nothing to do with a tax file number offence or any other taxation offence. The sentence for imprisonment arose out of the wrongdoer's status as an illegal immigrant, an offence or offences for which he had been dealt with at the same time. That explains the reference in the press release to the offender's being an illegal immigrant-something which would seem to have no relationship to the tax offences or their seriousness. But it does not explain why the press release has been expressed in the way in which it has. </PARA>
<PARA> Mr Peter Roach, believing that an error had been honestly made and that the Commissioner would correct it once he had been informed of the facts, wrote to the Commissioner. The reply that came to hand was sufficient to cause such concern that it became the base of the article which I am referring to today. This article quotes the Commissioner's reply, and I would like to comment on a number of the statements quoted. Firstly, the Commissioner states:</PARA>
<PARA>I agree that the statement of facts contained in the media release . . . could be construed as implying the defendant received a prison sentence for tax offences. </PARA>
<PARA>I do not know how else this would be construed. The Tasmanian newspaper articles I referred to at the beginning of my speech were headed `Tax Evaders Beware' and quoted directly the relevant section from the Australian Taxation Office release, which states:</PARA>
<PARA>The magistrate found the defendant guilty of 9 charges, including using another person's tax file number, using a false identity in the course of his employment and making a false and misleading statement in a tax return. He was sentenced to 6 months imprisonment and fines totally $9186. </PARA>
<PARA>The press release does not imply that it `could be' misconstrued. This is more than semantics. The press release states that because of the misuse of the tax file number, amongst other misdemeanours, the man was imprisoned. There is no question about this. But that is not all. The Tax Commissioner in his letter back to Mr Peter Roach says:</PARA>
<PARA>The release was written on the basis of information supplied to our National Office by staff who attended the court hearing. The release was then referred back to staff to check the facts for accuracy before it was issued. </PARA>
<PARA>Unfortunately, in this case, this procedure was not sufficient to ensure that the release was unambiguous. </PARA>
<PARA>The release was not ambiguous. The Commissioner should have conceded that the press release was wrong and issued a statement to this effect. Rather, the public was left with the impression that misuse of the tax file number could lead to six months imprisonment and a 200 per cent fine. In reply to this accusation, the Commissioner states:</PARA>
<PARA>Nevertheless, I do not believe the comments attributed to the Commissioner of Taxation are seriously misleading. </PARA>
<PARA>Further, the Commissioner states:</PARA>
<PARA>To my knowledge our media release did not receive any significant coverage. </PARA>
<PARA>I have already noted that in Tasmania the press release did receive wide coverage and, according to Peter Roach, the information that a prison sentence and misuse of the tax file number are linked has been used by a major publisher here and on the mainland. Therefore, a retraction of the original release is warranted and also necessary. Those who commit tax offences do warrant prosecution and enforcement is necessary. But let us have the correct facts. The punishment deserves to fit the crime. </PARA>
<PARA> This is not the only area where the ATO has implied more than is necessary in its press releases or comments. Let us take the auditing of Australia's top 100 companies. Our Tax Commissioner has been quoted as saying that the majority of Australia's top 100 companies have not paid enough tax for a number of years, that the top 100 companies have revealed significant understatements of tax. </PARA>
<PARA> When asked by journalists whether this was tantamount to accusing the companies of cheating, this was denied. However, little was made of the fact that the audits revealed no cases of tax avoidance as under part IVA of the Income Tax Assessment Act. Most issues covered by the large case audits were technical disputes. The amounts collected by the Tax Office represented grey areas in the law-the same areas which have been in dispute between the Tax Office and large companies for many years because the tax laws have contained a great deal of uncertainty. Before self-assessment, the grey areas in the laws were identified through assessing procedures and ATO inquiries, but now this is the responsibility of the companies and they have to know the law as they, not the ATO, determine their tax liabilities; yet it is the Taxation Office or the Commissioner who determines the interpretation of the law through his rulings and discretions. As a result, a catch 22 situation exists.</PARA>
<PARA> The editorial in the Australian of 1 July summarises this situation aptly. It states:</PARA>
<PARA>In the case of the top 100 companies, the extent of their crime seems to have been an over-zealous attempt to minimise tax, compounded by the confusion of self assessment according to highly complex tax laws. </PARA>
<PARA> Mr Boucher (has) eschewed an air of sanctimoniousness when alleging these abuses, if that is what they are. Self-righteousness will have to wait until there is a genuine attempt to simplify the tax laws, and embody them in a spirit of public service.</PARA>
<PARA>However, the overall result in the publicity realm, which concerns me, is that Australia's top 100 companies have been tainted by the ATO as possible cheats. The implication is there, no matter what the Commissioner says. As the article in the Australian of 1 July states, `The taxman's zeal comes at a price'. According to Bob Bryant of the Corporate Tax Association, who was quoted in yesterday's Australian Financial Review, this `vigorous' campaign of auditing `has led to unprecedented hostilities'. According to the article, Mr Bryant said:</PARA>
<PARA> Relationships between major companies and the ATO has suffered. These taxpayers are more wary of the commissioner today and are less inclined to take him at his word.</PARA>
<PARA>These are unfortunate comments indeed and are worth drawing to the attention of the Senate. Therefore, I am concerned that the Australian Taxation Office has misused its publicity machine. A big brother attitude as a consequence of disseminating and promoting fear based on incorrect facts seems to become part of that pattern. This should not be so. Comments and releases from the Australian Taxation Office should always err on the side of honesty and correctness. A campaign of fear and misinformation should have no part in `its effective publicity campaign to educate taxpayers and other clients'. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1402">
<TITLE>Performing Animals: Referendum</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1402" SPEAKER="Calvert Sen P.H." NAMEID="5F4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator CALVERT</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Tasmania)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.14 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I will be brief. I just wish to raise a matter that came to my attention in the last day or so. Honourable senators may or may not be aware that on Saturday North Sydney is holding a local government election. As part of the election, I believe, five matters of referendum will be placed before the voters. I believe that the now member for North Sydney, Ted Mack, who is in the other place, had something to do with that. I have spoken to him about this. I have no argument with having referendums at the same time as local government elections. In fact, I think that is a great idea. But I am concerned about the way in which this particular matter was dealt with.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I refer to the third referendum question, which is very controversial and not one that I want to argue the Yes or No case for. It states:</PARA>
<PARA>Should circuses with performing animals be banned from operating on public land in the Municipality?</PARA>
<PARA>I do not have to tell you, Mr Deputy President, that if this referendum question is carried, obviously other councils might try the same idea and, rightly or wrongly, circuses with performing animals could be banned in a lot of municipalities. I am led to believe by the circus people who contacted me only yesterday that the majority of them first found out about this information last Saturday. In the meantime the animal liberation movement has been campaigning quite strongly for the Yes case, as is its right. I believe Silvers Circus was supposed to be preparing the No case for this referendum. It had been approached for help but had not replied; neither had it not contacted any of its colleagues. The Circus Federation, for instance, was never contacted and did not have the opportunity to have any input. The Yes and the No questions, for what they are worth, are on the paper to be presented to the electors of North Sydney on Saturday. One of the claims of the Yes case reads:</PARA>
<PARA>Animals are forced to perform through fear and cruelty-beating often used to break an animal's spirit. </PARA>
<PARA>The circus people quite rightly would oppose that; the record shows that there has never been any evidence of the truth of that claim. Another claim reads:</PARA>
<PARA>All major animal protection societies oppose performing animals in circuses. </PARA>
<PARA>I know for a fact that definitely is not true. I have a list of a dozen animal welfare groups. I know that the RSPCA and ANZFAS-and I suspect Australians for Animals-have gone on record as being opposed to having performing animals in circuses and perhaps some others have. But I do not believe that the Australian Federation for the Welfare of Animals, the Australian Veterinary Association and the New South Wales Animal Welfare Advisory Council have gone on record as being so opposed. The people who vote on this particular matter on Saturday should know that some of the accusations made in the Yes case-and I have had a look at the No case which seems to be quite straightforward-do not seem to be correct. Whilst the information at the top of the page for the third referendum question includes the statement, `The Yes Case has been prepared with input from Animal Liberation', I just wonder how far democracy goes. </PARA>
<PARA> I am concerned that at the end of the day an injustice may be done. I think the question of whether performing animals should be banned from operating on public land or anywhere in circuses is something that is up to the people themselves. I have said before that if people have objections to seeing performing animals in circuses, they should not attend. We have in place the appropriate laws to ensure that animals are not treated cruelly. I just wished to place those concerns on the record. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1><DEBATE.SUB1 PAGE="1402">
<TITLE>Ministerial Response</TITLE>
<SPEECH PAGE="1402" SPEAKER="McMullan Sen R.F." NAMEID="5I4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="ACT" GOV="1">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5I4">Senator McMULLAN</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Australian Capital Territory-</ELECTORATE><ROLE>Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer)</ROLE><TIME.STAMP>(12.19 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I know that the question of summing up on the adjournment has somewhat gone out of fashion, and I do not want to reintroduce it, but Senator Watson raised some matters that peculiarly go to the area for which the Treasurer (Mr Kerin) has given me responsibility. I give an undertaking that I will make sure the matters that he raised are comprehensively looked at. I have already made arrangements from here to ensure people are made aware of the matters he raised and that there will be some examination of them.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> I note that Senator Calvert made a campaign speech for the referendum on Saturday and that is one of the reasons that we have adjournment debates. That was a legitimate use of it, but I cannot go to the merits of the matter. I undertake to Senator Watson that the matter he raised will be examined. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
<SPEECH PAGE="1403" SPEAKER="Lewis Sen A.W.R" NAMEID="NG4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NG4">Senator LEWIS</NAME><ELECTORATE>(Victoria)</ELECTORATE><TIME.STAMP>(12.20 p.m.)</TIME.STAMP></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;I congratulate Senator McMullan on his response to those people who spoke on the Senate. I say to Senator McMullan and to the Senate in general that I think that is a principle that ought not to be lost for the Senate. The fact that some of the Ministers of the current Government do not do that is to the detriment of the Senate. I certainly hope that when we get into government we maintain the principle that has been a principle of this Senate for a very long time.</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA> Question resolved in the affirmative. </PARA>
<PARA>Senate adjourned at 12.21 p.m. </PARA>
</SPEECH>
</DEBATE.SUB1></DEBATE><DEBATE TYPE="Documents" PAGE="1403"><TITLE>DOCUMENTS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA>The following documents were tabled:</PARA>
<PARA> Australian Bureau of Statistics Act-Proposal for collection of information 1991-No. 16-New topics in the monthly population survey.</PARA>
<PARA> Census and Statistics Act-Australian Bureau of Statistics-Statements of disclosure of information 1991-</PARA>
<PARA> No. 1-List of names and addresses of superannuation funds and schemes for the Insurance and Superannuation Commission.</PARA>
<PARA> No. 2-List of names and addresses of South Australian State public sector agencies for the Treasury Department, the Department of Labour and the Public Accounts Committee, South Australia.</PARA>
<PARA> Civil Aviation Act-Civil Aviation Orders-Part 82, Amendment, dated 30 August 1991.</PARA>
</PROCTEXT>
</DEBATE></CHAMBER.XSCRIPT><ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS PAGE="1404">
<TITLE>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</TITLE>
<PROCTEXT><PARA>The following answers to questions were circulated:</PARA></PROCTEXT>
<ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1404"><TITLE>Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme: Age Pensioners</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="928">(Question No. 928)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1404" SPEAKER="Patterson Sen K.C.L." NAMEID="LI4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LI4">Senator Patterson</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services, upon notice, on 17 June 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) How many PBS items were dispensed to aged pensioners in the months January, February, March, April, May and June 1990.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) How many PBS items were dispensed to aged pensioners in the months January, February, March, April, May and June 1991.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1404" SPEAKER="Tate Sen The Hon M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator Tate</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-The Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) The question relates to the January to June period before and after the introduction of a $2.50 pensioner co-payment on 1 November 1990.</PARA>
<PARA>  It should be noted that prior to this date the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme (PBS) `pensioner' category, who received PBS drugs free of charge, comprised the following groups of patients:</PARA>
<PARA>    aged pensioners</PARA>
<PARA>    invalid pensioners</PARA>
<PARA>    supporting parents</PARA>
<PARA>    sheltered employment pensioners</PARA>
<PARA>    rehabilitation allowance pensioners</PARA>
<PARA>    sickness beneficiaries</PARA>
<PARA>    war widows</PARA>
<PARA>    service pensioners without war caused disabilities</PARA>
<PARA>    dependent spouses and children of the above groups</PARA>
<PARA>  The PBS `concessional' category, who were charged $2.50, comprised the following groups:</PARA>
<PARA>    unemployment beneficiaries</PARA>
<PARA>    low income earners</PARA>
<PARA>    special beneficiaries</PARA>
<PARA>    dependent spouses and children of these groups; and</PARA>
<PARA>    all other DSS pensioners who did not qualify for a Pensioner Health Benefit card.</PARA>
<PARA>  From 1 November 1990, following the introduction of the $2.50 patient co-payment for the `pensioner' category, the above categories were combined as the one concessional category.</PARA>
<PARA>  The number of PBS prescriptions dispensed to aged pensioners only is not available as the PBS processing system does not compile statistics which distinguish between different types of patients within categories. However, the total number of PBS prescriptions dispensed to all patients in the above categories is available. The following table provides this dispensing data and combines the `pensioner' and `concessional' categories for the 1990 months in order that a comparison can be made:PBS Prescription Dispensing By Month By Category</PARA>
<PARA>  1990  1991</PARA>
<PARA>  Concessional  Pensioner  =Total  Concessional</PARA>
<PARA>Jan  731,413  5,319,695  6,051,108  4,772,754</PARA>
<PARA>Feb  765,501  5,111,330  5,876,831  4,787,273</PARA>
<PARA>Mar  930,158  6,118,123  7,048,281  5,429,687</PARA>
<PARA>Apr  813,888  5,446,668  6,260,556  5,516,996</PARA>
<PARA>May  897,102  6,218,254  7,115,356  4,636,631</PARA>
<PARA>Jun  795,651  5,772,004  6,567,655  175,141</PARA>
<PARA>  This table is subject to a number of qualifications as outlined below:</PARA>
<PARA>    the table is based on data processed to 30 June 1991.</PARA>
<PARA>    due to the variable time lag between pharmacists supplying drugs and transmitting their dispensing details to the Health Insurance Commission (HIC) complete dispensing data takes at least three months to capture and consequently accurate dispensing data for June 1991 will not be available until October 1991.</PARA>
<PARA>    the effect of the $2.50 charge is masked by;</PARA>
<PARA>      hoarding of prescriptions prior to 1 November 1990 and a subsequent downturn in later months as hoarded prescriptions are utilised in lieu of new prescriptions, and</PARA>
<PARA>      the seasonal pattern of safety net prescribing which should result in higher rates of dispensing in the second half of the calendar year as compared to the first.</PARA>
<PARA>    comparison from year to year is also subject to some distortion due to differences in classification of safety net prescriptions.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1405"><TITLE>Australian Security Intelligence Organisation</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="981">(Question No. 981)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1405" SPEAKER="Coulter Sen J.R." NAMEID="TF4" PARTY="AD" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="TF4">Senator Coulter</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Attorney-General, upon notice, on 20 June 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  With reference to the visit by ASIO to the registered officer of the political party, Australians Against Further Immigration (AAFI), Dr Rod Spencer and his wife, Robyn, on the Wednesday prior to the Menzies by-election on 11 May 1991, an election in which AAFI stood a candidate:</PARA>
<PARA>  (1) Which Minister gave this direction to ASIO.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) Did the registered officers of other political parties standing in the by-election also receive visits from ASIO.</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) What was the purpose of the visit to Dr Spencer.</PARA>
<PARA>  (4) Is it normal practice for ASIO to investigate candidates standing for political office in this country.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1405" SPEAKER="Tate Sen The Hon M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="SA">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator Tate</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-The Attorney-General has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) ASIO interviewed Dr Spencer under the provisions of the Australian Security Intelligence Organization Act 1979 and not in response to a direction from any Minister.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) ASIO did not interview Dr Spencer in relation to an investigation of AAFI, but as part of a routine ASIO inquiry unrelated to that group. No investigation was made of any political parties standing in the Menzies by-election.</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) The purpose of the visit to Dr Spencer was to seek his assistance in relation to a group being investigated by ASIO to establish whether the group's activities were relevant to security as that term is defined in section 4 of the ASIO Act.</PARA>
<PARA>  (4) No.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1405"><TITLE>Kakadu National Park</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="1004">(Question No. 1004)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1405" SPEAKER="Tambling Sen G.E.J." NAMEID="6E4" PARTY="CLP" ELECTORATE="NT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="6E4">Senator Tambling</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 10 July 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) In relation to all land within the Kakadu National Park (including the area added to the Park by Proclamation dated 21 June 1991): (a) what interests in respect of that land or in respect of any minerals on, in or beneath that land were held (other than by the Commonwealth or a Commonwealth agency), and by whom, immediately before the land was declared to be within the Park; (b) what (i) Commonwealth, and (ii) Northern Territory laws apply to the interests identified in response to (a): and (c) which of the interests identified in response to (a): (i) had expired at some time before 21 June 1991, when did they expire and for what reason, or (ii) are expected to expire at some future time, when will they expire and for what reason in each case, or (iii) are not expected to expire at some specific future time.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) On what occasions, and in respect of what interests, has the Minister administering the National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act given approval in writing under paragraph 8B(1)(b) of the Act.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1405" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="NT">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator Bolkus</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-I am advised that the answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) Kakadu National Park consists of a number of separate areas of land that have been declared to be part of the Park at different times. The status of the numerous mining and other interests which exist, or which may exist, within the Park is not a simple matter. Their status will depend on whether they were in existence on 1 July 1978 or created subsequently and, what action if any has been taken in respect of a particular interest since that date.</PARA>
<PARA>  Prior to commencement of the Northern Territory (Self-Government) Act 1978 on 1 July 1978 the fee simple of all land in the Northern Territory was vested in the Commonwealth. All exploration for minerals and mining was regulated by the Mining Ordinance 1939 and its Regulations (except in the case of prescribed substances within the meaning of the Atomic Energy Act 1953, for which exploration and mining was regulated by the Atomic Energy Act 1953 and Regulations made under it).</PARA>
<PARA>  On and from 1 July 1978 the fee simple of all land in the Northern Territory became vested in the Northern Territory except such land as the Commonwealth re-acquired pursuant to section 70 of the Northern Territory (Self-Government) Act 1978. Subsections 70(2) and (3) of the Northern Territory (Self-Government) Act 1978 enabled the Commonwealth to re-acquire Northern Territory land for a public purpose approved by the Governor-General. By virtue of subsection 70(4) those interests notified in the Gazette prior to the commencement of self-government vested in the Commonwealth immediately after the commencement of section 69 of that Act on 1 July 1978. Among the areas of land that were reacquired by the Commonwealth on 1 July 1978 were those which together now comprise the Park. By reason of the Self Government Act all mining interests that existed in that land on 1 July 1978 continued to be held from the Commonwealth in accordance with the provisions of the Mining Ordinance 1939 and its Regulations as they stood on that date. Those interests were also subject to the Lands Acquisition Act or, where the land was declared to be part of the Park, the National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act. Similarly, any new mining interests would have to be created under and subject to the Lands Acquisition Act 1955, the Lands Acquisition Act 1989 or the National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act 1975.</PARA>
<PARA>  Therefore, since 1 July 1978 the creation and management of mining or other interests in the land which now comprises Kakadu National Park has been the responsibility of the Commonwealth and not the Northern Territory Government.</PARA>
<PARA>  The number of interests which do or which may now exist in the Park is large, running into the</PARA>
<PARA>hundreds. It is not presently possible to provide an answer to the honourable senator's question in respect of each such interest. They would need to be examined separately to assess whether a particular interest was in existence on 1 July 1978 or created subsequently, whether it has expired or will expire at some future time and, if expired whether the interest has been renewed or extended.</PARA>
<PARA>  Whatever mining interests may exist in the Park, subsection 10(1A) of the National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act 1975 (which commenced on 18 May 1987) does not permit operations for the recovery of minerals to be carried on in the Park.</PARA>
<PARA>  Should there be a particular interest or interests to which the honourable senator's question relates I would be happy to provide the relevant information.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) My colleague the Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories has informed me that on no occasion has approval been given for renewal of interests pursuant to paragraph 8B(1)(b) of the National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1406"><TITLE>Health, Housing and Community Services: Programs and Schemes</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="1083">(Question No. 1083)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1406" SPEAKER="Alston Sen R.K.R." NAMEID="LD4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="LD4">Senator Alston</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister representing the Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services, upon notice, on 26 July 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  Name each of the programs and schemes in your portfolio which are accessed primarily by people aged 60 years and over or have been set up specifically for such people and what was the appropriation for each of these schemes in 1990-91.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1406" SPEAKER="Tate Sen The Hon M.C." NAMEID="NJ4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="VIC">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="NJ4">Senator Tate</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-The Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>Special Appropriations</PARA>
<PARA>        ($000)</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 2.2: Home And Community Care Allowances</PARA>
<PARA>  National Health Act 1953.</PARA>
<PARA>    Domiciliary Nursing Care Benefit  33,007</PARA>
<PARA>Special Appropriations</PARA>
<PARA>        ($000)</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.2: Financial Support</PARA>
<PARA>    Aged or Disabled Persons Homes Act 1954  189,856</PARA>
<PARA>  National Health Act 1953.</PARA>
<PARA>    Nursing Home Benefits  1,555,957</PARA>
<PARA>  Appropriation Bill 1</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 2.1: Home And Community Care Services</PARA>
<PARA>    Home and Community Care (200.05)  1,800</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.1: Assessment</PARA>
<PARA>    Residential Care for Older People (200.06)  184</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.2: Financial Support</PARA>
<PARA>    Residential Care for Older People (200.06)  172,195</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.3: Quality Of Residential Care</PARA>
<PARA>    Residential Care for Older People (200.06)  2,830</PARA>
<PARA>  Appropriation Bill 2</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 2.1: Home And Community Care Services</PARA>
<PARA>    Home and Community Care (831.06)  281,134</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.1: Assessment</PARA>
<PARA>    Nursing Homes (831.07.01)  24,411</PARA>
<PARA>    Hostels (831.07.02)  1,120</PARA>
<PARA>Sub-Program 3.3: Quality Of Residential Care</PARA>
<PARA>    Hostel Outcome Standards--Gerontic Training (832.00.05)  100</PARA>
<PARA>  Bill 1 and 2 items have been adjusted for bills 4 and 5 (Revised/Additional Estimates). Special Appropriation items are actual outcomes for the 1990-91 financial year.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1407"><TITLE>Computer Power Group</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="1148">(Question No. 1148)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1407" SPEAKER="Calvert Sen P.H." NAMEID="5F4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="5F4">Senator Calvert</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister for Defence, upon notice, on 13 August 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) What savings are envisaged from the Defence Supply Systems Integration contract worth $9 million which has recently been awarded to the Computer Power Group?</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) As this is the first stage of the contract, when are further stages planned and what is their likely cost?</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) What is the Australian ownership of the Computer Power Group?</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1407" SPEAKER="Ray Sen The Hon R.F." NAMEID="UI4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="TAS">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="UI4">Senator Ray</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) There are no savings arising from the contract itself. The contract was awarded primarily to assist the Department to reduce the significant risk in coordinating and managing an undertaking as large and complex as the Supply Systems Redevelopment Project.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) There is one further stage to the engagement, which may be optionally exercised at the end of Stage 1, dependent on satisfactory performance in Stage 1. The second stage, which covers the detailed design and implementation of the Standard Defence Supply System, is expected to commence in April 1992. The estimated cost of integration services for Stage 2 is approximately $28 million.</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) Advice from the office of the Chief Executive Officer and Chairman of the Board of Directors of Computer Power Group Ltd is that the company is in excess of 90% Australian owned.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON><ANSWER.TO.QON PAGE="1407"><TITLE>Australian Democrats: National Party of Australia</TITLE>
<QUESTION.NUMBER QON.NUMBER="1162">(Question No. 1162)</QUESTION.NUMBER><QUESTION PAGE="1407" SPEAKER="Macdonald Sen I.D." NAMEID="YW4" PARTY="LP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="YW4">Senator Macdonald</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1"> asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 16 August 1991:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) What is the entitlement, in numbers and classifications, of staff made available to the Senators and Members of the Australian Democrats and the National Party of Australia.</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) What is the basis for the number of staff allocated to Senators and Members representing those political parties.</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) On what authority and under what legislation (please identify clauses) are allocations of staff made.</PARA>
</QUESTION><ANSWER PAGE="1407" SPEAKER="Bolkus Sen The Hon N." NAMEID="XE4" PARTY="ALP" ELECTORATE="QLD">
<TALK.START><TALKER><NAME NAMEID="XE4">Senator Bolkus</NAME></TALKER>
<PARA IN-LINE="1">&mdash;-I have been advised that the answer to the honourable Senator's question is as follows:</PARA></TALK.START>
<PARA>  (1) Numbers and classifications of staff are as follows:</PARA>
<PARA>  Australian Democrats</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Private Secretary Grade 4A</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Private Secretary Grade 3</PARA>
<PARA>    2 Private Secretary Grade 2</PARA>
<PARA>    3 Private Secretary Grade 1</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Clerk</PARA>
<PARA>    3 Assistant Private Secretary Grade 2</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Assistant Private Secretary Grade 1</PARA>
<PARA>  National Party of Australia</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Private Secretary Grade 4A</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Media Adviser</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Private Secretary Grade 2</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Private Secretary Grade 1</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Assistant Private Secretary Grade 2</PARA>
<PARA>    4 Assistant Private Secretary Grade 1</PARA>
<PARA>    1 Clerk</PARA>
<PARA>    2 Steno Secretary Grade 1</PARA>
<PARA>  In addition, each Senator or Member is entitled to employ three electorate staff (four where an electorate exceeds 200,000 square kilometres in area).</PARA>
<PARA>  (2) The number of staff positions allocated to the National Party was initially determined by the Leader of the Opposition who provided to the National Party, staff positions from the block of positions provided to the Opposition parties.</PARA>
<PARA>  The split up of positions has been formalised in determinations subsequently made on the enactment of the Members of Parliament (Staff) Act 1984. As a minority party, the number of positions provided to the Australian Democrats has regard to the resource levels provided to the other parties in the Parliament.</PARA>
<PARA>  The Leaders of the National Party and of the Australian Democrats have the discretion to allocate positions to individual members of the relevant Parliamentary Party.</PARA>
<PARA>  (3) Members of Parliament (Staff) Act 1984, Part III--Staff of Office-Holders, Sections 12 and 13 and Part IV--Staff of Senators and Members, Section 20.</PARA>
</ANSWER></ANSWER.TO.QON></ANSWERS.TO.QUESTIONS></HANSARD>
